<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/concurso-propoe-a-jovens-desenhar-a-identidade-da-cidade-atraves-da-banda-desenhada/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Macao Week in Wuhan attracted 255 thousand visitors</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/semana-de-macau-em-wuhan-atraiu-255-mil-visitantes/</link><description>The street promotion of the “Macao Week in Wuhan • Hubei”, held from September 5 to 8 in Wuhan, attracted 255,000 visitors to the site. For four days, the event allowed to “experience the diverse charm of Macao's Tourism +’, further increasing the reputation of Macao ”, according to the Tourism Services Directorate,“ contributing to increase the willingness of visitors to visit Macau and promote the development of the tourism economy ”.

The “Macao Week in Wuhan • Hubei” was successfully held, according to the Tourism Services (STD), attracting 255,000 visitors over four days. The event was held on two ways with “face -to -face promotion + online promotion”, conjunction with tourist promotion sessions and macao gastronomic promotion. According to STD, the event “showed, in every respect, the rich" Tourism +"content of Macao, attracting more visitors from the interior of China to visit Macao at the holidays of the National Day of the Popular Republic of China and the Festival of the Lunar Cake, to experience festivities and events."
The place chosen for the promotion was the “Wuhan Customs House Square”, in the city of Wuhan, where several thematic zones were installed, with elements of tourism, trade, culture, culture and creativity, sports and entertainment. In the exhibitor of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, cultural and tourist resources and tourism model were promoted, promoting joint tourism between Macau and Hengqin Island.
According to an STD statement, Macao tour operators together presented more than 26 million Renminbis in tourist offers, including airplane tickets, hotel accommodation, restoration, among other characteristic tourist products, with precision marketing at street promotion and on online travel agency platforms.

Shows and animation

During the promotion, they were presented close to 90 shows, including the Macau Tourism Mascot “Mak Mak”, which led a street dance group from Macau to open the promotion, lion dance, martial arts, dragon dance at night, Portuguese folk dance, band concert and street dance. The six integrated tourism and leisure companies also provided animation groups to animate the festive environment of the promotion, which attracted a large number of viewers, says STD.
Between September 2 and 8, the organizing entity took advantage of the “Yangtze River Light Show” to project a “Macao Week of Wuhan Week • Hubei” Themed Light show on the four banks of the two rivers (Yangtze River and Hanjiang River). During the street promotion, a 3D Mapping video projection show was presented at “Wuhan Customs House Square”.
Several digital influencers held 11 live broadcast sessions and produced graphic texts and short videos to present the highlights of the event. At the same time, the main media in the country also reported on the event, and the Macao Social Communication bodies and the province of Hubei participated in the event, “further expanding their influence and broadly spreading their effects”.
Prior to the opening of the event, STD organized a Macao Tourism Promotion Seminar with a contact scholarship session, which attracted the participation of more than 120 tour operators, with a view to promoting cooperation between Macao, Hubei and Hengqin tour operators, deepening contacts in the sector and in joint business opportunities.

Tourism and Gastronomy

Between September 5 and October 8, at Hotel Wanda Reign Wuhan, the activity of gastronomic promotion “Wuhan and Macau flavors” offers a themed buffet with typical macanese and Portuguese dishes. On September 4, an experience session for the media was also held, through the appeal of digital influencers and the coverage of the media to release the activities. Herlander Fernandes and Pedro Miguel Santos do Carmo, heads of a Macao integrated tourism and leisure company, also exchanged experiences about the gastronomic culture with the team of Wuhan cooks, promoting the image of Macao as a creative city of gastronomy.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:33:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Court recognizes joint parenting to lesbian couple</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/tribunal-de-hong-kong-reconhece-parentalidade-conjunta-a-casal-lesbico/</link><description>A Hong Kong Court considered illegal to prevent a lesbian couple from registering the motherhood of the child conceived by in vitro fertilization by considering that this exclusion violates the rights to the child's privacy and family life.

The decision of the lower court, released on Tuesday by the local press, represents a milestone in the fight for the rights of homoparental families in the Special Administrative region Chinese.
The couple, identified as R, of Chinese nationality, and B, a South African citizen with permanent residence in Hong Kong, married abroad in 2019. The son, identified as K and born in 2021, was conceived through reciprocal in vitro fertilization, with an egg of B and pregnancy by B.
However, the local civil registration recognized only B as a legal mother, leaving R - who has the only genetic bond with the child - without any official parental status.
The dispute dates back to 2022, when the couple began a lawsuit to reinterpret local legislation and ensure the recognition of R as a mother. Judge Queeny Au recognized as “progenitor according to consumed law”, but without clarifying the concrete rights, as it considered that this would overcome the competences of the Court.
In view of the Justice Department's refusal to change the birth certificate, a new judicial revision was requested by 2023.
Judge Russell Coleman, who presided over to the latest hearing, classified the previous decision as “empty”, as he did not give to any effective rights or legal obligations. He stressed that the omission of R on the birth certificate could undermine his parental role, affecting the child's dignity and identity. "Reflects a sense of inferiority resulting from the absence of a legal framework of recognition," said the magistrate, citing a decision of 2023 of the last court that requires the protection of same -sex union rights.
Coleman rejected the government's argument that the birth certificate was “unintentionally” and stressed that inaccuracies in this document may impair the privacy and development of the child's identity at important times in his childhood.
The judge also rejected the government's suggestion that R should ask for legal protection from the child, considering that “a parent is a parent” and that such an alternative is insufficient.
The court urged lawyers to propose concrete measures to execute the sentence.
In Hong Kong, same -sex marriage is not fully recognized and is only admitted to limited purposes such as taxation or inheritance after court disputes.
In 2023, the last court gave the government two years to create a clear legal framework for same -sex couples. However, a bill on medical rights and posthumous decisions faces strong opposition and should be voted on yesterday to the Legislative Council. The court decision represents an advance in the struggle for equal rights of the LGBTQ community in Hong Kong, where the legal recognition of same -sex unions remains restricted and controversial. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:30:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau returns to normal after Tapah passage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/macau-regressa-a-normalidade-apos-passagem-do-tapah/</link><description>The Tapah tropical cyclone continues to move away from Macao after taking the storm signal. 8 between 9 pm on Sunday and 15h on Monday. All storm signs were eventually removed the night the day before yesterday, as the wind in the region weakened and the system moved into the continent.
The storm occurred simultaneously with the astronomical tide phenomenon, which raised the water level by about one meter and forced the emission of the warning of 'Storm emerge' yellow for a period of 45 and a half hours. Civil protection services were highlighted for the low areas of Macao, more favorable to flooding, where they sensitized residents and tourists regarding storm protection measures and ensured the normal functioning of drainage systems and eventual evacuation plans. In the early hours of Monday, light floods were found in the inner port and mud, although they did not cause significant incidents.
Until yesterday morning, the Civil Protection Operations Center (COPC) recorded 25 occurrences throughout the territory and four injured - three with slight injuries and one person who needed to be hospitalized due to fractures. While signal No. 8 remained avenge, the body's open lines received 23 calls of consultation and support requests, mostly related to the operation of parking parks, the closing measures of the bridges or the operation of the border posts. The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) also reported a case of tariff negotiation and three cases of transport services without authorization by taxi drivers.
Yesterday, the region returned to normal with the reopening of the four maritime bridges and the resuming the operation of public transport, educational institutions and health care services.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:54:59</pubDate></item><item><title>UN employees in Thailand reinforce knowledge on exploitation prevention and sexual abuse</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/funcionarios-da-onu-na-tailandia-reforcam-conhecimentos-sobre-prevencao-da-exploracao-e-abuso-sexual/</link><description>During the month of August, United Nations (UN) employees in Thailand participated in a series of small group formations on exploration prevention and sexual abuse (PSEA). Organized by the UN National Team Psea Task Force, the sessions reflected a commitment of the whole system to awareness, reinforcing accountability and guaranteeing safe and respectful workplaces.
The initiative brought together the Economic and Social Commission for Asia and the Pacific (Escap), the United Nations Development Program (UNDP) and the resident coordinator's office in Thailand under a One Un approach, gathering resources to address PSEA and emphasizing that the protection of affected populations is a shared responsibility.
The training was taught through several unstructured sessions to create space for active discussions. A dedicated session was called by the resident coordinator for bosses, while a trainee training session equipped the focus points and those responsible for human resources with the skills necessary to transmit learning within their agencies.
"We analyzed how to be an active spectator, how to recognize and answer if something happens and how to change our own behavior," explained Yanthe Cornelissen, head of the inadequate UNDP sexual conduct unit, which facilitated training along with members of the Psea task force in Thailand. "The victim -centered approach is fundamental to everything we do."
The training was built around interactive case studies based on real -life incidents. Participants practiced the recognition of signs of abuse, the establishment of clear limits and the application of complaint procedures.
For Maria Fe Villena, Escap's Language Service Assistant, the format worked well: "It was a good way to refresh and reinforce our understanding of Psea. Training reminded us what to do when confronted with delicate situations."
The training also helped to clarify the channels of complaint. "I was not familiar with the mechanisms nor was it clarity about the focal points," said Ladawan Pitipala, Senior Assistant at Escap. "Now I know who to turn to."
For others, the formation highlighted the responsibility that each team member has. "To adopt PSEA is not just about complying with regulations, it is humanity," said Pipat Poopeerasupong, United Nations Program Management Officer. "We all have the responsibility to observe and denounce possible inadequate conduct."</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:28:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai appeals again to the vote of civil servants in the elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/sam-hou-fai-volta-a-apelar-ao-voto-dos-funcionarios-publicos-nas-eleicoes/</link><description>After issuing a letter in which he settled civil servants to vote for Sunday's legislative elections, the Chief Executive again appealed to the exercise of voting rights at a meeting with civil service leaders. On Sunday, special buses will be made available at the border posts and at the University of Macao, with a view to facilitating the travel of all voters.

The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, chaired the day before yesterday with a meeting with civil service leaders at the government's headquarters, where he returned to the participation of civil servants in the legislative elections and recalled the various measures implemented aimed at facilitating travel to the polls.
As he had previously stated in a letter addressed to civil servants, Sam Hou Fai recalled that the suffrage for the elections "constitutes not only a right, but also a civic duty" to which all voters must adhere. In this sense, he called for “all public services” facilitate “the travel of employees in service” to the different voting places - 37, in total, distributed all over the territory.
According to an informative document published yesterday, 29 service stations will also be installed on streets or parks near voting places: 14 in the North Zone, nine in the central and southern areas and six in Taipa and Coloane. In addition to providing information about the elections and voting assemblies, employees present in these posts will also make available the “necessary assistance” to voters with “specific needs”.
On the 14th, the buses and the slight meter will operate for free during the election time, from 9am to 9pm. In order to facilitate the displacement of voters with addresses registered outside the border and teachers and university students, four special lines with matches for the Macao Forum and a line connecting to the University of Macai will also be available.
GCS informs that, taking into account the expected traffic for voting places, special bus waiting points will be installed and displaced employees to the areas of exits, in order to provide support and assistance to voters and detect situations that affect the traffic order in the immediate vicinity.

Elections are “political event of enormous importance”

At the same meeting at the Government headquarters, Sam Hou Fai also considered that these elections represent "a political event of enormous importance for MSAR and a highlight of the current government since its inauguration," according to a statement from the Communication Office (GSC). It is recalled that these are the first elections to take place after the review of the electoral law to the Legislative Assembly, which now criminalizes the incitement to abstention and to determine the exclusion of all candidates that the authorities consider insufficiently patriotic.
The ruler stressed that leaders in the management level “must assume a connection role between superiors and subordinates”, namely through the promotion of vote, facilitating the travels of employees and cooperation between different services and public entities. The fulfillment of these measures is, it argues, “a basic requirement for the ethical and moral principles of civil service” and an essential step to ensure that the electoral process stems in a “legal, fair, impartial and righteous environment”.
Earlier this month, the Chief Executive sent a letter to workers of services and public entities in which he settled them to vote in the legislative elections - as well as "to their family and friends" - and pointed out that this is a way of demonstrating "fidelity to mashes." Days after the issuance of this letter, the chairman of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), Seng Ioi Man, ensured that “the issue of disciplinary responsibility” will not be applied to civil servants who choose not to vote in the legislative elections.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:34:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao sovereignty transfer ensured “cultural identity” of the region, says Montenegro</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/transferencia-de-soberania-de-macau-assegurou-identidade-cultural-da-regiao-diz-montenegro/</link><description>Xi Jinping and Luís Montenegro met yesterday in Beijing. After the meeting, the Chinese president stated that Portugal is a “good friend of China”, recalling the “proper way” in which countries resolved the issue of Macao's sovereignty transfer. The Portuguese Prime Minister, who today goes through the MSAR, said that the transition from Macau represented "a good expression of the way we can converge and we managed to ensure cultural identity."

In Beijing, Luís Montenegro met yesterday with Xi Jinping. In a brief statement after the meeting, the Chinese President considered that both countries resolved "the issue of Macao properly through friendly negotiations."
The Portuguese Prime Minister, who is now passing through the MSAR, expressed agreement with the words of Xi Jinping about how the transition from the Macao de Portugal administration to China has taken place in 1999. “We had in the transition from Macau a good expression of how we were able to converge and managed to ensure the cultural identity and relationship between the special administrative region of Macao, with Portugal and China,” he said.
Montenegro also stated that it has its close relationship with Russia so that it is possible to “build just and lasting peace” in Ukraine. ”I cannot help, on behalf of the government of Portugal, to transmit to the President that we count a lot with your contribution and the close relationship that China maintains with the Russian federation to be able, as fast as possible, to build a fair and lasting peace,” he said, by the Lusa agency.
Later, the prime minister expressed confidently that the appeal he addressed to China's president to use the close relationship with Russia in favor of peace in Ukraine "will not fall into a rotor bag," coming from "a friendly country."
Luís Montenegro, questioned by journalists in the forbidden city about which Eco had to Xi Jinping, said: “I believe that the appeal from a friendly country from a European Union country from a country, such as Mr. President Xi Jinping, also emphasized that he has an identity of values ​​and route, he will not fall into a rotor bag,” he said.
Saying not being able to answer for the President of the Popular Republic of China, Montenegro has manifested convinced that Portugal has done what is required of this conflict.
"My conviction is that, to our dimension and without any kind of pretentiousness, we do what is required to a nation with history and the international respectability that Portugal has. We are builders of bridges, we are protagonists of the approach between peoples, we are advocates of peace, defenders of values, respect for people's rights," he said.
Montenegro considered that, at the meeting with Xi Jinping, he was limited to “being frank, loyal and direct in the appeal” so that China's ability to influence and “bring practical results” to Ukraine.
Earlier, Montenegro stressed that, in the international context, Portugal and China have maintained "on many occasions a base of cooperation and sharing of values."
"China has a key role in the global and international context, a permanent member of the United Nations Security Council and we expect your contribution to build bridges between peoples, bring some of those who are in conflict, promote peace, promote multilateralism, promote respect for human rights," he said.
"As Mr. President said, Portugal and China have a relationship founded on a story that has shared with various times in common, but also a relationship facing the future. I remember Mr. President's visit to Portugal for seven years and I also want to convey the greetings of Mr. President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa," he said.
Luís Montenegro landed in Beijing early Monday afternoon. The prime minister's official agenda began with a ceremony of deposition of a wreath at the monument to the heroes of the people, in Tiananmen Square, in which he was accompanied by his wife and three ministers who are part of this visit: Paulo Rangel, Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Manuel Castro Almeida, Minister of Economics and Territorial Cohesion, and Graça Carvalho, Minister of Environment and Energy. After the passage through Macao, the Portuguese Prime Minister went on to Japan.

“Portugal is a good friend from China,” says Xi

After the meeting with Montenegro, Xi Jinping said that “Portugal is a good friend of China”, and praised the international role of previous prime ministers António Guterres, Durão Barroso and António Costa.
“I remember that in 2018 I made a state visit to Portugal, which left me a beautiful and deep impression,” he said, taking the opportunity to ask Montenegro to transmit to the Portuguese head of state, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, “sincere greetings”, according to the simultaneous translation into Portuguese of his statements.
The Chinese president stressed that China and Portugal "are both countries with deep history, and the two peoples have idiosyncrasy, openness, inclusion, progress and autonomy", arguing that "Portugal plays an important and unique role on the international stage."
Xi Jinping also highlighted “the important role” played by three former Portuguese prime ministers in international and regional affairs. "The Secretary General of the United Nations, António Guterres, the president of the European Council, António Costa, and the former president of the European Commission Durão Barroso. I have good relations with them," he said.
"Portugal was also the first country in Western Europe to sign with China cooperation acts under the" one track, a route "initiative, and the first eurozone country that issued titles" in Chinese currency, he said.
Quoted by Chinese state agency Xinhua, the Chinese president also pointed out that in recent years the two countries have achieved fruitful results in cooperation in various areas, establishing a model of mutual respect and mutual benefit for countries with different social systems and national conditions.
Noting that this year is the 20th anniversary of the establishment of the comprehensive strategic partnership China-Portugal, Xi said that the country is willing to reinforce strategic communication with Portugal, to guide bilateral relations in the right direction, to make good relationships even better and to contribute even more to the prosperity and progress of the two countries and the world through solidarity and cooperation.
"The more turbulent and interconnected the international panorama, the greater the need for China and Europe to reinforce communication, reinforce mutual trust and deepen cooperation," said Xi, appealing to Portugal to work with China to maintain the position of the China-UE partnership and promote sustainable, stable and healthy development of China-UE relations.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:59:49</pubDate></item><item><title>China analyzes new laws to foster ethnic unit and standardize Mandarin</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/china-analisa-novas-leis-para-fomentar-unidade-etnica-e-padronizar-uso-do-mandarim/</link><description>China analyzed two legislative projects on Monday to reinforce ethnic integration and the promotion of the use of mandarin among minorities, under President Xi Jinping's strategy to consolidate national identity.

Segundo informou ontem a imprensa local, um dos diplomas, a proposta de “Lei para a Promoção da Unidade e Progresso Étnicos”, foi apresentada ao Comité Permanente da Assembleia Popular Nacional (APN), o órgão legislativo máximo do país.
The Official News Agency Xinhua considered the bill to be “an urgent requirement to foster a strong sense of the community of the Chinese nation and to advance the construction of a unified national identity”.
With seven chapters that cover cultural identity, social integration, economic development, supervision and legal responsibilities, the proposal underlines the promotion of interethnic exchanges through cultural, educational and tourist initiatives.
The project was registered in the five -year plane of the 14th APN Legislature, which ends this year, and was also discussed by the Chinese Communist Party Politburo in August at a meeting chaired by Xi Jinping.
In parallel, a review of the “commonly spoken and spoken common Chinese language law was presented, with 32 articles distributed by five chapters, which provides for comprehensive measures to standardize and promote the use of mandarin in sectors such as public services, education, international communication and digital space.
According to Xinhua, Mandarin "is a fundamental element of Chinese culture and a national symbol, such as the flag, the hymn and the emblem." The review also establishes the third week of September as the “National Mandarin Promotion Week”.
The proposals fall into the Xi Jinping policy to build “a sense of the community of the Chinese nation”, launched in 2014 and reaffirmed in 2021, and arise in the context of international scrutiny over Beijing's approach to ethnic minorities in regions such as Tibet and Xinjiang, where authorities intensified the regulation of local language and culture.
Critics warn that assimilation threatens to erod regional cultures, as occurred in the inner Mongolia, where Mandarin became mandatory as a teaching language, along with the censorship of artistic works and the revocation of local laws considered incompatible with national ethnic policy.
According to official data, more than 80% of the Chinese population speaks Mandarin and 95% of literate adults use normalized characterized, with the rate of illiteracy around 2.7%. However, challenges remain related to unequal language promotion, insufficient regulation in public services and digital space and the need to adapt to the digital age and artificial intelligence.
The review project also reinforces the legal principles by adding as objectives “the strengthening of the consciousness of the Chinese nation community and the consolidation of cultural confidence”, providing that “no organization or individual can prevent citizens from learning and using the national common language”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:30:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines receive 21st edition of the New Format Volleyball World Cup and 32 selections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/filipinas-recebem-21-a-edicao-do-mundial-de-voleibol-com-novo-formato-e-32-seleccoes/</link><description>The Philippines will host from this Friday the 21st edition of the Men's Volleyball World Championship, with a new expanded format to 32 selections, including Portugal, and three European favorites: Poland, Italy and France.

With a new expanded format, from 24 to 32 participants, more selections thus reach the two pavilions around the capital Filipina, Manila, to play the first unique year tournament since the first edition (1949), in another change, by passing the competition to Bianual, instead of quadrennial as it was being.
In the Philippines, the second Asian country to receive the Men's World Cup, after Japan (1998 and 2006), eight 'Poules' will open the competition, from which the two best selections are investigated, advancing to the round of 16.
It is in this lot that Portugal expects to be, with a difficult group, which includes United States, Cuba and Colombia, on the way to the final, scheduled for September 28.
Among the favorites, in theory, is Italy, which has just won the women's World Cup and will seek to get the same among men, reaching the tournament as champion in title.
The Italians have been looking for the first consecutive 'BI' since 1998, having as first opponents Ukraine, Belgium and Algeria, in Group F, and arrive as one of the main selections to have an eye.
Last year, Olympic gold smiled at the home team in Paris2024, and France will want to join him a first world title, never even coming to a final-has the best result the 2002 bronze.
Poland has gone with the silver of the last Olympic games and, in Manila, will face group B the Netherlands, Qatar and Romania, the latter a selection with two finals played - and lost - but not participating in a world championship since 1982.
The Polish, led by the 'stars' Jakub Kochanowski and Wilfredo Leon, go after the fourth world scene, the first since the two straight in 2014 and 2018.
Outside the European continent, two former champions seek to end the fasts of titles, especially Brazil, three times champion, but without getting gold for 15 years, but also the United States, without winning since 1986.
The Brazilians won the bronze in the last edition, occupying the third place in the hierarchy, and bring as main figures Ricardo Lucarelli, Alan Souza and Bruno Rezende.
In the same group H is the Czech Republic, another former champion, Serbia and China, while Asian champion, Japan, is along with Libya, Canada and Turkey.
The Japanese arrives in number five in the world ranking, led by Poland, and led by Ran Takahashi, having appealed to the Philippines, who often face Asian competitions, to 'lend them' the support of the stands.
In other 'little', Chile's return includes a confrontation with Rok Mozic's Slovery, fourth in the last world. On the other hand, the tournament features two rookies, starting with the hostess, while Colombia will play a World Cup for the first time before Portuguese, Americans and Cubans. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:27:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Casinos invoiced 4.45 billion of patacas in the first week of September</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/casinos-facturaram-445-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-na-primeira-semana-de-setembro/</link><description>Gross game revenues in the first seven days of September reached 4.45 billion patacas, which gives a daily average of 635 million patacas, estimates JP Morgan. This value is lower compared to the previous months, however, compared to September last year, there was a jump of more than 10%. The institution also says that in September, gross game revenues should be around 19 and 19.5 billion Patacas.

In the first seven days of September, casinos got gross revenues of 4.45 billion patacas, said the brokerage firm JP Morgan citing data released by the sector. This brand represents a daily average of 635 million patacas.
Compared to the daily average of July and August (714 million per day), the September mark is below. In the report, quoted by the Ggrania portal, JP Morgan explains a break with the factor of seasonality, as summer months are historically stronger. Already compared to September last year (575 million per day), the numbers of the first week this month recorded an increase of more than 10%.
JP Morgan predicts that in September, gross game revenues are 19 and 19.5 billion patacas, ie more between 10% to 13% compared to the same period last year.
If this growth will be made to take gross third-quarter game revenues of 2025 to the highest level of the last 23 quarters, with an increase between 14% and 15% compared to the previous year, to about 63 billion patacas, JP Morgan analysts indicate.
Recently, Citigroup also indicated that in the early days of September, there was an increase of 27% in the value of average bets per player compared to the same period last year. The average bet per player rose to $ 24,550 dollars from Hong Kong from 19,389 Hong Kong dollars the year before. The total bets observed by Citigroup analysts in the early days of September this year was $ 12.3 million.
Deutsche Bank and Seaport had already released reports last week indicating that game revenues in September could increase about 13% compared to last year's same -year period. The estimates of the two institutions pointed to gross game revenues in September of the order of 19.7 billion Patacas.
In August, game recipes hit the postpandeia record, with 22.15 billion patacas. In the general calculation of the first eight months of this year, the game industry has faced more than 163 billion patacas. Last year's entirely, gross game revenues rose to 226.7 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:58:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Nepal's army with a strong presence on the streets of Katmandu after violent disorders</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/exercito-do-nepal-com-forte-presenca-nas-ruas-de-katmandu-apos-disturbios-violentos/</link><description>The Nepalese army patrolled yesterday morning the streets of the capital, Katmandu, after a day of violent disorders marked by the resignation of the country's Prime Minister KP Sharma Oli.

Police Nepalese suppressed brutally last Monday demonstrations that denounced the government's decision to block social networks and the corruption of the elites, causing at least 19 dead and hundreds of injured.
Despite the restoration of social platforms Facebook, X or YouTube, the promise of an investigation into police violence and the departure of Oli, groups of young protesters looted on Tuesday public buildings and residences of Nepalese political leaders.
Parliament was set on fire, as was the residence of the dismissal prime minister, according to AFP journalists.
On Wednesday, the streets of the capital were full of wreckage of vehicles and barricades, and there was still smoke leaving the burned buildings or looted stores during the riots, according to the testimony of the same news agency. "It is calm this morning, the army is everywhere on the streets," an AFP told a highlighted military man who refused to reveal his identity because he was not allowed to speak to the media. No official balance of the riots has so far been released.
Nepal's army appealed on Tuesday to the country's population in the Himalayas with 30 million inhabitants to keep calm and warned "activities that could lead the country to revolt and instability."
In a video message, Nepalese General Ashok Raj Sigdel, appealed to "all groups involved in the demonstrations to recover calm and stress a dialogue."
Back in power in 2024, 73 -year -old Kp Sharma Oli explained that he was fired "so that measures could be taken with a view to a political solution."
The president of the country, Ramchandra Paudel, also exhorted "all, including protesters, to cooperate for a peaceful resolution of the difficult situation of the country."
Other appeals to calm and containment were made by the UN and neighboring India. "Nepal's stability, peace and prosperity are of capital importance to us," said Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi.
The political situation remains very uncertain in Nepal, while waiting for a successor to the head of the dismissal government. Mayor of Katmandu since 2022, the former 35 -year -old former engineer and rapper Balendra Shah also appealed to the population to “contain evidence”. “Be ready (…) to take over the reins of the country,” he launched on Facebook, presented as an unavoidable figure of the transition that is avoid.

Nepalese opposition leader released from prison during protests of young people

Opposition leader Nepalese, Rabi Lamichhane, was released from prison by a multitude of protesters during a violent street protest on Monday, who made at least 25 dead and forced the resignation of the Nepal government.
The release of Lamichhane, who has already spoken to the population, occurred simultaneously with that of hundreds of prisoners from Nakhu's arrest and the capital's central arrest, according to images published on social networks.
In total, authorities estimate that more than 2,000 prisoners escaped across the country after collapse of the prison system. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:29:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumer prices fall again in August in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/precos-ao-consumidor-voltam-a-cair-em-agosto-na-china/</link><description>Consumer prices in China fell again in August, highlighting persistent deflationary pressures, while a more moderate decrease in the factory departure prices suggests an effect of Beijing's campaign against price wars.

The Consumer Price Index (IPC), the main indicator of inflation, retreated 0.4% in homologous terms last month, according to data released yesterday by the National Statistics Office (GNE) of the Asian country.
The value was below market expectations, after a poll from the Wind Financial Agency to predict a 0.2%drop. In July, the IPC remained unchanged from the same month of 2024.
The second largest economy in the world has been facing more than two years deflationist pressures, with poor internal demand and excessive industrial capacity to penalize prices, while uncertainty in international trade makes it difficult to flow from suppliers.
Deflation consists of a drop in prices over time, as opposed to a climb (inflation). The phenomenon reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly dangerous, as a drop in the price of assets, as a lawsuit under credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
Another effect is to lead to the postponement of consumer and investment decisions as a result of lower pricing expectations in the future, and can create a price -descendant spiral and difficult to reverse, affecting the entire economy.
The drop in prices began in 2022, with the devaluation of the most important active in China: residential real estate. The drop in the price of real estate led to a break from families' confidence, resulting in a contraction of consumption. This, coupled with the country's excessive production capacity, has fostered a price war between manufacturers and retailers, raising a deflationist spiral.
Beijing, however, took measures to end the price war. The Chinese Communist Party also promised last July to combat “irrational competition” in various sectors.
According to Dong Lijuan, the GNE statistic, the IPC drop resulted “mainly from the high comparative base of a year” and below -seasoning food prices. "By category, the main factor was the descent of food prices," he said, adding that underlying inflation accelerated for the fourth consecutive month, benefiting from the continuous impact of internal demand stimulus policies.
In August, the prices of consumer goods fell 1% compared to the same period of 2024, while the services rose 0.6%, the cabinet said. Food prices retreated 4.3%. Excluding food and energy, underlying inflation increased by 0.9% in homologous terms.
The Producer Price Index (IPP), which measures the evolution of factory exit price, fell 2.9% in August, noting the 35th consecutive month of contraction. The amount was in line with the 2.88% drop provided for by Wind, but represented an improvement compared to the 3.6% decrease in July.
According to Dong, the falling of the fall was reflected in the “continuous improvement of competition in the domestic market, which helped contain homologous descents in specific sectors”, signaling preliminary effects of the government campaign against the so-called “involution”-fierce competition between companies that have pressured prices on various sectors. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:29:49</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM received delegation visit from Paulista State University</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/upm-recebeu-visita-de-delegacao-da-universidade-estadual-paulista/</link><description>A delegation from Paulista State University (UNESP), headed by the vice-rector of the institution Cesar Martins, visited the Polytechnic University of Macau (UPM), where he was received by Vivian Law, a substitute dean. The two parts exchanged impressions on the reinforcement of exchange in higher education, the promotion of qualified framework training programs and the deepening of cooperation in scientific research.
During the meeting, Vivian Law said that "UPM has excellent teaching and research quality and continues to increase its international influence and position in the world ranking." In addition, "it has maintained close cooperation with higher education institutions and academic federations of Brazil, and obtained fruit results in international cooperation in the areas of scientific research, seminars of famous teachers and mobility of teachers and students."
The UPM recalls that this year is the 51st anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations between China and Brazil, intending to “unfold a diversified cooperation with UNESP in various areas, namely in scientific and technological innovation and the incubation of technologies, in order to contribute to the construction of the city (university) of Macao and Hengqin international education, and to the cooperation of higher education between China and the China and the China and the Higher Education and those between China and Portuguese -speaking countries ”.
In turn, Cesar Martins expressed the desire that the two higher education institutions could “continue to promote exchange in higher education, deepen cooperation in scientific research and stimulate the development of academic and scientific innovation of the two institutions”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:54:28</pubDate></item><item><title>CANDIDATURES FOR STD Financial Support Programs open on September 12</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/candidaturas-a-programas-de-apoio-financeiro-da-dst-abrem-a-12-de-setembro/</link><description>Applications to financial support programs “Travel by Macao”, “Macao Flavors” and “Coastal Waterfront” are open between 9am tomorrow and 5:30 pm on October 3, and should be presented on the “Financial Support Program for 2026” page of the Tourism Services (STD). Today, an 'online' clarification session will be held so that interested associations can get more information, upon pre-email registration.
The three thematic programs aim to support non -profit associations, legally constituted in Macao, to organize “Tourism +” projects. The first program, “Traveling through Macao”, aims to boost the flow of tourists and the economy in the Macau community neighborhoods by enriching cultural experiences in these zones, making them more attractive to visitors.
The Support Program “Flavors of Macao” combines tourism, gastronomy and creativity, by leading visitors to prove macau gastronomic products and promote the region as a “creative city of gastronomy”. The last program, “amusements in the coastal edge”, is intended to take advantage of Macau's sea and coastal areas to streamline diverse coastal tourism or leisure experiences.
After the reception period, the Tourism Fund will analyze proposals according to specific evaluation criteria for each program and disclose the results in December. Approved activities will be launched between January 1 and December 31, 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:32:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Chefs Alain Ducasse and Dong Zhexiang collaborate in a culinary event at City of Dreams</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/chefs-alain-ducasse-e-dong-zhexiang-colaboram-em-evento-culinario-no-city-of-dreams/</link><description>After a first collaboration in 2012, chefs Alain Ducasse and Dong Zhexiang (or Dong) meet in two planned dinners for October 8 and 9 at City of Dreams. Those interested in participating in this “culinary dialogue” between the two legends of the Alta-Kinha can book their place through contact with the Alain Ducasse at Morpheus restaurant.

The Alain Ducasse at Morpheus restaurant, located at the City of Dreams, will host a dinner organized by chefs Alain Ducasse and Dong Zhenxiang on October 8 and 9, at 7 pm.
The base price is 3,488 patacas for an eight dish menu, which can be complemented with six glasses of wine (for another 1,888 patacas), a combination of three types of tea and three glasses of wine (1,288 patacas) or just tea (188 patacas). City of Dreams warns in a statement that places for this gastronomic experience are limited and can be reserved through telephone contact with the restaurant, by 8868 3432.
Alain Ducasse and Dong Zhenxiang collaborated for the first time in 2012, at a meeting that took place on the prestigious “Jules-Verne” restaurant at the Eiffel Tower in Paris. Thirteen years old, the two great figures of gastronomy again meet for an “intercultural dialogue that transcends borders”, as the organization describes. “Each dish, refined over a decade as a vintage led to maturity, intertwines the deep philosophies and artistic sensitivities of both masters in true culinary consonance,” reads the document.
Of the eight dishes planned for the will, three are signed by Dong Zhenxiang and the remaining by Alain Ducasse. The Chinese chef, also known as “Dong”, is internationally recognized by flavors that mix Chinese culinary traditions with modern and international influences, merging the “beauty of Chinese cuisine in terms of color, aroma, taste and shape” with “the charm of oriental gastronomic aesthetics”. Its signature plate-a contemporary version of Pato to Beijing-was included in the Morpheus menu, which also includes shredded white tofu in black truffle soup and squid paint and sealed chives.
A legendary figure of French cuisine, chef Ducasse oversees almost 30 restaurants in nine countries. Many of these have been awarded Michelin stars - as is the case with Alain Ducasse at Morpheus, who will now receive this gastronomic experience. The five dishes elaborated by the European chef "reimaginate timeless French classics through a modern lens", giving rise to "deep but timeless creations."
These include spices decorated with spices and Kvistal caviar, 'vol-au-event' accompanied by blue lobster and veal gyclose, Xavier cheese with salad and figs and two desserts: Piemonte hazelnut delight with white truffle and chocolates from Parisian chocolate les manufacturers alain ducasse.
Guests are invited to be part of this “celebration of art, culture and creativity” in a “culinary dialogue” between “two legends” that brings together the best of western and eastern dining. Morpheus - awarded two Michelin stars and a “diamond seal” of Black Pearl Restaurant Guide - is “the perfect screen for this gastronomic encounter”, describes the City of Dreams, citing the elegance of furniture created by French artisans and the sophistication of the chandelier with more than 600 hand -cut crystals.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>South Korea and Austria in pyrotechnic confrontation in Macau Tower Bay</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/coreia-do-sul-e-austria-em-confronto-pirotecnico-na-baia-da-torre-de-macau/</link><description>The 33rd Macao International Fire Competition (CIFAM) continues this Saturday with the Pyrotechnic Companies of South Korea and Austria, which will feature fireworks in the Bay against the Macao Tower. The event will take place at 21h00 and 21h40, “helping to attract more visitors and promote the night economy in community neighborhoods,” says a statement from the Tourism Services Directorate (STD).
The South Korean company Hwarang Art Pyrotechnics, which participates for the first time at CIFAM, will present its musical and pyrotechnic performance with a creative design with South Korea characteristics, says STD. On September 13, at 21h00, it will present its exhibition under the theme “Universe of Lake”, an artistic interpretation of a legend of a shepherd and a weaver through the firefight.
The show of the Austrian company “Fireevent”, in turn, is scheduled for 9:40 pm. The company participated in CIFAM in 2011, 2015 and 2018, returning this year to compete in Macau. Under the theme “The Power of Harmony”, the company “will use the power of fire and music to enhance beauty and solidarity, share love, friendship and joy”, can be read in the STD statement.
The body recommends to the public the six best points of fire-to-fire viewing and to take photographs of the exhibitions, namely: on Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue from the Kun Ecumenical Center Age to the Marginal Leisure Zone of the Kun Iam statue, on the riverside tour of the Macao Science Center, on Sagres Avenue (next to the Mandarin East Hotel, Macau) Nam Van, on the marginal path of the lake (next to the Yoho Hotel Treasury Island Resorts World), and on Ocean Avenue in Taipa.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>David Hartung's artistic look at Sichuan's soul on exhibition on the mud</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/o-olhar-artistico-de-david-hartung-sobre-a-alma-de-sichuan-em-exposicao-na-taipa/</link><description>A photographic exhibition that transcends decades of experience within the studio, patent in Macao until November, reveals the cultural and human depth behind one of the strongest gastronomies in the region. Through the dedicated lenses of American photographer David Hartung, “The Flavors of Sichuan: A Tribute to the Art of Sichuan Cuisine” proposes a sensory journey to the flavors, traditions and faces that shape the unique identity of the Chinese province of Sichuan. It is scheduled to open for September 24 at 5:30 pm at the Village Art Space Taipa.

A show of delicacies, faces and villages of an intense people. Among the flavors of his fiery food, the polychrome of the figures reveals itself in the dedication of an artist specializing in the good table photograph. Taipa Village Art Space receives, from September 24 to November 26, an exhibition that promises to transport visitors to the heart of Sichuan province. The show, consisting of 34 color and black and white photographs, is by David Hartung, a US documentary photographer who has recorded, for most of his life, the cultural transformation of Asia.
The project, which began in 2019 and was interrupted by the pandemic, was resumed in 2023 with multiple trips to Chengdu. Hartung was not limited to photographing finished dishes. His view was to dive into the essence of gastronomic culture, exploring landscapes, rural communities and artisans. Guardians of centenary knowledge. From the hands of tofu masters to producers of fermented bean sauce, from farmers to chefs who dominate the complex palette of flavors in the region. In between the spicy, the aromatic, the narcotic and famous “suitcase”, the series builds a holistic portrait.
The exhibition coincides with the release of a photography book of the same name, a great edition that expands the visual narratives now presented in Macau. The curator of the exhibition, Pamela Chan, underlines the perfect sync between the theme and the place: Macau, like Chengdu, is a creative city of UNESCO's cuisine, becoming the ideal stage for this celebration.
Hartung's narrative goes beyond the surface portrait of dishes. Through documentary work of breath, the photographer captures the intersection between history, geography and people. The province, once a crucial axis of the old tea horses route, has unique microclm and soils that dictate the availability of singular ingredients. However, the exhibition argues, through the images, that the true soul of Sichuan's kitchen lies in human wisdom transmitted between generations.
As curator Pamela Chan points out, Sichuan's wealth is also a product of its deeply connected history. The province, once a vital artery of the regional food market, prospered through centuries of trade and cultural exchanges with Tibet and Yunnan. These historical routes, which still throb, brought influences that merged and enriched the local gastronomic identity, creating a harmonious mix of history, culture and traditional culinary techniques.
For David Hartung, based in Macao since 2008, this project is the culmination of a decade of progressive focus in the gastronomic world. His previous work, including books such as “Macao Remends” and “Cafes of Taipei”, demonstrate a unique appetite to tell stories through material culture. Now it raises this mission, using food as a guiding thread to explore identity, memory and belonging.
The exhibition is both a photographic show and an invitation to a sensory journey, where photographs made in the professional studio style enhance the almost palpable core and flavors. It is a tribute to the details that define a region and, above all, to the hands that create them.
The exhibition “The Flavors of Sichuan: A Tribute to the Art of Sichuan Cuisine” will be open to the public from Tuesday to Sunday, from 12h00 to 20h00, at Taipa Village Art Space, after the opening scheduled for September 24, at 5:30 pm. The entrance is free. The project has the support of the Fund for Cultural Development.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Montenegro went through Macau with the “firm purpose of taking further” cooperation relationship</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/montenegro-passou-por-macau-com-o-firme-proposito-de-levar-mais-longe-relacao-de-cooperacao/</link><description>Luís Montenegro was, yesterday morning, visiting Macau. The Portuguese Prime Minister said he wanted to “take further” the relationship of cooperation between Portugal and the Economic, Social, Cultural and Historical level. From the meeting with Sam Hou Fai, he removed the promise that Masters also wants to deepen the relationship with Portugal and that there will be a more agile regime for the assignment of residence to Portuguese citizens. Au Kam San's arrest was not addressed with local authorities because "there are matters that deserve some modesty."

In a short time in Macau, Luís Montenegro made it clear that the purpose of the visit was to reiterate “the firm purpose of taking further” the “cooperation relationship”, as well as the “preservation of a connection that has been fruit - despite having its problems, is part of the history of sharing”.
The Portuguese prime minister was yesterday morning in the territory as part of the itinerary of a visit to Asia. In a delegation, which was also part of Paulo Rangel, Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, and Manuel Castro Almeida, Minister of Economics and Territorial Cohesion, Montenegro was in Beijing between Monday and Tuesday. After visiting Macao, who lasted only one morning, the Portuguese Prime Minister went on a trip to Japan.

“More agile” regime for the assignment of residence to Portuguese

At Mishes, yesterday started with a meeting with Sam Hou Fai. After the reception organized at the consular residence, Luís Montenegro spoke to journalists and said that one of the topics discussed with the head of the Executive of the MSAR was the restrictions on the attribution of new titles of residence for citizens of Portugal. This is a matter that dates back to 2023, when the MSar authorities failed to accept new requests for residence for Portuguese on the basis of “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing only by family meeting or previous connection to the territory. Since then, the Portuguese authorities have indicated that they are in contact with Macau to resolve the issue.
"Things are referred so that we can have the consecration of a more agile, easier, more expedition regime," said the prime minister, stressing that this solution will allow "to overcome this embarrassment that we know exists." The leader of the Portuguese government explained that the goal is that "the dynamics are as easily as possible, that the rules are fast and shape not to disagree with this positive mobility."
Montenegro was optimistic, highlighting the “positive phase” of the relationship between the two parties in the economic, social, cultural, historical and identity realm. "We want to continue to comply with a mutual cooperation relationship based on the documents that presided over the transition [sovereignty], which turned 25 last year and attributes responsibilities to all," he said, revealing that Sam Hou Fai "proved highly cooperative and sensitized" to "deepen this relationship."
In a statement issued by the Government of MSar on the meeting between Sam and Montenegro, it is read that both parties “exchanged opinions on how to enhance the unique role of Macau in the process of consolidating and reinforcing friendly relations between China and Portugal, and the continuous strengthening of exchange and cooperation between Macao and Portugal”.
Quoted in the statement, Sam Hou Fai stressed that “the government of MSAR has always attributed, throughout its development, great importance to the protection and respect for the rights, customs and cultural traditions of the Portuguese residents of Macao, proactively promoting the teaching and diffusion of the Portuguese language”. In addition, at the governmental level, “MSAR has maintained good communication and exchange with the Portuguese part,” says the press release.
Photography Eloi Carvalho
Au Kam San detention was not a conversation subject

Since the purpose of the visit was cement ties and preserving a connection with the MSA, Luís Montenegro decided not to talk about the arrest of Au Kam San at the meeting with Sam Hou Fai.
It is recalled that the Democrat and former deputy to the Legislative Assembly of Macao, who has Portuguese citizenship, was arrested in late July. The Judicial Police (PJ) said there were "strong evidence" of Au acted "in collusion for a long time with external forces" and urged the hatred against Beijing, "seriously endangered the security of the state." Its detention was the first related to the State Security Defense Law in the history of MSAR.
Although the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Portugal was guaranteed at the end that the subject deserves “the best attention of the Portuguese authorities, rightly in future meetings at the political level”, Luís Montenegro did not want to talk about the subject with SAM because “there are subjects that deserve some modesty in treatment and this is one of them”. The Prime Minister still said that this is a theme that the Portuguese Government accompanies, but “with the necessary discretion”. Montenegro did not mean whether Portugal provided any kind of support to the detained Democrat.
Balanced the 25 years after the transfer of sovereignty from Macao, from Portugal to China, Montenegro said it has been a path in which it was possible to “safeguard the most relevant interests and contribute to the economic and social development of this territory”. This path "is not exempt from tensions and obstacles, as in all processes that imply changes."
At the same press conference, the prime minister said that the next meeting of the Macao-Portuguese Joint Commission will be held at the 4th to 6th of February next year.
 
Many compliments to the Portuguese community
Photography Eloi Carvalho
At noon, the Portuguese community was in weight at the consul's official residence to see members of the Portuguese government. This occasion was used by the Prime Minister to leave praise for the Portuguese who reside in Macao.
“I mean that we attribute special importance to those here in the most varied activities, which bring the values ​​of Portugal and carry and preserve the Portuguese culture and tradition, being a link between our countries and our peoples, and can, through your work, take the concrete result of the various areas in which we have come to cooperate,” said Montenegro in his speech, highlighting the “deep share bonds” allows. The Portuguese ruler also spoke about the preservation of the Portuguese language as “identity factor, irreplaceable and also as a factor of approximation”.
Addressing to the Portuguese in Macau, Montenegro said: “All manifestations of economic, social and civic activity that provide, on this side or on the side of Portugal, [allows] we can take the effort to build societies with prosperity, wealth creation and give opportunities to all, leave no one behind, promote equality of opportunities and social justice”.
“We count on you to be - our diplomats do not harm me - our privileged ambassadors on the ground, those who represent our values, our interests, our ambition to be more productive, to build our society more prosperously and also to help the other peoples of the world find the way to justice and for equal opportunities,” he said. "It is this spirit that corresponds to our history of almost nine centuries of universal vocation that brought us here, that does not let us get out of here and that projects to the future."
Montenegro ended the speech underlining that the Portuguese in Macau can count on the Portuguese government, and that the Portuguese government also has the Portuguese in Macau.

EPM is “very important active”

Between the meeting with the Chief Executive and the reception at the Consular Residence, Luís Montenegro went to visit the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM). Acácio de Brito, director of the institution, and Jorge Neto Valente, president of the EPM foundation, among others, accompanied the prime minister on the visit to the facilities. Montenegro unveiled a sign that marks his passage through the school, listened to the Chinese and Portuguese anthem sung by a group of students and first saw the recent works carried out in that institution. He also had a meeting with those responsible for the institution.
In a brief statement to journalists after a visit to the school, the prime minister began by pointing out that the EPM “is a very important active” to which the Portuguese Government attributes a “great strategic relevance in the promotion of Portuguese teaching and also in the possibility of giving conditions of training and qualification to many hundreds of young people every year”. "The interest of the government will always be to support the preservation of our identity, our culture, our projection in the world," he said.
Montenegro also stressed that the Portuguese presence in Macau is “synonymous with our universal vocation and our perspective of looking into the world and contributing to the development of all geographies”, within the idea of ​​“valuing people and the idea of ​​progress and development that promotes peace, social justice, respect for people's rights”.
Neto Valente was pleased for Montenegro's visit and said that the Portuguese government promised “all the commitment” to collect the needs of the EPM. The president of the foundation also said that the problems with the teachers are remedied. Now, Neto Valente has advanced, the EPM is finding difficulties at local level, as Macao authorities are taking time to approve the schools that the school wants to bring from Portugal and, in addition, the direction of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) is “interfering” in the institution's pedagogical autonomy. "There are disagreements in the way of appreciating the skills of teachers" that EPM wants to recruit, but "who has to say which teachers are competent and qualified to give the Portuguese curriculum in Macao is the school."</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:37:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Muslim tourism should grow in the second semester</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/turismo-muculmano-deve-crescer-no-segundo-semestre/</link><description>The tourism sector in Macao predicts that the flow of visitors from the Middle East will grow in the second half of this year. Andy Wu, president of the Macao Tourist Association, note that the arrival of this visitors' layer Macau has been increasing “gradually” since July, when the new visa exemption measured for five countries came into force: Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Barém and Oman.

The president of the Macao Tourist Industry Association revealed that the tourist market originated in the Middle East has been increasing since July, providing for a gradual increase in the number of Muslim visitors over the second half of this year.
Speaking to Cheng Pou newspaper, Andy Wu said that visa exemption for five Middle East countries - a measure implemented in July - has encouraged "gradual" growth of this tourist market in Macao, although it comes "a time for adjustments." Nevertheless, the official considered that the “exclusive” focus on the Middle East visitors “is neither objective nor particularly significant” in the general framework of international visitors, since this slice of tourists still occupies an unin -significant place in the international tourist market.
As Andy Wu recalls, the flow of halal travelers is currently represented, above all, by the tourists of Malaysia and Indonesia, two Muslim countries that appear on the list of the top ten markets of international visitors. According to statistical tables published in the Macao Tourism Data Plus, a platform of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), Indonesia occupies the 6th place on the list with 119,492 visitors between January and July, while Malaysia appears in 7th place with 98,361 people.
At the same newspaper, the president of the Macau Tourist Association pointed out that the reinforcement of the 'Halal' options in Macau will “improve tourists' experiences and enrich their travels”, while contributing to the diversification of the international visitors market and the recovery numbers recovery. Andy Wu cites as a reference the growing flow of visitors from South Korea and India, increasingly expressive in recent years, resulting in the opening of several restaurants that serve these types of customers and their culinary preferences.

Focus on the Muslim Market

The visa exemption policy for 30 days for national citizens of Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Barém and Oman was announced in June and officially entered into force on 16 July.
The measure was announced at a time when the Macao government seeks to attract a Muslim market through the offer of 'halal' options in the territory and boosting large -scale tourist campaigns in Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, Indonesia and Malaysia. The most recent campaign took place in late August, when STD and several tourist operators of Macau were present at the Indonesian International Tourism Fair. STD has already announced that it will return to the country in October for a new large -scale tourism promotion.
In 2025, for the first time, Macau began to appear in 16th place in the overall ranking of the Global Muslim Travel Index - GMTI), published by Crescecentrating and Mastercard. Recognition was largely due to the publication of a tourist guide specifically conceived for Muslims, with the dissemination of relevant cultural and gastronomic aspects and recommendations of its own itineraries to this layer of visitors, evaluated according to Islamic law.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:58:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services want to “break taboos” on World Suicide Prevention Day</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/servicos-de-saude-querem-quebrar-tabus-no-dia-mundial-da-prevencao-do-suicidio/</link><description>Health services marked World Suicide Prevention Day with a statement in which they made known the Mental Health Support Network in Macao. Currently, nine territory health centers offer external mental health and psychotherapy consultations, while the Conde de São Januário Hospital Psychiatry Department (CHCSJ) has a 24 -hour emergency service.

World Suicide Prevention Day was pointed out yesterday, September 10, and health services marked the occasion with a statement stressing the need to “break taboos” and raise awareness of mental health problems.
The date was chosen in 2003 by the International Association for Suicide Prevention, in conjunction with the World Health Organization (WHO). The theme for the years 2024 to 2026 is "Changing the Narrative on Suicide", encouraging a collective discussion about suicidal behaviors and various ways to ask for help and prevent mental health crises.
In this context, health services highlight in a statement that the causes of suicide are “complex” and related to “diverse factors”, so the entire population - from health professionals to “residents and various sectors of society” - should play together the “guardian role” and listen, help and encourage people with emotional problems to look for support tools.
In addition to the Caritas open line, available 24 hours a day through number 2852 5222, individuals suffering from emotional disturbances can consult the electronic health service information page of health services, available in Chinese and Portuguese. In this platform, it is possible to collect information about the physiological, cognitive and emotional consequences of stress episodes, read a series of answers to “frequent questions” about mental disturbances, learn relaxation techniques and self-assessment of the psychological state through four mental health diagnostic tests, depression, anxiety and sleep health.
The 'website' also includes a section designed to demystify “frequent misconceptions” about suicide, as the preconceived ideas that “mental patients only commit suicide” or that “who speaks of suicide just wants to draw the attention of others”. Health services explain that the persistence of these myths about suicide within society contributes to losing so “the opportunity to save lives” and support those who need it.
In the statement, the authorities remember that external mental health and psychotherapy consultations have been created in nine health centers and have been subsidizing two non -profit institutions for the provision of psychological consultations, with the aim of widening this service network. The Psychiatry Service of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ) also took measures to support more urgent cases with the availability of psychiatric specialists in the emergency service, in service for 24 hours, and the creation of a contact mechanism with health centers and social service institutions.
Health services report that they are also striving to “actively spread the importance of mental health” by promoting community activities and thematic lectures, intended for different age groups, in “All Macao Zones”. According to the data provided by the authorities, between June and August this year, there was the participation of more than 17,700 people in the multiple activities organized in this regard, such as the “seminar on the mental and psychological health of children and adolescents or the activity“ exercise for all, strengthening body and mind ”.
The statement emphasizes that the work of awareness of mental health problems in Macau is a government priority, which has collaborated in this sense with health services, the Institute of Social Action (IAS), the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) and other social institutions.
The most recent statistics show a growing trend in the number of suicides committed in the MSAR: If the year 2023 had already been highlighted by reaching the highest number of the last decade, 88, the total of 2024 victims has reached 90. This is the highest number of suicide cases since at least 2013, the last year to reassemble the records of health services and the direction of statistics services and Census (DSEC).</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 23:34:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Contest proposes to young people to draw the identity of the city through the comics</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/10/concurso-propoe-a-jovens-desenhar-a-identidade-da-cidade-atraves-da-banda-desenhada/</link><description>The “ninth art” comes to give new life to the streets of Macau. Somos Somos Association of Portuguese Language Communication (ACLP) has just launched the first “BD-Macau” visual art competition, a biannual contest that challenges young people residents of telling stories of the city through the comic band. With open registrations until October 5, the initiative aims to foster local creation and immortalize, in black and white or in color, the urban landscape and the cultural uniqueness of the territory.

Somos ACLP is looking for the next generation of artists from Macau. Not in the art of painting, nor the installation or photography, but among the comic books of the comic. The association launches the first edition of the “BD-Macau” visual art competition, a contest and workshop directed to young people residents between 15 and 25, with the clear objective of encouraging them to create original drawn bands with and about the city.
The project, which will have a biennial periodicity, starts with free theme, giving card the creativity of the participants. There are, however, requirements that anchor the stories in local reality: narratives must unfold in Macau, highlighting their sociocultural specificities and urban landscape. Each work must have a minimum of four boards (a set of strips) and, if you include text, it must be written in one of the official languages: Chinese or Portuguese.
To equip aspiring authors with the necessary tools, the Association organizes an optional workshop on October 11, with a cost of 100 patacas. The training will be in charge of two experienced names: Wesley Chan, president of Hyper Comic Society, and Rodrigo de Matos, a recognized and resident cartoonist in Macao. The session will address design, character creation techniques and narrative development, serving as a valuable project incubator.
O prazo para inscrições no workshop termina a 5 de Outubro, enquanto os trabalhos finais devem ser submetidos entre 12 de Outubro e 30 de Novembro. O júri, composto pelos dois formadores e por Natacha Fidalgo, representante da Somos ACLP, avaliará as obras com base na sua originalidade, qualidade artística e na forma como retratam a identidade de Macau.
The first three classifieds will be awarded 7,000 patacas monetary awards to the winner, 4,000 patacas for second place and 2,000 patacas for the third. In addition to financial recognition, the association leaves the possibility of a book edition that brings together the best bands designed in the contest, depending on the qualitative assessment of the jury.
The initiative presents itself as a proposal of Somos ACLP to stimulate local cultural production and contribute to the imagetic registration of mutations and the progress of the city, as well as a simple contest. By fostering the Macao theme comic band, the Association exposes the territory as a place of cultural confluence and a sino-illusopone basis, perpetuating its architectural and historical richness through the trace of its young people.
The “BD-Macau” visual art competition is sponsored by the Culture Development Fund and the support of the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR).
Registration for the “BD-Macau” visual art competition should be made through the Somos ACLP website, where the full regulation and workshop program are available.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>