<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/china-mantem-objectivo-de-colocar-astronautas-na-lua-antes-do-final-de-2030/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>North Korea condemns a US aircraft carrier visit to Porto Sul-Korean</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/coreia-do-norte-condena-visita-de-porta-avioes-dos-eua-a-porto-sul-coreano/</link><description>North Korea yesterday condemned the visit to Busan, in South Korea, US Nuclear Airparts USS Carl Vinson, considering the maneuver a "political and military provocation." "The cruel maneuvers of the United States for the confrontation [with North Korea] were intensified in March with the appearance of Carl Vinson on the Korean peninsula," said Kim Yo Jong, sister of leader Kim Jong Un, according to official news agency KCNA.
"Since the arrival of the new government this year, the United States has increased political and military provocations against North Korea and" continued the hostile policy of the former government, "added Kim Yo Jong, one of the regime's leading spokesmen.
The USS Carl Vinson, a chief ship of a San Diego-based attack group in California, arrived in Busan on Sunday for a visit scheduled for Sunday, according to the US Navy. "The visit to Busan demonstrates the commitment of the United States to the region, strengthening relations with the leadership of the Republic of Korea and the local population," said the US force in a statement.
The aircraft carrier should participate in the annual “Freedom Shield” sets with South Korea within a few days.
Military cooperation between Seoul and Washington is regularly convicted of Pyongyang, who considers her to invade her territory and often retaliates with missile tests.
Kim Yo Jong criticized "the hostile policy of the United States," which, according to her, is "sufficient justification (for North Korea) indefinitely strengthens her nuclear determination force."
North Korea justifies its nuclear weapons program for the threats it says to face from the United States and its allies, including South Korea.
US President Donald Trump who had a rare series of meetings with Kim Jong Un during his first term, said in an interview that he would contact the North Korean leader, whom he called the "smart type."</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:36+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire in Toi San caused five injuries and forced the withdrawal of 300 people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/incendio-em-toi-san-provocou-cinco-feridos-e-obrigou-a-retirada-de-300-pessoas/</link><description>Five people were injured in a fire in the Toi San area, near the siege doors on Monday night, including two children who suffered serious burns. The fire occurred in Block II of Jardim Cidade building and will also have caused an explosion, causing several objects to fall to the street. The firefighters revealed that the cause of the fire was a gas escape. The incident forced the withdrawal of a hundred families, a total of about 300 people.
 
A fire in a residential building in the North Zone caused five injuries and a gas leakage will have been the cause. The fire took place in Block II of Jardim Cidade Building, in the area of ​​Toi San, on Monday night around 9 pm. The incident that occurred in the 19th of the building also caused the fall of objects to the Pou Choni Rua, including a washing machine, bedding, windows of windows and glasses.
The five injured were sent to the hospital for medical treatment, and three people, who needed immediate help due to burns, are residents of the fraction where the fire was recorded.
According to the Fire Department (CB), quoted by Radio Macau in Chinese language, a two -year -old boy and an eight -year -old girl suffered a third degree burns, considered a severe degree, with a 20% and 25% burning level, respectively. A 53 -year -old maid suffered second -degree burns, with a burn level of about 35%. The three were aware when they were taken to the hospital unit.
A 66 -year -old elderly person, who resident in another fraction on the 19th floor of the building, needed medical care due to the inhalation of smoke, and a 20 -year -old woman who passed through the area was injured due to the fall of objects, having suffered a laceration on her right -hand man.
At a press conference, the authorities advanced that the fire forced the withdrawal of about 100 families involving 300 people. A total of 19 emergency vehicles and 67 firefighters were mobilized for the operation, including CB's special relief team to reinforce the service.
Lam Chon Sang, CB's second commander, said the body received the fire notification at 21h05 and the team arrived in the scene within five minutes. Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, the official added that the door's elevators were signs of having been hit by an explosion, namely the 19th floor elevators.
"The fact that the elevators did not work made it difficult to rescue work and at the same time prevented the water connection process," Lam Chon Sang explained, indicating that the firefighters had to move to the floor. The fire was extinguished in two minutes after the water supply connection, the firefighters pointed out.
Several residents in the area said they heard an explosion. The CB, upon arriving at the scene, immediately turned off the building's gas system and notified the gas company to attend the place for inspection. The body also requested the direction of soil services and urban construction to send personnel to verify the safety of the building's structure.
 
IAS Provides Help
 
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) said it was aware of the fire and were sent social workers to the site to provide necessary support to affected families. According to a statement, the IAS Island Ilha do IAS island center can provide temporary reception services and make basic life equipment available to needy. It is appealed to residents with needs to call number 28261126 in order to obtain proper services and supports.
Several community service associations also sent employees to the scene to support residents. According to IAS, the Community Center of Tamagnini Barbosa of the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) is open to residents who need temporary shelter, and there are currently about 30 residents affected to remain in this center.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:52:32+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Military Budget is 'strong dish' of the annual session of the maximum legislative agency of China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/orcamento-militar-e-prato-forte-da-sessao-anual-do-orgao-legislativo-maximo-da-china/</link><description>China should announce today the military budget for 2025, at the opening of the annual session of the country's maximum legislative agency, at a time when the United States proposes an agreement to reduce defense expenses.
 
Analysts consider that the most likely to spend on the Armed Forces continue to increase, like what has happened in recent decades.
Beijing argues that the increases are "appropriate and reasonable" and aim to face "complex security challenges" and insists that their military modernization "does not constitute a threat to any country."
In eastern Asia and southern Pacific, however, China has adopted a more assertive stance, which resulted in successive picardies with neighboring countries, including Japan, Philippines or Vietname, and has caused the apprehension of Australia and New Zealand, as Beijing widens its influence on the region's small island nations.
In recent years, Beijing's expenses with his Armed Forces have stabilized in annual growth rates of about 7.2% of the Chinese state budget. Last year, this value ascended to 1.67 billion of Yuan.
Analysts believe, however, that China's actual expense with the defense is significantly higher than the announced in the official budget. "If they significantly divert this growth rate of about 7%, whether above or below it, I think this will be significant," wrote Brian Hart, director-help and member of the American Think Tank (') Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS). “I also think it will be significant if we see the [Chinese] employees to abandon the longstanding statements that defense expenses are linked to GDP growth. I do not foresee that they change these things, but they are certainly aspects to take into account, ”he said.
In addition to having the world's largest permanent army, China has the largest navy and recently launched its third aircraft carrier. The country has a huge reserve of missiles, fighters, war ships capable of throwing nuclear weapons, advanced surface ships and nuclear -powered submarines.
On the other hand, China has a military base in Djibuti, in the horn of Africa, and modernized the Ream naval base in Cambodia, which offers him a semi -permanent presence in the Gulf of Thailand, facing the disputed Southern China Sea.
The modernization effort has generated concerns between the United States and allies, which fear China Invada Taiwan. Beijing claims the territory, which acts as a sovereign political entity, as its province, which must be forcibly reunited if necessary.
Last year, Taiwan's Air Defense Identification Zone (ADIZ) raids in China (ADIZ) increased by about 80%in homologous terms, reflecting the growing military pressure on the island, since the William Lai has reached the power.
Regarding the statements of US President Donald Trump, who proposed a summit with Chinese President Xi Jinping and Russian President Vladimir Putin to negotiate a reduction in defense budgets of the three great powers, Beijing Countertops that Washington is expected to take the initiative. "Once it appeals to 'America First', Trump should take the initiative to reduce military expenses," replied the spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry, Guo Jiakun, at a press conference. "China's limited expense with the defense is entirely necessary to safeguard national sovereignty, security and its development interests, as well as to protect world peace," he said.
The National Popular Assembly (APN), whose annual session runs until March 11, is made up of about 3,000 delegates, including a representation of the Armed Forces. Delegates are not, however, elected by direct suffrage, and the "leading role" of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) is "a cardial principle." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Literary festival brings poetry to the inner port between March 21 and 30</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/festival-literario-leva-poesia-ao-porto-interior-entre-os-dias-21-e-30-de-marco/</link><description>The 14th edition of Rota das Letras - Macao Literary Festival will take place between March 21 and 30. The festival returns this year to the Barra Zone and has as its main theme poetry. The 50th anniversary of the end of the colonial war and the 100th anniversary of Lin-Tchi-Fá publication, Lotus flower, will also be focused. Lisbon Poetry Orchestra, Xana, Xu Jinjin, Valério Romão and António Costa Silva, among others, will be present.
 
The 14th Route of Letters - Macau Literary Festival will take place between March 21 and 30, the organization announced. In this edition, the event returns to the Barra area and will have as its theme poetry, as happened in 2019.
The festival's program has two dozen lectures, three exhibitions, a movie cycle, a concert, visits to schools and photography and creative writing workshops. The detailed program will be released soon by the organization.
The usual musical part, which takes place on March 29, will be in charge of Lisbon Poetry Orchestra, which makes its debut in Macao. The band will present a show entitled “The Surrealists”, bringing as a special guest Xana, the vocalist of Radio Macau. The Poetry &amp; Music, from the former responsible for the organization of the Beijing Literary Festival, Anthony Tao, will make the first part of the concert, with a performance that will have as its theme “The Myth of Writing”.
Since the focal point of this edition is poetry, Rota das Letras brings Macau several Chinese poets, such as Xu Jinjin, an interdisciplinary artist who divides his time between Shanghai and New York, exposing his works regularly in museums of both cities. Xu Jinjin was recently awarded by the American Society of Poetry. Xu Jinjin join, among other poets, Valério Romão, from Portugal, Zang Di and Jia Wei, from Beijing, Chan Ka Long and Wang Shanshan, from Macao. Poetry recites, presentations of new books, lectures and workshops will take place in the building of the former Municipal Slaughterhouse.
The occasion will serve to mark the 100th anniversary of the publication of Lin-Tchi-Fá, Flor de Lotus, a book of poems by Maria Anna Acciaioli Tamagnini. At the festival, unpublished translations of the work to Chinese and English will be launched.
The Rota das Letras will also mark the 50th anniversary of the end of the colonial war and independence of the Portuguese -speaking African countries through an exhibition of Portuguese photojournalist Alfredo Cunha, who covered these historical events. In addition, director Luís Filipe Rocha, who adapted to the cinema the novel “Your Face will be the last”, by João Ricardo Pedro and also addresses the theme of decolonization, returns to Macao, after, in the late 1980s, the programming of TDM and filmed “Love and Foot”, an adaptation of Henrique de Senna Fernandes.
Still within the theme of decolonization, Macau António Costa Silva, writer, poet, essayist and former Portuguese Minister of Economics and Sea, will come. António Costa Silva will present in the territory the novel “Dismissed Angola”, over a period lived half a century, “when in the midst of a fratricidal war was sought to build the Angolan nation”.
Chen Jiming, vice president of the Guangdong Writers Association, will also be present. Throughout his career he has collected literary distinctions, including the annual prize of Chinese literature for the best novelist, the people's literary award and China Good Book Award, among others. “City of Seven Steps” and “Monologue out loud” are two of the author's most awarded novels.
They will also be part of this edition of the Rota das Letras authors of English. British writer Paul French brings to the festival his last two works: “Her Lotus Year”, a biographical of Wallis Spencer, “Winsor Duchess,” about the period he lived in China during the 1920s; and “Destination Macao”, a collection of stories about some of the most fascinating figures in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. Hong Kong's Tony Banham presents the result of his investigation into the sinking of the Lisbon Maru ship. Thomas Dubois, a Beijing -based author, makes known to China in “Seven Banquets”, a deep study of the history of Chinese cuisine.
Books for the youngest will be taken to schools by Chen Shige, the first post-Annos 80 writer to gain the highest distinction of children's literature in China, and by André Letria, a Portuguese illustrator and editor who already has several of his works published in Chinese language. Hong Kong's illustrator Sophia Hotung comes to the festival to share his art with the Macao audience.
On the eve of the festival's opening, Wang Zhengping, considered one of the great masters of Chinese photographs, inaugurates in the Tap Seac Gallery, the exhibition “The Wind blows on the prairie”, a poetic look at the fields of pasture of the inner Mongolia and who inhabits them. Rao Yongxia, Wang's disciple, followed her footsteps and shows her work days later at the Holy House of Mercy Hostel gallery.
The event, organized by the Arts and Letters Society and Prail Editions, is sponsored by MGM Macau, also with the support of the Culture Development Fund and other entities.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Exhibition portrays the inheritance of Porcelain Cantonesa around the world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/exposicao-retrata-a-heranca-da-porcelana-cantonesa-pelo-mundo/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation gallery yesterday opened the exhibition “Return to Navigation”, by artist Lei Iat Po. The show, which includes about 40 pieces of large porcelain of Macao and Guangzhou, features the rich inheritance of Porcelain Cantonese around the world. It will be on display until March 14 and entry is free.
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) inaugurated yesterday the exhibition “Return to Navigation”, by ceramist Law IAT PO, which brings together an engaging collection of Porcelain works of Macao and Guangzhou. This show, curated by Margareth Lei Siu Heng, features about 40 pieces of colorful porcelain in the traditional style of the artist province collected by the artist over years of study in practice. Relics that act as a testimony of the cultural and artistic legacy of past Chinese dynasties, as well as symbols of an old Chinese economy, which already had its progress in the global panorama of product exports, highlighting the Rio das Pearl Delta as the center of this activity.
Canton porcelain, also known as Guangcai, dates back to the Qing Dynasty, when manufacturing has consolidated itself as an important industry for export. This type of porcelain has become extremely popular in European courts and among the western aristocracy, playing a crucial role in promoting Chinese culture in the West during the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
The exhibition reveals the essence of this type of porcelain, famous for its palette of strong and glazed glazen colors, as well as its intricate patterns and golden -painted golden applications. The development of this ceramic art was not limited to mainland China. In the twentieth century, porcelain production gained new vitality in territories such as Hong Kong and Macau, especially after instability in production in the rest of the country. The 1950s attended radical growth in international demand for these exotic pieces, reflecting the taste for oriental products at the time of the war, especially in Europe and America. Many of these pieces carried a stamp in his shim where he read "made in Macau".
Law IAT PO, the artist behind the exhibition at the FRC gallery, is a living example of this tradition. Born in Macao in 1954, his interest in porcelain art was shaped since childhood, influenced by his father, who was directly involved in the production and export of pieces to the European and American market. Law IAT PO worked at your father's Guangcai Wooden Basis Factory and, later, at the Guangcai Colorful Porcelain factory. Throughout his career, the artist had the opportunity to learn from traditional masters, such as renowned master Zhao Zhuo, perfecting his painting and coloring techniques.
Exposed works are not only exceptional examples of a technical skill developed after years of practice, but also represent a rich fusion between oriental and western cultures. The dedication of law IAT PO to preserving this art and its rich history is palpable in each of the pieces presented, according to the organization's statement.
Those interested in visiting this exhibition will have the opportunity to appreciate these works until March 14th. Entry is free.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Philippines launch missing military hunting mission</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/filipinas-lancam-missao-de-resgate-de-caca-militar-desaparecido/</link><description>The Philippine Air Force declared yesterday the disappearance of a military fighter after the aircraft loses communication during a night mission, and launched an operation to locate the two pilots. “Shortly after midnight March 4, 2025, a FA-50 fighter disappeared during a nightly tactic operation. The aircraft lost contact with the rest of the formation involved in the mission, minutes before reaching the target area, ”the Philippine Air Force said in a statement.
The remaining planes involved in the operation failed to establish immediate contact with the South Korean manufacturing hunt, which led military authorities to announce an “extensive and thorough search operation”.
The condition of the pilots is unknown, with the Air Force manifested "Hope to locate them soon."
The plane disappeared during a night-supporting night operation, which fought insurgents in the southern Philippines, the US Agency Associated Press wrote.
The country acquired 12 FA-50 fighters from 2015 from Korea Aerospace Industries Ltd., by 18.9 billion of Philippines (315 million euros), as part of a military modernization program, which was repeatedly paralyzed for lack of funds.
In addition to rebel operations, fighters have been used in a series of activities, from large national ceremonies to patrolling the disputed Southern Sea of ​​China.
In recent years, the Philippines have recorded several accidents with military aircraft, the last of which in February, when a US military man and three people linked to the defense sector died during a recognition mission.
The deadliest accident in the recent history of the archipelago involving a military plane occurred in July 2021, when a C-130 Hercules quadrimotor fired in an aerodrome on the southern island of Jolo, causing 50 dead and 53 wounded.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:36+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao members at CCPPC suggest reinforcing the exchange of qualified frames in the Great Bay</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/membros-de-macau-na-ccppc-sugerem-reforco-de-intercambio-de-quadros-qualificados-na-grande-baia/</link><description>Yesterday the third session of the 14th National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Advisory Conference. Macao representatives in this political advisory agency have said they will focus on topics such as the formation of qualified pictures and their exchange in the Great Bay, namely in the area of ​​science and innovative technology. Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macao Council of the Council of State affairs, said he hoped that CCPPC members will contribute to the prosperity and stability of the regions.
 
Local education, the formation and attraction of qualified staff and the academic exchange are among the topics that Macao representatives in the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) will address the agency's annual session, which started yesterday and will end next Monday.
Chen Jimin, academic and also secretary of the University Council of Science and Technology of Macao, said that at this year's session will give priority to the development of higher education, talent formation and macao's innovative science and technology.
“Higher education is an important development vehicle and innovative technology will be a starting point. I hope Macao focuses on talent formation, attracting qualified paintings to promote the integrated construction of science and technological education, ”he said in statements to the newspaper or Mun.
The university professor recalled that during Xi Jinping's visit to Macau last year, the Chinese president expressed his support that Macau becomes an international high -level talent center. "Macao, in this case, should take the opportunity of the great bay and hengqin to achieve this goal."
In addition, another CCPPC member Kou Kam Fai said he will make proposals on the education and physical and mental health of young people. The deputy considers that the realization of the National Games this year will be a good occasion to promote the exchange of talented athletes between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau.
“The most important thing is that it can promote patriotic education, especially the process of fighting athletes and the conquest of the country's honor in sport. I believe it is a learning opportunity for young people in Macao, ”he said.
The director of the Secondary School was concerned concerned about the health of young people, particularly in the postpedemic era. Thus, Kou Kam Fai will propose measures to reduce the pressure of school work on students, improve teacher education and promote healthy development of family relationships.
In turn, Fanny Vong, dean of the University of Tourism of Macao, suggests facilitating the entry into Macau by qualified paintings outside the MSAR, such as talents from the areas of finance, conventions and exhibitions, and arts, coming from Beijing, Tianjin and Hebei, as well as those of the Yangtze River Delta, such as Shanghai and Hangzhou.
 
Meeting with Xia Baolong
 
Macao members at CCPPC arrived on Monday at Beijing and attended a meeting with Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong work office and Macau of the China Communist Party Central Committee and director of the Hong Kong and Macau affairs to the Council of State.
According to a statement, Xia Baolong welcomed members of Hong Kong and Macau at CCPPC and expressed hope that they “conscientiously fulfill their duties and responsibilities,” actively participating in the discussion of policies.
It also hopes that members “implement full and accurately need the principle of 'a country, two systems' and fully support the executive's heads and the Raes governments in governance in accordance with the law.” For Xia Baolong, members should also accelerate Hong Kong's “advancement to prosperity” and the economic diversification of Macao, contributing to the prosperity and stability of the roes.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:53:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan wants tighter residence rules for people from Hong Kong and Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/taiwan-quer-regras-de-residencia-mais-apertadas-para-pessoas-de-hong-kong-e-macau/</link><description>Taiwan is considering more tight rules for the assignment of residence and citizenship to citizens from Hong Kong and Macau, with a view to avoiding Chinese influence through immigration, Taiwanese press said. Unlike other foreign citizens, residents of Hong Kong and Macau can now apply for permanent residence and get Taiwan identity ticket after a year residing on the island.
Taiwan is now considering changes, establishing that citizens from the two Chinese administrative regions have to reside on the island four years before they became eligible for the permanent residence, said a familiar official with the subject, quoted by the Taipei Times newspaper.
It is intended with the changes to avoid the influence of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) in Taiwan through the immigration of Hong Kong and Macao, said the same source, which asked not to be identified. The measure is part of a “legislative reform related to national security,” he added. Another change that is being considered, said the same source, is to end citizenship to people from Hong Kong and Macau with long -term residence.
Also according to the proposed changes, the residence applicants of Hong Kong or Macao who have worked for the China Communist Party (CCP), the Chinese Armed Forces or Chinese public institutions will be the subject of strict analysis and requests may be refused, he continued.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Acute gastroenteritis is still active in Macao, with increased cases in February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/gastroenterite-aguda-continua-activa-em-macau-com-aumento-de-casos-em-fevereiro/</link><description>Norovirus infection was the main disease contracted earlier this year, but now cases of rotavirus infection. From January to February, the average number of weekly gastroenteritis cases decupated from 2 to 20. Most of these cases are related to collective outbreaks, registered mainly in schools and homes.
 
Acute gastroenteritis remains active in Macao, with a significant increase in cases of rotavirus infection. Given this situation, health services call for the entire population to redouble attention to personal, environmental and food hygiene practices in order to contain the spread of the disease.
According to data released by health authorities, medical care for acute gastroenteritis at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center and Kiang Wu Hospital has been kept “high”, following a sharp increase in cases from December last year. The average number of users in these establishments rose from about 925 per week in January 2025 to 1,271 in mid -February.
Monitoring data indicates that norovirus infection was the main disease contracted in January, a trend that in February came to take place with the rotavirus virus. If, in January, the average weekly cases did not exceed both, in mid -February this number grew ten times to 20. In the same period last year, only three cases were recorded.
Most new cases are related to sporadic situations or collective gastroenteritis outbreaks involving a large number of people. Health services have been notified of 17 cases of collective gastroenteritis infection since the beginning of the year, covering about 198 patients - a significant increase compared to the same period last year, in which ten cases were accounted for. Most infected manifested only slight symptoms, and no serious or fatal cases were recorded.
Health services recall that acute gastroenteritis can be transmitted by contaminated foods, contact with contaminated objects or inadequate treatment of vomiting or patient excrement. The incubation period varies from hours to days, depending on the different pathogenic agents (the most common being noroviruses, rotaviruses and salmonella) and the most common symptoms include nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain and fever.
Health and restoration professionals are especially advised not to attend the workplaces when they have symptoms such as nausea or diarrhea, and should seek immediate medical care. Health authorities also appeal to day care centers, schools, homes and other similar institutions notify the Center for Prevention and Control of Health Services Diseases from any collective infection situation through number 28700800.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro light breaks passenger record in February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/metro-ligeiro-bate-recorde-de-passageiros-em-fevereiro/</link><description>The light meter registered an average of about 27,100 passengers per day in February. This is the highest number of passengers since the means of transport started charging fares in February 2019.
February figures show a growth of 1,800 daily passengers compared to January-a month, which, it was already a 9.5% increase in December and 80.7% compared to the same month of 2024.
According to the analysis of the statistical data available on the Macao Metro Society page, the introduction of Hengqin's Father Van and (above all) lines seems to have brought a new breath to the passenger flow.
In November 2024, with the introduction of the Pai Seac Vai Vai line, the average passenger rose to 16,900, compared to the 15,200 registered in the previous month of October. The new record happened with the opening of the extent of the surface that connects Macau to neighboring Hengqin, with 2.2 kilometers, on December 2. This became the busiest month until then, accounting for approximately 23,100 daily passengers.
It is worth remembering that the light meter started with only one line, which was circulating only on Taipa Island, with a length of 9.3 kilometers and 11 stations.
The light meter was inaugurated on December 10, 2019 and this month continues to stop the absolute record, with a daily average of 33,000 passengers, and then the trips were free.
In February 2020, with the start of tariff collection and the detection of the first cases of infection by the new coronavirus in Macao, the daily average passenger fell to 1,100.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:31+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ron Lam accuses government of 'giving green light' to dismissals without just cause</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/ron-lam-acusa-governo-de-dar-luz-verde-a-despedimentos-sem-justa-causa/</link><description>Deputy Ron Lam reported that several workers from different sectors of game concessionaires in Macau will have been dismissed without cause, accusing the government of tacitly approving this practice.
According to a shared publication on social networks, the deputy received requests for assistance from several workers who claim to have received an unexpected notice from the game concessionaire for which they worked on February 28, ending their work contracts without presenting any reasons for the dismissal. The publication said that the affected worked in different departments of the sector, although without revealing the names and functions they performed.
"The farewell workers stated that, earlier this year, there were rumors that the government had" given green light "to the concessionaires to dismiss workers," he writes, arguing that the incident violated the "work rights" and the "social responsibility" indispensable to the sector-even maintained during the covid-19 pandemic, when the six major game concessionaires committed to "not adhering to" dismiss employees ”.
Ron Lam recalls that in 2025 the local economy has not yet fully recover from the impact of the pandemic (especially small and medium -sized companies) and that job offers for residents are still scarce. Therefore, "if the six largest game dealers continue to take the initiative to terminate the contracts of their local workers without reasonable reasons, this would not only be unacceptable for the community, but would also create a bad precedent and aggravate the already difficult situation of the job market in Macao."
The deputy ends the publication with a direct appeal to the Government of MSAR, installing the one that performs "an exhaustive investigation" about the incident and to "explain to the public why it has allowed" that the company in question has dismissed employees without explanation or other "transfer options".</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai promises to respond to the “problem of the unbalanced development of the economy”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/sam-hou-fai-promete-dar-resposta-ao-problema-do-desenvolvimento-desequilibrado-da-economia/</link><description>Noteworthy that there are “many factors of instability and uncertainty” and that Macao's economic environment will “undergo profound and complex changes”, the chief executive said that the government should “face and deal with the problem of unbalanced development of the internal economy”.
 
Sam Hou Fai met on Monday with a series of economists and academics to prepare the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for this year. During the meeting, the Chief Executive heard suggestions in the development of the local economy and the in -depth cooperation zone, among others. In the answer, Sam warned that Macao's economy will have to exceed various challenges.
At the time, the chief executive recalled that "global economic development faces many factors of instability and uncertainty," and that, moreover, "the internal and external environment of Macau's development will continue to undergo profound and complex changes." The government leader stressed that there are changes in the consumer model, which also brings "new challenges".
The boss stated that the government "has to properly face and deal with the problem of the unbalanced development of the Macao's internal economy" and should "promote industrial diversification and help sustainable development of SMEs, as well as develop, in the best way, the exploration of Hengqin under the cooperation between Guangdong and Macao."
Sam Hou Fai also said it was necessary to “promote the high quality transformation of scientific research results from higher education establishments and constantly injects a dynamic in the sustainable development of Macao's economy, through the deep integration of industry-university-investigation, as well as continually boosting the cultural and tourist economy and improving the business environment of Macau's population”.
At the meeting, Samuel Tong, president of the Macao Management Institute and president of the Directorate of the Macao Political Economy Study Association, asked the government to create a “human capital accumulation mechanism” to be driven by “comprehensive valorization and counterclass of traditional industries” and accelerated the second phase of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin.
In turn, Liu Ting Chi, director of the University of Macao Continuous Education Center (one), a professor at the Faculty of Business Management at that educational institution and a member of the Economic Development, said the government should attract more international companies to Hengqin.
Ricardo Siu, Associate Professor at the Faculty of Business Management at UM, proposed to reinforce the development of the local economy and support the technological transformation of micro, small and medium enterprises. Henry Law, associate chief in the department of the Faculty of Business Management of UM and vice president of the Board of the Macao Economic Association, defended support for small and medium enterprises and greater focus on investing, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:54:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gongbei Health and Customs Services Sign an agreement in the area of ​​Sanitary Control</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/servicos-de-saude-e-alfandega-de-gongbei-assinam-acordo-na-area-do-controlo-sanitario/</link><description>Alvis Lo, Director of Health Services of the Government of the Government, and Zhan Shaotong, Director General of Gongbei Customs Services, signed the “joint monitoring agreement of vector organisms between the gongbei customs and the health services of the Government of MSc”.
In a statement, health services clarify that the document aims to “deepen the mechanism for monitoring, prevention and control of transionic joint vector organisms of the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay”, in order to facilitate the passage and sanitary control of border posts and to safeguard the public health of passengers and residents.
Health services explain that, according to the agreement, both parties are committed to creating a working group for the joint monitoring of vector organisms, where they will share relevant information “to provide a scientific foundation for sanitary prevention and control decisions. In addition, the institution goes on, it is also foreseen the “joint realization of laboratory science and technology projects and research of scientific themes”, which qualifies as a “innovative cooperation model”.
The agreement was witnessed by Lam, secretary to the social affairs and culture of the Government of MSAR, which also exchanged impressions with the delegation led by the Deputy Director of the General Administration of Customs, Wang Lingjun. Also present at the event was the head of the Secretary's Office for Social Affairs and Culture, Lin Yuan.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:32+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan rejects Trump's statements that he is devaluing his currency</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/japao-rejeita-afirmacoes-de-trump-de-que-esta-a-desvalorizar-a-sua-moeda/</link><description>The Japanese government yesterday rejected the charges made Monday by US President Donald Trump that Japan is devaluing its currency, stating that it is in close communication with Washington on these issues.
“We are not adopting a policy to weaken our currency. If you remember our exchange market interventions in recent years, you will understand what I mean, ”said Finance Minister Katsunobu Kato at a press conference after the US President's comments.
Japanese government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi also denied that Tokyo is following a currency control policy and said that “currency issues will continue to be the subject of narrow consultations” between Kato and US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, as has happened since the summit between Trump and the Japanese Prime Minister Shiger, in Washington, on February 10th.
Japanese government comments appear hours after Trump threatened to have additional rates on Japan and China, claiming that these countries purposely devalue their currencies to take advantage of commercial benefits that exchange rate devaluation offers. "It's unfair to us," the United States said Trump, ensuring that the way they face such a situation "is easy, [it's] with tariffs."
Banco do Japan (Boj) has maintained a currency depreciation monetary policy for more than a decade to try to maintain inflation around its stable goal of 2%, causing a strong devaluation of yen over other currencies, especially the US dollar and the euro.
The devaluation of IENE has contributed to inflating companies' profits and the value of national exports, as well as having the boom of tourism.
In recent years, however, Japan will intervene several times in the currency market to contain accentuated devaluation of the yen, reflecting the divergence of monetary policies between Japan and the United States.
Since Kazuo Ueda became governor of Boj in 2023, the Japanese Central Bank has entered a rate of rise, but the yen remains weak. Trump's comments led to a sudden Iene appreciation of the dollar, which in the previous hours had been negotiated in the upper range of 148 units per dollar, before recovering to 149 units.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:37+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibition “Above Zobeia” is inaugurated in Macau after passing by Venice</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/exposicao-acima-de-zobeia-e-inaugurada-em-macau-depois-de-passagem-por-veneza/</link><description>The work co-created by artist Wong Weng Cheong and curator Chang Chan represented the Mashely at the Venice Biennial and will now be presented to the public, from March 7, at the Macao Art Museum.
 
The exhibition “Above Zobeida: Art of Macao at the 60th International Art Exhibition of La Biennale di Venezia” will be inaugurated on the 1st Floor of the Macao Art Museum, at 6:30 pm on March 7th. The show signed by Wong Weng Cheong and Chang Chan, as the title indicates, represented masters at the 60th International Biennial Art Exhibition in 2024.
In a statement, the Cultural Institute (IC) explains that the exhibition “reflects the concerns of young artists from Macao, from 'regional narratives' to 'global issues', reflecting on contemporary artistic practice from the vision of global citizenship”. The institute underlines that it is “of great importance that the exhibition will return to Macau, so that residents and tourists can appreciate the contemporary creations of young artists” in the region.
In the same note, it is read that the work is inspired by the novel “The Invisible Cities” by the Italian writer Italo Calvino, where the existence of a fictional city named “Zobeida” is mentioned. With this installation, artist Wong Weng Cheong deny the lines between reality and fiction in creating a seemingly fictional world, but full of metaphors for the imbalance of human civilization.
Chang Chan, an independent curator residing in Macao and London, adds that the work explores the concept of “foreign” and the apocalyptic anxiety of contemporary society, “through the displacement of identity and spatial alienation”. The public is also invited to enter this space and to become part of the piece, when captured by the cameras that make up the exhibition.
This is the ninth participation of masters in the International Art Exhibition of the Venice Biennial, having the first occurred in 2007. According to the data presented by the IC, the passage of the work through the Venice Biennial attracted about 77,000 visitors.
In the opening speech of the exhibition in Venice in April last year, the president of the Leong Wai Man Cultural Institute signaled the importance of showing the individuality and talent of young people integrated in the Macao art scene. "The Government of Macao will continue to create more conditions and opportunities for Macao artists, particularly for young artists, to create artistic works with the Chinese spirit and the characteristics of Macao, in order to continue to promote the development of Macao culture and cultural industries," he said at the time.
The Macao Art Museum is open every day, including holidays and except Monday from 10:00 to 19:00. The entrance to the exhibition is free.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China keeps the goal of placing astronauts on the moon before the end of 2030</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/05/china-mantem-objectivo-de-colocar-astronautas-na-lua-antes-do-final-de-2030/</link><description>The Chinese manned lunar exploration program is progressing and maintains the goal of placing astronauts in the Natural Satellite of Earth before the end of 2030, the Space Agency for Crew Missions from China said yesterday. In a statement, the agency stated that the main components of the project are progressing according to the scheduled calendar. This includes the heavy "long gear 10" heavy load rocket, the manned space ship "Mengzhou", the lunar land module "Lanyue", the lunar fact "wangyu" and the "Tansuo" space vehicle. All are in the phase of development of preliminary prototypes, and the conception work is underway according to the scheduled calendar, read in the same note.
At the same time, the authorities began the construction of new infrastructures at the Wechang Space Launch Center at the Hainan island province in the south of the country. Facilities include test and launch systems as well as land equipment to control the mission. The conception plans have already been approved and the works are about to begin, according to the statement. China's Crew Lunar Exploration Program foresees two “Long March 10” releases from Wechang to place the “Lanyue” module and the “Mengzhou” spacecraft in the lunar orbit. Once positioned, the two elements will be attached to space. Two astronauts will then be transferred to the lunar module, which will descend to the lunar surface with a motor -assisted landing. During its moon stay, the crew will use the “Tansuo” tube to perform scientific activities and collect samples. At the end of the mission, they will return to the “Lanyue” module, which will take them back to the “Mengzhou” spacecraft in orbit, after which they will take the return trip to Earth.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05T04:51:34+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>