<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/numero-de-visitantes-em-macau-tem-o-melhor-setembro-de-sempre/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Macau companies promise to increase salaries next year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/empresas-de-macau-prometem-aumentar-salarios-no-proximo-ano/</link><description>A survey of wages and benefits in the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area revealed that companies operating in Macau are expected to increase their workers' remuneration next year.
This survey was carried out at 258 companies in the Greater Bay Area, of which 39 were from Macau. All 39 Macau companies that participated in this survey indicated that in 2026 they will increase their employees' salaries. Approximately 15% of these companies said they will increase salaries by 3% next year.
The survey, cited by Chinese-language Radio Macau, also shows that the real average salary increase for Macau workers in 2025 was 1.6%, down from 2.8% last year. The average real wage increase for Hong Kong workers was 2.5%, down from 3.5% last year; and the average wage increase for workers in nine cities in Guangdong province was 1.8%, also lower than last year's 2.3%.
This survey was carried out between July and September by several universities and organizations in the Greater Bay Area. The Macau part was carried out by the Faculty of Business Management of the University of Macau. Lida Zhang, chairman of the inquiry panel and associate professor at the Faculty of Business Management at the University of Macau, said that “Macau will maintain stable performance in terms of remuneration, benefits and personnel changes this year.” “Both staff turnover and vacancy rates are lower than those in Hong Kong and Guangdong province, reflecting an overall stable human resources market,” said the academic.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:37:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand's Queen Mother dies at 93</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/rainha-mae-da-tailandia-morre-aos-93-anos/</link><description>Queen Sirikit, mother of King Vajiralongkorn of Thailand, died on Friday night at the age of 93, the Royal Household Office announced. The Queen Mother died “peacefully” in a Bangkok hospital at 9:21 pm on Friday, according to a statement. Sirikit, who had been hospitalized since 2019, suffered a blood infection this month, the same source added.
For more than six decades, Queen Sirikit was married to King Bhumibol Adulyadej, who died in 2016 and was Thailand's longest-reigning monarch. The Queen's public appearances have become rare since 2012, when she suffered a stroke.
King Vajiralongkorn issued “a royal order for the Royal Household Office to organize the royal funeral with the highest honors in accordance with royal tradition” and for the Queen Mother's body to rest in the Dusit Maha Prasat Throne Room of the Grand Palace.
Sirikit's birthday, August 12, is celebrated across the country as Mother's Day. On this occasion, government buildings, offices, shopping centers and apartments across the country hang portraits in honor of the sovereign. Sirikit became world famous for her permanent smile and glamorous image, wearing Thai silk dresses.
In Thailand, the queen committed to supporting several royal foundations and paramilitary organizations that, during the Cold War, defended the monarchy against the threat of communism, according to the Efe news agency.
Born in 1932 into an aristocratic family, she studied in Bangkok until she was 14, when she left for Europe, where her father, Prince Nakkhatra, was appointed ambassador to several countries.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:25:30</pubDate></item><item><title>First work by Angolan writer João Melo translated into Mandarin launched in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/primeira-obra-do-escritor-angolano-joao-melo-traduzida-para-mandarim-lancada-em-macau/</link><description>The first edition of a work by Angolan writer João Melo translated into Mandarin, “Será Este Livro Um Romance?”, was launched in Macau, with simultaneous publication in mainland China.

The translation, carried out by Chen Qian, was sponsored by the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries (Macau Forum).
The objective was, “through literature, to build a spiritual bridge between Sino-Lusophone cultures and promote exchange between different civilizations”, said the secretary-general of Forum Macau, Ji Xianzheng.
The founder of the publishing house Os Macaenses Publicações, which published the book in Macau, lamented that Angolan literature “remains an unexplored territory” by Chinese readers. Cyan Cheong In Cheng said he hopes that the launch of João Melo's work “will be the beginning of a cultural dialogue” between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
In addition to the edition in traditional Chinese characters presented in Macau, the edition in simplified characters will also be launched simultaneously in mainland China.
The editor-in-chief of Chinese publisher Lijiang Publishing, Zhang Qian, said she hopes that João Melo's work will “inject new dynamism into the study of African Lusophone literature” in China.
In a video message sent for the occasion, the Angolan writer congratulated Forum Macau for the “initiative to publish writers in Portuguese” in the Chinese market. João Melo lamented that African Lusophone literatures are “still little publicized internationally”.
However, on the sidelines of the ceremony, Ji Xianzheng admitted to Lusa that “Is This Book A Novel?” It should be the only book to be translated under the auspices of the Macau Forum.
None of the other Portuguese-speaking countries responded to the organization's request to choose a work of their national literature in Portuguese to be the next to be translated, lamented the leader.
Even so, Ji assured that the Macau Forum will continue to look for “other ways to promote cultural exchanges” between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
The launch of the translation of “Será This Livro Um Romance?” It took place within the scope of the 17th edition of the China-Portuguese Speaking Countries Cultural Week, which kicked off on September 26th.
This was the first year that the event took Portuguese-speaking cultural and artistic groups beyond the territory, to the neighboring city of Zhongshan and the Chinese capital, Beijing, recalled the organization's secretary-general. Ji Xianzheng was speaking during the inauguration of an exhibition that brings together 27 works of fine art by 23 Portuguese-speaking authors, until November 18, at the Gallery of the Institute for Municipal Affairs. The leader revealed that more than 70 thousand people visited the same exhibition while it was on display at the Xiangshan Commercial Culture Museum, in Zhongshan, between September 29th and October 12th. Lusa</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Vietnam tries to counter growing protectionism and assert itself as the new ‘Asian tiger’</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/vietname-tenta-contrariar-crescente-protecionismo-e-afirmar-se-como-novo-tigre-asiatico/</link><description>Vietnam is growing at the pace of industrial relocation from China, but the permanence of foreign companies is not guaranteed as rising costs and trade tensions threaten intermediate economies.

“In 15 years, this factory will be in Cambodia, Bangladesh or Pakistan,” Denis Almeida, sales manager for Brazil's JBS in Asia, told the Lusa agency, referring to the company's production unit in Bien Hoa, an hour from Ho Chi Minh City, the metropolis of almost 10 million inhabitants, located next to the Mekong Delta, one of the longest rivers on the planet.
The warning illustrates a growing dilemma faced by intermediate economies like Vietnam, whose room for maneuver is narrowing in a context of geopolitical rivalry, trade war and new barriers to global trade. “When buffaloes and oxen fight, it is the mosquitoes who suffer,” says a local proverb cited by analyst Nguyen Khac Giang, in an article in The Diplomat magazine. “Vietnam can no longer simply connect to the circuit with the highest return,” he explained.
The new wave of protectionism that began after Donald Trump's return to the White House at the beginning of this year threatens the economic model that transformed Vietnam into one of the biggest beneficiaries of the first phase of the trade war between the United States and China, during Trump's first term (2017-2021).
On April 2, the US President announced tariffs of up to 46% on Vietnamese products, accusing the country of serving as a warehouse for the re-export of Chinese goods. After negotiations with Washington, Hanoi accepted a dual tariff system: 20% on locally produced goods and 40% on products of Chinese origin processed in Vietnam.
The impact was immediate: the purchasing managers index (PMI) fell to 45.6 points in April – the lowest value since the pandemic. In September, it once again surpassed the 50-point line, signaling a slight expansion in business conditions.
Hanoi's response included a diplomatic offensive led by To Lam, new general secretary of the Communist Party of Vietnam, including meetings with Chinese President Xi Jinping, visits to Russia and Central Asia, and new trade agreements with countries such as France and Thailand. Vietnam is also about to open an embassy in Lisbon, signaling a more active foreign policy.
In 2024, the trade surplus with the USA reached 104 billion dollars (89 billion euros), almost three times more than in 2017. The economy grew 7.09% in 2024, and the Government set an ambitious target of annual growth of 10% between 2026 and 2030, with a strong focus on manufacturing industry and renewable energy.
On the skyline of Ho Chi Minh City, the steel skeletons of under-construction skyscrapers and glass-enclosed office towers herald the birth of a possible new “Asian Tiger” – a term used for Singapore, South Korea, Hong Kong and Taiwan, which experienced accelerated economic growth in the second half of the last century.
At the end of the afternoon, thousands of motorbikes clog the streets of the city formerly known as Saigon, the capital of South Vietnam, a US ally during the war. Everything is served or done on the street – coffee, meals or barbershop – on disposable chairs and tables, placed throughout the alleys, alleys and avenues.
With around 110 million inhabitants and 70% of the population of working age, Vietnam continues to attract labor-intensive sectors such as textiles, footwear or furniture. The average industrial salary has doubled in the last decade, but remains low: around 350 dollars per month (300 euros). According to the most recent PISA data, Vietnam ranked 34th out of 81 countries, with the second best result in Southeast Asia, behind only Singapore. “Vietnam has one of the most advanced education systems among developing countries and will quickly migrate to sectors with higher added value”, predicted Denis Almeida.
The JBS factory in Bien Hoa is an example of the country's industrial expansion. Dressed in blue uniforms, the 750 workers at the JBS Couros unit are distributed across 11 production lines, in an area of ​​35 thousand square meters. Since it was acquired by the Brazilian multinational, ten years ago, production has multiplied eleven times, to more than half a million square meters of leather per month. “We are going to set up another line and add 90 thousand square meters to production this year”, said Almeida. “We are growing in Vietnam at the pace of the migration of footwear and furniture production from China”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:26:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Commercial exhibitions in Macau end with more than 140 agreements</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/exposicoes-comerciais-em-macau-terminam-com-mais-de-140-acordos/</link><description>Three trade exhibitions held in Macau ended with the signing of more than 140 cooperation agreements, 15% of which involve Portuguese-speaking countries. According to the organizers, the number of agreements signed during the four days registered “an increase of more than 30% compared to the previous year”.
 
Three commercial exhibitions held in Macau ended Saturday with the signing of more than 140 cooperation agreements, said the organization, noting that 15% involve Portuguese-speaking countries.
The 2nd China-Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition (C-PLPEX), the 30th Macau International Fair (MIF) and the 2025 Macau Franchise Exhibition (2025MFE), took place simultaneously, between Wednesday and today.
The number of agreements signed during the four days registered “an increase of more than 30% compared to the previous year”, covering areas such as “integrated tourism and leisure, ‘big health’ of traditional Chinese medicine, cutting-edge technology, conventions and exhibitions, culture, sport, agricultural products, brand agency, Sino-Lusophone cooperation, among others”, said, in a statement, the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macau (IPIM).
Still according to IPIM, 15% of these agreements involved Portuguese-speaking countries, “reflecting the value of the exhibitions in deepening economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries”.
On the other hand, IPIM also mentioned, almost 80% of the agreements signed were related to the '1+4' industries.
The '1+4' model, created by the Government of Macau as a response to the need to diversify the territory's economy, which is deeply dependent on gambling, intends to focus on the following sectors: health and well-being industry, modern finance industry, cutting-edge technology industry and, finally, the conventions, exhibitions and commerce, culture and sports industry.
IPIM, the note also reads, made more than 350 companies aware of the “investment environment and commercial advantages of Macau”.
To date, 68 companies, including from Portugal and Brazil, “have already signed the declaration of investment intentions, which represents an increase of 70% year-on-year”.
Furthermore, over these four days, more than 600 business representatives from Portuguese-speaking countries, Southeast Asia and various regions of mainland China visited Macau and the Deep Cooperation Zone, “in order to get to know its commercial areas and its commercial environment”.
The Macau-Guangdong Deep Cooperation Zone, in Hengqin, is a special economic area, created in 2021 with a view to economic diversification and regional integration of the Macao SAR with the rest of the country.
This year, C-PLPEX, MIF and MFE brought together more than 1,100 exhibitors from almost 30 countries, receiving more than 85 thousand participants, according to IPIM. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:41:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste becomes the 11th member of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/timor-leste-torna-se-o-11-o-membro-da-associacao-das-nacoes-do-sudeste-asiatico/</link><description>Timor-Leste concluded its membership of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations on Saturday, after more than a decade of preparation, which began in 2011 with the submission of the application for admission.

Timor-Leste's entry as a full member of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) took place in Kuala Lumpur, during the 47th summit of heads of state and government, which will run until Tuesday.
The Timorese President, José Ramos-Horta, stated that Timor-Leste's accession to ASEAN is the realization of a dream, which began almost half a century ago. "Today, we realized a dream that began almost half a century ago, a vision of regional belonging that predates our own independence. I remember discussing this idea when I was a young man of 25", said the head of state, quoted in a statement released to the press. "When we formally presented the candidacy, in 2011, the path was not yet defined and required great perseverance. This success belongs to many", stated Ramos-Horta.
The Nobel Peace Prize winner, who witnessed the moment of accession in Kuala Lumpur, expressed his “deep gratitude” to all ASEAN leaders and gave special recognition to the support of former Indonesian President Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono. "I also thank all Timorese leaders, past and present, including Prime Minister Xanana Gusmão, for their visionary leadership and tireless efforts to improve the well-being of our people. This is a victory for the entire nation, a moment of immense pride and shared achievement", added the Timorese President.
ASEAN was created in 1967 by Indonesia, Singapore, Thailand, Malaysia and the Philippines, and was later joined by Brunei Darussalam, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar and Vietnam. With 676.6 million inhabitants, ASEAN is the third most populous region in the world, after India and China.
The declaration on Timor-Leste's admission to ASEAN was signed by the Timorese Prime Minister, Xanana Gusmão, and the representatives of the other member states, and was then delivered to the Secretary General of ASEAN, Kao Kim Hourn, accompanied by Xanana Gusmão and the Timorese Head of State, José Ramos-Horta. The flag of Timor-Leste was then raised on the ceremony stage.
Na cimeira, dedicada ao tema “Inclusão e Sustentabilidade”, vão ser abordados temas como paz regional, resiliência económica e crescimento inclusivo, e haverá reuniões bilaterais com os Estados Unidos, China, Japão, Índia, Coreia do Sul, Austrália e União Europeia. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:24:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Government wants, in the long term, consumption of recycled water to represent 10% of the total</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/governo-quer-que-a-longo-prazo-consumo-de-agua-reciclada-represente-10-do-total/</link><description>The Government drew attention to water conservation and the promotion of efficiency in consumption. In a statement in anticipation of the Government Action Lines for next year, the Office of the Secretary for Transport and Public Works points out that “Macau faces a significant shortage of fresh water”, with around 99% of the raw water consumed coming from the interior of China.
The authorities report that the demand for water has registered a sharp increase, with the volume of raw water supplied to Macau in 2024 reaching around 105 million cubic meters, which represents an increase of more than 83% compared to 1999.
Therefore, “to ensure a stable and safe water supply, Macau must count on the solid support of the country, while at the same time reinforcing the implementation of measures aimed at diversifying water sources and promoting the reduction of consumption”, reads the press release from Raymond Tam's office, which adds that “the use of recycled water is a fundamental policy of the MSAR Government to promote the reuse of water resources and safeguard the security of water supply in Macau”. Recycled water is water that has undergone advanced treatment with a view to its reuse.
The Executive recalls that diplomas were recently promulgated that establish the technical requirements applicable to the design, installation, identification, testing and water quality of recycled water supply systems. Therefore, “the sector will be able to design, build and operate recycled water supply systems in accordance with these standards, ensuring compliance with safety and quality requirements throughout the transport and distribution process”.
On the other hand, the Coloane Recycled Water Station is being built, with completion scheduled for the first quarter of 2026. This Station will have a daily capacity of 2,500 cubic meters and will supply recycled water, as a priority, to public housing in Seac Pai Van and the University of Macau, for flushing toilets and irrigating green spaces. Furthermore, work on drawing up plans for the Coloane Recycled Water Plant Phase II and the Artificial Island Recycled Water Plant will begin in the first quarter of 2026.
In conclusion, the Government states that it will “continuously expand the scope of use of recycled water and consider expansion for other purposes”. The medium-term goal is for recycled water consumption to represent 5% of Macau's total water consumption, with the long-term goal to exceed 10%.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:38:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation accelerates in September for the third consecutive month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/inflacao-acelera-em-setembro-pelo-terceiro-mes-consecutivo/</link><description>Inflation in Macau accelerated in September, for the third consecutive month, in a month in which the consumer price index fell again in mainland China.
The index in Macau rose 0.47% in September, year-on-year, 0.2 percentage points more than that recorded in August (0.27%), and the highest value since January (0.57%), according to official data.
According to the Statistics and Census Services Directorate, the acceleration in inflation was mainly due to food products and non-alcoholic drinks (+0.56%). The cost of meals purchased outside the home rose 1.56%.
Spending on apartment rent or mortgages rose 0.85% and 0.63%, respectively, after the Macau Monetary Authority approved, on September 18, the first interest rate cut since the end of 2024.
The Legislative Assembly approved, in April 2024, the end of several taxes on the acquisition of housing, to “increase liquidity” in the real estate market, defended the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Lei Wai Nong, at the time.
With the recovery in the number of visitors, the region recorded a 20.2% increase in the price of jewelry, goldsmithing and watches, popular products among tourists from mainland China.
The cost of tours and hotels for Macau residents' overseas trips increased by 7.94%, while expenditure on education and vehicle fuel rose by 1.67% and 2.21%, respectively.
In mainland China, by far Macau's largest trading partner, the CPI fell again by 0.3% in September, year-on-year, the second consecutive month of deflation (annual drop in consumer prices) and the sixth in the nine months of the year.
Deflation reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly serious, as a fall in the price of assets, usually contracted using credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
The value recorded in September surprised analysts, who predicted a smaller price contraction, of around 0.1%.
The world's second largest economy continues to be under deflationary pressure, due to the combination of weak domestic demand and excess industrial capacity, aggravated by the trade war with the United States, which has made it difficult to dispose of inventories accumulated by companies.
The producer price index, which measures ex-factory prices, fell 2.3% in September, marking the 36th consecutive month of contraction, despite representing an improvement compared to the 2.9% drop recorded in August.
Chinese authorities have reiterated that strengthening domestic demand will be one of the central economic priorities for 2025. In the neighboring region of Hong Kong, inflation remained unchanged, at 1.1%, in September.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:37:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai promises to comply with guidelines from the fourth plenary session of the CPC Central Committee</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/sam-hou-fai-promete-acatar-orientacoes-da-quarta-sessao-plenaria-do-comite-central-do-pcc/</link><description>The fourth plenary session of the 20th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCP) ended last Thursday. The Chief Executive congratulated the “successful” closing of the session and promised that the Macao SAR Government will “unite and lead the various sectors in learning and implementing the spirit enshrined in the fourth plenary session, so as to contribute to Macau’s strength to promote modernization with Chinese characteristics”.

Describing the PCC plenary session as “an event of enormous significance”, in which Xi Jinping delivered “important speeches”, the Chief Executive recalled that the proposals for the formulation of the 15th Five-Year Plan for economic and social development were approved.
This five-year plan defines several principles that must be fulfilled, as well as the objectives for economic and social development for the next five years, which include “building a modern socialist country”, promoting the “great revitalization of the Chinese nation through Chinese-style modernization” and implementing a new development philosophy, for example. At the same time, the importance of maintaining the long-term prosperity and stability of Hong Kong and Macau, “of promoting the peaceful development of cross-strait relations, of advancing national reunification and building a community with a shared future for humanity” was also highlighted.
“The session showed the determination to write new chapters regarding the two miracles, the rapid economic development and the long-term social stability of the country, in a joint effort towards opening a new situation for modernization with Chinese characteristics”, said the Macao SAR Chief Executive, quoted in a Government statement.
In the shared message, Sam Hou Fai highlighted that “the Macao SAR Government has determinedly implemented the spirit enshrined in the important speeches of President Xi Jinping, delivered during his visit to Macau, and the decisions of the Central Government, striving to promote new progress and new results in the adequate diversification of the economy and integrated development between Macau and Hengqin, with key industries developing with quality, and presenting highlights exceptional.”
The Chief also reiterated that the Government “will study ways to fulfill the spirit of the fourth plenary session, take a series of measures with pragmatism, constantly increase the effectiveness of governance, unite and lead the different sectors of Macau, and seize the new opportunities arising from the 15th National Five-Year Plan”.
Furthermore, “it will also continue to implement, fully, precisely and unwaveringly, the principle of ‘one country, two systems’, firmly defending the sovereignty, security and development interests of the State”, taking advantage of the “institutional advantages” of the role as a “platform for international cooperation”, in order to “boost the development of Macau with high quality in all areas, and make a greater contribution to beginning the new horizon of Macau full construction of a strong country and the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation through modernization with Chinese characteristics”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:41:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal Point – 27 October 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/ponto-fatal-27-outubro-2025/</link><description>The fourth plenary session of the 20th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCP) ended last Thursday. The Chief Executive congratulated the “successful” closing of the session and promised that the Macao SAR Government will “unite and lead the various sectors in learning and implementing the spirit enshrined in the fourth plenary session, so as to contribute to Macau’s strength to promote modernization with Chinese characteristics”.

Describing the PCC plenary session as “an event of enormous significance”, in which Xi Jinping delivered “important speeches”, the Chief Executive recalled that the proposals for the formulation of the 15th Five-Year Plan for economic and social development were approved.
This five-year plan defines several principles that must be fulfilled, as well as the objectives for economic and social development for the next five years, which include “building a modern socialist country”, promoting the “great revitalization of the Chinese nation through Chinese-style modernization” and implementing a new development philosophy, for example. At the same time, the importance of maintaining the long-term prosperity and stability of Hong Kong and Macau, “of promoting the peaceful development of cross-strait relations, of advancing national reunification and building a community with a shared future for humanity” was also highlighted.
“The session showed the determination to write new chapters regarding the two miracles, the rapid economic development and the long-term social stability of the country, in a joint effort towards opening a new situation for modernization with Chinese characteristics”, said the Macao SAR Chief Executive, quoted in a Government statement.
In the shared message, Sam Hou Fai highlighted that “the Macao SAR Government has determinedly implemented the spirit enshrined in the important speeches of President Xi Jinping, delivered during his visit to Macau, and the decisions of the Central Government, striving to promote new progress and new results in the adequate diversification of the economy and integrated development between Macau and Hengqin, with key industries developing with quality, and presenting highlights exceptional.”
The Chief also reiterated that the Government “will study ways to fulfill the spirit of the fourth plenary session, take a series of measures with pragmatism, constantly increase the effectiveness of governance, unite and lead the different sectors of Macau, and seize the new opportunities arising from the 15th National Five-Year Plan”.
Furthermore, “it will also continue to implement, fully, precisely and unwaveringly, the principle of ‘one country, two systems’, firmly defending the sovereignty, security and development interests of the State”, taking advantage of the “institutional advantages” of the role as a “platform for international cooperation”, in order to “boost the development of Macau with high quality in all areas, and make a greater contribution to beginning the new horizon of Macau full construction of a strong country and the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation through modernization with Chinese characteristics”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:28:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese research center sees signs of Chinese market opening</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/centro-de-investigacao-portugues-ve-sinais-de-abertura-do-mercado-chines/</link><description>The Portuguese center Fibrenamics – Institute for Innovation in Fibrous and Composite Materials told Lusa that there are signs of a greater opening of the Chinese market to collaboration with foreign countries in cutting-edge technology. "Clearly there are beginning to be very interesting and positive signs of opening here. This exhibition is proof of that", said the marketing director of Fibrenamics.
Pedro Pacheco was speaking during the third day of the second edition of the China–Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition, which is taking place simultaneously with the 30th Macau International Fair. “Without a doubt, we are already seeing very interesting signs of the opening of the Chinese market,” said the executive, before traveling to Guangzhou, capital of the neighboring province of Guangdong. “It's a company that approached us and asked us to go there and talk to them, in order to innovate a little, improve quality or performance or added value to the market”, explained Pacheco. “We want to be on that front line, we want to feel the pulse of this opening, this new mentality”, added the marketing director.
Fibrenamics, which has the University of Minho among its partners, is a technology and innovation center that studies solutions for architecture, construction, sport, medicine, protection and transport. “Our focus is clearly international”, said Pedro Pacheco, who pointed to Macau as “an ideal point” to approach China, “also because of this cultural proximity, the language issue”.
The Institute for Innovation in Fibrous and Composite Materials has already developed personal protective equipment for the Portuguese Army and collaborated with universities in the United States.
The director of business innovation at Fibrenamics, Eduardo Bacelar Pinto, admitted that “the logics that we can call geopolitical” can complicate international cooperation. But the researcher from the University of Minho stressed that “knowledge is intangible, it does not pass through customs, nor does it have to be transported”.
The innovation developed at Fibrenamics currently allows “business values ​​to be shared” with concern for environmental protection, added Bacelar Pinto.
The executive expressed interest in using Macau or the special economic zone in neighboring Hengqin as a base to explore the mainland China market. “We need to have some local opportunities and partnerships, because alone I think it is very difficult”, admitted Bacelar Pinto.
Fibrenamics' director of business innovation said he saw desire and interest in possible partnerships with universities, research institutions or private companies.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:35:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Firefighters report fewer fires and ambulance departures</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/bombeiros-registam-menos-incendios-e-saidas-de-ambulancia/</link><description>The Fire Department saw a decrease in its operations, both firefighting and ambulance departures. From January to September this year, firefighters recorded 621 cases of fire escapes, 8.68% less than the same period last year. Forgetting to turn off stoves and short circuits in electrical installations continued to be the main causes of fires.

The number of operational actions by the Fire Department (CB) continues to decline and registered 39,892 cases between January and September this year, which corresponds to a drop of 2.43% compared to the same period last year.
Data for the first three quarters were revealed on Friday, with the report showing that the number of firefighting operations decreased by 8.68%, going from 680 cases, at the time of analysis in 2024, to 621 cases this year. Among them, 507 cases were recorded without the use of hoses, which accounted for 81.64% of the total number of fires.
The authorities noted that the main causes of the fires were identical to those found in the past, with the flames being due to forgetting to turn off the stove, short-circuiting of electrical installations, burning of incense and candles or votive papers, flames that were not completely extinguished and mechanical or equipment failures. The aforementioned reasons led to 387 cases, which represented 62.32% of the total number of fires.
The ambulance departure from CB had 33,758 cases, which is equivalent to a reduction of 366 occurrences (1.07%) compared to the same period last year. According to firefighters, the general emergency cases essentially dealt with dizziness, abdominal pain, breathing difficulties, vomiting, fever and various types of injuries.
In a statement, the CB highlighted that it had been sending agents to buildings to carry out inspections and fire safety inspections, having carried out 8,330 inspections in the first nine months of the year. In this way, 81 administrative sanctioning procedures were completed related to the placement of motorcycles and various objects on the evacuation paths. There were also 28 administrative sanctioning procedures that were initiated and are being monitored.
With regard to firefighting awareness, firefighters said they had organized 128 lectures, with the participation of 9,299 residents, as well as 72 evacuation and incident drills, with the participation of 16,703 people.
The CB, in addition, carried out a total of 5,343 safety inspection actions for dangerous substances until September in places such as industrial buildings, gas stations, fuel depots, intermediate warehouses, food establishments, stores that sell the respective product of dangerous substances and storage facilities.
In these inspections, agents reviewed fire prevention equipment, storage quantity and surrounding environment, in order to ensure that the storage of dangerous and combustible substances “obtained sufficient security guarantees”, he highlighted. Firefighters completed two significant administrative sanctioning procedures in the first three quarters, which involve excessive storage of liquefied petroleum gas.

THIRTEEN FALSE ALARMS IN QINGMAO
 
During Friday's press conference, the CB stated that 13 fire alarms were reported at the Qingmao border post during the first three quarters of this year, but they were false alarms. The situation has already been communicated to the building management entity and the fire safety company.
Regarding the causes of false alarms, the CB stressed that they could be caused by the malfunction of the smoke detectors in the fire prevention systems. The authorities, in this case, ensure that they will carry out regular inspections and maintain contact with government departments within the building, to organize periodic seminars on fire safety and evacuation drills. They revealed that three fire evacuation drills were carried out at the Qingmao station in recent years.
Firefighters, on the other hand, issued a note to draw public attention to the correct use of gas appliances, in order to prevent carbon monoxide poisoning. They noticed that the weather is gradually getting colder and citizens will spend more time using gas appliances.
According to the CB, gas water heaters must be purchased from professional suppliers, must have safety guarantees and must be installed by professionals in accordance with the product installation instructions. Citizens should periodically order maintenance from suppliers and professionals for their devices and, if they notice abnormalities in the operation of devices, they should stop using them immediately and inform the respective agent or person qualified to carry out the check or repair.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:44:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Car invades restaurant in Areia Preta and causes six injuries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/carro-invade-restaurante-na-areia-preta-e-provoca-seis-feridos/</link><description>A car crashed and crashed into a restaurant in Areia Preta this Saturday, causing six injuries. The 60-year-old driver claimed that he pressed the accelerator by mistake while parking. The restaurant was seriously damaged and the owner said it would take at least a month to repair the establishment.

Six people were injured this Saturday after a sports car collided with a restaurant in Areia Preta. The 60-year-old driver of the car, two waitresses and three restaurant customers suffered minor injuries and were all taken to hospital for treatment.
The incident occurred at 2:30 pm when a Lamborghini car suddenly crashed into the establishment on Rua de Ma Kau Seak, causing disorder at the scene.
According to newspaper Ou Mun and several videos and images circulating on social media, the two glass doors at the restaurant's entrance were broken, with fragments of glass scattered across the floor, and the door frames were deformed. Several tables and chairs were destroyed, as well as a large number of porcelain plates. There were also bloodstains visible on the floor inside and outside the scene. A large crowd gathered near the restaurant due to the noise of the collision.
The car was parked inside the restaurant when police and firefighters arrived at the scene, noticing damage to the front and a broken rear windshield.
According to the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the driver reported during the interrogation that he was trying to park the car and accidentally pressed the accelerator instead of the brake, causing the vehicle to collide with the restaurant.
"The video surveillance images at the scene show that the driver drove the vehicle from the NAPE area to Areia Preta, stopping at the discontinuous yellow line and then tried to adjust the parking of the vehicle. We believe that the driver stepped on the accelerator by mistake", highlighted Leong Wa Chi, deputy head of the CPSP Traffic Department, at a press conference held on Saturday.
The driver in question is a resident and, according to the CPSP spokesperson, obtained his license in Macau, having tested negative for alcohol. The vehicle involved in the accident had been registered in Macau for more than ten years and the driver had purchased the vehicle more than a year ago. The authorities will proceed with the preliminary accusation of administrative infraction for negligence in starting the car, as well as the offense to physical integrity due to negligence.
The Fire Department (CB) revealed that the victims are residents and non-resident workers, aged between 37 and 75 years. The driver suffered minor injuries to his left leg.
Ng Chon Leong, First Chief of CB's Areia Preta Operational Post, added that a male customer suffered more serious injuries with a laceration to his head, and was found passed out next to the vehicle, while the other two customers had minor injuries, one with cuts on his hands and the other with a bleed from his mouth and bruises on his chest. Two restaurant employees were also taken to hospital to receive medical care, one with a fractured chin and the other suffered shock and emotional distress.
In the operation, firefighters sent a total of six vehicles to the scene, including two rescue vehicles and four ambulances.
The restaurant owner predicts that repairing equipment and replacing tables and chairs “will take a considerable amount of time”, rendering the business inoperative for at least a month, with the actual financial loss still awaiting further calculation.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:45:06</pubDate></item><item><title>External credit in yuan soars as China campaigns to reduce dependence on the dollar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/credito-externo-em-yuan-dispara-com-campanha-da-china-para-reduzir-dependencia-do-dolar/</link><description>China has quadrupled external credit in its currency, the yuan, in the last five years, including loans to Angola and Brazil, accelerating the effort to reduce dependence on the dollar and internationalize its currency.

Beijing is intensifying the use of the renminbi (or yuan) in the global financial system, through increasing loans, deposits, bonds and international trade financing instruments, in an effort to reduce exposure to the dollar and strengthen the country's financial autonomy, according to official data.
Data from China's State Administration of Foreign Exchange shows that Chinese banks' foreign fixed income assets exceeded US$1.5 billion at the end of June, with the volume of renminbi-denominated assets reaching US$484 billion – including US$360 billion in loans and deposits, more than triple compared to 2020.
According to the Bank for International Settlements (BIS), Chinese bank credit to developing countries in renminbi has increased by US$373 billion in the last four years, with 2022 marking a turning point in these borrowers abandoning the dollar and euro.
With relatively low interest rates in China, countries such as Kenya, Ethiopia and Angola converted old dollar debt into yuan, while Brazil, Indonesia, Kazakhstan and Slovenia announced public debt issues in renminbi – so-called panda 'bonds'. In June, the Brazilian Government revealed that it is preparing its debut in the Chinese bond market, in an operation seen as a “clear sign of adherence to the yuan internationalization process”. “For China, being able to settle trade in renminbi shows that, whatever happens, it will continue to be able to transact,” said Adam Wolfe, economist at Absolute Strategy Research, cited by the Financial Times.
The use of the renminbi in trade financing has also soared. Data from the SWIFT international payments system indicate that the share of the Chinese currency has quadrupled in the last three years, to 7.6% of the global market – second place, behind only the dollar.
This growth has been supported by an increasingly dense network of renminbi clearing banks outside China and swap lines with trading partners in several regions, as well as the strengthening of the Chinese cross-border payments system, CIPS, which has handled more than 40 billion yuan (483 billion euros) per quarter since the beginning of 2024.
In parallel, Hong Kong authorities launched a “roadmap” to transform the city into a global hub for renminbi transactions and liquidity, including measures to strengthen the debt market and open foreign access to the interbank repos market in mainland China – a crucial step, according to Karen Lam of Simmons &amp; Simmons, to make renminbi assets more functional and appealing. “The impact could be as relevant as what was achieved with the stock exchange connection programs,” said Paul Smith, head of markets for Japan and North Asia at Citibank, referring to the mechanism that connects Hong Kong to the financial markets of Shanghai and Shenzhen, on the Chinese mainland.
Still, obstacles to full internationalization persist. According to the IMF, the renminbi represented just 2.1% of global official reserves at the beginning of this year, far below the dollar (58%) and the euro (20%). Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:27:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Government wants to raise minimum wage by one pataca per hour</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/governo-quer-subir-salario-minimo-em-uma-pataca-por-hora-trabalhadores-domesticos-continuam-excluidos/</link><description>The Executive Council presented, on Friday, a proposal to amend the minimum wage law for workers, which provides for an increase from 34 to 35 patacas per hour. Thus, the minimum monthly salary increases from 7,072 to 7,280 patacas. Domestic workers remain forgotten.
The Executive Council presented, on Friday, a proposal to amend the minimum wage law for workers, which stipulates a slight increase of one pataca per hour. The Government's proposal foresees that the minimum wage will increase from 34 patacas per hour to 35 patacas per hour.
Doing the math on the daily remuneration, the minimum value will go from 272 to 280 patacas. In weekly terms, the minimum wage increases from 1,632 to 1,680 patacas. This means that the minimum wage will increase from 7,072 patacas per month to 7,280 patacas.
In the proposal, which has now been submitted to the Legislative Assembly (AL) for discussion, the Government stipulates that the new values ​​must come into force on January 1st of next year. The authorities estimate that the number of workers benefiting is around 18,200 people, representing 4.4% of the total number of workers, with “workers in the building administration and cleaning services sectors being the main beneficiary groups”, according to the Executive.
In the note released about this proposed change to the law, the Government says that it arrived at this value taking into account the opinions of representatives of employers and workers within the Permanent Council for Social Coordination (CPCS), and also considering the “macroeconomy, the labor market, workers' remuneration and the operational situation of employers in Macau during the second period of implementation of the minimum wage for workers”. O objectivo é alcançar um “equilíbrio de um conjunto de factores”, designadamente o “ambiente de negócios dos empregadores, a garantia dos direitos e interesses dos trabalhadores e a capacidade de aceitação dos consumidores”.
The topic had been debated at the CPCS meeting in mid-September. At the time, employers said they “vehemently” disagreed with a possible increase, justifying that companies would not be able to handle these values. “The data shows that the economic recovery is incomplete and increasing the minimum wage would be a ‘double burden’, especially for SMEs”, said Vong Kok Seng, bosses’ representative at CPCS at the time.
DOMESTIC WORKERS STILL OUT
This minimum wage law will continue to not cover workers who provide domestic services. However, the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL) stipulates, in the standards for approving the hiring of domestic workers, that employers must offer a minimum remuneration of 3,200 patacas per month for these professionals.
At the Executive Council's press conference, Chan Un Tong, director of DSAL, indicated that currently the median salary of these workers is around 3,800 patacas and stated that, “even when excluded from the general regime, there are mechanisms that guarantee reasonable remuneration”. “Even if this legislation does not apply to them, this does not mean that their rights are not protected”, he stressed.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:50:03</pubDate></item><item><title>More than a thousand people flee Myanmar for Thailand after raid</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/mais-de-mil-pessoas-fogem-de-myanmar-para-a-tailandia-apos-rusga/</link><description>More than a thousand people, mostly Chinese, have fled Myanmar for Thailand since Wednesday, following raids by the Burmese army in one of the country's largest online fraud centers, Thai provincial authorities announced.
The provincial administration of Tak (northwest) said in a statement that 1,049 people crossed the border with Myanmar to reach Mae Sot between Wednesday and Friday morning, according to the France-Presse (AFP) news agency. The majority were Chinese men, the Thai immigration office said.
The Tak provincial administration said those who fled also included Indians, Pakistanis, Vietnamese, Burmese, Thais and citizens of a dozen other countries.
The military junta in power in the former Burma announced on Monday that it was carrying out a raid on the KK Park complex, located across the Thai border.
Around 40 people who left this complex, including citizens from Taiwan and several African countries, used small boats to cross the Moei River and reach Thailand, local officials told AFP.
Thai security agents, stationed on the other side of the river, searched the luggage while the people under control handed over their cell phones and climbed into trucks, according to a video from the French news agency.
Images broadcast on Thursday by the Thai public channel PBS showed people using Styrofoam boxes to swim across the river and reach Thailand.
Online fraud networks, whether sentimental or commercial, have thrived in Myanmar along the little-guarded border with Thailand with the civil war triggered by the military coup that overthrew the Burmese government in February 2021.
Most of the complexes are under the control of Chinese criminal groups, in collusion with Burmese militias.
According to experts, the junta in power in Myanmar turns a “blind eye” to the networks in the hands of militia allies who, in return, control the border regions on behalf of the military.
Burmese state media reported that authorities recently detained “118 foreign nationals from 14 countries who entered Myanmar illegally and were involved in online gambling and scams” ​​in the KK Park area. The Burmese junta said on Monday it had seized 30 Starlink internet receivers. Two days later, Elon Musk's Space X announced that it had deactivated more than 2,500 Starlink receivers used by cybercrime centers in the region.</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:24:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of visitors to Macau has the best September ever</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/26/numero-de-visitantes-em-macau-tem-o-melhor-setembro-de-sempre/</link><description>Macau received almost 2.8 million visitors in September, 9.8% more than in the same period in 2024 and the highest figure ever for this month.

The number of tourists passing through the territory was the highest for any September since the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) began compiling monthly data, in 1998, still during the Portuguese administration. However, more than 56% of visitors (1.56 million) arrived on organized tours and spent less than a day in Macau.
In 2024, the Central Government announced a series of measures to support Macau, such as increasing the tax exemption limit for goods for personal use purchased by visitors from China. At the same time, the Chinese authorities expanded the list of places with “individual visas” to visit Hong Kong and Macau to 10 more cities in China. Furthermore, since January 1st, residents of the neighboring city of Zhuhai can visit Macau once a week and stay for up to seven days.
As a result, the overwhelming majority (90.6%) of tourists arriving in Macau in September came from mainland China or Hong Kong, while less than 260,400 were international visitors.
The city received a total of almost 29.7 million visitors in the first ten months, 14.5% more than in the same period in 2024 and the second highest figure ever for the start of a new year.
According to official data, the number of tourists passing through Macau was only surpassed between January and September 2019 – before the Covid-19 pandemic -, a period in which it registered more than 30.2 million visitors.
On January 17, the director of Tourism Services said she expected between 38 and 39 million visitors this year. In August, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes set a goal of more than three million international visitors by 2025.
In the first nine months of the year, Macau received almost 1.9 million tourists from abroad, 12.4% more than in the same period in 2024. Citizens of Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Bahrain and Oman began to be exempt from visas to enter the city from July 16th.
Despite the increase in the number of tourists, the average consumption of each visitor in Macau, excluding casinos, fell 12.3% in the second quarter of the year, compared to the same period in 2024.
At the beginning of May, DSEC pointed to the “change in visitors' consumption patterns” as one of the main reasons for the 1.3% drop in Macau's economy between January and March.
It was the first time that the territory's Gross Domestic Product shrank, in year-on-year terms, since the end of 2022, when the region began to lift restrictions due to the covid-19 pandemic.
Macau received 34.9 million visitors last year, 23.8% more than the previous year, but still far from the record, 39.4 million, set in 2019, before the pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-26 22:42:35</pubDate></item></channel></rss>