<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/apn-arranca-com-foco-na-economia-e-guerra-comercial-com-eua/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Ricardo Chaneton, the chef who already wanted to be a doctor: "What we eat can heal or kill us"</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/ricardo-chaneton-o-chef-que-ja-quis-ser-medico-aquilo-que-comemos-pode-curar-nos-ou-matar-nos/</link><description>What is the balance of this first professional experience in Macau, in MGM?
We found, when organizing the event, that this is the first time that Latin American cuisine has been presented in Macao. It is a great achievement for me and MGM, which becomes a pioneer in this regard. We are bringing ingredients that no one has experienced before… Today, for example, I served a plate with Mashua, an ingredient that throughout Asia is only served in two sites: AJI and Mono. The idea is to make the guests feel special and bring something new, different, to the gastronomic experience in Macao. In another subject, I must say that it is great to have a fully equipped kitchen, where nothing is missing. It makes our work easier. In terms of team, I would say that I am very surprised. We have Philippines, People from Continental China, Macao, Hong Kong… It's positive to see how everyone mixes, thanks to MGM's culinary scene. It is a very working, attentive team that pays attention to the slightest details. Yesterday, we reunit at 7 pm to do a training and were taking notes and asking very interesting questions that made me think, "My God, why do you ask me this?" It is great to work with people who challenge us and make us feel that we need to be at a certain level. I am already used to doing these promotional events and is hard work, but confidence in the team makes everything easier. We are all at the same level of synchronization. They know exactly what I am trying to achieve in terms of quality or objectives.
 
How have their culinary techniques evolved over years of learning in different countries?
When you start cooking, we are always interpreting someone else's kitchen. It is this mixture of kitchens where we pass that it is influencing, until the day comes when we are giving the orders.  As I was born and raised in Venezuela, adapting me to Spain was easy. They are both family -oriented and sharing cultures; We are always happy around the table. The difficulty, for me, was the fact that in Venezuela we did not have restaurants with Michelin stars. The pressure level, the level of demand for excellence… and it was a molecular cuisine restaurant, which was like opening the brain and sticking in there immense theory and information. I loved it. I forced me to ask questions like “why this and not that?” or "Why two centimeters and not five?" France has expanded my horizons even more. The restaurant where I worked had no menu and the dishes could change every day. I usually compare it to a grandmother's kitchen: it was like opening the fridge and inventing a plate based on the ingredients we had available. France taught me to have intent and to be creative, as a grandmother to cook for the family. I learned that the real kitchen is not related to the thermometer or the balance, but to common sense, intent and creativity.  And then we have Hong Kong, of course, a vibrant and diversity city. However, my first city in Asia was not Hong Kong, but Shanghai. I was also often Nanjing. It was in mainland China that I learned a lot about different flavors, ingredients and textures. I love it in Chinese kitchen: the textures. Chau-chau rice is capable of being the best example, because in a simple fried rice bowl we can have about 15 textures. We have a stall texture, another drunk, firm, gelatinous, vegetables mixed with rice… All spoonfuls are different and never become boring. My way of working is also asking questions and knowing how to listen. I have people of many different cultures working with me: Philippines, Mexicans, Guatemalas, Argentines, Brazilians, French, Germans, Australians… and I hear customers, too. I was already criticized by my own team for listening so much customers, but the truth is that I learn from them.  How has my approach changed over time? Here is the answer. It is an endless journey that will continue to change tomorrow. In ten years, we may talk again and my approach will be different.
 
The great constant in his work seems to be the nostalgia of childhood in Venezuela, and just see the comments he receives on social networks to realize that the affection is reciprocal. Many Venezuelans comment: “What a proud!”
I often say that Venezuelans are always cooking what someone else has done and we have lost our identity, in a way. As I never worked at a Latin American restaurant in Venezuela, I effort to reconnect with the origins. It is through food that I honor the ties with the place I come from and where I grew up; where I have the most amazing memories of my personal life. After starting to cook, everything became related to the work. It's a way of calling me to the past and the flavors I grew up eating. When we received the star Michelin, I was the first Venezuelan chef to receive this honor in the country's history. My Instagram account had eight thousand followers and, in 2022, when we received the first star, reached more than 40 thousand in a week. So many messages to encourage me, to congratulate myself. We respond to more than three thousand messages, me and my team, one by one. The whole team was clinging to the mobile phone: everyone had my password and were in charge of responding to different types of messages. One person dealt with requests for radio interviews, another of the interviews for magazines. To people, I answered. Public relations staff asked me not to do so: it was a waste of time, they said. But I felt the need to thank, because what goes back too. These people took time out of their lives to congratulate someone who did not know. It took me some time, but in the end I was able to answer all the messages. It was a beautiful moment. It is good to be part of an industry based on hospitality, sharing, and represent my country. My passport is Italian, but I say I'm Venezuelan because it wasn't in Italy that I was born, grew or lived. It is a feeling of belonging. I lived in France seven years, but I can't say I'm French. And now I have lived nine years in Hong Kong, but I can't say I'm from Hong Kong either.
 
How did you live in Hong Kong influence your personality? For example, I know you hired a Feng Shui master before opening the restaurant…
It was my partner who told me about it, when we opened. I thought, "Okay, I don't believe in anything, but I believe in everything." So why not? We all need to believe something.  Whenever the Feng Shui master visited the spaces where we considered opening the restaurant, he went around and said, "No, this is not the right place," until we found the space where we founded the mono. He returns every year, on the occasion of the Chinese New Year, to tell us what we need to change. 99% of the time, it says nothing excessive. When I speak of excessive, I mean… two years ago, Feng Shui advised against the use of red color. It turns out that Michelin's dish is red and was oscided right at the top of the kitchen. So we printed a blue deadline following the guidelines of the Michelin guide. The following year, the master returned and this time the dish had to be red. This year of the serpent, the master advised us to move to gold or silver, so there we will have to change again. It is still in production, but as soon as I can go there put it in silver tones. In the western world we also have the 13 as a number of bad luck, don't we? So it is not very distant from what we believe in the West. There are this kind of beliefs around the world.
 
The world of high-cove is associated with a lot of pressure and hours of extraordinary work. Is there any myth associated with this area that is not exactly true?
It is sad that we focus only on the high school, because there are so many other professions that require dedication and many hours of work. The kitchen is perhaps the most famous because it is the most disclosed. There are so many TV shows, series… and the people who watch TV love drama. But we think of doctors, volunteers in war zones, military industries, pilots, airport traffic controllers… I see many young people from the new generation constantly saying: “So many hours”, “I want to give up”… Okay, it depends on what the ambitions of each person are. If we want to be the best, we have to work hard. And it is not as if it is so eternally. But of course, being in a service industry, we have to be hospitable. In this sense, we are never out of time. We are always working with it in mind. It is a chip within us who never disconnect and that encourages us to serve people and help…
 
Before deciding to embark on gastronomy, he even considered to be a doctor. Do you consider that both professions approach in this sense? Do you have the purpose of helping people?
Undoubtedly. In Chinese culture, in particular, food is seen as medicine. Ginger warms up, lemon cools… and I believe it is true: what we introduce into our body can heal or kill us. If we do not pay attention to allergies or have food out of time or in poor condition, we can kill someone. If we go to a humble restaurant in a village that is not prepared to welcome food intolerances, we can die. Our profession is delicate and it is necessary to take it seriously. Chefs and even restaurant managers feel a lot of pressure to be everywhere, constantly alert, with their skin nerves. This is an industry that serves people, and people are all different. We have to consider each client and try to serve it as best as possible.
 
How has the world of upper-heart to evolve? Do you feel there is an effort to make you more inclusive?
I think this high-coven stereotype as a very rigid, formal and conduct codes has been changing, but it still exists. There are Japanese Sushi restaurants where, if the customer arrives a late minute, it is treated like garbage and can do nothing but swallow and return to the hotel. You cannot take pictures or use perfume; It is necessary to obey a certain type of dress code. Still, I think gastronomy is moving to a more affordable experience. Even if we go to the country most famous for gastronomy, France, or in restaurants with three Michelin stars, we see the maitre d 'put our hands on the table and talk casually to customers. In Mono, what we try to do is a very fresh line between casual and fine dining. For me, Fine Dining is attention to detail. This is what the Japanese taught us with the word MOTENASHI, which basically means anticipating customer needs. If you notice that a client has a small mouth, I try to anticipate and clarify that he can give two or three toothsides in an inflated so that he does not feel uncomfortable. The high-big one is not being tie, very formal, with impeccable hair. No doubt it sounds beautiful, it sounds so nush, but if you have this presentation and then provide a rude or rushed treatment… if you notice that the customer is cold and not offering something to cover, what is this flawless look worth?  The question of dress code relates more to respect for other customers. If someone appears in the restaurant with an elegant fact, it won't feel good if the table client is using shorts and cap. At the time of the reserve we warn that you can't wear a cap - many people ignore and, finally, we say nothing. All good. They are there for fun. The problem is theirs: they will be ridiculed because the person at the next table is well dressed and the soslaio look. But there is a point about which we have to speak honestly: the fine dining industry is experiencing difficulties. Not only Mono, but all restaurants in the world. We cannot afford to refuse customers or create problems. We try to accommodate as much as possible. Above all, it is a matter of common sense and principle. We are in the hospitality industry; We receive people and they have needs that we need to accommodate. As simple as that.
 
What is the fine dining anyway? How does food become art in this industry? When does a dish go from food to an artistic experience?
Art can be defined as a series of human activities that, through techniques and improvement of certain elements, can cause emotion. Cooking a noodles bowl is a human activity. If it evokes emotion or not, this is what defines the artistic element. For example, yesterday I ate bitches in a MGM restaurant and was delicious. This is the art. The restaurant may not have a Michelin star, may not be at the top of the world's best restaurants in the world, but has evoked a concrete emotion in me. He made me say, "Well, that's exactly what I wanted." In the culinary arts, we always try that our creations - be they a noodles bowl or a pigeon - provoke emotions and that the artist transmits something through his plate to the person he receives him. Therefore, if the message is well received and awakening emotions, I think we can call it art. And this applies to all areas. Perhaps what the end point is doing is also art. The way they conduct the interview, the feelings that arouse in people who read it, the way they deliver words, the knowledge about the work they are doing… All this can also be art. Everything can be art.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Family aggregates begin today to choose fractions of economic housing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/agregados-familiares-comecam-hoje-a-escolher-fraccoes-da-habitacao-economica/</link><description>Family aggregates skilled from the 2019 Economic Housing contest can begin today to choose the fractions. This morning, the first group of household aggregates will go to the Housing Institute (IH) to choose the fractions.
After choosing the economic housing fraction, the contractors must sign the Power and Selling Agreement and the related documents. At the time of signing the promissory contract, no payment is required. IH ensures that it will reserve enough time to treat formalities regarding mortgage loans by their household aggregates and will then notify the promissos-compliances through letters, to pay the housing values ​​and the treatment of formalities related to the reception of the keys of fractions indicated by the HI.
The economic housing contest opened in 2019 was the last held under the former Economic Housing Law. HI says that by February 24, 2025, 2,993 selected acquirers gather the requirements, and is sent by groups on the choice of fractions, accompanied by sales price discrimination tables. The electronic version of the catalog with the description of fractions for sale and the situation of the sale of fractions are available on the body's electronic page for consultation and unloading.
Economic housing available for acquisition in this contest are located in the Tong Seng Building (Lot B4), Tong Chong Building (Lot B9) and Tong Kai Building (Lot B10), in Zone A of new landfills, totaling 3,017 fractions, including 760 T1, 1,000 T2 and 1,257 T3 typology.
Fractions - Zone A Economic Housing Model of the new landfills are located on the 2nd floor of the Mong Tak Mong Housing Building there are, being the respective typologies, materials used and similar delivery criteria, and the selected purchasers may visit.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:12:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ias uses film “Ne Zha 2” to foster Chinese identity with young people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/ias-usa-filme-ne-zha-2-para-fomentar-identidade-chinesa-junto-dos-jovens/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS) organized, last Saturday, a screening session of the Chinese animation movie of Comedy and Fantasy “Ne Zha 2” at the Macao Cineteatro. The session was directed to children and adolescents from various homes of children and young people in Macao, as well as family support services. About 600 children with their parents were present.
IAS hopes that through the film, "support to participants will be provided that they are aware of self-improvement and self-realization." Authorities also expect young people to reinforce the "positive attitude towards life" and, at the same time, improve their knowledge of the country's soft power, as well as "strengthen the sense of identity with Chinese culture, in favor of its integration in both society and the environment and conjuncture of the country's development."
The organism also hopes that activity "not only allows children to feel the affection and love of government and society but also contribute to conveying the positive energy and planting in the heart of the same seeds of hope and courage."
The young people could then “enjoy a party party party brought by this great national film, understand the typical charm of traditional Chinese culture, feel the joy in the world of light and harvest the energy of love and courage,” reads in the IAS statement.
In the statement, the authorities ensure that the government “will continue to pay attention to the needs of children and adolescents of the families of the base social stratum and to work closely with the various social sectors to more diverse, support and assistance necessary for individuals and families in difficult situations, accompanying them to overcome various challenges of life in order to promote social inclusion and harmonious development”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:04:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan's largest fire in three decades has consumed 2,100 hectares and remains active</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/maior-incendio-do-japao-em-tres-decadas-ja-consumiu-2-100-hectares-e-continua-ativo/</link><description>The largest forest fire in Japan in three decades has consumed 2,100 hectares and remains active in offunate. Due to the spread of the fire, the city issued new evacuation orders early in the morning, affecting 1,197 people, which were transferred to 12 centers.
 
The largest forest fire in Japan in three decades has consumed 2,100 hectares and remains active in Office, province of Iwate, extending to a forest and surrounding neighborhoods near the city of Sanriku.
Faced with the spread of the fire, the city issued new evacuation orders at 7:00 am yesterday, affecting 1,197 people, which were transferred to 12 centers. "We are working to extinguish [the fire] as soon as possible, looking at the safety of residents at the same time," Yoshimasa Hayashi, said yesterday, said at a press conference.
The Japanese National Agency for Fire and Catastrophs Managed this Sunday has appealed to firefighters from all over the country to the union of efforts to combat fire and especially in the impediment of “propagation of fire in the resident area,” added Hayashi.
About 1,700 firefighters from 453 archipelago departments participate in the operation, supporting local force on the ground and air, with helicopters of self-defense forces (army).
Since the beginning of the fire last Wednesday, at least one death has been confirmed and the number of destroyed houses ascends to 84, but the authorities expect the numbers to increase when it is possible to evaluate the true dimension of the catastrophe, as the fire fighting efforts are currently prioritized.
The southern coast of the province of Iwate, where the city of Sanriku is located, has been on a dry weather alert since February 18, a phenomenon that favored the spread of the flames.
The local meteorological observatory provided for the maintenance of dry weather this Monday, although temperatures have passed hot and spring over the weekend to a sharp descent.
Forest Fire, the largest in the country for over three decades, has been raising among the residents of the earthquake and tsunami of 11 March 2011, which devastated the coast of offunate, making more than 500 dead and missing, and destroying a large number of houses and buildings. "It's as if Tsunami came ahead and the fire behind," described a 70 -year -old man who lived the 2011 earthquake in statements to the NHK public television station. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:13:14+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Expected 6.5% increase in game revenues of 2025, focusing on the second semester</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/esperado-aumento-de-65-nas-receitas-de-jogo-de-2025-com-foco-no-segundo-semestre/</link><description>Seaport Research Partners provides for a 6.5% annual growth in Macao game revenues, with a more significant increase in the second half of the year. Game operators await the deliberations resulting from the two sessions, which start today, to know how to impact the economic and tourist growth of MSAR.
 
Gross Macao game revenues may increase 6.5% in the year 2025 compared to the same period, according to consulting firm Seaport Research Partners.
The Vitaly Umansky Analyst, quoted by the Gggrasia Portal, notes that growth could be particularly expressive "in the second half of the year," as a consequence of "increasing operator marketing efforts and improving consumer sense feeling in China."
Umansky explains that the two annual sessions of Beijing, starting on March 4 and 5, should result in the implementation of strategies for Chinese economic growth, such as the approval of new fiscal stimuli and flexibility measures, which will positively affect gambling revenues and tourism.
It is recalled that these two sessions of China's main legislature, the National Popular Assembly (APN) and the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), usually occur in parallel in early March and have as its main objectives the definition of goals and priorities for the country's economic and social developments.
"With increasing customs rates in the United States, we hope that Chinese political responsible will seek to expand consumption more vigorously and improve the confidence of home consumers," continues the Seaport Research Powers analyst, quoted by Inside Asian Gaming, adding that this "favorable wind" would also cover the Macao region.
It warns, however: "One of the most prominent areas remains the reinforcement of the real estate market, which has contributed to the slowdown of the economy and significantly weakened consumer confidence, although there are signs of improvement."
Gggrasia points out that the probable reinforcement in the area of ​​tourism is sustained by the changes introduced by Beijing in 2024 to attract international visitors. These include widening the list of visa exemption countries (which has included Portugal since October last year) and the availability of Wechat Pay and Alipay electronic payment services to foreign users.
The latest forecasts are followed by data released by the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination (DICJ) last Sunday, which reported a growth of 6.8% in gross revenues reached in February compared to the previous year. There was also an improvement compared to January 2025, in this case of 8.2%.
It is important to remember that the estimate of growth of gross brace revenues of the MG and gambling fell from 7% to 3% at the beginning of the year, after a new year of the little bustling serpent. At the time, Citigroup's analysts said Macau would not have been able to reach gross revenue of early 589 million per day in January, as well as the approximately 900 million patacas in the first five days of February.
The prognosis for the second half of 2025 was more positive, with various events and shows planned for the summer time and the hope that the holidays of China National Day boost tourism and the economy of mashes.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:12:50+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China aims at US agricultural exports in response to Trump rates</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/china-visa-exportacoes-agricolas-dos-eua-em-resposta-a-taxas-de-trump/</link><description>China is considering the adoption of measures against US agricultural and food exports, in response to the US decision to increase rates on Chinese products by 20%, official press said yesterday.
"If the United States persists in the application of unilateral rates and officialize these measures, China will respond with firm and energetic countermearts," the Global Times, the Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper, has warned after the US has promised to impose more customs rates on Chinese products from March 4.
Possible retaliation would include tariff and non -tariff measures, with US agricultural and food products among the main targets, the newspaper wrote, which cites an anonymous source of the Chinese regime.
Last Friday, the Chinese Ministry of Commerce expressed in a statement the “firm opposition” to US plans, adding that China “repeatedly” that “unilateral rates violate the rules of the World Trade Organization (WTO) and“ harm the multilateral commercial system ”.
US President Donald Trump pledged to impose an additional 10% rate on China-he had announced 10% previously-with the argument that the country did not make enough efforts to combat Fentanil entry into the US.
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce has stated that "China is one of the countries with the most strict and comprehensive drug control policies in the world" and has actively cooperated with this issue with all nations in the world, "including the United States."
Trump made the rates of "progress" depend on the fight against fentanyl trafficking, also announcing 25% rates against Mexico and Canada. “Drugs are coming from Mexico and many of them are coming from China; Not all, but many of them are coming from China, ”he said.
Beijing responded last month to the first round of Trump rates with 10% and 15% tariffs on certain US products, as well as new export controls of essential minerals and an anti-monopoly investigation against the Google American technological giant.
In the first presidency (2017-2021), Trump had a tense relationship with Beijing by imposing several rounds of rates on goods from China, to which the Asian country responded with rates on US exports.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:04:44+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Carbon emitted by falling public buses</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/carbono-emitido-pelos-autocarros-publicos-em-queda/</link><description>Last year, the carbon emitted by the fleet of the two public bus operators was reduced by 3.9% and 7.5% compared to 2023. The information was released by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Che Sai Wang.
 
Last year, the two public bus operators - TCM and Transmac - reduced carbon emissions by their fleets by 3.9% and 7.5% compared to the previous year. By 2023, the reduction had been more pronounced, between 18.2% and 30%.
The information was shared by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Che Sa Wang.
Citing data from the Traffic Affairs Directorate Directorate (DSAT), DSPA also recalls that, until January 31 this year, 929 buses powered by new energies were circulated, belonging to the two bus operators, representing more than 92% of the total public buses operating in Macao. According to the data provided by the two bus operators in the last triennium, "the total carbon volume issued by the operational fleet of these two operators has decreased significantly."
On the other hand, until January this year, they operated in Macao 210 taxis moved exclusively to electricity, representing 11.9% of the total number of taxis in circulation, and 1,526 hybrid taxis, corresponding to about 86.2% of the total number of taxis in Macau.
At the interpetement, the deputy linked to the Association of Macao Public Function Workers (ATFPM) asked for details about the measures to promote the use of ecological vehicles. DSPA has given as examples the tax on new vehicle tax that use alternative energy and the creation of over 2,200 charging places for light cars and more than 600 charging places for moped and electrical motorcycles in public parking parks. In addition, this year was launched the pilot project for installation on the roads/neighborhoods, of Cyclomotor Battery Cabinets and Electric Motorcycles for Exchange.
"In the future, the Government of MSAR will continue to be aware of the increase in the number of electric vehicles and technological development, maintaining communication with the sector, as well as looking for more appropriate places in order to increase the number of these loading and battery exchange facilities," reads the DSPA response.
Authorities also remember that in order to intensify the inspection of obsolete vehicles and with high emissions of pollutant exhaust gas, as well as raise the owners' awareness of the repair and maintenance of their vehicles, from March last year, the random inspection inspection inspection was resumed in compliance with the exhaust gas emissions, and the inspection should not be subjected to the necessary reparation and inspection. Extraordinary or a new inspection, otherwise they are slaughtered.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:12:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Asylum requests in the EU fall 11% in 2024 compared to the previous year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/pedidos-de-asilo-na-ue-caem-11-em-2024-face-ao-ano-anterior/</link><description>The number of asylum requests in the community space fell 11% by 2024 compared to 2023, the Union Agency for Asylum (USAA) announced yesterday, revealing that requests from Syrians, Afghan, and Turkish "decreased significantly." “In 2024, the EU+ [European Union and also Switzerland, Norway and Iceland] received about one million asylum requests for the third consecutive year. However, a slight decrease compared to 2023 reflected the deviation of the typical seasonal standard in the second half of the year, ”says USAA in his report on the analysis of annual trends yesterday published. According to the European Agency, “several of the main nationalities of asylum applicants in the EU+ recorded a significant decrease by 2024”, as requests for Syrians (151,000), Afghan (87,000) and Turks (56,000) lowered 17%, 24%and 45%, compared to 2023.
Among the total 'cake' of about 1,014,000. Asylum in EU+, Latin American nationalities have also registered "remarkable changes in protection requests in 2024," the USAA said in a press release. In particular, Venezuelans (74,000) filed a record number of requests, an increase of 9% compared to 2023, while Colombians' requests (52,000) diminished almost one fifth (-18%) in 2024. Spain ”, according to the agency. As for Spain, "after a surge of ship arrivals to the Canary Islands, the Malians (17,000) and the Senegalese (14,000) had more than double the requests in the EU+, compared to 2023," is explained.
Last year, Germany (237,000) again received the largest number of asylum requests in the EU+, although the number was a lower third (-29%), compared to the previous year. Although Spain (166,000), Italy (159,000) and France (159,000) received numbers similar to the previous year of asylum requests in 2024, returning to about 16% of the total EU+total, these member states were confronted "with a new dynamic." "For example, the Peruvians (27,000), who continued to submit a significant number of requests at EU+, began to submit their requests especially in Italy in 2024, where they became the second most populous nationality," specifies the USA.
Still in 2024, about 4.4 million people displaced due to Russian Ukraine invasion were receiving temporary EU protection. Some Ukrainians submitted asylum requests to EU countries, registered last year “a significantly greater number” of requests (for 27,000), a 90% climb compared to 2023 and especially France and Poland. "The number of Ukrainian orders received in 2024 reminiscent of the initial numbers of 2022, after the start of the large -scale Russian invasion of Ukraine," he concludes.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:04:38+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Common sense, intent and creativity”, the secret ingredients of chef Ricardo Chaneton</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/bom-senso-intencao-e-criatividade-os-ingredientes-secretos-do-chef-ricardo-chaneton/</link><description>What defines the high-covenant? How does a meal go from a mere combination of ingredients on a plate to a sensory and artistic experience? Chef Ricardo Chaneton was challenged to answer this question, on the sidelines of the first lunch of a three -day culinary show organized by MGM Cotai. The answer was given in two moments: at the end of the event, in conversation with the end point, and throughout the gastronomic experience.
 
Macau received, between February 20 and 22, the first event of the series “Gastronomic Travel of Chefs Estrela”, promoted by MGM Cotai. Venezuelan chef Ricardo Chaneton was the guest of honor, bringing to the AJI restaurant a tasting menu of eight dishes that proposed to combine the flavors of South America with the refined techniques of French cuisine.
Chaneton is used to seeing his name associated with the word "star." He worked on some of the most prestigious restaurants in the world, from Spanish Kique Dacosta to Petrus of Hong Kong, passing to the French Mirazur. The restaurant it founded in Hong Kong, Mono, has been consecutively recognized with a Michelin star since 2022 and is currently on number 27 on the list of Asia's 50 best restaurants. The 38-year-old chef had already visited Macao on several occasions: just cross a bridge and “he's so close, but so far” from Hong Kong's frantic rhythm. However, it is the first time that comes to the neighboring region with the chef uniform, in an absolute debut for his career, the history of MGM and the Statute of Macau as a creative city of gastronomy.
It took three years for this lunch to come to fruition, as MGM Cotai's cooking director Adam Mathis explains. The connection between them dates back to an old professional partnership in a restaurant in Hong Kong (“I was my boss,” Chaneton rectifies, between laughs, “and while I am here will continue to be my boss”), which eventually consolidated in a friendship resistant to the years and work in different regions. In the “very aggressive, very competitive” city that is Hong Kong, the memories and stories in common around what Mathis does not hesitate to call “the most beautiful thing in the world” prevail: the food.
The time the event was Marinar transpires in the service of excellence, perfected to detail. As the previous dishes were removed and the following positioned on the table, Ricardo Chaneton was contextualizing the newly worked delicacies with a brief presentation monologue. Explained how each ingredient complemented to ascertain this or that brake in the final combination; He mentioned the origin and form of production of everything that ended on the plate but started well before, at the time of cultivation. Ensuring that everything is done with your own hands is “difficult”, as you confessed in the interview that followed lunch, but also “this is the beauty” of what is done in the mono restaurant. Let's think of the sourdish bread served with olive oil, one of the signing dishes that most approved waves got around the counter. Oil is produced by a lady who told us the chef as she gestured to illustrate the movement, comb the branches of the olive trees with her own hands and then collect the olives on the floor. Bread, labels, stamps, serial numbers: Everything is hand -made daily by the chef and his team in a kitchen that, he says, "is small, small, small."
Among the descriptions of different textures and flavors and the indications of how to consume dishes (some required utensils, others could be taken to the mouth), the greatest constant was the references to the house. Some dishes referred to Venezuela's street food; Others, he said, reminded him of meals that his grandmother prepared as a child. Ricardo has an Italian passport, by ancestry of his mother, but does not identify himself as such: at the cultural and identity level, is “100%” Venezuelan. At the gastronomic level, it was also in South America that his trip started. It was the grandmother who cooked; The mother “did not do much”, but remembers every detail of the “two or three” dishes she prepared. And it was irrelevant that his father only knew how to make pumpkin soup - "it was the best pumpkin soup in the world." Today, it honors him at the Mono restaurant with an aesthetic choice whose meaning will go unnoticed to many: a wall full of vinyl records his father used to play.
If we think of chef Chaneton's culinary experience as a gourmet dish, nostalgia will probably be the basic ingredient - and also the most lasting taste. Sprinkled as topping on the flavors of Latin America, come the teachings from all over where he went from Europe to Asia, from the first cookeds to the first Michelin star. The result is a fusion of nostalgia and experiences and learning that individualizes their work among other fine dining restaurants in Hong Kong, Asia, in the world. If a chef is a storyteller, repeating one of the commonplaces in the world of high school, the stories narrated by Ricardo Chaneton are absolutely unrepeatable.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Postponed public tender to assign taxi licenses</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/adiado-concurso-publico-para-atribuicao-de-licencas-de-taxi/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) announced that the new public tender for the attribution of taxi licenses was postponed, due to the need to change administrative regulations and optimize the contest process.
The president of the General Association of Macau Taxi Drivers, Tony Kuok, suggested the organization of a clarification session on the subject, in order to reinforce communication with the public and explain the procedures, requirements and legal content relevant to the contest.  Among the points that require additional clarifications, according to Kwok, the existence-or not-of a law on labor relations is included.
The Association's president also recalled that more than 300 licenses will expire in June: more than 200 relating to ordinary taxis and about 100 taxi radios (those that can be called by telephone call).
Ku Heng Cheong, a traffic advis council member, agreed with the need to improve the contest process and stressed, on the other hand, the importance of developing a passenger transport service online - for example, through the Macau Smart Go platform. In the face of DSAT's concern and taxi sector in relation to this issue, Ku Heng Cheong considered that the initial development of any industry will inevitably impact the existing industry and the industry and the industry and the existing industry and the existing industry and that it is up to the government to find a balance between platforms and drivers and safeguard the safety of passengers.
It is recalled that the Association of Professionals and Taxi operators in Macau has recently rejected the implementation of a passenger transport service by application, claiming that private companies such as Didi or Uber are incompatible with the region's social and road conditions. Alternatively, sector workers suggest the development of an application to call taxis.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:04:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Financial Reserve investments yielded nearly 31 billion last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/investimentos-da-reserva-financeira-renderam-quase-31-mil-milhoes-no-ano-passado/</link><description>The RAEM's financial reserve registered an investment income of the order of 30.95 billion Patacas in 2024, the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) said yesterday. At the end of 2024, the value of the reserve's capital was in the 616.2 billion patacas. In a statement, AMCM warns of the challenges that the reserve will face this year.
 
The MSAR Financial Reserve grew 30.95 billion Patacas last year due to investments made. Thus, a 5.3%annual profitability was registered, the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) said yesterday. The body adds that, by the end of 2024, the value of the financial reserve's capitals ascended to 616.21 billion patacas, of which the basic reserve represented 153.39 billion patacas and the extraordinary reserve 462.82 billion.
In a statement, AMCM explains that, last year, "in the context of a gradually controlled inflationary situation, the central banks of many countries have successively reduced their political interest rates, which favored the tendency of financial markets." However, "the variation of the growth pace of the main world economies, geopolitical complications and the gradual adjustment of market expectations regarding central bank interest rates have caused financial assets to retire from their maximums at the end of the year."
AMCM also points out that "although global financial markets have continued to float this year, the most diverse allocation of financial reserve assets played a complementary role, helping to balance returns and risks." The MSAR reserve “focuses on allocation of high quality assets that can provide stable returns and have lower risks, while moderately optimizing the structure of the license portfolio to achieve the preservation and appreciation of capital”, explains the body.
The reserve "plays an important role in supporting social and economic stability," the government points out, adding that Macau is currently "in a crucial period of economic recovery", so the executive "must use and allocate public financial resources with caution."
This year, “facing geopolitical uncertainty”, AMCM predicts the prices of various types of assets, “bringing challenges to the management of financial reserves in the current year” are affected.
"Given the uncertain environment of the financial market and to ensure that the financial reserve continues to play an essential role in supporting the implementation of public financial policies of MSAR and guaranteeing the capacity to pay long -term public finances, we will adhere to the basic principle of" effective and stable "by dealing with the financial reserve," the AMCM, giving priority to "control of the risk of descent", to "detention of a higher proportion of a proportion. high security and liquidity investment products ”and the“ timely adjustment of allocation in response to market conditions ”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:13:13+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Must receives seminar on sustainable architecture with Marco Imperidori</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/must-recebe-seminario-sobre-arquitectura-sustentavel-com-marco-imperadori/</link><description>The Circle of Macao Culture Friends (CAC) organizes, on March 20, a seminar dedicated to sustainable architecture, with the presence of Professor Marco Imperidori. The event, entitled “Care Architecture” and “Arte Sella: a balance between architecture and nature”, will take place in Room 220, Block N, Macao University of Science and Technology (Must), between 15h00 and 18h15. Participation is free, but subject to prior registration.
The seminar, which is part of the Continuous Professional Development Program (CPD), will be conducted in English and will address topics such as energy efficiency in buildings, innovative construction systems and harmonization between architecture and nature. Marco Imperidori, a full -seated professor and researcher in the polytechnic di Milano, is a renowned figure in the field of sustainable architecture and technological innovation. With vast academic and professional experience, Imperidori has been taught in various institutions, including the University of São José, where he was a visiting professor between 2015 and 2023. His research focuses on the creation of high energy efficiency buildings and the integration of construction systems that promote sustainability. He is also the author of numerous publications on architectural innovation and energy conservation.
Participation in the seminar is limited to a maximum number of registrations, so the timely registration is recommended. Interested parties can register online or scan the QR code available in the disclosure material. The deadline for registration ends on March 19, 2025, at 5:30 pm. Participants wishing to obtain a certificate should register their presence and pay a rate of 200 patacas.
This event was sponsored by the Macau Foundation and the institutional support of the Musting School of Humanities and Arts, the Macao Architects Association and the SCM Albergue.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:03:28+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China maintains a position and avoids commenting on the Trump-Zelensky meeting</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/china-mantem-posicao-e-evita-comentar-a-reuniao-trump-zelensky/</link><description>China yesterday reaffirmed its position on the war in Ukraine and avoided commenting on the tense meeting between US President Donald Trump and Ukrainian homologist Volodymyr Zelensky in the White House on Friday.
Asked at a press conference about Trump's statements, which accused Zelensky of risking World War II and not ready for peace, the country's Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman, Lin Jian, has just stressed that "China will continue to play a constructive role in the search for a political solution to the Ukraine crisis." When asked again about the meeting in Washington, the spokesman reiterated the same answer and added that China "is neither the creator of the crisis in Ukraine nor part involved in the conflict."
Beijing supports "all efforts aimed at a peaceful resolution" and hopes that conflict parties will find "a sustainable and lasting solution that responds to their respective concerns," he said.
Since the beginning of the war in Ukraine, China has maintained an ambiguous position on conflict, appealing to respect for the “territorial integrity of all countries,” including Ukraine, and attention for the “legitimate concerns of all countries” in a reference to Russia.
Beijing was opposed to unilateral sanctions against Moscow and appealed to "decancing and a political solution." However, the West accused China of supporting Russia's military campaign, something the Asian country has always denied.
China has sent diplomatic representatives to the region and presented peace initiatives, such as the plan it elaborated with Brazil last year, which did not include the removal of Russian troops and was rejected by Kiev.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:12:44+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Mixue's actions debut in Hong Kong with 40% appreciation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/accoes-da-chinesa-mixue-estreiam-se-em-hong-kong-com-valorizacao-de-40/</link><description>The largest chain of food and drink products in the world, Chinese Mixue, debuted yesterday on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange with gains of up to 40%after an almost record offer. The actions opened with an increase of 29.4%compared to the pre-opening price of 202.5 dollars from Hong Kong and, in the middle of the session, were rising 40.05%.
This situation contrasts with the tendency of other local rival companies that also opened capital last year and, after the initial enthusiasm, registered strong falls, given the intense competition in the sector.
Mixue said on Friday that the search for its actions was 5.258 times higher than the number of actions offered, which makes it one of the most successful initial public offering operations in the history of the former British colony scholarship. The company based in Zhengzhou, downtown China, raised $ 3.455 billion from Hong Kong with Opi.
Mixue, which focuses especially on the popular bubble teas (tea with milk and tapioca balls), ice cream cones or soda, had over 46,000 stores worldwide in late 2024, more than double the number at the end of 2021, which attests to its rapid expansion thanks to the cheap product model.
These numbers exceed better global names, such as McDonald's and Starbucks, which are the only ones to overcome the mark of the 40,000 stores worldwide.
The fourth to first place jump from the table took place at the end of the third quarter of 2024, according to Singapore's Momentum Works consultant, who recalls that the vast majority of points of sale is in China, with only about 4,800 spread through Vietnam, Malaysia and Thailand.
However, the Chinese chain remains the fourth largest in the world in terms of sales in the global beverage sector: the $ 6.59 billion that sold by 2023 puts it behind Starbucks, Inspire Brands-owner of Dunkin 'Donuts and Baskin-Robins-and Tim Hortons.
Mixue focuses on low-cost drinks, maintaining product prices usually below 10 yuan, a segment expecting a 17.6%annual growth, by 2028, when this market will reach the equivalent of about $ 160 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:05:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial activity in China increased to a maximum of three months in February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/actividade-industrial-na-china-aumentou-para-um-maximo-de-tres-meses-em-fevereiro/</link><description>China's transforming industry activity has grown in February to the strongest pace of the last three months, according to a private analysis based on sector data released yesterday.
The Shopping Managers Index (PMI, the industry's reference indicator), compiled by the British Economic Information Company IHS Markit and published by Chinese CAIXIN magazine, rose 0.7 points to 50.8 points in February.
When it is over 50 points, PMI suggests an expansion of the sector, while below this barrier presupposes an activity contraction.
The value also exceeded the expectations of analysts, who expected a more modest recovery for about 50.3 points.
This weekend, the National Statistics Office (GNE) released its official PMI for February, which has also hit its best reading since November. In this case, it has passed negative in January (49.1) to the expansion level (50.2) last month.
According to Wang Zhe, CAIXI economist, the “powerful recovery” of consumption during the New Year's holidays lunar has boosted confidence in the sector, although the economy still faces problems, such as uncertainty in the labor market or family income, which make efforts to boost internal demand.
Prior to the opening this week of the annual session of China's highest legislative agency, the National Popular Assembly, Wang appealed to support measures to focus on market expectations and society's concerns, giving priority to demand side initiatives.
Zichun Huang, analyst at British Capital Economics consultant, highlighted the improvement of both production and new orders in February, also referring to greater demand from abroad.
In the latter case, the analyst stated that the external demand for Chinese products is probably driven by US importers, who are accelerating their purchases before the additional fees announced by US President Donald Trump, and expecting new rates to be applied later.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:08:20+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao deaf association appeals to reforms in the hearing health system</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/associacao-de-surdos-de-macau-apela-a-reformas-no-sistema-de-saude-auditiva/</link><description>The Macao deaf association requested a reform in the hearing health system, focusing on legislation, economic support and services integration. With more than 5,000 cases of hearing impairment in the territory, the association warns of increasing acquired hearing losses, such as those caused by industrial noise or aging. The Director-General, Lau Sut Man, advocates regular follow-ups, public education and review of noise control standards to create a comprehensive system that promotes hearing health at all ages.
 
The Macao Deaf Association defended this week the need for deep reform in the territory's auditory health system, pointing out three priority axes: legislation, economic support and services integration. The Association Director-General, Lau Sut Man, in statements made to the newspaper or Mun, stressed that the number of cases of hearing loss acquired, such as damage caused by exposure to age-related industrial noise or hearing degeneration, has recorded a significant increase in recent years. Currently, the association provides support to about 800 people, but it is estimated that the actual number of individuals with hearing problems in need in the territory is higher than official data.
According to the latest statistics, there are more than 5,000 people with hearing impairment in Macao, which represents almost half of the total of individuals with disabilities in the territory. This number places deafness as the second largest cause of deficiency in the region, a fact that has led the association to press authorities to create a broader and more effective hearing protection system. Lau Sut Man defended the implementation of a model that covers the entire life cycle, from childhood to old age, integrating intervention strategies directed to specific groups such as babies, adolescents, elderly and workers exposed to noisy environments.
The official also warned of the need to review in force noise control standards to ensure an alignment with international standards, and to create a data platform that allows monitoring the needs of the population in hearing health.
"The current policy is mainly based on disability assessment data, which excludes many unhealthy cases and limits access to rehabilitation subsidies and services," explained the director general. This scenario has excluded many individuals who, despite facing hearing difficulties, do not fit the criteria for receiving economic support.
Hearing loss is often seen as a natural consequence of aging, but can lead to other health complications if it is not properly diagnosed and treated. Although Macao already performs hearing tracks in newborns, there is no regular detection mechanism for the various age groups. This gap has been pointed out as one of the main challenges for the prevention and early treatment of hearing problems. The Association defends the integration of hearing screening for different ages in the public health system, as well as the development of education strategies to promote hearing health among the population.
One of the groups that has deserved particular attention from the association is that of young people, who are increasingly exposed to risks associated with prolonged ear use and the frequency of noisy game environments. The creation of public education campaigns and the inclusion of hearing screening in school health programs are some of the suggested measures.
The Macao deaf association expects these proposals to be considered by the government at the next set -up plan for rehabilitation and support for the elderly. The creation of a hearing health data platform, reviewing noise control standards and improving the economic support system is seen as essential steps to ensure that hearing health is accessible to all.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:14:04+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections for the Legislative Assembly scheduled for September 14</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/eleicoes-para-a-assembleia-legislativa-agendadas-para-14-de-setembro/</link><description>The elections for the Legislative Assembly are scheduled for September 14 and the maximum amount of expenses spent for each application is set at 3.5 million patacas, equal to the previous elections. The Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly attributes “great importance” to the elections because they are the first after the review of the electoral law.
 
The date for the elections for the 8th Legislative Assembly (AL), which will be held on September 14, was set. It will also be the first scrutiny for the hemiciclo after the revision of the electoral law for LA last year, which provides for the exclusion of candidates considered non -patriots.
The information was announced through an executive order published yesterday in an official bulletin. An order of the Chief Executive, also published yesterday, established that the limit of expenses that each application can spend in the legislative elections was fixed at 3,549,622 Patacas, the same as in the 2021 elections.
Seng Ioi Man, chairman of the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Committee (Caeal), pointed out that legislative elections are "great importance" because they are the first elections after changing the law, so CAEAL will be seriously implementing the principle of "Macau ruled by patriots" and advances election work according to laws and high quality. "
On the sidelines of a CAEAL meeting held yesterday, the official recalled that the review of the electoral law for AL was passed in April last year, which stipulates, according to Seng Ioi Man, an “improvement of the candidates' eligibility verification mechanism and the National Security safeguard law system, as well as reinforcement of the provisions of non -compliance with law”.
"In this way, a more equitable, fair and righteous electoral environment will be created, as well as better conditions for eligible voters to participate actively in the elections," argued the judge of the Court of Second Instance.
It is recalled that, before the amendment of law, in the legislative elections of direct suffrage in 2021, the candidacy of five lists and 21 candidates, 15 of which pro-democracy, “not defending the basic law” and not being “faithful to mashes” was excluded.
The exclusion was later confirmed by the Last Instance Court, which gave “as a reset” that at least two of the candidates participated in support activities incompatible with Macao's legislation, namely the June 4 vigils.
At that time, of the 323,907 voters voted only 137,279, which represented the highest abstention rate since the establishment of the MSAR, while the influx rate was 42%, which contradicts the 57% stake in 2017.
 
Important dates
 
The chronology was released yesterday for the elections, which indicates that Caeal begins to make the form available for the constitution of a candidacy committee from Thursday and the agent must present to Caeal the candidacy and the political program before June 26. In case of absence of complaints from Caeal's decision, the list of admitted candidacies will be published, late, on July 18.
Electoral propaganda made through commercial advertising will be prohibited from June 27, while the election campaign period will take place between August 30 and September 12.
CAEAL, moreover, issued Instruction No. 1/CAEAL/2025 with binding value, which determines criteria and rules related to electoral propaganda, electoral expenses, duty of neutrality, the duty of confidentiality and the mode of voting.
 
Traditional elections and associations
 
The president of Caeal was also asked about the impact on the integrity of elections by candidates who have close connection with traditional associations, namely the possible ambiguity between the election campaign and the activities of the associations.
Seng Ioi Man, in this case, stated that the social assistance activities of the associations in which the candidates participate "should not be linked to the electoral elements", giving an example of the attribution of related gifts and slogans, as "residents receiving gifts may be confused."
"Candidates should clearly know the requirements and legal restrictions and have the sensitivity and awareness that this type of behavior is prohibited," he warned. However, the official stressed that there is no need to ban him from attending events, provided that the candidate does not mention his candidacy and the political program at the event.
The Macao Hemiciclo consists of 33 deputies, 14 of which are elected by direct suffrage, 12 for indirect suffrage and seven appointed by the government. Most of the elected by suffrage are the context of traditional local associations, including workers, women and residents, as well as connections to the communities of Jiangmen and Fujian.
 
Open line and online portal for complaints
 
For this year's legislative elections, Caeal and the Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) have together created an open line for complaints, which operates 24 hours a day, and an electronic page for complaints, to which any resident can appeal if it detects electoral offenses. The online portal is already on service and the direct line 2899 7733 is running today.
The deputy commissioner against corruption, Wong Kim Fong, stressed that the prevention and fight against electoral corruption is the statutory competence of CCAC, and the corruption commissioned has already instructed the supervision of legislative elections.
According to the press conference, CCAC and Caeal have established a communication and coordination mechanism with other competent departments and, whenever a complaint that is related to other organisms is received, will be sent to the competent services to follow him. "CCAC will oversee electoral activities in all aspects and monitor, according to the law and without tolerance, all situations of electoral corruption," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:15:18+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>APN starts with focus on the economy and trade war with the USA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/04/apn-arranca-com-foco-na-economia-e-guerra-comercial-com-eua/</link><description>China's maximum legislative agency begins its annual session focused on maintaining the impetus of recovery in the world's second largest economy, in a period of aggravation of the trade war with Washington.
 
Advances in the area of ​​Artificial Intelligence, materialized by the DeepSeek platform, and the recent meeting between Chinese President Xi Jinping and private sector entrepreneurs, returned confidence to investors, resulting in the strong recovery in China's financial squares. But optimism is already being disturbed by the entry into force of new customs rates in the United States over Chinese products.
The National Popular Assembly (APN), whose annual session runs until March 11, is described by the official press as the “supreme organ of state power in China” and the “maximum expression of socialist democracy”.
The President of the Assembly, Zhao Leji, is officially the number two of the Chinese hierarchy, following the Secretary-General of the Communist Party and President Xi Jinping. The Prime Minister, I read Qiang, is number three.
The approximately 3,000 delegates to APN, including a representation of the Armed Forces, are not, however, elected by direct suffrage, and the "leading role" of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) is "a heart principle."
Delegates include the political elite, business, technological, media and artistic leaders of the Asian country.
This week, the delegates will pass new laws, political appointments and government reports, which detail the progress of various departments and ministries. The budget for defense or the economic growth target are usually announced on the first day.
Analysts expect Beijing to set the goal of economic growth by about 5%. In order to achieve this goal, politicians should increase China's official budgetary deficit to the highest value of the last three decades, injecting liquidity into a deflationist economy, a profound real estate crisis and, more recently, the aggravation of trade war with the United States.
Almost two months after Donald Trump's new presidency began, the world's two largest economies are shocking, making it more urgent for Beijing to stimulate domestic consumption.
In recent years, exports have been the main growth engine of the Chinese economy, but protectionist measures adopted by the US and other business partners oblige Chinese leaders to prioritize the expansion of internal demand.
China is prepared to change its politics this year, said Yao Yang, professor of economics at Beijing University, quoted by Bloomberg news agency. The official warned that the measures are not yet bold enough. "My first concern is that the fiscal stimulus is not large enough, especially if we consider the debt of local administrations," he said.
Investors in currency are attentive, as authorities have focused more on maintaining the Chinese currency, Yuan, stable than to make monetary policy more flexible.
China's Central Bank has consistently fixed the exchange rate above 7.2 yuan per dollar, contrary to predictions that China would devalue its currency to compensate for the increase in customs rates by the US. “The trade war will undoubtedly be at the top of the agenda at APN's closed door. With more rates to be applied just a day before the opening [plenary session], it is unlikely that China's budgetary position immediately change. But with the increase in external pressures, political decision makers will be able to accelerate the application of stimuli, ”wrote Bloomberg.
This means that the government will have to increase its own investment and encourage companies and families to spend more. A fundamental indicator for evaluating the magnitude of the stimulus is the expansion of the public deficit.
Authorities should increase the purpose of this year's official budgetary deficit to about 4% of GDP, against 3% in 2024, according to different analysts.
The package foreseen by economists includes a quota of two billion Yuan (263 billion euros) for new sovereign obligations - twice the volume of last year - and up to four Yuan billion (526 billion euros) in new obligations of local administrations. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-04T04:12:45+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>