<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/templos-e-fronteira-colonial-sao-cenario-de-combates-entre-tailandia-e-camboja/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>DSAL promises “favorable” conditions for locals to work in the financial sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/dsal-promete-condicoes-favoraveis-para-locais-trabalharem-no-sector-financeiro/</link><description>The Directorate of Labor Affairs Services confirmed the adjustment and control of the number of non-resident workers, thus promoting the entry and professional development of locals in the financial sector and administrative jobs. According to the organization, the Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion has helped, since May, the job matching of more than 4,000 people.

Legislative Assembly member Ella Lei was concerned about the lack of opportunities for residents to work in administrative or financial sectors, but the Government assures that it is creating “more favorable conditions” for the development of locals’ professional careers in these areas.
The Labor Affairs Bureau (DSAL) also promised that it will adjust and control the number of non-resident workers, in an “appropriate and timely” manner, taking into account the trend of Macau's economic development and the needs in the labor market.
It will also adopt several measures to “support Macau residents in accessing employment and increasing their competitiveness in employment, striving to coordinate the balance between supply and demand in the employment market, making every effort to ensure the rights and interests of residents in terms of priority in access to employment”, he highlighted.
The guarantees were given in response to a question from Ella Lei, where the proportion of non-resident workers in the Macau labor market once again became a topic. According to the deputy, many residents work or intend to work in administrative or financial sectors, but many positions are occupied by non-resident workers.
DSAL data show that, until the end of September this year, the financial sector had 881 non-resident workers, of which 456 were unskilled and 425 specialized. Ella Lei considers that there are still “plenty of recruitment opportunities” for local workers and space for locating management staff in this sector, taking into account that there were still around 500 residents who wanted to work in the financial sector.
The deputy, in this sense, suggested that the Government define a clear proportion for the occupation of specialized or management positions by local workers in the financial sector and in administrative positions. However, DSAL did not take any position on the matter. Instead, he highlighted the results of the work of the Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion that the Government of Sam Hou Fai created in May this year.
“Since the creation of the Working Group to date, through large-scale recruitment sessions, specific matching sessions and professional placement actions, among other work, more than 4,000 people have been successfully supported in their job search”, emphasized DSAL, explaining that the group analyzes the situation of the local job market, collecting information on job vacancies and organizing job matching actions for young people.
DSAL, according to the response, organized in November, together with the Macau Banks Association, a specific matching session for the banking sector in 2025, which provided more than 200 job vacancies in that sector, but the placement results are still being collected.
Another initiative was the launch this year of the specific “Employment + Training” Plan by DSAL and Macau financial technology companies. According to the authorities, the program aims to encourage the sector to create clear conditions for career progression, being able, after completing three years of practical training in a work context in different areas and passing the exam, to be promoted to the level of manager or manager, in order to encourage professional advancement and the training of qualified local management staff for modern financial development.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:17:55</pubDate></item><item><title>More than seven thousand teachers received training on national security</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/mais-de-sete-mil-docentes-receberam-formacao-sobre-seguranca-nacional/</link><description>Over the last three academic years, more than seven thousand teachers have participated in training courses related to national security. It represented the vast majority of non-higher education teaching staff in Macau, with the number varying between 7,025 and 7,325 in those years. The Education and Youth Development Services announced the launch of more activities to deepen the patriotic feeling of teachers, students and young people.

The Constitution, the Basic Law of Macau and the Law on the Defense of State Security are elements that are now part of the core development activities program for teaching staff in Macau. Between the academic years 2022/2023 and 2024/2025, the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) held more than 100 training course sessions related to national security, which were attended by more than seven thousand teachers.
DSEDJ, in response to a written question from Congresswoman Wong Kit Cheng, said that these training courses, aimed at teaching staff, were “Training on National Security Education, “National Security and the ‘One Country, Two Systems’ Principle” and “Lecture Series: Education on National Security”.
It should be remembered that, in Macau, teaching staff in public and private non-higher education schools must participate in nuclear development activities, with a certain number of hours of participation in order to obtain career promotion. And, according to the Macau Children's Database, from the Institute of Social Action, the number of teaching staff in kindergarten, primary and secondary education was 7,025 in 2022/2023, 7,157 in 2023/2024 and 7,325 in the last academic year. In other words, the Government's national security training covers the vast majority of the local teaching team.
DSEDJ, in its response, said it had also invited, between April and June this year, the Center for the Study of Constitutional Law and Basic Law of the Faculty of Law of the University of Macau to hold a training course for teachers, entitled “the application of the Constitution, the Basic Law and education on national security in the course ‘Moral and Civic Education’”.
Its objective was to “strengthen Macau teaching staff’s understanding of the principles of governance in accordance with the law, the concept of national security and the general perspective of national security, as well as enhance their professional pedagogical capacity”.

TRIPS TO THE CONTINENT
 
According to Kong Chi Meng, director of DSEDJ, in response, around 20,000 participations of teachers and students are organized and financed annually in activities carried out in the context of study itineraries in the country, with visits to the “National Bases for Demonstration of Patriotic Education” and the “National Educational Bases for Scientific Popularization”.
The authorities have also created a series of branded educational activities for patriotic education, such as the “National Defense Education Day”, which “enriches the pedagogical quality and options regarding the education of love for the Fatherland in Macau”.
In this sense, to “deepen patriotic feeling and awareness for national security”, DSEDJ guarantees that it will continue to organize and subsidize teachers, students and young people to travel to patriotic education bases and the “Education Training Base on General Perspective of National Security for Macau Youth” in the interior of China, as well as to participate in visits and study to historical ruins or “red education” bases.
Emphasizing efforts to promote patriotic education, the organization summarized that the work follows three principles – guiding, systematic and innovative, with updating curricula and teaching materials and carrying out systematic activities, among other means. Through these measures, DSEDJ hopes to cultivate students' patriotic feelings from their childhood.
It should be remembered that the legal framework for regular education in the local school system in force requires that students learn systematically in class about the education of love for the country and Macau. The complementary teaching materials for “National Security Education” have been part of the pedagogical plan from pre-school to university education in Macau since the 2024/2025 academic year.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:15:43</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP received a complaint about illegal dog breeding in Hac Sá</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/cpsp-recebeu-denuncia-sobre-criacao-ilegal-de-caes-em-hac-sa/</link><description>Authorities were alerted to the alleged breeding of around 70 dogs in a house on Estrada de Hac Sá, which were causing noise and affecting the health of the surrounding public spaces. The situation was assessed by the Public Security Corps (CPSP) last month, and no evidence of any “abnormal” situation was found. The case was revealed by the president of the Council of Administration for Municipal Affairs (CAAM), Chao Wai Ieng, who admitted that there are not yet conditions for the full implementation of the CED (“Capture, Sterilization, Return”) program across the entire territory of Macau.
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) received a complaint in November about the alleged breeding of “a large number of dogs” in a house on Estrada de Hac Sá, in Coloane. After inspection, authorities confirmed the breeding of four dogs in the house in question, although they did not find “abnormal” or unsanitary situations. The case was disclosed by the chairman of the Council of Administration for Municipal Affairs (CAAM), Chao Wai Ieng, in response to a written question from deputy Leong Hong Sai.
In the question sent to the Government at the end of October, the deputy linked to the General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau expressed concern about the increase in the number of stray animals in Macau, with particular expression in the Hac Sá Village, and its consequences on the community environment. Leong Hong Sai urged the Government to collaborate with “the community and civil associations” in the management of stray dogs and cats in the territory, through the implementation of “scientific and humane methods” that take into account factors such as “the rights and interests of animals”.
In the first of three points, the deputy began by questioning the authorities about their plans to take advantage of the Municipal Kennel facilities and create conditions to “reduce and control, in the long term and in a humane way, the number of stray dogs and cats, in order to reduce the impact on the community”.
In the response document, Chao Wai Ieng states that the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) “has given importance to controlling stray animals at source”, namely through inspection and capture with traps, promoting adoption and sterilization and cleaning up garbage and food waste on the street.
The IAM's strategy is twofold, as the person responsible explains: while trying to reduce the proliferation of stray animals, efforts are also made to ensure that some of the animals are adopted “by appropriate adoption families, so that they can be cared for properly, thus achieving palliative and definitive effects”.
On the other hand, the institute has also been “improving and optimizing the facilities of the two municipal kennels” – carrying out, for example, the renovation of spaces for activities and ventilation and thermal insulation facilities.
CPSP RECEIVED COMPLAINT IN HAC SÁ
On a second point, deputy Leong Hong Sai mentioned that he had received complaints regarding the breeding of “around 70 dogs” in the Povoação de Hac Sá, generating concerns among residents. “How will the authorities execute the law in a rational way to improve the situation and allow the community to return to an ideal environment?”, he asked.
The CAAM representative begins by ensuring that the IAM “constantly deploys personnel” to carry out patrols in the “black spots” of the city, including in this definition areas such as the Concórdia Industrial Park, the Vale das Borboletas, Vila de Coloane, the Ká Hó Dam and the Hac Sá Dam. “If there are situations of violation of the provisions of the Animal Protection Law by owners during the inspection, the offenders will be charged in accordance with the law”, guarantees the person in charge.
The situation mentioned in the written statement was recognized by the CPSP, which at the beginning of November received a letter from the Consultative Council for Community Services of the Islands alleging the existence of “a large number of dogs being raised in a house on Estrada de Hac Sá, next to the Ancient Path of Seac Min Pun”. According to the complaint, the animals were affecting the health of the surrounding public spaces.
On the 6th and 7th of November, the CPSP sent agents to the aforementioned area for an inspection, and it was found that four dogs were being bred with the appropriate license in an “independent house”. So far, the authorities emphasize, the sanitary conditions of public roads remain “normal”, and no “traces of stray dogs” or other situations outside the law have been found.
However, the CPSP says that it “will continue to monitor this situation” and that any requests for support or complaints regarding “disturbing noise” will be reported immediately to the competent services.
CED PROGRAM STILL WITHOUT CONDITIONS
In a third and final question posed to the Government, Leong Hong Sai recalled that, currently, stores or associations that want to sterilize and return stray animals under the CED (“Capture, Sterilization, Return”) program are required to submit “to various registrations” and to assume “legal responsibilities for future acts on the street committed by these animals” – which often leads to the withdrawal of participation in the program.
In response, the president of CAAM admits that there are no conditions to fully develop the measures foreseen in the CED program in all areas of Macau, citing factors such as “the high population density” of the region and “the influence on the lives of the population, the ecological environment of the forests [and] public health”. “The IAM will continue to study various viable methods to control stray animals, taking into account the viability and consensus of society”, guarantees the person in charge.
The CED pilot project was presented by the Government in 2022, although concrete plans for its implementation were never outlined. Instead, stray dogs and cats captured by the Municipal Kennel – and which meet certain requirements – are made available for adoption under the “Capture-Sterilize-Adopt” (CEA) program, under the risk of being slaughtered if no potential adopters are found.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:16:20</pubDate></item><item><title>“I would like to work in the hyperreality created by casinos”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/gostaria-de-trabalhar-na-hiper-realidade-criada-pelos-casinos/</link><description>Photographer Edgar Martins won the Grand Prize of the Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025, worth 25 thousand euros, for the work “Anton’s Hand is Made of Guilt”. In an interview with PONTO FINAL, the artist, who grew up in Macau, but now lives in England, tells how it all happened, but also talks about his career and also mentions the role that the territory had and has in his life.
 
What is the importance of the Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025?
In Portugal, it quickly established itself as one of the biggest art awards, not just photography. I was as surprised as I was happy. I don't tend to categorize my work as photography, in the traditional sense of the term, but it is, for all intents and purposes, photographic, and photography doesn't do very well when it's forced to compete with other mediums. I imagine it must be a difficult award to evaluate, because each artist has to present only one work — and, in my specific case, it is one work within the context of a seven-year project. Not only is choosing the work difficult, but making this work representative of the work in general is also very difficult. I am happy with the fact that the jury was able to see beyond these three photographs — it was a triptych, a work composed of three photographs on the wall — and that they understood that, in a project about the disappearance of a friend, what is visible is always based on a vast field of invisibility.

The inspiration for this triptych is the death of his photojournalist friend in the Libyan Civil War. How did this happen?
Not just death, but kidnapping — disappearance. We know he was killed, but the hardest part is his disappearance. The fact that there are no answers, that there is no conclusion to this whole process.

Does it therefore have a much more personal value, compared to other work already done?
It's the most personal work I've been involved in, but it's part of a deliberate break I made with my way of working, around 2015. The Libyan Civil War was in 2011. Anton disappeared in 2011. By then, I had already started thinking about more ethically complex topics and wanted to work on them, but I couldn't do it in the way I was working at the time. I had to make a conscious break with my methodology and this work is the third of three projects that took place, starting in 2015. The first was a collaboration with the National Institute of Legal Medicine and Forensic Sciences, on the representation of suicide and homicide. How photography can represent something that is absent. What does it mean for photography if it does not identify with the referent, but with its absence? The project that followed that was the collaboration with a prison here in England — a three-year project, but where I also thought about this issue of absence, in prison as a space that generates absences.

Why do you tend not to consider your work as photography?
It's photographic. I don't know if I consider it photography, in the traditional sense of the word, or at least today. I think that, at a certain point, especially in the first ten years of my artistic practice, I perhaps considered it more photography, because I was more linked to the structures of photography and a very photographic way of working. What interests me, nowadays, is much less that and more what I see as the insufficiencies of photography.

What is beyond photography, in the case of the triptych?
My work always references what is beyond what we are looking at. The image, by itself, tells us little and, often, on purpose. This is all to encourage a much more active relationship with photography. I always ask myself why we demand everything or nothing from an image and how I can try to create a much more active relationship with the work in the viewer. It is in this sense that I say that the work deals a lot with the issue of the absence and insufficiency of photography, because it is always alluding to something that goes beyond the physicality of the image. In the specific case of this triptych, I am convinced that it only won the prize because it had already had an exhibition in Portugal and that perhaps the jury would already have more information about the work than the images that were on the wall. And, if they didn't, I'm even happier, because, in fact, they managed to see beyond that. The images are three portraits taken, over three different years, of a lady, who was a Libyan dissident, and represent just a lady in a niqab. I wanted to bring this human component to the work and decided that it would be brought by local people who had fought in the war, who had been affected by the war or people who had also lost family members in circumstances similar to Anton's. It is through these people that I tell Anton's story: I traveled through Libya with them. The images end up talking about Anton's story, through a polyphonic exploration, of this idea of ​​trauma. It is through their stories that I talk about Anton, but also about the Libyan Civil War in general. As I live in England, I knew that there was a very large dissident Libyan community and I wanted to photograph one of these people. The people I photographed in the book [Our War] are the same set of people, who I photographed over the course of four or five years. I asked this lady [from the triptych] if I could speak to her and, in that first meeting, I didn't even imagine that we would take photographs, I often don't. In fact, all the people I photographed in this book, I spent almost two years getting to know them before photographing them. This lady said she wanted to be photographed and that she wanted to assert her voice, when all these years she had been without it. But then I started to notice that she was nervous and felt uncomfortable. I understood why: a person who had been running for so many years, so as not to be found by the Gaddafi Government, to suddenly be exposing herself in this way, perhaps it would have been too big a step for her. I even suggested that we cancel the photographs and do it at another time, but she said: I want you to photograph me, but let me do this.

Is that where you went to get a niqab?
She went to the kitchen and made a niqab very quickly with some plastic bags and I photographed her like that. Afterwards, we agreed that I would photograph her again and, the following year, she wanted to be photographed again with the niqab. The third time I went to photograph it, I already knew that this was how I was going to photograph it. This triptych is insufficient, because it is incapable, by itself, of telling this story, this three-year relationship that we established. Por outro lado, há algo muito mais interessante, que não consegue contar, que é o facto de, por trás deste niqab, estar a história pessoal dela, aquilo que a levou a sair da Líbia e a pedir asilo político noutro país. É a isso que me refiro quando digo que a fotografia é quase anti-fotográfica, está sempre a apontar para estas insuficiências, as lacunas da fotografia.

Throughout his career, he has explored themes such as war, prison, technology and urbanism. Are there other topics you would like to explore in the future?
The choice of themes has always been very organic. In the first 12 or 13 years of my artistic practice, it started with themes related to urbanism or our relationship with the modern city, because I was studying that in my master's degree. This quickly ended up evolving into our relationship with technology. Then I was obsessed, for almost ten years, with working in these technological environments. I collaborated for two and a half years with EDP and, in Portugal, with the European Space Agency. This was a project lasting almost four years. At the end of that project, as I spent a lot of time in Munich, I ended up presenting a project to BMW. None of these projects had a commercial aspect. They were all self-financed through grants or cultural support. The automobile factory is the apotheosis of mobility in this luxury and transitional society in which we live and I asked BMW if we couldn't do a project that would put this into question. I asked them if we could do a project within their facilities, within the factory, where we would have to stop production to produce the photographs. Although they have not worked with artists since the 90s, they had already collaborated with Andy Warhol, in the 70s, and with Candida Höfer. They had that history and were very receptive to the idea. This year I thought that this way of working had come to a natural end, that there was very little I could explore in this type of theme, with this way of working, and this also coincided with Anton's death, where I wanted to start exploring more complex themes. From the moment I did this, my way of working changed. In these technological projects, I spent almost 15 years avoiding photographing people. You don't see a person in any of those photographs I took during that period. On the one hand, this is a consequence of long exposures. On the other hand, it is a decision that I had made since the work began to contain this human component. There was a component that united all these projects, including this last project I did, this idea of ​​absence. There is a guideline that unites all these works and, in different phases, there is one work that, in essence, influences the other, but there are two distinct periods here. In this second period, it has not only themes, but also more hybrid, multifaceted and multimedia approaches.

What period are you currently in?
I think I'm still very focused on the approach of this last project, because the work is finished, but I haven't done many exhibitions yet. I am writing about this project, which is the next phase: research work on the project itself. As this was the longest work I've worked on and a difficult work, on several levels, not only regarding the seriousness of the topic, but also ethically complex, logistically complex to be able to carry out, with trips to North Africa and everything else. This led me to try to find a way to maintain my sanity during these very long projects. Often, I need to work on more instinctive things and these ways of working are related to these projects or they are not new projects, but ideas that I am exploring and some of these ideas end up being translated into methodologies. Now I'm looking for these more instinctive ways of relating to photography.

In 2009, he was involved in a controversy in a project with the New York Times, in which he was criticized for the use of photoshop in a published essay. Did this controversy somehow make sense to you? Where did you position yourself in this debate?
What happened was a misunderstanding between me and the New York Times and we sorted things out between us. Nowadays, the same conversation is being had with artificial intelligence. The conversation might have been interesting, but it had nothing to do with what really happened. This reminds me of when this project [Our War] won the Sony World Photography Award 2023, not in relation to my work, but a similar controversy was generated, also poorly founded, because one of the artists who had won the award competed with a photograph created by artificial intelligence and, then, on the day of the ceremony, decided not to accept the award. But it was an insignificant thing in the context of the ceremony. At the time, they asked me what my relationship was with artificial intelligence. What I said about photo manipulation using photoshop is that it is a tool. These are all instruments, but it is important that the context is clarified.

He grew up in Macau, but almost never exhibited in Macau. Do you plan on doing any work related to the territory?
The first major photographic project I did was in 1999, in Macau. At the time, it made sense to do this project, because Macau was going through a huge transition phase. I would like to go back and work on some project about this idea of ​​casinos or the casino economy, this hyper-reality created by casinos. I don't work as a tourist, I need to be living in a place to be working. Macau was very important to me: it opened my eyes to a way of being that would not have been possible in any other context. I consider Macau my second home. I would like to return and do a project in the future. There were two occasions where I was to exhibit in Macau, but, for one reason or another, it didn't happen. But it made perfect sense to present one of these projects that I have been working on in the territory. Macau had such a huge importance in my decision to study photography, that it makes no sense not to have exhibited in Macau in the last 15 years.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macau will host the prestigious World Choral Music Symposium in 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/macau-sera-anfitriao-do-prestigiado-simposio-mundial-de-musica-coral-em-2026/</link><description>Macau will for a moment be the world capital of collective singing. The Macau Choral Art Association (AACM) announced that the city will host, for the first time, the prestigious World Symposium of Choral Music (WSCM), which will take place from 23 to 28 August 2026. The event, organized under the auspices of the International Federation of Choral Music (IFCM), an international organization affiliated with UNESCO, puts the territory on the route of major global artistic gatherings, following the 2023 edition in Istanbul.
Under the motto “Reimagining the Future”, the symposium restructures the city into a global stage of excellence and choral innovation during five intense days of activities. The program will include gala concerts, workshops, academic forums and exhibitions, creating an international bridge for the choral community and fostering new artistic partnerships.
The choice of Macau as the headquarters is due to its unique symbiosis of Eastern and Western cultures, its “vibrant artistic panorama and its rich heritage”, factors considered ideal for creating an inspiring environment where “voices from all continents can truly converge”, as highlighted by the organization.
The participation of 14 world-renowned choirs has already been confirmed, including the Hamilton Children’s Choir (Canada), the Madrigal Choir (Philippines), the Estonian ensemble Vox Clamantis, the Crazy Singers Choir (Hong Kong), the Shanghai Youth Choir (China), the Ansan City Choir (South Korea) and the prestigious World Youth Choir. In addition to the performances, the symposium will feature 40 lectures with world-renowned speakers leading masterclasses and workshops.
One of the objectives highlighted by the organization is the integration of local talent. The Macau Choral Art Association expressed its intention to include choral groups from Macau, “particularly the renowned school choirs that have delighted our local enthusiasts for so many years”, ensuring that the city's choral community will have an active role in the event.
The holding of WSCM 2026 in Macau is seen as a significant milestone in the international affirmation of the territory as a center for cultural exchange and musical celebration. The organization also expressed its gratitude for the support of the Diocese of Macau and calls for the active involvement of public and private sector institutions to make the event “the highlight of the year”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Fitch predicts China's growth to slow to 4.1% in 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/fitch-preve-abrandamento-do-crescimento-da-china-para-41-em-2026/</link><description>Financial rating agency Fitch Ratings forecasts that mainland China's economy will grow 4.1% in 2026, a slowdown from the 4.8% estimated for this year, due to weak domestic demand and deflationary pressures.
In a report released yesterday, Fitch indicates that both consumption and fixed investment continue to fall, mainly due to the prolonged decline in the real estate sector, which contributes to the risk of deflation becoming more entrenched in the world's second largest economy.
The agency classifies the outlook for the country as “deteriorated” and warns that calibrating fiscal and monetary policies to boost domestic demand and counter deflation will be one of the main challenges for Chinese authorities.
Fitch estimates a public deficit of 7.9% of GDP in 2026, slightly below the 8.4% this year, and a rise in the public debt ratio to more than 75% of GDP. “Domestic demand remains weak, with consumer confidence at low levels, reflected in property sales that are expected to fall by another 7% next year”, highlights the document. Fitch also expects a slow exit from the current deflationary cycle, with the GDP deflator remaining practically zero in 2026.
Despite the relief brought by the recent trade agreement with the United States, which reduced tariffs and lifted some restrictions on technology exports, the agency expects a moderation in China's external performance next year, with exports losing momentum after the effect of bringing forward orders registered in 2025.
For Taiwan, Fitch forecasts economic growth of 2.5% in 2026, after a strong expansion of 6.1% this year, driven mainly by high global demand for semiconductors used in artificial intelligence applications and new technologies.
The agency notes that the external sector will continue to support the island's economy, but warns of risks related to the possible imposition of North American tariffs on semiconductors and a possible slowdown in investment in artificial intelligence. Domestic demand is expected to remain weak, with household consumption showing little strength
Fitch maintains China's credit rating at 'A' with a stable outlook, following a cut in April that reflected "persistent weakness in public finances." Taiwan maintains its rating at 'AA' with a stable outlook, although with the caveat that tensions in the Strait and uncertainty about United States policy represent risks for the future.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:02:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Past and present intersect again in a photographic project by Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/passado-e-presente-cruzam-se-novamente-em-projecto-fotografico-de-goncalo-lobo-pinheiro/</link><description>Photojournalist Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro presents on December 16th, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, the second and final volume of his project “What was, will not be again…”. Accompanied by an exhibition with 20 photographs, the book makes a visual parallel between Macau's historical points and its current locations, including a special photograph taken in the 19th century. At the same time, a line of skateboards inspired by the first volume of the work will be launched.

Next Tuesday, December 16th, at 6:30 pm, at the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) gallery, Portuguese photojournalist Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro will present the conclusion of his most personal photographic project about the city. This is the second and final volume of the book “What was, will not be again…”, which will be accompanied by an exhibition of 20 photographs that will be on view until January 10, 2026.
The work, which functions as a “meeting between the past and the present”, according to the author, is the result of more than a year of collecting historical images of the territory. "I acquired them at auctions, on the Internet, from individuals, in stores and even in Portugal. Some images were also lent to me", explains Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro. This time, the book includes a particularly rare photograph, taken in the 19th century at the Macau Protestant Cemetery.
The project was born from the realization of the profound urban transformations that the city has undergone. "Macau has changed a lot in recent years. The old photographs attest to this. And now, what to do with them?", asks the photojournalist. “In the vast majority of cases, what was will never be again…”, he concludes, highlighting the difficulty of, in many scenarios, finding points of contact with the past today due to the disappearance of buildings and spaces.
The book, with almost 80 pages and 40 photographs, has a preface by the Portuguese writer and professor Henrique Levy, who lived in Macau in the 1980s. In the text, Levy describes Macau as “a city of encounters, cultural fusions and coexistence between intertwining worlds”, where “the Portuguese heritage coexists with Chinese tradition and multiple Asian influences”. The edition is designed by Carlos Canhita, endorsed by Ipsis Verbis and sponsored by Banco Nacional Ultramarino (BNU) and Fundação Rui Cunha.
Parallel to the launch of the book, a new line of skateboards produced in collaboration with local brand Exit Macau will be presented, dedicated to the first volume of the project. The boards highlight three icons of the city, the Ruins of São Paulo, Largo do Senado and the Temple of A-Má. This initiative continues a fruitful partnership that, four years ago, resulted in the “My City” collection and, more recently, the “Race Series”, dedicated to the world of motor racing in Macau.
The book “What was, will never be again…” Volume 2 will be on sale for MOP250 in several bookstores in Macau and online, as well as through the photographer's website. The skateboards from the “What was, will never be again…” collection will be on display in the FRC gallery during the exhibition period. The photographer also highlighted that the proceeds from books and photographs sold on the launch day, December 16, will go entirely to the Hong Kong branch of Habitat for Humanity, with the recent Tai Po fire disaster in mind.
Born in Lisbon, Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro is an established name in photojournalism, with a career that began in 2000 in Portugal and since 2010 has been developed mainly in Macau. With a degree in Communication Sciences and a master's degree in Documentary Photography from LABASAD in Barcelona, ​​the photographer has extensive experience in newsrooms, having worked for the newspaper A Bola for six years, being editor-in-chief of Hoje Macau, photographic coordinator of Macau magazine and photojournalist at PONTO FINAL. He currently collaborates with the Lusa agency and is one of the official photographers of the International Volleyball Federation (FIVB). His career is marked by numerous international awards, including medals at the Budapest International Foto Awards, the Prix de la Photographie Paris and the Tokyo International Foto Awards, among other distinctions.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tai Kin Ip says the modern financial sector is “one of the Government’s priority industries”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/tai-kin-ip-diz-que-sector-financeiro-moderno-e-uma-das-industrias-prioritarias-do-governo/</link><description>The Secretary for Economy and Finance spoke yesterday at the inauguration of the fourth edition of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area Financial Forum, where he recalled that the Investment Funds Law will come into force next January. According to Tai Kin Ip, preparatory work for the Securities Law is also underway, although there is no scheduled date for its launch.
 

Tai Kin Ip was present yesterday at the inauguration ceremony of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area Financial Forum, where he gave a speech on the integrated development of the financial sector and productive sectors in the three regions. The secretary began by highlighting that the modern financial sector is one of the priority industries of the Macau Government, which has also dedicated “special importance” to the construction and development of the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin.
The minister stressed that, since last year, with the new Government taking office, “every effort has been made to promote the development of adequate diversification, including accelerating the growth of the modern financial sector, with an emphasis on the bond market, wealth management and new areas such as financial technology”. The aim is, therefore, to take advantage of “Macau’s unique advantages” and build a platform open to the outside world, which “interconnects with the world and serves the country’s new standard of ‘dual circulation’”.
Regarding the bond market, Tai Kin Ip informed that the Government has been optimizing, in a phased manner, the Macau Central Securities Depository (CSD), a system opened in 2021, as well as the network service and interconnection with Hong Kong. In parallel, the preparatory work for the Securities Law, developed by the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM), continues to advance, with a view to accelerating the creation of a bond market that “serves as a bridge to the interior of China and creates connections with the international market”.
In turn, the Investment Funds Law will come into force next month, “further strengthening the legal foundations and development environment of the funds industry in Macau”. The secretary also assured that the Government will continue to deepen cooperation mechanisms with mainland China and Hong Kong, such as the “Cross-border Financial Management” pilot project, with a view to promoting the integration of the wealth management markets in the three regions.
With regard to financial technology, the secretary recalled that the update of the Real-Time Immediate Settlement System was completed this year, another system implemented by AMCM that came into operation in 2020, allowing the time needed to carry out interbank transfers in renminbi and Hong Kong dollars to be reduced. At the same time, a memorandum of understanding was also signed with the People's Bank of China, in order to “promote interconnection between the rapid payments system in mainland China and that of Macau”.
At the same time, the Macau digital currency (“e-MOP”) project has also continued to advance “in an orderly manner”, with the construction of the central system and the completion of small-scale transaction tests in ‘sandbox’ scenarios – that is, in a controlled regulatory environment.
It should also be noted that, as announced in April, the Government continues to move forward with the creation of a government fund for industries and a guidance fund for the transformation of scientific and technological results, having already set up a working group to coordinate these projects.
Addressing the experts and academics present at the Forum, Tai Kin Ip said he hoped to count on their “valuable opinions” for the Government’s future work. “The Macao SAR Government will continue to promote the role of modern finance as an ‘engine of economic growth’, to boost the adequate diversification of Macau’s economy, proactively assuming a more significant role in the development of the Cooperation Zone and the Greater Bay Area,” he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:14:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese PM regrets “serious impact” of tariffs with international organizations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/pm-chines-lamenta-grave-impacto-das-tarifas-junto-de-organismos-internacionais/</link><description>Chinese Premier Li Qiang warned yesterday of the “serious impact” of tariffs and other trade restrictions on the global economy, when inaugurating a new edition of the ‘1+10 Dialogue’ with international financial institutions in Beijing.
Li stated that the proliferation of trade barriers since the beginning of the year demonstrated that “tariffs harm third parties, but end up backfiring against those who impose them”, which, according to the government official, has reinforced global calls in defense of free trade.
Before the leaders of the main international financial and commercial institutions, the head of the Chinese Government highlighted that the world is facing “complex and profound changes”, marked by the rise of protectionism, geopolitical turbulence and gaps in global governance.
The forum, which takes place under the motto “Share global governance, promote global development”, aims to “build a more fair, reasonable and effective system”, said Li, highlighting the role of organizations present in the stability of the world economy.
The Prime Minister identified three key concepts that will mark the year 2025: tariffs, green transition and artificial intelligence (AI).
On climate, it marked the tenth anniversary of the Paris Agreement and reaffirmed China's commitments, including the objective that more than 30% of the country's energy consumption comes from non-fossil sources, with the installation of 3.6 gigawatts of solar and wind capacity – more than six times the level recorded in 2020.
Regarding artificial intelligence, Li highlighted the accelerated advancement of Chinese open models, such as DeepSeek, which are “driving industrial transformation” and the growth of new sectors such as intelligent robotics. "Free trade, overcoming global challenges and collaborative innovation are goals that no entity can achieve alone. They require collective effort", he highlighted.
Participating in the meeting are the director general of the International Monetary Fund (IMF), Kristalina Georgieva, the president of the New Development Bank, Dilma Rousseff, the secretary general of the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development, Rebeca Grynspan, and the president of the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank, Jin Liqun.
Also present are the director general of the Bank for International Settlements, Pablo Hernández de Cos, the president of the World Bank, Ajay Banga, the director general of the World Trade Organization, Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala, and representatives of the International Labor Organization, the Financial Stability Board and the OECD, among others.
Tal como em 2024, existe a possibilidade de os participantes se reunirem também com o Presidente chinês, Xi Jinping, embora esse encontro ainda não tenha sido confirmado.
A visita de Georgieva coincide com a fase final da missão do Artigo IV do FMI, cujo relatório anual sobre a economia chinesa será apresentado esta quarta-feira em Pequim.
O ‘Diálogo 1+10’ realiza-se um dia após o Politburo do Partido Comunista Chinês ter anunciado que manterá em 2026 uma política fiscal “mais proativa” e uma postura monetária “moderadamente flexível”, num contexto marcado pela fraca procura interna, risco de deflação e persistência da crise no sector imobiliário. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:04:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Conference unravels the story of cross-border funerals and Macau refugees</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/conferencia-desvenda-a-historia-dos-funerais-transfronteiricos-e-dos-refugiados-de-macau/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts today, at 7pm, a conference that sheds light on a unique and little explored aspect of Macau's social history. Entitled “Cross-border Issues of Funerals and Refugees: Macau in the mid-20th century”, the lecture is part of the Cycle of Public Lectures on History and Heritage, organized in a regular partnership between the FRC and the Department of History and Heritage of the University of São José.
The guest speaker is Carlos Ka Nok Lo, assistant professor of Research at the Department of History at the University of Macau and Associate Researcher at the Institute of Advanced Research at the same university in Hengqin. The presentation will be based on the research he is developing for his second monograph, entitled “Death and Funeral Practices in the Macau Special Administrative Region, China”, scheduled for publication in 2026.
Carlos Ka Nok Lo's investigation reveals that, from the mid-19th century, Portuguese authorities in Macau implemented measures that prohibited Chinese residents from burying their dead on the Macau Peninsula. With the modernization of administrative systems, in 1881, Kiang Wu Hospital was formally authorized to supervise Chinese burials and manage the Chinese Cemetery. This process established a unique pattern of cross-border burial between Macau and Xiangshan County (today south of Zhuhai), a practice that, the researcher highlights, persists to this day.
The academic will also address the turbulent period of the Japanese invasion of China in the mid-20th century, which triggered mass migration to Macau.
The conference, which will last one hour and will be presented in English, will be moderated by Priscilla Roberts, associate professor and head of the Department of History and Heritage at the University of São José.
The event has free entry.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:05:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong expands removal of protective nets on scaffolding due to fraud</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/hong-kong-alarga-remocao-de-redes-de-proteccao-em-andaimes-devido-a-fraude/</link><description>Hong Kong ordered the removal of protective nets installed on scaffolding in more than 200 private buildings after the discovery of falsified safety certificates. The decision was motivated by the fire that devastated the Wang Fuk Court public housing complex, killing at least 159 people.

The Hong Kong Government ordered the immediate removal of protective nets installed on scaffolding in more than 200 private buildings after the discovery of falsified safety certificates.
The decision was motivated by the fire that devastated the Wang Fuk Court public housing complex on November 26, killing at least 159 people, with 31 people still missing.
The fire exposed deficiencies in the protection of renovation projects, particularly in the use of protective nets on facades to prevent falling debris.
As these networks are not fireproof, they acted as accelerators, driving the spread of flames in Tai Po, in the New Territories, north of Hong Kong.
Official investigations confirmed that the burned buildings used heat-resistant mesh, which allowed the flames to spread quickly and consume several towers in the residential complex.
After inspections of other buildings, authorities detected adulterated materials in two other complexes, linked to a manufacturer in mainland China.
The discovery prompted Hong Kong's Buildings Department to urgently order the removal of all similar materials from the facades of private properties, deeming them an unacceptable risk.
As of 5pm on Monday, a total of 227 buildings had already dismantled these networks, while three others received deadline extensions to complete the operation this week.
The police expanded the investigations to four complexes spread across different urban districts due to the possibility of more widespread use of fraudulent certificates.
In parallel, the Department of Labor opened an investigation into a suspicious case of scaffolding inspection certificates with changed dates, apparently signed in advance.
The Independent Commission Against Corruption detained at least 11 people linked to the Wang Fuk Court rehabilitation contract, including employees of the consultancy company responsible for technical supervision, project directors and managers, subcontractors specializing in scaffolding and intermediaries.
The leader of the Hong Kong Government, John Lee Ka-chiu, promised close cooperation with the new parliament — elected on Sunday, in the second vote after the exclusion of the pro-democracy opposition — to promote structural reforms that strengthen safety in construction and rehabilitation projects.
The fire, the deadliest in Hong Kong since 1948, accelerated administrative and criminal measures aimed at plugging gaps in the construction sector's chain of responsibility, from product certification to on-site inspection. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:04:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Temples and colonial border are the scene of fighting between Thailand and Cambodia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/10/templos-e-fronteira-colonial-sao-cenario-de-combates-entre-tailandia-e-camboja/</link><description>The current conflict between Thailand and Cambodia results from a historical dispute over the border established more than a century ago, when France occupied what was then Indochina, and over the sovereignty of Hindu temples. The armies of the two countries, which already registered violent clashes in July, have been fighting since Sunday for control of areas where religious buildings from the 11th century are located, a time when the region was controlled by the Khmer Empire (802-1431). Thailand said it had recorded the deaths of four soldiers since Sunday, and Cambodia of eight civilians. Once forgotten ruins covered by vegetation, domination over places of worship has rekindled nationalist feelings, according to Spanish news agency EFE.
The Thai army reported clashes on Tuesday around the temples of Ta Kwai, also known as Ta Krabei, and Ta Muen Thom. They are both located close to the dividing line between the Thai province of Surin and the Cambodian province of Oddar Meanchey. Of little strategic military value, control over these religious centers became a matter of high patriotic weight. “While neither country wants a full-scale war, both consider the disputed temples and surrounding territory important to their national history and identity,” said Southeast Asia expert Tom Pepinsky of Cornell University. “Domestic politics in both countries exacerbate these tensions,” said the American political scientist from New York University, in a comment sent to EFE.
One of the most significant precedents in the sovereignty dispute is the Preah Vihear temple, a large complex built on top of a 525-meter cliff that serves as a natural border between the two countries. The International Court of Justice (ICJ) in The Hague ruled in 1962 that the temple, declared a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 2008, is located on Cambodian land. Bangkok then complied with the decision, but maintained its claim on the adjacent land, as the only access route was via roads from Thailand. Friction over these territorial claims culminated in conflicts in 2008 and 2011, which left more than thirty dead. Phnom Penh appealed again to The Hague, which again agreed in 2013, and again asked the ICJ to intervene in June. Bangkok rejects recourse to international justice and prefers to resolve the disagreement through bilateral mechanisms.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:01:08</pubDate></item></channel></rss>