<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/fundo-de-desenvolvimento-da-cultura-atribuiu-95-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-a-mais-de-mil-projectos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Coutinho pede estratégias de combate ao desperdício alimentar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/coutinho-pede-estrategias-de-combate-ao-desperdicio-alimentar/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho leaned over the problem of food waste in a new written interpelation sent to the government, calling for strategies to combat a “structural challenge” with social, economic and environmental implications. 
José Pereira Coutinho referred yesterday a written interpellation to the government in which he warns of food waste in Macau and requests the clarification of the strategy to combat what he considers to be a “structural challenge” in the region, with “social, economic and environmental implications”.
The president of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) began by contextualizing the issue in Macao, relating it to a “abundance culture” that occurs at social events such as banquets, buffets and other celebrations around an ordinary table.
At the same time, in what Coutinho calls “ethical paradox”, there are institutions of solidarity and non -profit associations in the territory that have sought to collect these food surpluses, being confronted with “significant operational difficulties” such as weak collaboration by hotel, casinos and restaurants.
In addition to the unequal distribution of food products by the population, the deputy also notices the environmental consequences of food waste, which implies “the emptying of strategic resources (water, energy, human and financial)” and “the uncontrolled emission of greenhouse gases”.
"Despite meritorious initiatives of non -profit associations, insufficient sensitization of the population for the structural reduction of food waste persists," laments the deputy. "In addition, the MSAR faces critical infrastructural deficiencies in the management of organic waste, manifested in the absence of industrial composting centers and intelligent logistics networks to donate surpluses in time."
According to data cited in the interpellation, the MSAR is above the European Union average with 1.4 kilos of waste waste daily by each inhabitant. Remembering that the United Nations (UN) has stipulated the reduction in 50% of per capita waste by 2030, Coutinho appeals to the Government of MSAR to promote “disruptive technologies” or “innovative solutions” to contain the problem, giving as an example “mobile processing systems” or “dynamic expiration management protocols”.
In light of the foregoing, the deputy directs to the government a set of tripartum issues about the measures of awareness of the population, partnership creation and encouraging the companies of the food sector. In the first question, Coutinho calls for clarification regarding the predicted awareness campaigns and how they will be implemented, “explicitly” all phases of the food chain, from agricultural production to final consumption.
It also questions whether the government intends to “move forward with the creation of a specific legal framework that encourages or obliges the separation of organic waste” or rules that encourage supermarkets to donate their own consumption surpluses to social solidarity institutions.
The second question sent to the authorities is related to the creation of measures that facilitate “systematic partnerships” between commercial establishments and private entities, such as food banks or charities, while ensuring the existence of specific food security protocols for these situations.
“How do you intend the Government of MSAR to ensure legal certainty and reduce potential liability barriers to commercial establishments that hurt almost expired foods in good condition?”, Includes Coutinho, recalling the “good Samaritan” law projects - legislation that exempts liability or criminal establishments to donating food - that are already in other countries.
In a third and last question, the deputy is specifically focused on concrete incentive measures, such as the attribution of tax benefits or subsidies of encouragement to companies that choose to donate their food surpluses. On the other hand, support plans are also suggested to foster cooperation between commercial establishments and consumers - allowing, for example, that they acquire foods close to the expiration date at reduced prices.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:09:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Ever more and more dependent on the game industry</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/receitas-da-raem-cada-vez-mais-dependentes-da-industria-do-jogo/</link><description>Between January and July this year, the total public revenues of MSAR was led by about 61.8 billion patacas, with 86.2% of this value from the game industry. Data from the budgetary execution released on the FINANCE SERVICES DIRECTION (DSF) page show that public coffers are increasingly dependent on casinos.

MSAR coffers are increasingly dependent on the game industry. Data updated on the Finance Services Directorate (DSF) page show that 86.2% of management's current revenues between January and July this year came from casinos. This is the highest percentage of recent years.
In the first seven months of this year, the total current management revenues of the administration was 61.8 billion patacas, and 53.3 billion (86.2%) came from the game sector. In the same period of the previous year, MSAR current revenues had been 61.4 billion patacas, with revenues from the game occupying a proportion of 84% (51.6 billion patacas).
In the first seven months of 2023, the weight of game revenues in management's current revenues was 79.9% and in the same period of the previous year of 66.1%. Between January and July 2020 and 2021, the proportion was 77.2% and 72.7%, respectively.
In 2024, the casinos that operate in the territory contributed 88.1 billion patacas for the total revenue of the administration, which reached 109.5 billion. Thus, the weight of the game in MSAR revenues by 2024 was 80.4%.
Between January and July this year, gross accumulated game revenues were over 140 billion patacas, 6.5% more than in the same period last year.
It is recalled that the review of the game law, which came into force in 2022, stipulates that the concessionaires operating casinos in the territory have to pay a direct tax of 35% of their revenues, plus an annual amount of 2% to a public fund and 3% for urban development, tourism promotion and social security of the MSc.
Data from the budget execution published on the DSF website also show that the current expenses of the MSAR between January and July this year were 39.9 billion PATACA. Most expenses have to do with transfers, support and allowance (27.2 billion patacas), followed by personnel expenses (9.3 billion patacas). The budget balance was thus 11.6 billion of patacas, plus 2.3 billion compared to the same period last year.
By July, investments in the Administration Investment and Development Expenses Plan (PIDDA) totaled 9.6 billion patacas, representing 49.4% of what was enrolled in the budget for this year.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:13:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs: China expects efforts from the United States to a day of the end of the truce</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/tarifas-china-espera-esforcos-dos-estados-unidos-a-um-dia-do-fim-da-tregua/</link><description>China yesterday appealed to the United States "efforts" to achieve a "positive result based on equality, respect and mutual benefit," one day to expire the current commercial truce between the two largest economies in the world.
 
"We hope that the US will collaborate with China to fulfill the important consensus achieved between the two heads of state, take advantage of the established economic and commercial consultation mechanism and strive to obtain a positive outcome based on equality, respect and mutual benefit," said the spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry in a statement.
In May, the parties woke up in Geneva the current truce, which ends on Tuesday, predicting a reduction of 115 percentage points in the tariffs applied since the beginning of April, which then resulted in a 'de facto' commercial embargo.
The last business round took place at the end of July in Stockholm, where both delegations expressed the desire to maintain dialogue to avoid climbing in a trade war that threatened to decompose supply chains and shake markets.
After this meeting, Chinese chief negotiator, Li Chenggang, said that an extension of the truce was agreed, but US commercial representative Jamieson Greer warned that Chinese imports could reach 80% or 85% if an agreement was not reached to correct commercial imbalance and “overcapacity” Beijing exporter.
Later, Greer stated in an interview with CBS jail that the parties are "working" to extend the truce, while US Secretary of Trade Howard Lutnick has admitted a new "90-day" break.
The meeting in the Swedish capital followed meetings in Geneva and London and a telephone conversation in June between US President Donald Trump and Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping to try to exceed differences.
The United States even imposed 145% rates on Chinese products, while Beijing raised customs rates applied to US goods to 125%, before Washington reduced taxes to 30% and China to 10%.
At the London meeting in June, China approved rare land export requests and the US suspended some "restrictive measures" against Beijing, including chips export controls.
However, on Sunday, Trump urged China to quadruple US soybeans, something that some analysts interpret as a condition to prolong the truce.
In recent days, Washington has also emerged to sanction Beijing for importing oil from Russia due to Moscow's refusal to end the war in Ukraine, which could compromise negotiations.
China advocates the right to maintain normal trade relations with other partners and rejects Washington's pressure, while Trump prepares for a historic meeting with Russian President Vladimir Putin on Friday in Alaska, which could redefine the current feature of disputes between great powers. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:05:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Torrential rains in southern Japan cause flooding and disturbances in transportation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/chuvas-torrenciais-no-sul-do-japao-provocam-inundacoes-e-perturbacoes-nos-transportes/</link><description>The torrential rainfall that have been felt on the island of Kyushu, Japan, have caused various floods and landslings. Japanese authorities have already registered several injuries and missing.

Intense rainfall on Kyushu's main Japanese island yesterday caused flooding and landslides, causing several injuries, missing and disruption disturbances during Bon Bon Holiday Week.
The low pressure system that has been held in the region since last week has caused torrential precipitation in the province of Kagoshima, in the south, and in the northern part of the island.
The Japan Meteorological Agency has issued the maximum alert level in Kumamoto province, indicating that precipitation has exceeded 40 centimeters in the last 24 hours and predicting more rain until Tuesday afternoon in Kyushu. As the clouds advance to the east, towards the Tokyo region, the agency foresees up to 20 centimeters of rain in western Japan.
According to the fire and disaster management agency, local authorities have issued exit orders to tens of thousands of people in Kumamoto and in other six provinces. Defense forces troops were sent to Kagoshima to provide drinking water to the affected populations, Government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi said.
In Kumamoto, rescue teams were looking for three people from a family hit by a landslide while moving to an evacuation center. Two were rescued alive, but the third remained missing. Two other people were missing in other areas of the province.
Several people were also given as missing after falling into rivers that overflowed in Kumamoto and the neighboring province of Fukuoka.
In the city of Kamiamakusa, about 20 people arrested in a campsite and other residential areas were awaiting rescue, public television reported NHK.
Television images showed flood of muddy water to drag trees and broken branches while residents walked with the water for the height of their knees.
Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba said the government is supporting search and rescue operations and assisting affected areas, appealing to the population to "use the maximum caution" and "prioritize actions to save lives."
The heavy rains also affected trips during the Bon holiday.
High -speed trains between Kagoshima and Hakata in northern Kyushu, as well as local rail services, were suspended. Although the circulation was partially resumed in Kyushu, services began to be affected in western Japan as rain advanced east.
About 6,000 dwellings were left without electricity in Kumamoto, according to the company Kyushu Electric Power.
Last week's torrential rains left a missing and four injured in Kagoshima. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:04:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Government launches chronic disease tracking plan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/governo-lanca-plano-de-rastreio-de-doencas-cronicas/</link><description>The chronic disease screening program is now open to Macao residents of 18 years of age or over, whose scope of service covers hypertension, diabetes, cancer screening, dyslipidemia, obesity and other chronic diseases.
The initiative was launched yesterday on Monday by health services, which aims to encourage residents to perform, on their own initiative, the screening and management of chronic diseases.
Through the program, adult residents can resort to consultation with private clinics who adhere to the program and, depending on the medical recommendation or personal situation, select the tracking package and go to collaborating institutions to perform clinical analysis tests.
Private doctors, after clinical testing, will provide residents for recommendations for medical examinations, interpretation of results, personalized health guidelines and monitoring of disease diagnosis.
Health services add that, after obtaining the consent of residents, test data can be loaded in the system in the “single account” application. Residents may also use electronic health valleys or other means to pay their medical expenses.
For this program, health services performed training and preliminary accreditation work to 90 Western doctors from Macao. Of the participating doctors, about 80% were under 45 years old and approximately 50% were under 35 years.
Chan Iek Lap, president of the General Association of Macao Medicine Sector, told the newspaper or Mun that training can raise the clinical skills of young doctors, and the program promotes the development of private medical sector and reduces pressure on public medical services.
Until late June, a total of 85 doctors completed the training and obtained approval in the exam. Currently, 79 qualified Western doctors entered to join this program.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:07:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Approved more than two thousand projects in the industrial and marketing development fund</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/aprovados-mais-de-dois-mil-projectos-no-fundo-de-desenvolvimento-industrial-e-de-comercializacao/</link><description>The Directorate of Supervision and Management Services of Public Assets updated the information about the financial support of the Industrial Development and Marketing Fund, revealing that it granted, in the first half, more than 2,000 subsidies, in a total of over 124 million patacas.
The amount verified a slight increase compared to the same time as last year, when 122 million patacas were granted.
The maximum individual funding money from this fund between January and June exceeded 9.2 million Patacas, and was attributed under the Small and Medium Enterprises Support Plan, which approved 22 support requests.
Commercial activities related to the North Zone stood out among the projects funded in the first six months of the year. The Industrial and Commercial Association of the North Zone of Macau received funding for seven events in this area, and the Stores Promotion Plan in the North Zone spent subsidy on more than 2.4 million Patacas.
Other initiatives such as the project “North Zone exclusive bus careers”, the “North Zone beautification plan” and “Lunar cake festival carnival in the North Zone” had pecuniary supports ranging from 361,000 patacas at 1.8 million Patacas.
In addition, the Macao Live Transmission Association was assigned 2.3 million for the expenses of the organization of the “Macao 2025 North Zone Thematic Promotion Project”.
Macau's industrial and commercial association was also granted 2.4 million patacas for the North Zone consumption parking subsidy plan, which took place last June with a view to “encouraging residents to consume in the North Zone during weekends and public holidays, boosting the business of small and medium enterprises”, justified the entity.
The competition of 'Startup' 929 Challenge was also part of the list of beneficiaries, with which the Macao Sino-Lusopone Platform Association for Sustainable Development received 1.3 million patacas for the contest.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:06:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Guangdong registers drop in cases of chikungunya fever after outbreak in July</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/guangdong-regista-queda-de-casos-de-febre-chikungunya-apos-surto-em-julho/</link><description>The Chinese province of Guangdong registered 1,387 new local cases of chikungunya fever between August 3 and 9, a descent against 2,892 counted the previous week, under the outbreak started in July. Most recent infections focused on the city of Foshan, followed by the provincial capital, Canton, and Zhanjiang. During this period, no serious cases or deaths associated with the disease were recorded, according to the Guangdong Disease Control and Prevention Center, quoted on Sunday by state television CCTV.
Chikungunya fever is a viral disease caused by the homonymous virus and transmitted mainly by Aedes gender mosquitoes, which reproduce in small water accumulations. The most common symptoms include high fever, joint pain and rash. Quoted by CCTV, the director of the Institute for Prevention and Control of Infectious Diseases of Guangdong, Kang Min, said the increase in cases in Foshan shows signs of containment and that the total weekly maintains fall trend. However, he warned that the disease continues to cover a vast geographical area and that the high international mobility of the province increases the risk of imported cases.
Health authorities have recalled that the elimination of mosquito breeding sites, controlling adult specimens and bites protection are the main measures to lock transmission.
The provincial government, which manages a population of about 126 million, had notified by 4 August more than 7,000 cases of the disease. The time of typhoons and rainfall intensified the activity of mosquitoes in the region, which, according to the authorities, requires maintaining surveillance and control measures.
The World Health Organization (WHO) requested in July preventive measures to avoid epidemics such as 20 years ago, after detecting large -scale outbreaks on Indian islands such as Mayotte, meeting or mauria, and the spread of disease to nearby countries such as Madagascar, Somalia or Kenya.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:06:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao and Hong Kong contemporary comic band featured at the Rui Cunha Foundation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/banda-desenhada-contemporanea-de-macau-e-hong-kong-em-destaque-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>Shared squares between regions. The Rui Cunha Foundation today serves as a meeting point between two generations of the Asyan comic band. “Comics 2025 + Hong Kong Machines” presents first the new talent of five Macao artists, followed by the iconic nostalgic robots of Felix IP, Hong Kong master. A visual set that shows how this art continues to reinvent itself. For those who enjoy telling stories through drawing, the exhibition brings a different trip in each trait.

The Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery becomes, once again, a stage of colors and strokes with the exhibition “Comics 2025 + Hong Kong Machines”, which opens to the public today at 18:30. Divided into two distinct parts, the show promises to take visitors on a trip for the best of the comic book and contemporary illustration, highlighting both local Macao talents and the recognized Hong Kong artist Felix IP.
The first part of the exhibition, which will take place from 12 to 16 August, presents about 30 works by five artists from Macau: Leung Wai Ka, Nasu, Vincent Ho, Yeung SIU and ST - all members of the Macao's Cultural Exchange Promotion Association (Apicbdam). This collective annual edition, entitled “Comics 2025”, brings together the latest comic band creations, the traditional manga and various forms of illustration, demonstrating the diversity and vitality of the local artistic scene on the subject.
The second part, scheduled from 19 to 23 August, will be dedicated to the most recent work of the renowned artist Felix IP, unavoidable figure in the world of animation and Asian comic band. The inauguration of this phase will take place on August 19, at 16h, with the presence of the author himself. IP, which collaborated on productions such as “Ninja Turtles” and “Astroboy”, brings Macau its acclaimed “Hongkong Machines” series, a collection of illustrations that combines futuristic robotic machines with nostalgic elements of his childhood in Hong Kong. The series, already awarded prizes such as Golden Dragon Award and Asia-Pacific Animation &amp; Comics Art Book Award, has recently expanded to other Asian markets, giving rise to derivations such as "Singa Machines", "Malaysia Machines" and "Taiwan Machines."
Visitors will also have the opportunity to know their latest project, “Daydream Notebook”, distinguished with a silver prize in the Hong Kong comic book support program.
The curatorship of the exhibition is in charge of Howard Chan, president of Apicbdam, who underlines the importance of this event as a platform of cultural and artistic exchange. Quoted in the Rui Cunha Foundation statement, Chan points out that the event reinforces the association's mission to promote local comic band and create bridges with international creators such as Felix IP.
Since its inception in 2014, Apicbdam has been working to foster collaboration between local and international artists, reinforcing the role of Macau as a creative hub in the Greater Bay region in this area. This exhibition represents not only a meeting of generations and styles, but also a dialogue between tradition and innovation, where Felix IP mechanical robots talk to the new contemporary drawn bands of the macanese artists.
For sequential art connoisseurs and Asian pop culture, this initiative is a special occasion to witness the evolution of the comic band in Macao, something that still grows and develops in the region. The show will be evident in the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery until August 23, with free admission.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Culture Development Fund has attributed 95 billion of patacas to more than a thousand projects</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/12/fundo-de-desenvolvimento-da-cultura-atribuiu-95-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-a-mais-de-mil-projectos/</link><description>Between January and June this year, the Culture Development Fund assigned more than 95 million Financial Support Patacas to 1,140 projects in the cultural and artistic areas in Macao. Both the granted value and the number of activities increased compared to last year's same period. Subsidized projects covered photography or painting exhibitions, opera or dance shows, as well as film festivals.

The amount of financial support granted by the Cultural Development Fund in the first half of this year a 15.8%increase in annual terms. In the first six months, the fund channeled a total of 95.5 million patacas to 1,140 projects.
Although not indicating the number of financing requests received, the body revealed that it approved 790 projects in the first quarter, which were assigned 24 million patacas. In addition, it also gave green light to 350 projects in the second quarter, which received subsidies of 71.5 million patacas.
The information was made available on the public dissemination platform for public financial support information, supervision and management services. At the Cultural Development Fund, between January and June 2025, both the number of approved projects and the assigned funds were growing compared to the same period last year.
In the first half of the last year, the Cultural Development Fund funded 893 projects, in a total amount of 82.5 million patacas, of which 65.6 million were given until March and 16.9 were until June.
The financial support of the first half of this year was also the highest since the creation of the fund in 2022, after the merger of the former Fund of Cultural Industry and the former Cultural Fund.
According to the lists published by the authorities, the funded projects covered cultural and artistic activities, such as visual arts exhibitions, music or dance shows, literary creation activities or intangible cultural heritage, and film festivals, among others.
To Casa de Portugal in Macao, for example, the value of 187,000 financial support Patacas in the first six months of the year was granted to carry out “Literary, Musical and Theatrical Creation Activity”, as well as by the “Once Upon a Time Projects”, “a story before bed” and “Fado at the Window”.
The “Somos! - Portuguese Language Communication Association” received 580,000 Patacas until June to carry out visual arts activities and an exhibition of Portuguese cartoonist António.
Of the other known entities are the Curb (Center for Architecture and Urbanism), which was awarded 1.4 million Patacas as a subsidy of activities, various exhibitions and the architectural photographs contest this year, while D'As Macau - Cultural Association obtained 615 thousand patacas for the projects as the play "Home Sweet Home".
The Cultural Development Fund also conferred the CUT Audio-Visual Association subsidies in 570,000 patacas, intended for a movie magazine, a film festival and other events.
 ART FOR ALL SOCIETRY has been provided financing at 1.1 million patacas. Already 10 Marias Cultural Association received 442 thousand patacas, the ox warehouse raised 1.5 million patacas, while the Institute of European Studies of Macao obtained 323 thousand patacas of financial support.
According to the presentation, the Culture Development Fund aims to support the development of activities and exchange in the cultural and artistic areas, projects of the cultural industries, as well as the activities and projects intended for the safeguarding of cultural heritage.
It is recalled that throughout last year the fund launched 11 financial support plans, which were received more than two thousand candidacies and 1,148 projects were approved after evaluation, with a total amount of financial support was 186 million patacas, whose majority of subsidy (71%) was granted to the area of culture and arts and the rest was attributed to the domains of cultural industries and cultural heritage.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 03:12:02</pubDate></item></channel></rss>