<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/culpa-e-dor-pesam-sobre-sobreviventes-um-mes-apos-incendio-de-hong-kong/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Unemployment rate remains at 2.3%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/taxa-de-desemprego-mantem-se-nos-23/</link><description>The Macao SAR's overall unemployment rate in the period between September and November remained unchanged at 2.3%, compared to the period between August and October. The unemployment rate exclusively for residents also did not fluctuate, remaining at 1.7%.
According to data released by the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC) last Friday, the global underemployment rate was 1.5% and the resident underemployment rate was 2%, which reveals increases of 0.1 and 0.2 percentage points, respectively, compared to the previous period.
Statistics also reveal that the number of unemployed residents was 6,700, the majority of whom had previously worked in the retail trade and gaming industry.
The gaming sector lost 0.2% of its workers and wholesale and retail trade lost 1% of its employees. The restaurant sector reduces its workers by 0.4%. Conversely, the hotel sector increased its human resources by 0.3%, as did the construction sector.
The unemployment rate has been decreasing over the last few years following the pandemic. In 2022, the Macao SAR's overall unemployment rate was 3.7% while that of residents alone was 4.7%. In 2023, the rates were 2.3% and 2.9%, respectively. Last year, unemployment rates were already at their current level.
According to preliminary estimates from migration records, the average number of MSAR residents and non-resident workers who worked in the MSAR but lived abroad was estimated to be around 109,300 in the reference period. The total workforce, made up of these individuals and the active population living in the Macao SAR (385,600), was 494,900 people, 2,700 more than in the previous period.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:47:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of people vaccinated against flu is 15% higher than last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/numero-de-pessoas-vacinadas-contra-a-gripe-e-15-superior-ao-ano-passado/</link><description>The Health Services indicated that 240 thousand doses of flu vaccine were ordered during this quarter and, at the end of September, priority was given to administering the vaccine to high-risk groups, having been administered to all Macau residents in mid-November. To date, 179 thousand people have been vaccinated, which represents an increase of 15% compared to last year. Of these, 95% were vaccinated in nursing homes, 50% in elderly people over the age of 65 and 70% in students, said Alvis Lo, director of Health Services, in joint meetings with Community Health Councils.
Given the increase in the flow of people during the peak flu season and on holidays, authorities are appealing to the population, especially the elderly, chronically ill, children and pregnant women, to get the flu vaccine as soon as possible. The public must also pay more attention to individual and environmental hygiene, and can wear a mask in places with a large concentration of people; You should wear a mask when you experience symptoms and seek medical treatment as soon as possible. Early administration of antiviral medications by high-risk people can reduce the risk of serious cases occurring. Alvis Lo also indicated that the Health Services will continue to reinforce surveillance and response measures, facing the challenge of respiratory diseases in winter and spring.
At the meetings, the issue of smoking was also addressed. In this field, the authorities mentioned that the rate of tobacco use among the population aged 15 years and over and among young people aged between 13 and 15 years shows a decreasing trend, having already achieved the objective of reducing the rate of tobacco consumption by 30% by 2030 defined by the World Health Organization and the Action Plan for Healthy Macau, compared to the year 2020.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:49:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Zhuhai participate in exchange meeting on water supply</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/macau-e-zhuhai-participam-em-reuniao-de-intercambio-sobre-o-abastecimento-de-agua/</link><description>The water authorities of Macau and Zhuhai recently met to discuss water conditions and coordinate salinity control measures during the dry period, to ensure the safety and capacity of water supply in both regions.
The Macau side, where the meeting took place, was represented by the Maritime and Water Affairs Bureau (DSAMA). In turn, the interior of China was attended by two organizations: the Zhuhai Water Affairs Department and the Zhuhai Water Environment Holdings Group LTD.
The relationship between Macau and Zhuhai is “close and interdependent” with regard to water supply, as highlighted by the director of DSAMA, Wong Soi Man. She also recognized that the Zhuhai Water Affairs Department has been strengthening the guarantee of raw water supply to Macau, increasing the capacity to respond to salinization or contamination of drinking water.
The official added that the organization will continue to cooperate with the neighboring region in promoting water supply security, while at the same time investing in Macau's emergency water supply capacity. In this regard, Wong Soi Man recalls that the project to expand the Seac Pai Van Reservoir, which should be completed in 2028, will allow water consumption autonomy to be expanded to 12 days.
Participants at the meeting also discussed the price of raw water supplied by Zhuhai to Macau, which, as stipulated in the Guangdong-Macao Water Supply Agreement, is expected to undergo an adjustment in 2026. This new value will remain fixed until 2028, the year in which a new three-year adjustment will be made.
According to authorities' forecasts, the natural inflow of water into the Xi River basin is expected to be between 10% and 30% below average in the period between the current month of December and February of next year, suggesting a drier winter than usual. In a statement, DSAMA explains that the main upstream reservoirs began storing water in advance, with effective storage capacity reaching 90%. The reservoirs in Zhuhai “are also operating at high levels”, guarantees the organization, in order to combat the intrusion of salt water during the dry period and guarantee the security of the water supply in both regions.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:46:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau, Guangzhou and Zhuhai sign memorandum on low-altitude economy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/macau-cantao-e-zhuhai-assinam-memorando-sobre-economia-de-baixa-altitude/</link><description>Macau, Guangzhou and Zhuhai signed, last Thursday, a memorandum of cooperation to strengthen the low-lying economy. The signing of the agreement took place during the 2025 Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area High-Quality Development of Low-lying Economy Conference.
The Economic and Technological Development Bureau (DSEDT) signed this agreement with the Guangzhou Municipal Development and Reform Commission and the Zhuhai Development and Reform Bureau to “promote the synergistic development of the low-lying economy at the regional level”.
The memorandum aims to establish a regular inter-regional cooperation mechanism, with a focus on carrying out in-depth cooperation in the areas, namely, harmonization of technical standards, alignment of security supervision, exploration of innovative application scenarios and cooperation in the industrial chain. All parties will jointly explore experimental application points in areas such as cross-border intelligent logistics, emergency rescue and urban management, in order to promote the application and implementation of technologies related to low-altitude economy in real scenarios.
The organization says that this conference attracted a wide participation of representatives from the government, industrial, academic and research sectors from the Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau regions.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:48:16</pubDate></item><item><title>China reviews foreign trade law and expands response to “external struggles”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/china-reve-lei-do-comercio-externo-e-amplia-resposta-a-lutas-externas/</link><description>This Saturday, China approved a revision of the foreign trade law, which strengthens the legal framework for the development of cross-border trade and expands the legal tools for responding to “external struggles”.

According to the state agency Xinhua, the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress (APN, legislative body) gave the 'green light' to the new version of the rule, which will come into force on March 1, 2026, after a vote held this Saturday. The revised law incorporates a series of reforms, which until now were applied through regulations or sectoral policies.
These include the system of negative lists for cross-border trade in services, support for new formats and models of external trade, the push for digital trade and the acceleration of the construction of a “green” trade system.
The text also establishes provisions for the State to advance in alignment with “high-level international economic and commercial standards” and participate in the formulation of global rules in this field, according to Xinhua.
With the aim of optimizing the environment for foreign trade, the law also reinforces the protection of intellectual property rights linked to international commercial activities.
In this sense, it stipulates that the State will improve the level of regulatory compliance of foreign trade operators and their ability to manage risks related to intellectual property.
The standard also introduces a commercial adjustment assistance system, aimed at “stabilizing industrial and supply chains”, an aspect that has gained relevance in recent years in the face of commercial and technological frictions with the United States and other partners.
One of the highlights of the review is the expansion and improvement of the so-called “set of legal tools” for the defense of China's external interests, at a time marked by the trade truce reached with the United States and the persistence of tensions with other actors, such as the European Union.
The reform is approved weeks after Beijing and Washington agreed to a one-year trade truce, which includes tariff reductions and the temporary suspension of some restrictions, although Chinese authorities have insisted, in parallel, on the need to protect national economic security.

Sanctions on US companies and executives for arms sales to Taiwan

China announced the imposition of sanctions against 20 US defense companies and ten of their executives for “participation in arms sales to Taiwan in recent years”. The decision, which takes immediate effect, affects companies such as Boeing, Northrop Grumman Systems, L3Harris and VSE, and provides, among other measures, the ban on new investments in China, restrictions on cooperation with Chinese entities and the freezing of assets that may be under the jurisdiction of the Asian country. “The Taiwan issue is at the core of China's fundamental interests and is the first red line that cannot be crossed” in relations between Beijing and Washington, warned the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs in a statement.
Beijing did not specify the concrete economic scope of the measures nor the volume of operations of the affected companies in the Chinese market, but highlighted that “any entity or individual involved in the sale of weapons to Taiwan must pay the price for its mistakes”, adding that it “will continue to take firm and decisive measures” to “protect sovereignty, security and territorial integrity”.
The United States does not maintain diplomatic relations with Taiwan, but it is the main arms supplier and maintains a policy of strategic ambiguity regarding possible intervention in the event of a conflict.
This announcement came amidst an escalation of tensions between the two powers over Taiwan, following the recent signing, by the President of the United States, Donald Trump, of the National Defense Authorization Act for the 2026 fiscal year. This law allocates around one billion dollars to cooperation initiatives in matters of security on the island and reinforces the legal framework for future arms sales to Taipei. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:44:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal Point – December 29, 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/ponto-fatal-29-dezembro-2025/</link><description>This Saturday, China approved a revision of the foreign trade law, which strengthens the legal framework for the development of cross-border trade and expands the legal tools for responding to “external struggles”.

According to the state agency Xinhua, the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress (APN, legislative body) gave the 'green light' to the new version of the rule, which will come into force on March 1, 2026, after a vote held this Saturday. The revised law incorporates a series of reforms, which until now were applied through regulations or sectoral policies.
These include the system of negative lists for cross-border trade in services, support for new formats and models of external trade, the push for digital trade and the acceleration of the construction of a “green” trade system.
The text also establishes provisions for the State to advance in alignment with “high-level international economic and commercial standards” and participate in the formulation of global rules in this field, according to Xinhua.
With the aim of optimizing the environment for foreign trade, the law also reinforces the protection of intellectual property rights linked to international commercial activities.
In this sense, it stipulates that the State will improve the level of regulatory compliance of foreign trade operators and their ability to manage risks related to intellectual property.
The standard also introduces a commercial adjustment assistance system, aimed at “stabilizing industrial and supply chains”, an aspect that has gained relevance in recent years in the face of commercial and technological frictions with the United States and other partners.
One of the highlights of the review is the expansion and improvement of the so-called “set of legal tools” for the defense of China's external interests, at a time marked by the trade truce reached with the United States and the persistence of tensions with other actors, such as the European Union.
The reform is approved weeks after Beijing and Washington agreed to a one-year trade truce, which includes tariff reductions and the temporary suspension of some restrictions, although Chinese authorities have insisted, in parallel, on the need to protect national economic security.

Sanctions on US companies and executives for arms sales to Taiwan

China announced the imposition of sanctions against 20 US defense companies and ten of their executives for “participation in arms sales to Taiwan in recent years”. The decision, which takes immediate effect, affects companies such as Boeing, Northrop Grumman Systems, L3Harris and VSE, and provides, among other measures, the ban on new investments in China, restrictions on cooperation with Chinese entities and the freezing of assets that may be under the jurisdiction of the Asian country. “The Taiwan issue is at the core of China's fundamental interests and is the first red line that cannot be crossed” in relations between Beijing and Washington, warned the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs in a statement.
Beijing did not specify the concrete economic scope of the measures nor the volume of operations of the affected companies in the Chinese market, but highlighted that “any entity or individual involved in the sale of weapons to Taiwan must pay the price for its mistakes”, adding that it “will continue to take firm and decisive measures” to “protect sovereignty, security and territorial integrity”.
The United States does not maintain diplomatic relations with Taiwan, but it is the main arms supplier and maintains a policy of strategic ambiguity regarding possible intervention in the event of a conflict.
This announcement came amidst an escalation of tensions between the two powers over Taiwan, following the recent signing, by the President of the United States, Donald Trump, of the National Defense Authorization Act for the 2026 fiscal year. This law allocates around one billion dollars to cooperation initiatives in matters of security on the island and reinforces the legal framework for future arms sales to Taipei. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:43:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Experts foresee challenges in the growth of Macau’s economy in 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/especialistas-perspectivam-desafios-no-crescimento-da-economia-de-macau-em-2026/</link><description>Experts contacted by the Lusa agency foresee challenges in the growth of Macau's economy for 2026, with the recovery of the gaming sector contrasting with weak domestic consumption and pressure for diversification.

Economist Henry Chun Kwok Lei, professor of Business Economics at the University of Macau and vice-president of the Macau Economic Association, maintains a “cautiously optimistic” outlook for 2026, predicting Gross Domestic Product (GDP) growth of around 2.5% during the next financial year.
“The high base of gross gaming revenue this year, projected between 246 and 248 billion patacas, will condition the growth potential in 2026. Even if casino revenue increases by around 4%, to more than 250 billion patacas, its contribution to global economic growth will decrease,” Henry Lei told Lusa.
Ben Lee, a gaming consultant in Southeast Asia, has a more positive outlook. “Gross gaming revenue has already reached 226.5 billion patacas by November this year, so it is more than likely that we will exceed the projection of 228 billion,” he said.
The estimate for game revenue for 2026, the analyst added, is “a little conservative”. “Unless we go back next year, based on the current situation, gross revenues could reach a value between 260 and 270 billion patacas by the end of 2026”, he estimated.
The forecast included in the Budget for 2025 pointed to total revenues of around 240 billion patacas, but the weak start of the year, especially after the tariff war triggered by the United States, raised alarms among the economic team of Sam Hou Fai's Executive, which approved in June an Amending Budget in which it cut 4.56 billion patacas in the revenue forecast, highly dependent on the gaming sector (around 83% of Macau's GDP).
The Macau Economic Association predicts that annual GDP growth in 2025 will be around 5.4%, an estimate based on the “stable and positive trend of the main indicators of economic development, the globally stable functioning of the budgetary and financial systems and the maintenance of low unemployment rates”.
As for next year, adds the association, “the Macau economy is expected to maintain a stable and positive trajectory”, although the global panorama “continues to be characterized by interconnected turbulence and complexity”.
The Government Budget for 2026, approved by parliament on December 19, points to a 3.5% increase in Macau casino revenues next year, reaching 236 billion patacas, still the highest value since the pandemic.
Other critical challenges that Macau faces in 2026 are stimulating local consumption and supporting small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs). Speaking to Lusa, Lei Choek Kuan, president of the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau, pointed to the “irreversible” change in consumption patterns underway and highlighted the importance of government support for companies to maintain confidence.
Economist Henry Lei advocates a deeper structural transformation that goes beyond subsidies and suggested that local SMEs should look for differentiation and premium services — such as “improving after-sales service, developing creative cultural products and creating high-end culinary experiences” — to serve a niche demographic with high purchasing power, rather than competing on price with mainland China. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:50:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Cases of communicable diseases increase in November</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/casos-de-doencas-transmissiveis-aumentam-em-novembro/</link><description>Data released by the Health Services indicate that cases of communicable diseases that require mandatory reporting increased slightly in November, to 3,951. Highlighting the cases of norovirus infection, which rose 400% compared to the previous month of October.

The Health Services recorded a total of 3,951 cases of notifiable diseases last November, a slight increase of 3.21% compared to the 3,828 registered in October. Among the 45 diseases that require mandatory declaration in Macau, those with the greatest expression in the month under analysis were norovirus infection, chickenpox, salmonella infection and dengue and chikungunya fevers.
Norovirus infection was responsible for five cases in November. This number, although small, represents an increase of 400% compared to October, a month in which only one case was recorded. On the other hand, compared to the 39 cases reported in the same month of 2024, there is an increase of 87.2%.
This disease, which affects the gastrointestinal tract, is transmitted mainly by consumption of contaminated food or water or by contact with patient secretions. The Health Services warn of the possibility of outbreaks in nursing homes, schools and other collective establishments, which manifest themselves through food poisoning or gastroenteritis.
Chickenpox was another disease that showed significant changes compared to the previous month, with a total of 34 cases diagnosed – that is, a decrease of 48.5% compared to the 66 cases in the same period of 2024 and an increase of 78.9% compared to the 19 cases in the previous month of October.
It is an acute and highly contagious infectious disease, which occurs predominantly in children aged between five and ten years in the form of skin rashes. Although it can occur at any time of the year, it is particularly prevalent in winter and spring. In addition to vaccination, maintaining good personal and environmental hygiene is essential to preventing the disease, as the virus is transmitted through contact with infected people or contaminated objects.
Health Services were also notified of seven cases of salmonella infection. This number represents a reduction of 46.2% compared to the 13 cases registered in the same month of 2024 and 68.2% compared to the 22 in the previous month of October. Salmonella is associated with warmer climates, as heat accelerates the decomposition of food and increases the risk of the bacteria proliferating. Although it can occur throughout the year, most cases occur between July and October – that is, the hottest period of the year. The decrease in the number of cases in monthly terms may therefore be associated with the onset of colder temperatures.
Routes of transmission often include ingestion of contaminated water or poorly prepared food, although transmission between humans can also occur via the fecal-oral route. The infectious period can last for several days, weeks or (rarely) months, manifesting itself in symptoms such as nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, fever or abdominal cramps.
Finally, authorities draw attention to four imported cases of dengue fever and three cases of chikungunya fever. Both fevers are transmitted through the bite of Aedes mosquitoes that carry the virus, presenting similar clinical manifestations (such as muscle pain, headache, nausea, fatigue, fever or skin rashes).
According to the Health Services, the most effective way to reduce the risk is to adopt three essential measures: preventing the proliferation of mosquitoes, preventing mosquitoes from entering indoor areas and protecting against bites outdoors.
Under current legislation, health professionals and medical institutions in Macau have the responsibility to report cases of communicable diseases within the legal deadline. The authorities recall that the implementation of individual protection measures is essential for the prevention of diseases covered by this definition.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:52:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Residents’ income increased by 9.4% in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/rendimento-dos-residentes-registou-aumento-de-94-em-2024/</link><description>The gross national income of the Macao SAR was, in 2024, 392.81 billion patacas, that is, 9.4% more compared to the previous year. According to accounts from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), gross national income per capita was 572,614 patacas last year.

The Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC) did the math on the Macao SAR's gross national income and concluded that, in 2024, this figure was 392.81 billion patacas, that is, 9.4% more compared to the previous year. This data refers to the total income obtained by residents from carrying out economic activities within and outside that economy, corresponding to GDP plus the income obtained by residents who invested abroad, minus the income obtained by non-residents in the Macao SAR.
Analyzing the gross national income per capita, a value of 572,614 patacas was found and the GDP per capita corresponded to 579,533 patacas. A decrease of 4.75 billion patacas was also recorded in relation to GDP at current prices in the reference year (397.56 billion patacas), which reflects a net outflow of income from external factors, says DSEC.
The authorities say that total inflows of income from external factors – the income obtained by residents who invested abroad – reached 111.77 billion patacas in 2024, rising 3% in annual terms, “thanks to the investment portfolio income obtained abroad by resident companies and investors (35.55 billion patacas) having increased by 22.3% in annual terms”.
Highlights include income from reserve assets (10.29 billion patacas), income from direct investment (1.48 billion patacas) and employee compensation (139.8 million patacas), which increased by 14.1%, 75.6% and 122.1%, respectively. In turn, total outflows of income from external factors – income obtained by non-residents in the Macao SAR – amounted to 116.52 billion patacas, falling 2.5% year-on-year, “mainly due to the income from other investments obtained in the Macao SAR by non-resident companies and investors (38.2 billion patacas) decreasing by 8.4%”.
DSEC also says that, “with the intensification of exchanges between the MSAR and Hengqin”, the income obtained by companies and investors from the MSAR in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin reached 761.4 million patacas in 2024, of which 621.6 million were income from direct investment and 139.8 million were employee compensation.
In terms of direct investment income obtained by companies and investors in the Cooperation Zone in the Macao SAR, they stood at 29.6 million patacas in the reference year, with factor income obtained by the Macao SAR in the Cooperation Zone recording a net inflow of 731.7 million patacas, that is, 2% more in annual terms.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:53:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un praises blood spilled alongside Russians in Ukraine</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/kim-jong-un-louva-sangue-derramado-ao-lado-dos-russos-na-ucrania/</link><description>North Korea and Russia share “blood, life and death” in the war in Ukraine, North Korean leader Kim Jong Un emphasized in his New Year message to Russian President Vladimir Putin.

In a message published Friday by the North Korean state news agency KCNA, Kim said that 2025 was a “truly significant year” for the alliance between Pyongyang and Moscow, strengthened by having “shared blood, life and death in the same trench”.
According to South Korean and Western intelligence services, Pyongyang sent thousands of soldiers to fight alongside Moscow during the invasion of Ukraine, which began almost four years ago.
In Vladimir Putin's New Year's message to Kim Jong-un, the Russian leader celebrated the “heroic entry” of North Korean soldiers into the war in Ukraine.
The congratulation, sent on December 18th, also highlights the strategic partnership treaty signed between the leaders last year and calls for the reinforcement of the bilateral “relationship of friendship and alliance”.
North Korea only in April confirmed the deployment of troops to support the Russian military campaign against Ukraine and the death of North Korean soldiers in combat.
In early December, Pyongyang admitted having sent, in August 2025, troops to the Kursk region, in Russia, close to the border with Ukraine and at the time under occupation by Ukrainian forces. The presence of North Korean military personnel allowed Russia to go on the offensive to dislodge the occupying Ukrainian troops.
At least nine soldiers from an engineering regiment were killed during this 120-day deployment, as Kim Jong Un acknowledged in a speech given on December 13, after the unit's return.
Casualty estimates released by South Korean intelligence services point to 2,000 deaths among Pyongyang's units, which may have had between 15,000 and 20,000 soldiers on the ground.
The North Korean leader sent New Year greetings to Vladimir Putin a day after he ordered an increase in missile production to 2026.
Pyongyang has significantly increased its missile tests in recent years, which analysts say are aimed at improving its precision strike capabilities, challenging the United States and South Korea and testing weapons for export to its ally Russia.
North Korea and Russia have strengthened their ties since Moscow invaded Ukraine in February 2022. In addition to sending troops to fight for Russia, Pyongyang supplies Moscow with artillery shells, missiles and long-range rocket systems.
In return, Russia sends North Korea financial aid, military technology and food and energy supplies, according to analysts.
Russia invaded Ukraine on February 24, 2022, with the argument of protecting pro-Russian separatist minorities in the east and “denazifying” the neighboring country, independent since 1991 – after the disintegration of the former Soviet Union – and which has been moving away from Moscow's space of influence and moving closer to Europe and the West. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:44:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of visitors breaks pre-pandemic records</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/numero-de-visitantes-quebra-recordes-pre-pandemia/</link><description>This Saturday Macau surpassed the target of 39.41 million visitors, a number that surpassed all pre-pandemic records. The tourist flow during the Christmas holidays contributed to these results, bringing almost 1.5 million visitors to the territory in just one week.

Macau received 1,478,959 visitors between December 20th and 5pm yesterday, according to data released by the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP). The enormous tourist flow of the last week, marked by several holidays and festive days, contributed to Macau setting a new visitor record and surpassing pre-pandemic figures, with the arrival of around 39.41 million tourists since the beginning of the year.
Among the nine border posts providing access to the territory, the Portas do Cerco, the Hengqin Border Post and the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge stood out as the preferred crossings for visitors. Adding up the data from all the days under analysis, it appears that Portas do Cerco was the busiest border crossing with almost half a million visitor arrivals (474,956).
In turn, the Hengqin station – which in this period had 201,219 visitor arrivals – yesterday, for the first time, surpassed the milestone of 30 million passengers. According to Chinese-language radio station TDM, the estimated daily average is 83,000 passengers – 38% of them tourists and 27% Macau residents.
According to the same source, the region yesterday set a new record number of annual visitors – a number that is expected to continue to increase significantly until the end of December, with New Year's Eve celebrations. Visitors to Macau this year now total 39.41 million, surpassing the previous record set in 2019.
It is worth remembering that, at the beginning of this year, the person responsible for the Tourism Services Department (DST), Helena de Senna Fernandes, set the arrival of 38 to 39 million visitors to Macau as a target for 2025.

DAY 27 WAS THE BUSIEST

The week of holidays and long weekends began on December 20th, on the day commemorating the establishment of the Macao SAR. On this day, a Saturday, there were 295,300 cross-border movements of visitors, divided between 149,484 entries and 145,816 exits. The border posts most used by visitors entering Macau were Portas do Cerco (72,228), the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge (24,654) and the Hengqin Border Post (23,982).
The following day, corresponding to the Winter Solstice holiday, was less busy. The CPSP recorded 232,571 visitor movements: 109,878 entries and 122,693 exits. The Cerco Gates (46,661), the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge (24,176) and the Hengqin Border Post (16,237) continued to be the border crossing points of choice for visitors arriving in Macau.
On December 22nd, a Monday, border visitor movements fell again to 208,817 – 110,181 entries and 98,636 exits. Nevertheless, the two main border posts registered a slight increase in the number of visitor arrivals compared to the previous day: 47,475 people entered through Portas do Cerco and 25,408 through the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge.
On the 23rd, the total number of visitor arrivals and departures rose again to 216,606 thanks, above all, to the departure of 106,517 visitors. In the opposite direction, 110,089 tourists entered Macau, with the majority choosing to access the territory through Portas do Cerco (46,735) and the sea bridge (25,012).
On Christmas Eve, authorities counted 223,387 visitor entries and exits at border posts, with the number of entries (115,194) exceeding the number of exits (108,193). Although Portas do Cerco, Hengqin and the bridge that connects Macau to neighboring regions continued to occupy the podium of the busiest border posts, the highlight of this day goes to the Outer Harbor post, which exceeded 4,000 entries for the first time this week (more specifically, 4,478).
December 25th saw 254,989 border movements of visitors. This number includes 129,974 entries from visitors who wanted to spend the Christmas Day holiday in Macau. The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge saw the highest traffic of the entire week on this day, with 42,186 entries.
Visitor movements on the 26th reduced slightly to 253,162, with a greater number of departures (127,959) than entries (125,203). The passage that connects Hengqin to Macau had its greatest expression on this day, with the arrival of 26,053 visitors.
On the 27th, exactly one week after the Macao SAR's anniversary, the flow of visitors reached its peak with 311,347 border movements, the majority (156,918) corresponding to entries. The significant increase in visitors was felt, above all, at Portas do Cerco, which welcomed 72,684 visitors – that is, an increase of around 57.1% compared to the previous day.
The data made available by the CPSP until 5pm yesterday also indicates a very busy day, with 183,516 visitor movements (113,451 entries). At the time in question, Portas do Cerco had already registered the entry of 51,529 visitors.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:54:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Sino-Portuguese culture takes the stage in new theatrical production of the “Macasaphis” series</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/cultura-sino-portuguesa-sobe-ao-palco-em-nova-producao-teatral-da-serie-macasaphis/</link><description>The cultural fusion that defines Macau's identity and is manifested in the daily life of its streets, language and gastronomy, will now be transposed to the stage in a new local theatrical production. “Macasaphis Episode 3.0 Sino-Portuguese Culture”, the third edition of the Frost Ice Snow Creative Experimental Theater series, premieres in January at Macau Tower, proposing a contemporary artistic reflection on the cultural uniqueness of the territory and its heritage.

A new local theatrical production brings audiences an artistic journey through the territory's unique cultural identity. “Macasaphis Episode 3.0 Sino-Portuguese Culture”, an original creation by Frost Ice Snow Creative Experimental Theatre, will have its only major performance on January 10th, at 8pm, in the Theater on the 4th floor of the Macau Tower. With the support of the Cultural Development Fund, this show marks the third edition of the acclaimed “Macasaphis” series, which since 2022 has used fashion as a narrative medium to tell the stories that weave Macau's culture, making reference to the city's role as a fertile creative crossover ground.
According to the creators, the production's mission is to explore and celebrate Sino-Portuguese culture through the lens of everyday Macanese. The team describes the work as “an offering to the people of Macau”, with the central aim of creating a piece that resonates deeply with local audiences. The narrative aims to reflect how Macau residents understand and experience this cultural fusion in their daily lives, highlighting the “unique, inclusive, dynamic and diverse beauty” of local identity. Macau's characteristic humor will be a key element, allowing the audience to see themselves represented on stage and relive common memories, in a search for a shared sense of identity and belonging.
Artistically, the show takes the concept of crossing artistic boundaries to a “new level”, integrating six forms of expression in a single space: the stage. The work will feature a fashion show, a talk show, live music, theater, storytelling and dance. The look will feature ten original pieces of clothing, created specifically for the piece by renowned local fashion designer Ng Chi Wai (Memphis). Macau-born actress Ko Weng Si will lead the show through her talk show, while live musical performances will be performed by Chong Chi Ip and Wan Sin I, with original music by Kun Ka Ian. The dance component will include a reinterpretation of Portuguese folk dance by Lai Chit and Wong Weng Tong, completing a multifaceted experience that aims to guide the audience on an “unexpected artistic journey”. This innovative approach positions the project as an ambitious proposal for the current local creative panorama, fostering a multidisciplinary artistic collaboration that values ​​both tradition and experimentation, experimenting with both Portuguese and Chinese culture.
In addition to the main presentation, and as a way to deepen the public's involvement with the creative process, the company will organize the “Macasaphis 3.0 Fashion Exhibition”. This free exhibition will be on Observation Floor T58 of the Macau Tower, from the 12th to the 31st of January, displaying garments highlighted from the show, as well as sketches and materials that reveal the designer's creative process. The exhibition serves as a natural extension of the show, offering an opportunity for audiences to closely appreciate the meticulous design and stitching that brings the cultural narrative to visual life on stage.
“Macasaphis Episode 3.0” will last approximately 90 minutes, without intermission, and will be performed in Cantonese. Tickets, now on sale, are available in two categories, one for 180 patacas (general) and a special one for students for 160 patacas. Seats are not assigned and are occupied on a first-come, first-served basis. Tickets can be purchased through the company's social media platforms and the “Applied Theater” WeChat mini-program. This accessibility and the intimate format aim to democratize access to the cultural experience, aligning with the creators' vision of making art that is, above all, for and about the Macanese community.
Through this fusion of fashion, performance and cultural storytelling, Frost Ice Snow Creative Experimental Theater says it aims to reaffirm its deep relationship with local cultural engagement and in co-creating, with the community, the stories that define the region. The project is not limited to being an isolated event, but is part of a continuous four-year journey for the company, constituting a new milestone in its journey of interpreting and celebrating Macau's identity fabric.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Artist Tsang Tseng Tseng launches book about Master Wu Li and his legacy in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/artista-tsang-tseng-tseng-lanca-livro-sobre-mestre-wu-li-e-seu-legado-em-macau/</link><description>Local artist and academic Tsang Tseng Tseng (also known as San Zhen) launches this Tuesday, December 31, the book “Wu Li Art Research”, an in-depth investigation into the life and work of Qing dynasty painter Wu Li (1632–1718), one of the “Six Great Masters” of the early Qing period. The launch, organized by the Macau Contemporary Paint Association and supported by the Culture Development Fund, will take place at 3:30 pm at Bookand Bookstore. The book is dedicated to exploring an often less highlighted chapter in the history of local art. Wu Li's stay in Macau for two to three years and the profound influence that Western culture, which had already existed in the city for more than a century, had on his work.
Tsang Tseng Tseng, a doctoral student at the Chinese Academy of Art and professor at the City University of Macau, argues that, unlike his peers, Wu Li stood out as the only one among the “Six Masters” with mastery of figure painting, a skill he refined through the unique contact he had in Macau with Western artistic and religious elements. The investigation, which was born from the author's curiosity as a “native Macanese” to discover this historical connection, reveals how Wu Li's work naturally mixes the traditional Chinese landscape with Western influences, becoming a “perfect incarnation of the Macau ethos: ‘Chinese culture as the core, with diverse cultures in harmonious fusion’”.
Tsang Tseng Tseng used a methodology that crossed local archives, such as early Catholic documents and maps from the Macau Archive, with poetry collections and painting catalogs from Jiangnan scholars, offering a double perspective on the artist. The publication, structured in six chapters, covers everything from the artist's training and genealogy to a detailed analysis of his landscape painting, calligraphy, figure painting and the religious meaning (Buddhist and Catholic) in his work, with an entire chapter dedicated to “Wu Li's connection with Macau”. The launch session will be an opportunity to discuss the lasting impact of this historic bridge between East and West on contemporary art with the author.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>SJM receives green light to explore L’Arc Macau casino</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/sjm-recebe-luz-verde-para-explorar-casino-larc-macau/</link><description>SJM Resorts will be able to directly operate the L’Arc Macau casino. The group completed the acquisition of the space and the Government approved the direct operation of the casino from 2am tomorrow.

SJM Resorts has completed the acquisition of L’Arc Macau and will be able to operate the casino, after receiving the green light from the Government. Therefore, the direct operation of the L’Arc Macau casino by SJM Resorts takes effect from 2am tomorrow, December 30th.
This property is located in NAPE, on Avenida 24 de Junho, with a gross area of ​​approximately 86,438 square meters, comprising hotel accommodation, restaurants and bars, shops and the L’Arc Macau casino facilities.
The acquisition of the property by SJM was completed on December 17th, the group said in a statement sent to newsrooms. “This addition to the group's portfolio reinforces its position in a high-density catchment area, enhancing synergies between its Lisbon brand properties and allowing SJM Resorts to maintain loyal customers in geographic terms, improve customer circulation and expand its market reach”, explains the group in the press release, adding that “it maintains its commitment to contributing to the long-term development of Macau, reinforcing the urban fabric of the Macau peninsula, improving the quality and diversity of tourist offers and supporting Macau in enriching its role as the ‘World Center for Tourism and Leisure’, thus contributing to the sustainable development and long-term prosperity of the city”.
The Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) confirmed the authorization given for the operation of the casino on this property by SJM: “After analysis and consideration, the Macao SAR Government considered that the request [for the direct operation of the casino] meets the requirements and conditions of the respective legislation, and therefore granted authorization to the aforementioned request”.
“For the purposes of monitoring the operation and operation procedure of Casino L’Arc Macau, the DICJ will strictly inspect and designate employees to inspect, on site, thus requiring SJM to comply with the procedures in accordance with the operation plan presented by SJM, with a view to ensuring the normal functioning of the venue”, highlights the authorities’ statement.
The DICJ also guarantees that “it will continue to strictly inspect and supervise concessionaires operating games of chance in accordance with the law and in accordance with its powers, in order to promote the healthy and orderly development of the gaming sector in Macau”.
Last month, the group had already indicated that it would seek to acquire this property and that it would drop the Ponte 16 satellite casino. The acquisition of L’Arc cost SJM a sum of 1.75 billion Hong Kong dollars.</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:51:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Guilt and pain weigh on survivors a month after Hong Kong fire</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/28/culpa-e-dor-pesam-sobre-sobreviventes-um-mes-apos-incendio-de-hong-kong/</link><description>One month after a fire devastated a residential complex in Hong Kong and killed at least 161 people, family members tell Agence France-Presse (AFP) how pain and guilt take over these days of mourning.

Yip Ka-kui appears alongside his wife, Pak Shui-lin, in a series of photos he reviews on his cell phone. Memories recorded in front of the Egyptian pyramids, the Eiffel Tower or the Taj Mahal. “I feel guilty, I always have the feeling that I warned her too late and that, as a result, she couldn't escape in time”, he says.
Pak died exactly a month ago when a fire spread to seven towers of the Wang Fuk Court residential public housing complex. The 68-year-old husband is one of thousands of people who lost someone in their family in what is the worst fire in recent decades in Hong Kong.
The fire started when the net covering the bamboo structures between the ground floor and first floor of the Wang Cheong House block caught fire. The fire spread with unusual speed to the rest of the complex.
The residential complex, built in 1983 as part of a public affordable housing program, consists of eight 31-storey towers and around two thousand homes. According to the 2021 census, it was home to 4,643 people.
As the Hong Kong Government continues investigations and rescue operations, experts estimate that the scars will be difficult to heal for survivors, grieving families and witnesses.
Yip escaped first, but when the fire alarms didn't go off, the woman went to knock on neighbors' doors to warn them. "A few minutes' difference between us and I never saw her again. I can't accept that," he told AFP.
Shortly after the fire started, Isaac Yu, a psychologist, helped mobilize dozens of colleagues to support displaced residents. “The magnitude, immediacy and degree of shock exceeded” everything for which he and his colleagues were trained, he emphasizes. Yu explains that those who have lost everything can sometimes remain calm at first. However, the expert fears that they will collapse later and develop post-traumatic stress.
In this city of 7.5 million inhabitants, neighboring Macau, many followed the news at the time of the fire, which could have generated a significant mental burden, according to the psychologist.
Johnson Wong, 51-year-old commercial director, tells AFP that the family is going through a difficult time. Two close people remain missing.
Most of the bodies were identified by authorities, however, some remains were reduced to ashes. DNA tests, which take time to carry out, are necessary, police said, warning that the number of victims could rise.
Wong's wife expected good news about her sister and mother, but her worst fears were almost confirmed when she was shown photos of two charred bodies in the apartment where they lived. "If the [DNA test] is conclusive, that will mark the end. But if not, what can we do?" asked Wong. “It will take a long time to calm the family down.”
With the tragedy, Yip ended up moving to his children's house, but he already expressed his desire for the apartment where he lived to be rebuilt like the previous one. Hong Kong authorities have not yet committed to renovating or demolishing the dilapidated complex. The resettlement of those who lived there could take years.
Taking into account the magnitude of the tragedy, the local government created an independent commission of inquiry, chaired by a magistrate, with the aim of clarifying the causes of the start and rapid spread of the fire.
The commission should also examine the procedures applied in building rehabilitation contracts, assess the adequacy of the existing regulatory framework, analyze possible criminal liabilities and make recommendations to the Government.
On Tuesday, this commission visited the site as part of the investigation, which should result in a report within nine months.
Police said in early December that 21 people linked to various construction and subcontracting companies had been arrested, most for involuntary manslaughter and some for fraud. These numbers have not been updated since then.
Yip hopes that the authorities will clarify many of the aspects of the tragedy, which he considers to be incomprehensible. Wong appears more disillusioned: “Getting an answer is better than nothing, but can it make up for what we lost?” Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-28 22:45:11</pubDate></item></channel></rss>