<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/ipor-ajuda-club-lusitano-de-hong-kong-a-elevar-qualidade-do-ensino-do-portugues/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>PJ highlights a decrease in crime and says it combats the circumvents has obtained “remarkable” results</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/pj-destaca-diminuicao-da-criminalidade-e-diz-que-combate-as-burlas-obteve-resultados-notaveis/</link><description>Judicial Police Day (PJ) was marked by the corporation on Friday and Sit Chong Meng highlighted, at the time, the decreasing tendency of the general crime. In particular, the PJ director stressed the work of preventing and fighting the circumvents.
 
Judicial Police Day (PJ) was celebrated by the corporation on Friday. At the ceremony, the director drew attention to the PJ's efforts to prevent burla crimes, fighting “espionage activities and external interference” and the national security. General crime decreased in the first months of the year. "Public order and the situation of crime remain stable and under control," said the official.
Sit Chong Meng said that between January and May this year, 5,843 criminal proceedings were filed, a decrease of 1.1% over the same period last year; 2,858 were inquiry and complaint processes, representing a decrease of 11.1%. The total number of the processes completed was 6,379, plus 25.1%, and were referred to the judicial organs 1,641 individuals, which represents an increase of 17.6%. The PJ director also pointed out that in the first five months of the year 269 cases of theft were recorded, 27.1% over the same period last year.
The PJ indicated the director, “increased police mobilization to publicize shopkeepers and other people information about theft prevention, established a new cooperation relationship with the aviation sector, intended with several measures to prevent thefts in aircraft and also optimized the investigation mechanism to combat more effectively the crime continued as residence and in the bus propagation of this crime ”.
 
Crime in the game sector with significant increase
 
Although general crime was decreased, cases linked to the game sector made a 62.9% leap to 943 processes. According to Sit Chong Meng, the main reason for the climb was the entry into force of the illicit -playing law.
The PJ director stressed that information, data analysis and cooperation with sectors “for proactive combat in illicit loan activities” has been reinforced, and 83 cases of illicit loan and ten kidnapping were recorded, which represents a 20.2% and 41.2% decrease, respectively. With regard to the game -related circumvents, 251 cases were registered, an increase of 93.1% compared to the same period due to the fact that these slops were related to the money exchange burns and, from this year, these money exchanges were included in the statistics of game -related crimes.
As part of the repression of drug -related crimes between January and May this year, PJ has established 22 trafficking processes and ten consumption. "Although the rate of incidence of drug -related crimes continues to maintain a low level, PJ remains attentive, persisting in the direction of emphasizing information, intensifying combat, raising the drug and impulse technology, deepening interaction with local police and beyond borders and police cooperation," said Sit, stressing that "law enforcement work obtained notorious results."
 
Fighting Burns with “Notable Results”
 
Already the cases of burla, between January and May, "they decreased even more, which shows that public awareness about burla prevention is improving," said the PJ director.
There were 121 cases of telephone mockery, which represents a decrease of 27.1% compared to the same period; 228 cases of internet scams decreased 29%; and 205 online purchase cases with illicit credit card use decreased 7.2%.
However, at the end of April this year, the first case of burla involving artificial intelligence technology Deepfake arose in Macao. Since early April, they have fired the mists that simulate calls from the online payment platform service, causing damage to more than 100 people, "which showed that antiburla work is still facing lasting challenges," said the PJ official.
"PJ is striving to improve the prevention-control mode that combines prevention, recovery and combat, and develops antibur public work using various measures," he said, adding that, in May this year, the Bonda 3.0 Coordination Center has fully functioned with the work of fighting the technology based on new stage. More than 17,000 hits were also registered with the Wechat Anti-Burning mini-program in the first five months of this year. During the same period, in collaboration with the companies telecommunications operators, 263 phishing webs were blocked.
Regarding the recovery of circumventing money and losses, in the first quarter of this year, with the support of the Macao bank sector, it was possible to prevent and stop payment in 131 cases, which involved an amount of over 25 million patacas, and over the same period, PJ informed banks over 249 suspicious accounts. In addition, Continental China police froze 32 bank accounts based on PJ communication and successfully intercepted 440,000 Renminbis.
"PJ adopts an attitude of zero tolerance and is fully committed to investigating such cases," said Sit Chong Meng, pointing out that in the first five months, 98 members of fraudulent groups were detained.
 
Intensified work against espionage and external interference
 
The PJ director assured that the corporation leading to “strictly complied with the labor requirements established by the MSAR State Security Defense Commission and the hierarchical superior”, having “fully” the work of executing the state security, and intensifying the work of execution in the fight against “espionage activities and external interference for the combat of terrorism”. The safety risks assessment was also evaluated, "which managed to resolve in timely."
Given the current “increasingly severe” situation, PJ “maintains thinking based on more unfavorable presuppositions and conscientialization of danger, committed to committed to national security and stability of masters,” said Sit Chong Meng. "PJ promotes, in a deep and solid way, the dissemination and education of national security, striving to consolidate a good social environment in which Macao people have and should assume responsibilities related to the defense of national security," said the director.
The director of the PJ also said that, in the first five months of this year, the Center for Alerting and Response to Cybersecurity Incidents (Caric) sent 97 warnings to critical infrastructure operators, a 12%decrease in the face of the previous year's homologous period, and received and accompanied nine cases of cybersecurity incidents, one of which was a cyber attack, representing a decrease of four cases, "Showing that the situation remained stable and tended to a positive course."</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:55:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Parisian exhibition “Infinity Beyond Imagery” wants to transcend the boundaries of the form</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/exposicao-do-parisian-infinity-beyond-imagery-quer-transcender-os-limites-da-forma/</link><description>Macau Youth Art Association's “Infinity Beyond Image” collective exhibition was inaugurated last Friday at 6:30 pm at The Shopppes Parisian Macao. The project - which marks the first collaboration between the artist collective and the Parisian - will remain open to the public until August 23, with free admission to all visitors.
At the inauguration ceremony, the president of Macau Youth Art Association, Lai Sio Kit, acknowledged the “truly precious opportunity” to present the artistic creations of young local artists in a “artistic space so elegant”, thanking Sands China for “allowing the talents of young artists from Macao to flourish and that more people acquired a profound understanding of the artistic vitality nourished by this land”. On behalf of the association, Lai Kit said he hoped the exhibition "demonstrate the rich vitality of Macau's art to a wider audience."
The curatorship of the show is in charge of Hera Ieong, vice president of Macao Youth Art Association and responsible for multiple artistic societies that has already exposed their work in countries such as China, Japan and the United States of America. According to a statement from the association, the concepts of “infinity” and “image” that name the project derive from “oriental philosophy” and integrate into the purpose of “transcending the boundaries of form and technique, exploring the way art can incorporate the spirit of‘ expressing meaning through symbols ”and raise“ material expression to philosophical contemplation ”.
The way works were designed mirror this concept of fluidity, covering traditional means such as paint painting and handwriting, as well as “contemporary experimentation” between different art forms. In total, more than 80 pieces are brought together by emerging local artists such as Fong Wai Peng, Cheong Wan I, Leong Sin Teng, Leong Keng IP, Leong Kit Man, Elvis Mok Hei Sa, Kuok Chi Kei, Wong Kin Tong, Wong Sio Hang, Ieong Man Hin, Ieong Ka Fan, Zheng Xiaojun, Lu Shaoyi and Tam Chon Kit.
"Tradition should not be seen as a static symbol, but as a dynamic way of thinking. These works continue the dialectical relationship of eastern aesthetics, while seeking innovative ways for cultural heritage through the dialogue between the virtual and the real and between the old and the contemporary," describes the curator, quoted in the statement.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>International Gastronomy Festival brings food, fun and leisure to Macau until July 20</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/festa-internacional-da-gastronomia-traz-comida-diversao-e-lazer-a-macau-ate-20-de-julho/</link><description>Inaugurated on July 11, the International Gastronomy Cities Festival will remain in the fishermen's dock by the 20th, providing much more than a gastronomic experience. One of the main highlights of the event happens today, with the International Gastronomy Forum, in which 15 chefs and experts reflect values such as sustainability, creativity and inclusion in the world of Asian cuisine.
 
The International Festival of Cities of Gastronomy, one of the largest gastronomic events in Macao, opened its doors last Friday. In addition to a huge diversity of exotic flavors, textures and aromas from 22 countries from six continents, the party has a vast animation program consisting of games, musical performances and magic shows.
The opening ceremony was attended by members of the Government of RAM, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) and the six game dealers, also bringing together representatives from several of the 24 UNESCO gastronomy cities who joined the event. These include the Portuguese city of Santa Maria da Feira, represented in Macao by the deputy mayor António Gil Alves Ferreira.
Speaking at the ceremony, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of STD, highlighted the uniqueness of the gastronomic culture of Macao, marked by both Chinese and Western influences. Noting that “gastronomy is a language shared by all”, the official expressed the hope that the party will take a party “from the advantages of Macau as an international exchange platform, committed to preserving and transmission of gastronomic culture”, not neglecting the sustainability aspects contemplated in the United Nations (UN) agenda (UN).
The word was then passed to Denise Bax, secretary of the UNESCO Creative Cities Network, which participated in the ceremony with a video message where she recalled the origins of the project and her basic concepts of "creativity" and "sustainable urban development." As for future perspectives of cooperation between Macao and the UNESCO network, Bax was confident of the “many opportunities” possible not only in the area of gastronomy and tourism, but also in the “development of new sectors driven by culture and creativity”.
Also Colleen Swain, coordinator of the UNESCO Gastronomy Group and San Antonio's focal point in the United States, stressed that “this annual party has a profound meaning to the network's member cities,” according to an STD statement. By providing the meeting of multiple international cities and allowing Macao residents to try the flavors of different cultures, the event is “a platform for exchange and demonstration of culinary characteristics and cultural traditions” that are practiced all over the world.
 
Forum brings together 15 chefs and experts
 
One of the great highlights of the event happens today, between 9:00 and 13:00, at the Fisherman's Dock Convention and Exhibition Center. This is the “International Gastronomy Forum”, subordinate to the theme “The Flavor of Life: Culinary Connections of Macau”, in which dozens of chefs and relief personalities will share their perspectives on sustainability and inclusiveness in the world of culinary, in a program composed of two inaugural speeches and three thematic panels.
The inaugural speeches are in charge of chef Jordy Navarra, founder of the Filipino Toyo Eatary restaurant, and chef Varun Totlani, responsible for the Indian restaurant Masque Restaurant. In alignment with the central theme of the fair, “spices and herbs”, the discussion topics will focus mainly on the role of these ingredients in the enrichment of global cuisine.
The first thematic panel has as its starting point the theme “History and Legacy of Spices: Review of the Origins of Melting Culinary” and brings together Professor David Wiley, Thai influencer Chonlathip Rayamas and Chefs Vicky Cheng, Hironori Maeda and Murat Kara. According to STD, panelists and the public will explore “the influence of the spice trade on the evolution of the cultural panorama of Asia” and the development of melting kitchens on this continent throughout history.
“Flavors Symphony: Fusion cuisine in modern macao and the world” is the second panel of the day, composed by chefs Antonieta Fernandes Mannhão, Antimo Maria Merone, Jack Siew and Tony Woo and columnist Susan Jung. In this conversation with the public, the speakers will explain how they maintain the balance between tradition and innovation in the dishes they prepare, reconciling “innovative techniques” and “global perspectives” with the preservation of culture.
The last panel, entitled “Spices as Bridge: Celebration of Cultural Fusion and Communities”, is headed by chefs Raymond Vong, Ricardo Chaneton, Shelly Tai, Jun Kim and Norihisa Maeda. In this session, as the name implies, "the contributions of immigrant communities to the gastronomic richness of the territory and the role of culinary in promoting cultural fusion and social cohesion will be addressed."
"Participants will explore together the essence of gastronomic cultures and stories that transcend geographical and cultural limits, constituting an occasion that will allow to appreciate the value of Macao's inclusiveness, harmony and integration," writes STD.
 
Gastronomy and Leisure
 
The International Gastronomy Cities Festival takes place at the Roman Coliseu Square and the Legend Boulevard of Doca dos Fishermen, in the Nape area. In addition to the 34 creative cities of gastronomy that will be present in Macau - more than 60% of the total number - seven creative cities also participate in other artistic areas, two Chinese candidates to the UNESCO network and two cultural cities of East Asia.
The program is divided into three main components, one of them being the “International Gastronomy Forum” scheduled for today. The International Gastronomy Avenue, in turn, has 105 newsstands distributed in various origins: 25 newsstands represent cities in the interior of China; Nine newsstands come from other Asian cities such as Phuket, Hatay or Iloilo; 52 stalls will present local macao gastronomy; and 11 new newsstands will represent Portuguese -speaking countries, especially Brazilian cities such as Florianópolis and Belo Horizonte. This section will be open from 15:30 to 22:00, on weekdays, and from 15:00 to 23:00, on Saturdays and Sundays.
Also noteworthy is the “demonstrations of cities of gastronomy”, where chefs from 28 creative cities will hold more than 60 culinary sessions focused on the creative use of spices and herbs. Visitors have the opportunity to prove these creations at the place of the demonstrations, which take place daily between 3:30 pm and 10 pm.
But not everything is related to gastronomy. Throughout the period of the event, shows such as Portuguese folk dances, band presentation, artistic rope jump, street dances, puppet theaters, balloon modeling by clowns and magic tricks. There is also a diverse offer of interactive activities suitable for various age groups, where the whole family can participate, and a draw in which participants qualify to gain airplane tickets with round trip tickets between Macao and the interior of China.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Public accounts register damage before the reinforcement of social support</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/contas-publicas-registam-prejuizo-antes-do-reforco-de-apoios-sociais/</link><description>Public accounts in the territory reveal a loss of 289.4 million patacas in June. Macau registered in the first half of the year an surplus in public accounts of 11.4 billion Patacas. However, this value represents a 2.5% drop compared to the end of May.
 
Macao's public accounts reveal that the region lost 289.4 million patacas in June, even before a budget revision to reinforce social support.
According to published data online by the Directorate Directorate of Finance Services (DSF) on Friday, the territory registered in the first half of the year a surplus in public accounts of 11.4 billion Patacas. However, this value represents a 2.5% drop compared to the end of May, when Macau had a surplus of 11.7 billion patacas.
Still, the surplus of the city between January and June was 40.3% higher than in the same period last year and is already higher than the government's forecast for the entire year 2025: 6.83 billion of patacas.
Macao closed 2024 with an surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the one recorded the previous year.
Macao's public expense fell 8.2% in the first half of the year, compared to the same period of 2024, to 41.4 billion patacas.
The only reason for the fall was spending on social support and subsidies, which decreased 17.7% to 20.7 billion patacas. But the Legislative Assembly approved on Wednesday a government proposal to increase by 2.86 billion of Patacas in the expenses provided for in the budget, to reinforce social support. The review includes the creation of a subsidy, totaling 54,000 patacas, for children up to 3 years, to raise the lowest birth in the world.
Macao current revenue also dropped 0.95% in the first half of the year to 52.3 billion patacas.
The main reason for the decrease was a drop of 62.3%to 520 million patacas, in the “property income”, a heading that includes the revenue of land concessions. On the contrary, tax revenues over the game - representing 86.4% of the total - rose 1% to 45.3 billion patacas.
The six game operators in the city pay a 35% direct tax on the game's revenues, 2.4% for the Macao Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development, and 1.6% delivered to the Macau Foundation for cultural, educational, scientific, academics and philanthropic purposes.
Total revenues from Macao casinos reached 118.8 billion patacas in the first half of the year, 4.4% more than in the same period as 2024.
On April 15, the region's government leader Sam Hou Fai admitted a budget deficit in 2025, due to the slowdown in the game's revenues. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:54:53</pubDate></item><item><title>China dismantles 300 Dams to restore Yangtsé ecosystem</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/china-desmantela-300-barragens-para-restaurar-ecossistema-do-yangtse/</link><description>China has dismantled 300 dams and ended most hydroelectric plants in Chishui - an important tributary from the Yangtsé River - to protect threatened fish species and restore the ecosystem, official press said.
 
According to the official news agency Xinhua, until December 300 from the 357 existing dams at Chishui, also known as Rio Vermelho, were removed. In addition, 342 of the 373 small hydroelectric plants were deactivated, allowing several rare fish species to retract natural reproduction cycles.
Over 400 kilometers long, Chishui crosses the provinces of Yunnan, Guizhou and Sichuan, in southwest China, being considered by ecologists as one of the last refuges for rare and endemic species from the Yangtsé upper basin.
In recent decades, the intensive construction of dams and hydroelectric plants has restricted downstream water flow and, in some sections, has caused the flow of flow, according to Xinhua.
A situation that destroyed natural habitats and spawning zones, as well as blocking the migratory routes of various piston species.
Zhou Jianjun, professor of hydraulic engineering at Tsinghua University, explained that the closure of the centrals does not necessarily imply the physical demolition of infrastructure. "Most importantly, after the production of electricity ceases, the mode of water management can be changed to meet ecological needs," he said, quoted by Xinhua.
The agency added that since the beginning of ecological rehabilitation work, in 2020, species such as the Yangtsé stubble have recovered the habitat and vitality.
This species, declared extinct in nature by the International Union for Nature Conservation in 2022, was affected by the construction of dams and the development of river navigation since the 1970s.
However, researchers from the Chinese Academy Hydrobiology Institute of Science, led by Liu Fei, recorded encouraging recovery signs.
According to Xinhua, two Yangtzé sturgeon waves were released in Rio Vermelho in 2023 and 2024 and were able to successfully adapt to the natural environment.
Last April, the researchers released 20 adult sturctions in a Rio section in Guizhou, having recorded natural reproductive behaviors and the outbreak of eggs. "This feat demonstrates that the current ecological environment of Rio Vermelho is now suitable for the habitat and reproduction of the Yangtsé sturgeon," said Liu Fei.
The institute's latest data reveal a significant increase in aquatic biodiversity in Chishui, with greater diversity of fish species detected in various sections of the river.
Since 2020, China has implemented a series of measures to protect Yangtsé, including a ten -year moratorium on fishing and the regulation of hydroelectric plants.
In late 2021, the province of Sichuan completed the restructuring of 5,131 small centrals, ending 1,223, according to an official report, quoted by Xinhua.
Local authorities also banned sand extraction in watercourses in an attempt to preserve aquatic habitats.
In a statement issued in August, the Chinese government indicated that aquatic biodiversity has steadily improved since the adoption of these measures, especially the recovery of fish, invertebrates and amphibians. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:54:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuel supply cut shortly before Air India's plane crash</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/corte-no-fornecimento-de-combustivel-pouco-antes-da-queda-de-aviao-da-air-india/</link><description>The fuel power switches of the Air India Boeing engines that crashed shortly after taking off, killing 260 people, were in the "off" position shortly before the impact, according to a preliminary investigation report yesterday released.
The report, released by the India Air Accident Investigation Office (AAIB), does not draw conclusions or assign responsibilities, but says one pilot asked the other because he had cut the fuel, having the second pilot replied.
A total of 241 people aboard the Air India Boeing 787-8 Dreamliner died, and only one survived when the plane drew up on houses shortly after taking off in the city of Ahmedabad in the northwest of the country.
Authorities also identified 19 people killed on land, France-Presse (AFP) reported.
According to the report, Boeing reached a top speed of 180 knots (333 km/h) during take -off, when fuel switches went from “run” position to the “cutoff” position to the first engine and a second later to the second. Both engines began to lose power.
In the voice recording of the cabin, one pilot asks the other because he cut the fuel. The second pilot replies no. Less than a minute later, a pilot transmitted the "Mayday, Mayday, Mayday" help signal, and the plane picked up residential.
Airport surveillance images show that the emergency wind turbine, a small turbine used as a reserve power source at aircraft, was triggered during the initial climb shortly after decay. There were no birds in the area.
The plane began to lose altitude even before leaving the perimeter of the airport, according to the report. Air India Flight 171 fall, bound for London, was the first involving a B-787, which entered the service in 2011.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:55:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing defends as legitimate approach of Chinese hunting the Japanese military plane</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/pequim-defende-como-legitima-aproximacao-de-caca-chines-a-aviao-militar-japones/</link><description>The government of China defended the approaching Chinese fighter to a Japanese military aircraft in international waters in the sea of east China, ensuring that the maneuver was "legitimate, reasonable [and] professional."
 
The incident occurred on Wednesday, when a Chinese bomber fighter JH-7 approached a Japanese electronic intelligence aircraft YS-11eb at a distance considered insecure by the Japanese authorities, who presented a formal protest to Beijing over the maneuver.
Chinese Ministry of Defense spokesman Colonel Jiang Bin said Japanese recognition aircraft have entered the east of China air defense identification zone on "multiple occasions" to perform "approach recognition."
This air zone - which includes the Senkaku islands, run by Tokyo, but claimed by Beijing under the name of Diaoyu - was unilaterally announced by China in 2013 and is not recognized by neighboring Japan and South Korea. Legitimate, reasonable, professional and in accordance with regulations, ”said Jiang Bin.
The spokesman stressed that such “approximation and interference” activities by Japanese ships and aircraft “are the root cause of the risks for air and sea safety between China and Japan”. "We hope the Japanese side will advance in the same direction as China and create a favorable environment for the stable development of bilateral relations," Jiang said in statements quoted by Chinese state television CCTV.
In early June, a similar incident occurred in international waters in the Pacific, when a J-15 Chinese fighter, armed with missiles, upon the flight of the Shandong aircraft carrier, was only 45 meters from a Japanese military plane.
According to the Japanese Ministry of Defense, the P-3C Maritime Patrol aircraft of the Maritime Self-Defense Force proceeded a surveillance operation on the Pacific Ocean.
The Japanese government expressed “serious concern” to China with this incident and required measures to be taken to prevent it from repeating.
Also in June, Japan expressed concern about the increase in Chinese military maneuvers near its territory, leading it to disclose, in an unusual way, detailed information about these activities.
The two Chinese navy aircraft carrier, Shandong and Liaoning, “made about a thousand landing aircraft” between late May and mid-June, the Japanese Minister of Defense revealed. Gen Nakatani explained that one of the ships approached the islands of Iwojima and Santon and carried out more than 100 rigs and landings of aircraft in the exclusive Japanese economic zone near Okinotori, the southernmost island of Japan. Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:54:24</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP survey says that population is “satisfied” with their service</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/inquerito-do-cpsp-diz-que-populacao-esta-satisfeita-com-o-seu-servico/</link><description>The population is increasingly pleased with the global service provided by the Public Security Police (CPSP), concluded an inquiry conducted by the body itself. According to the results, the average classification of last year's CPSP performance was 4.4 points, being the highest of the last four years. The body assumed reinforced the transparency of information.
 
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) has conducted an inquiry regarding the degree of citizens' satisfaction about the services provided over the past year, concluding that the public is increasingly satisfied with the body's services compared to previous years.
According to the results of the survey released last week, the global average classification of last year's CPSP performance was 4.44 points, on a scale of 0 to 5 points, located at the “satisfactory” level.
Authorities highlight the climbing trend on the classification given by the population in recent years, and the classification obtained in 2023 was 4.41 points, while in 2022 and 2021 were 4.27 and 4.33 points, respectively.
The CPSP explained that the inquiry collected answers to the questionnaire of 1,356 people, who were local residents, residence applicants, non-resident workers, tourists, foreign students, as well as representatives of local companies and organizations, who had used police service last year. The inquiry was promoted according to the provisions of the public services and organizational performance evaluation regime, “serving as an important reference for service improvement,” said CPSP.
The inquiry comprises eight assessment factors, namely “personnel services”, “complementary environment and facilities”, “procedures and formalities”, “services information”, “confidence in service provision”, “electronic services”, “performance information” and “services integration”.
"The results show that the average rates of satisfaction of all factors are greater than 4 points. Among these, the 'staff services' obtained the highest classification, which indicates that citizens have a positive opinion on personnel service and the general performance of the service in 2024," the analysis stressed.
According to the inquiry report, the evaluation of eight factors registered an increase, except the element about the integration of services, which went from 4.32 points to 4.26 points.
CPSP has advanced to have received opinions on optimizing the quality of its public services, and the largest number of comments and suggestions are related to the domain of “service information”.
"With the continuous increase of the midfielders, the internet and intelligent technology, humans have entered the age of information explosion. In the information-based life environment, the construction of a complete information network and the breach of the information dissemination are a greater concern for people, it is found that reinforcement of transparency, clarity and detail is an indispensable part of subsequent optimization work," he said.
In addition, police authorities have committed to taking steps to simplify service processes, including requests and approval of orders, as well as increasing service efficiency.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:54:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.07.14</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/ponto-fatal-2025-07-14/</link><description>The population is increasingly pleased with the global service provided by the Public Security Police (CPSP), concluded an inquiry conducted by the body itself. According to the results, the average classification of last year's CPSP performance was 4.4 points, being the highest of the last four years. The body assumed reinforced the transparency of information.
 
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) has conducted an inquiry regarding the degree of citizens' satisfaction about the services provided over the past year, concluding that the public is increasingly satisfied with the body's services compared to previous years.
According to the results of the survey released last week, the global average classification of last year's CPSP performance was 4.44 points, on a scale of 0 to 5 points, located at the “satisfactory” level.
Authorities highlight the climbing trend on the classification given by the population in recent years, and the classification obtained in 2023 was 4.41 points, while in 2022 and 2021 were 4.27 and 4.33 points, respectively.
The CPSP explained that the inquiry collected answers to the questionnaire of 1,356 people, who were local residents, residence applicants, non-resident workers, tourists, foreign students, as well as representatives of local companies and organizations, who had used police service last year. The inquiry was promoted according to the provisions of the public services and organizational performance evaluation regime, “serving as an important reference for service improvement,” said CPSP.
The inquiry comprises eight assessment factors, namely “personnel services”, “complementary environment and facilities”, “procedures and formalities”, “services information”, “confidence in service provision”, “electronic services”, “performance information” and “services integration”.
"The results show that the average rates of satisfaction of all factors are greater than 4 points. Among these, the 'staff services' obtained the highest classification, which indicates that citizens have a positive opinion on personnel service and the general performance of the service in 2024," the analysis stressed.
According to the inquiry report, the evaluation of eight factors registered an increase, except the element about the integration of services, which went from 4.32 points to 4.26 points.
CPSP has advanced to have received opinions on optimizing the quality of its public services, and the largest number of comments and suggestions are related to the domain of “service information”.
"With the continuous increase of the midfielders, the internet and intelligent technology, humans have entered the age of information explosion. In the information-based life environment, the construction of a complete information network and the breach of the information dissemination are a greater concern for people, it is found that reinforcement of transparency, clarity and detail is an indispensable part of subsequent optimization work," he said.
In addition, police authorities have committed to taking steps to simplify service processes, including requests and approval of orders, as well as increasing service efficiency.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:53:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Recognition of heritage by UNESCO made Macau more than one city of game</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/reconhecimento-de-patrimonio-por-unesco-fez-de-macau-mais-do-que-uma-cidade-de-jogo/</link><description>Experts consider that the classification of the historic center of Macao by UNESCO, twenty years ago, boosted cultural tourism in the territory, supporting the diversification of an economy traditionally dependent on casinos, and warns of challenges in promoting heritage.
 
The Temple of Na Tcha, Chinese Sanctuary, and the ruins of Sao Paulo, facade of the former 17th-century Mother God Catholic Church, are side by side in the historic center of Macau. Early in the morning, families pose to the chamber at the bottom of the iconic stone staircase of the ruins.
“I like the sidewalk [Portuguese], it's special,” says Lusa Alina Wang, a Shanghai tourist. The eight -year -old son York Xiong adds: "The buildings are beautiful." Not everyone in the family, however, knows the story behind Macao's "former libris", reduced to the facade after fires. The patriarch, I read Zijian, was going to swear that it had been destroyed during World War II.
Beside, another family, is from Xi'na, associates the image of ruins with a Japanese bombardment in the great war.
20 years ago, on July 15, 2005, the Historic Center of Macao, a set of 22 monuments that combines Portuguese and Chinese architecture, joined the list of UNESCO World Heritage.
This milestone for the city's heritage, Lusa tells the direction of tourism services, brought more tourists to Macao, changing the visitor's profile, which stopped crossing the border just to play. "This changed the image of Macao from a 'city of the game' to a cultural destination, differentiating it in the Asia-Pacific region," he told Lusa that direction.
Since 2005, the government department has added through email, the tourism sector has been developing at an “rapid pace”. Macao visitors arrived from 16.14 million in 2005 to 34.93 million in 2024.
A study to visitors conducted by the Tourism Directorate this year reveals that 53.3%of tourists arrive in the territory to visit the heritage, surpassing those who want to shop (33.7%) and those who are most interested in gastronomy (18.5%).
For IP FEI Law, historian and former member of the Macao Cultural Heritage Council, the United Nations Statute for Education, Science and Culture (UNESCO) raised Macao's global profile. "The game has boosted the economy in the short term, culture should boost long -term growth," he told Lusa.
Macao's economy depends deeply on casinos, representing 80% of public revenues, and the government of the Chinese semi -autonomous region expects to raise 79.8 billion this year with the game tax. But if, on the one hand, the inscription of heritage came to help diversify the tourist's profile, you have to think of those who live in the city daily, noticed Ka Nok Lo, vice president of the Macao Heritage Ambassadors Association.
In an interview with Lusa, the official warned of the need not to turn Macau “into a Disneyland”, defending the balance between tourism and the needs of residents. "Museums should serve the community, as are libraries, bookstores, not just tourists," he said. Ka stressed, on the other hand, that the visitors still remain the narrative that unites the various places distinguished by UNESCO. "There is no story that turns on these monuments," he said.
The Macao government has as one of the main objectives to seek economic diversification, in order to reduce its dependence on the game industry through the development of new sectors.
And these are integrated tourism and leisure, traditional Chinese medicine (MTC) and “Big Health”, modern financial services, high and new technology, conventions, exhibitions, sports and commerce. But the appeal of the casinos is unavoidable, such as the families of Shanghai and Xi'an have highlighted. The day after the Macao Historic Zone tour, the visit to the region would continue in the modern resorts of the game concentrated in the Cotai zone, highlighting the double role of Macao as a gaming destination and cultural heritage. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:52:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Detainee former president of ICBC Macau for alleged connection to the Windsor Arch project</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/detido-ex-presidente-do-icbc-macau-por-alegada-ligacao-ao-projecto-windsor-arch/</link><description>The former president of China's Industrial and Commercial Bank (Macau) has been arrested and is being investigated. Chinese authorities reveal that Jiang Yisheng is now the target of a disciplinary inspection for committing "serious disciplinary offenses." The case of Jiang, who led the bank between 2018 and 2023, will be linked to a real estate loan granted to businessman NG Lap Seng regarding the Windsor Arch project in the mud.
 
Jiang Yisheng, former president of China's Industrial and Commercial Bank (Macau) (ICBC Macau), was arrested by the Chinese authorities for “serious disciplinary offenses”. The detention may be linked to a loan granted, during its term, to a construction project promoted by businessman NG Lap Seng, according to sources of the Global Caixin press.
Rumors have recently emerged that the banker would be missing, but an official central government notification confirmed that he was detained.
According to a note published by the Central Committee by the Disciplinary Inspection of the Chinese Communist Party last Friday, Jiang Yisheng is being investigated on suspicion of having committed serious disciplinary offenses, being undergoing a disciplinary inspection by the State Disciplinary Supervision Group and the Zhuhai Municipal Inspection Commission.
Jiang Yisheng was chairman of the ICBC Macao Board of Directors between April 2018 and June 2023, leaving the position held in the territory at the age of 56.
Jiang had been working on banking management at the ICBC Group for over 20 years and acted as president of the Zhuhai branch, vice president of the Cantão branch, vice president of the Guangdong Province Branch, general manager of the Guangdong branch international business department. In addition, he served as assistant general manager at ICBC Asia and ICBC Asia executive director.
In November 2021, the ICBC Macau led the creation of the Macao Securities and Funds Industry Association, of which Jiang Yisheng was the first president.
According to Jiang Yisheng's Global Cashin investigation is allegedly related to a real estate loan granted to fund the luxury residential venture Windsor Arch, being NG Lap Seng the former president of the Sun Kian Kian IP group, one of the promoters of Windsor Arch in mud.
 
Financial connections
 
Jiang's case occurs at a time when ICBC Macau requested the court the seizure of the assets of businessman NG Lap Seng to recover pending debts. Chinese press caxin global also indicated that ICBC Macau will have taken disciplinary measures against Jiang Yisheng earlier this year due to “significant failures” in the loan guarantee, although the exact amount of the loan was not disclosed.
According to an announcement published on 18 June by the Base Judicial Court, NG Lap Seng and his son, NG Kei Nin, and ten other people and companies were classified as argued in a freezing action at the request of ICBC Macao.
The assets to be seized include about 80 parking spaces, more than 40 office units, as well as bank deposits and actions evaluated in more than 1.7 million patacas on behalf of NG Lap Seng and his child.
NG Lap Seng, a well-known Magnata and Real Estate Prosecutor in Macao, was involved in a case of United Nations, for which he was sentenced in 2017 by the US Federal Court for six bribery crimes, capital bleaching and conspiracy, having been sentenced to four years in prison.
The US court concluded that NG paid hundreds of thousands of US dollars in bribes to two UN ambassadors between 2010 and 2015, in exchange for its support for a project to build a “United Nations Conference Center” in Macao. The project, which intended to turn Macao into a diplomatic center, had a potential value of thousands of dollars.
The businessman was eventually released in early 2021, after serving 34 months from the prison sentence for health reasons. Subsequently, NG Lap Seng was also involved in a case of corruption in Macao that involved two former directors of the extinct direction of soil, public works and transport services (DSSOPT), Li Canfeng and Jaime Carion, as well as real estate entrepreneurs Sio Tak Hong, William Kuan.
Ng Lap Seng was originally sentenced to 15 years in prison, but his sentence was reduced to two and a half years in 2023 after appeal.
The Windsor Arch Project was one of the projects, according to the local court, through which DSSOPT officials received benefits from real estate entrepreneurs involved in order to assist them in the process of construction projects, especially in terms of land use restrictions.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:53:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn presents digital trip through the history of Chinese porcelain on unpublished exhibition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/wynn-apresenta-viagem-digital-pela-historia-da-porcelana-chinesa-em-exposicao-inedita/</link><description>Operator Wynn will launch next weekend the first major immersive exhibition dedicated to Jingezen's porcelain, part of the cultural agenda of the Art Macao Art Biennial. The show combines digital technology and historical pieces to narrate the global influence of this Chinese millennial art, with an emphasis on its role in the cultural exchange between East and West.
 
Wynn Palace opens on July 18 the exhibition “Hello China, Hello Macao - The Odyssey of Jingezen Porcelain: A Heritage Voyage from Macao to the World”. This initiative marks the first large -scale presentation presentation, which uses immersive technology to tell the history of Jingdezen porcelain, a city recognized as the capital of this millennial art of Chinese origin, at a time when its production ovens are in the process of candidacy for UNESCO World Heritage Site.
The exhibition comes within the new cultural project “Wynn Culture”, which aims to promote Chinese cultural heritage and foster intercultural dialogue. The show was officially included in the program of “Macao, Culture of East Asia 2025” and has the aesthetic guidance of the renowned artisan master and educator Chang Shana.
Exposure is structured in two main axes. The “Imperial Kiln Treasures - Digital Rebirth” section at the Wynn Palace illuminarium features an unprecedented digital recreation of the Chinese porcelain's commercial route through four narrative chapters that cover over a thousand years of history. The section uses immersive projections and light and shadow technologies, to recreate the manufacturing process and the global journey of these pieces.
The “A Dialogue Between Past and Present - Symphony of Masters” brings together works by more than 30 contemporary ceramist masters and historical reference pieces. Highlights include the celebrated Buccleuch Vasses, emblematic specimens of the artistic fusion between East and West of the eighteenth century, and the first presentation outside China of the dove of peace, a work conceived by Master Chang Shana as a national offering of the Popular Republic of China.
The exhibition has special attention to porcelain Clark, a style developed during the sino-Portuguese exchange period, witnessing the historical ties between the two cultures. It also presents the contemporary series “Macau Science 1”, which reinterprets spatial exploration through traditional ceramic techniques, demonstrating the current vitality of this timeless art.
In addition, on July 18, the opening date, the “Silk Road Ceramic Journey · Macau’s New Chapter” seminar will be held, which will bring together international experts to discuss the role of ceramics in contemporary civilizational dialogue. The event will be attended by academics, curators and artists who will address the historical and current relevance of Chinese porcelain in the global context.
This exhibition is part of the broadest program of “Macao Art: Macau International Art Biennial 2025”, which runs in various spaces from the city until October. The Biennial, curated by Feng Boyi, presents the theme “Hello, what do you do here?” and includes six main exhibitions with works by renowned international artists such as Xu Bing and Ann Hamilton.
The exhibition “Hello China, Hello Macao-The Odyssey of Jingezen Porcelain: A Heritage Voyage from Macao to the World” will be officially open to the public from July 19 at Wynn Palace-Illumumium and Palace Reserve Club Gallery, with free admission from 11 am to 7 pm, and patent until October 19th.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Philippine authorities find alleged remains of missing in rooster fights</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/autoridades-filipinas-encontram-alegados-restos-mortais-de-desaparecidos-em-lutas-de-galos/</link><description>The Philippine Authorities found a bag of what appear to be charred human bones at the bottom of a volcanic lake where they sought the bodies of 34 rooster fighting gale, allegedly killed by the police.
 
"A team from the National Philippines (…) in coordination with the Philippine Coast Guard, recovered a white bag containing what appear to be charred human bones," the Justice Department announced in a statement.
According to the document, the authorities also have to make sure that the remains are human and, if so, will perform DNA tests to verify if they belong to any of the missing.
The Filipine Television Station ABS-CBN has advanced that search teams have also located other bags that have not yet been recovered.
Possible remains were found on the lake around the Taal volcano, south of Manila, where diving teams continue to search for the missing.
The case of 'sabunges', as the galle fight enthusiasts in the Philippines are known, dates back to 2021.
In just one year, at least 34 people linked to these competitions and the profitable online bets around the fights, very popular in the Philippines but prohibited since 2022, have disappeared.
Families and activists have been guaranteed in recent years that the 'Sabungaros' have been kidnapped and killed following rivalries in this multimillionaire underworld, and have repeatedly expressed frustration with the lack of progress in the investigation.
The incident remained “buried” until last month, when a man, Julie Padidongan, said in an interview with GMA national television that the 34 were killed and then thrown into the lake around the Taal volcano.
Padidoning claimed that the homicides were committed with the help of Philippines and accused businessman Charlie Ang, involved in organizing rooster fights and for whom the complainant worked as security, to order the disappearance.
According to the witness, the affections and workers of the rooster struggles were strangled and mutilated before being thrown into the lake.
Police investigators corroborated the details and evidence provided by the witness, which will be used in criminal complaints to present by the Justice Department against the suspects, he said.
The complainant claimed to have decided to speak out because his former debtor would be allegedly threatening to kill him and because he wanted to alleviate the agony of the victims' families. Ang, in turn, denied the accusations and complained against his former employee on Thursday, accusing him of threats and extortion.
The Philippine authorities detained and imposed restrictions a week ago to 15 police suspected of being involved in the disappearances.
Although prohibited in the United States and other western countries, largely due to concerns about cruelty to animals, the rooster struggle has been a popular pastime and a betting sport in many parts of Southeast Asian, including Philippines, but also in Latin America and some parts of Europe.
The game involves placing two roosters - with sharp bars or steel blades attached to the paws - in a battle, often to death, in the middle of the crowd's roar. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:55:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese government rejects EU accusations about illegal data storage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/governo-chines-rejeita-acusacoes-da-ue-sobre-armazenamento-ilegal-de-dados/</link><description>The Chinese government denied any involvement in the illegal storage of personal data on servers located in China after the opening of a new European Union investigation to the Tiktok social network. "The Chinese government attributes great importance to the privacy and security of data, and protects them according to the law," the Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning told a press conference.
According to Mao, "China has never demanded or requires companies or individuals who collect or store data illegally."
The spokesman also expressed the hope that "the European party respects the principles of market economy and loyal competition, and offers a fair, equitable and non-discriminatory business environment to companies from all countries."
The Irish Data Protection Authority (DPC), which operates on behalf of the EU, announced on Thursday the opening of an inquiry into the alleged storage of personal data from European users on Chinese servers, in a possible violation of community legislation.
The social video sharing network, with 1.5 billion users around the world, is detained by the Chinese company bytedance and has been scrupable from various western governments, due to fears that users' data can be used by Beijing for spy or advertising purposes.
By early May, DPC had already applied a 530 million euros fine to the Tiktok application for not guaranteeing sufficient protection of data from European users, which were accessible from China, although stored outside the country.
During this inquiry, the company admitted that some of these data were not only accessible, but were even stored in China, but were, however, eliminated.
Tiktok has attributed the incident to a technical problem and guaranteed never to have received requests from the Chinese authorities, or to provide them with any data from European users. However, according to the DPC, the company was not able to present sufficient guarantees against the possible access of the Chinese authorities under the Chinese laws to combat terrorism and counter -espionage.
According to the Irish authority, the new investigation aims to determine whether Tiktok has fulfilled the obligations provided for in the General Data Protection Regulation (RGPD) in the context of data flows currently concerned.
The investigation takes place in Ireland, a country where Tiktok's European branch is based, as with most major technological companies.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:53:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipor helps Lusitano de Hong Kong Club to raise quality of Portuguese teaching</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/14/ipor-ajuda-club-lusitano-de-hong-kong-a-elevar-qualidade-do-ensino-do-portugues/</link><description>The Portuguese Language Courses offered by the Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong will be guided by the Portuguese Institute of the Oriente (IPOR), thanks to an agreement signed in Macao, the two institutions told Lusa.
The Lusitano Club of Hong Kong, with about 400 members, has been available Portuguese courses for about five years, but the initiative “is not official”, the president said to Lusa, the institution, Patrick Rozario, who now wants to bring more quality to the institution's offer.
In this sense, Club Lusitano and Ipor signed, on Thursday, in Macao, an agreement that, among other purposes, wants to reinforce collaboration in teaching and learning Portuguese. “In the future, the Portuguese classes we offer in the Club will be under the guidance and approval of IPOR. We will continue to do what we have done, but IPOR will help us with the material and program,” said the president of the largest institution in the Hong Kong Lusodescendant community, founded in 1866.
Rozario also expects in the future to make the courses available for non-member. For now, specifies, “members and friends” - including 'Visas Gold' - have resorted to the linguistic program. "It seems that we have more and more people interested in attending Portuguese classes," said the Lusodescendent, noting that, in the last "four, five years", they passed there between 30 and 40 students.
The 'Visas Gold', also known as Residency Authorization for Investment Activity (Ari), are an investment program in Portugal that allows foreigners to get residence in exchange for investment in the country and attracted several people from China, including from the Hong Kong Semi -autonomous region.
About this partnership will work, the director of IPOR explained to Lusa that the courses will be organized by IPOR - including teaching programs and methodology - and trainers guided by the institution. "When issuing a certificate of the learning of these courses, which are made at Club Lusitano, the seal of IPOR has been departed, and the seal of IPOR offers the quality," he said.
Still with regard to the protocol signed on Thursday, Patrícia Ribeiro spoke of the intention of “strengthening collaboration in the cultural area and holding events” in Hong Kong. "We are invited to participate in fairs or festivals (…) like the consulate [of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong] does not have a office [in Hong Kong], but only one person -and not every day -the Lusitano club will be a support to be able to develop these activities and promote Portuguese language and culture," he noticed.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 03:53:15</pubDate></item></channel></rss>