<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/27/filipinas-procura-dez-desaparecidos-no-naufragio-de-ferry-que-causou-18-mortos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Profits of China's main industrial companies return to growth in 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/27/lucros-das-principais-empresas-industriais-da-china-voltam-a-crescer-em-2025/</link><description>The profits of China's main industrial companies grew 0.6% in 2025, breaking three consecutive years of declines, according to official data released by the Asian country's National Statistics Office (GNE).

Os ganhos das companhias analisadas totalizaram 7,4 biliões de yuan ao longo do ano recém-terminado. By sectors, the manufacturing industry grew by 5%, the production and supply of electricity, heat, gas and water increased by 9.4% and the extractive industry fell by 26.2%.
In December, the profits of the main industrial companies rose 5.3%, year-on-year, allowing a boost to data for the year as a whole, which until the previous month had accumulated an increase of 0.1%.
GNE statistician, Yu Weining, attributed the rise to the “role of new growth engines” such as equipment manufacturing (+7.7%) and high-tech manufacturing industry (+13.3%), while traditional sectors “continued to optimize the profit structure”.
The analyst warned that changes in the external environment “continue to intensify” and highlighted that the industrial transformation of the Asian country “implies certain adjustment pains”, with some companies facing “difficulties in production and operations”. “In the next stage, it is necessary to continue to promote deep integration between technological innovation and industrial innovation, continuously optimize the industrial structure, accelerate the formation of new productive forces and promote a sustained improvement in the profitability of industrial companies,” said the analyst.
To prepare this statistics, the GNE only takes into account industrial companies with annual revenues exceeding 20 million yuan.


European companies try to reduce China's weight in supply chains

European companies are trying to reduce China's weight in global supply chains, given restrictions on the sale of essential raw materials, said a report from the European Union Chamber of Commerce in China yesterday.
The document warned of Beijing's “considerable influence” over global industrial chains, which “now depend to a large extent” on China's exports. “China’s willingness to use its dominance (…) to pressure its trading partners, for example through export restrictions, is generating increasing unease in other countries,” noted the report.
The main example cited by the Chamber are the restrictions that Beijing has imposed on the sale of rare earths – essential for the manufacture of 'chips' or automobiles and crucial for the Defense industry. “Brussels is now seriously considering how to reduce its dependence on China in crucial matters,” the report reads. And, although the strength of the Asian country's industrial clusters makes many international companies dependent "to remain competitive", geopolitical issues such as the trade war with the USA made them "open their eyes" to "the dangers of depending on a single country", especially in the case of China.
But the President of the Chamber of Commerce in Shanghai, Carlo D’Andrea, acknowledged that, “in the short term, the alternative to China is China, although (…) other countries are approaching”, such as Vietnam in the textile sector or Indonesia in the manufacturing industry, in addition to Malaysia’s investment in semiconductor production. Companies are “giving greater priority to resistance and flexibility than to costs and efficiency”, explained the organization.
This is not the only point of friction between Beijing and Brussels: in the face of the aforementioned tariff war and the weakness of domestic demand, China increased its exports to the EU at an accelerated pace, but did not solve the problems of European companies doing business in the Asian country.
According to the business group, Beijing “knew it could count on the EU as a stable, albeit dissatisfied, trading partner”, but the issues mentioned could now lead Brussels to “adopt a more offensive strategy for its policy towards China”. "For many years, we thought that China would change, but now we realize that it won't change. It has too good a deal. (…) Europe has started to realize that if it doesn't change its strategy towards China, China won't change", explained D'Andrea.
In this way, Beijing's ability to control supply chains “may diminish over time as other countries' self-sufficiency initiatives mature.” “Little by little, China is becoming a simple piece of a global puzzle, perhaps with too many inherent risks to maintain its dominance indefinitely”, warned the report, which points out that, if Beijing maintains its course on trade policy, “the current climate of global uncertainty is here to stay in the long term”.
But European companies currently operating in China “will remain there for as long as possible” to take advantage of the innovation environment and “unparalleled production capacity”. “But both its willingness and its ability to place China at the center of its global supply chains could be undermined, depending on whether China decides to continue using its current dominance as a tool of pressure and how it does so,” the group pointed out.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 23:59:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul promises to fulfill agreement with US after Trump announces rate hike</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/27/seul-promete-cumprir-acordo-com-eua-apos-trump-anunciar-subida-de-taxas/</link><description>Seoul declared yesterday that it will communicate to Washington its intention to comply with the November trade agreement, after Donald Trump announced more tariffs on South Korean vehicles and other sectors due to delays in implementing the pact.

“Given that the increase in tariffs only comes into force after administrative procedures, such as its publication in the Federal Register, the South Korean Government plans to convey to the North American side its desire to comply with the tariff agreement, while at the same time responding calmly and gradually,” the presidential office said in a statement.
The statement came after the President of the United States, Donald Trump, announced on the social network he owns, Truth Social, that he will increase tariffs on “automobiles, wood, pharmaceutical products and all other products subject to reciprocal tariffs” from 15% to 25%, without indicating the date of implementation of the measure.
The Ministry of Economy and Finance indicated, in a message to the local press, that it is evaluating Trump's “intentions” to increase tariffs on South Korea again.
Although the South Korean presidency previously indicated that it has not received official notification from the US Government about the measure published by Trump, the ministry said it will contact Washington to report on the status of discussions in parliament and request parliamentary cooperation in processing the bill.
The document, presented to parliament in November, aims to support South Korea's investment commitment of 350 billion dollars (294 billion euros) in the United States, part of the agreement that set a basic tariff of 15% for these sectors.
The next session to review bills in the South Korean parliament takes place next Tuesday.
The South Korean Ministry of Commerce also indicated that it is closely monitoring the situation, according to the local news agency Yonhap, while the person responsible for the negotiations plans to travel soon to the USA, to discuss the matter with the North American trade representative Jamieson Greer.
Previously, the presidential office reported that Industry, Trade and Energy Minister Kim Jung-kwan, currently in Canada, plans to travel to the United States to discuss the matter with US Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick.
Some observers indicate that Trump's measure may be aimed at speeding up the approval of the project, before the imminent decision by the US Supreme Court on the legality of the US Administration's reciprocal tariffs.
Three and a half hours after the opening of the South Korean stock exchange, major car manufacturers Hyundai Motor and Kia registered declines, along with important biopharmaceutical companies such as Samsung Biologics and Celltrion, in an apparent reaction to Trump's announcement. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 23:57:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste records two deaths due to dengue since the beginning of the year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/27/timor-leste-regista-dois-mortos-devido-a-dengue-desde-o-inicio-do-ano/</link><description>Since the beginning of the year, Timor-Leste has recorded 850 cases of dengue, which caused two fatalities, said yesterday the head of the Department of Health Promotion and Education, Miliza Vital. “Since the beginning of January, we have registered a total of 850 cases of dengue fever and two children have died, according to data from the Epidemiological Surveillance Department of the Ministry of Health,” Miliza Vital told Lusa. D
íli recorded the highest number of dengue cases, with a total of 547, followed by Ermera, with 124, and Liquiçá, with 67. Asked about the reasons for the high number of cases, Miliza Vital explained that it is due to the fact that the community itself does not clean the surrounding environment. “The rainy season always causes water to accumulate and, when there is no cleaning or elimination of breeding sites, mosquitoes develop in these places, transform into adult mosquitoes and end up biting people, causing dengue infections”, explained the person in charge.
Miliza Vital also stated that the Ministry of Health is working together with the municipality of Díli, with the support of universities, various associations and the church, to raise awareness in communities about prevention. “It is necessary to educate and raise awareness among communities to recognize the problem of dengue and so that they know how to adopt prevention measures, such as covering, eliminating and turning over containers that accumulate water”, said Miliza Vital.
Health teams are also making door-to-door visits in the neighborhoods of the Timorese capital, which record the highest number of cases.
The Ministry of Health is also implementing the Wolbachia method, a strategy that involves the controlled release of mosquitoes with that bacteria, which reduces the ability to transmit the dengue virus to humans.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 23:58:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping reaffirms support for the UN in meeting with Finnish prime minister</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/27/xi-jinping-reafirma-apoio-a-onu-em-encontro-com-primeiro-ministro-finlandes/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping reaffirmed his support for the UN yesterday, declaring that he hopes that Beijing and Helsinki can work together for a world order based on that body, during a meeting with Finnish Prime Minister Petteri Orpo.

“China is willing to work with Finland to firmly support the international system of which the United Nations is the pillar,” said Xi, a statement that comes as US President Donald Trump seeks to create a new multilateral international institution that he himself has designated as the “Peace Council.”
Xi Jinping recebeu ontem, no Grande Palácio do Povo, Petteri Orpo, que iniciou uma visita oficial de quatro dias à China. Although China has been invited by the United States to participate in this “Peace Council”, which aims to work on resolving conflicts in the world and is widely seen as a competitor to the UN, Beijing has so far avoided saying whether or not it will accept the invitation.
Xi Jinping had also appealed to Brazil last week to defend, together with China, “the central role” of the United Nations in the international system, during an interview with his Brazilian counterpart, Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva.
Orpo highlighted the interest in talking to Xi Jinping about “international issues” and matters related to “bilateral cooperation”. The two countries remain divided on sensitive issues, such as the Russian invasion of Ukraine and the struggle of great powers' interests in the Arctic region.
Finnish Defense Minister Antti Hakkanen accused China in November of “massively financing Russia’s war effort” in Ukraine. On the other hand, a month earlier, Trump announced a project to build 11 icebreaker ships with Finland, during a visit by Finnish counterpart Alexander Stubb to the White House, in a sign of the strengthening of the North American presence in the Arctic, where it disputes its influence with Russia and China.
The Chinese leader is also preparing to meet with British Prime Minister Keir Starmer, who began a trip to China and Japan on Monday, according to Downing Street.
China highlighted the need to strengthen “political trust” and deepen cooperation with the United Kingdom, ahead of the official visit of the British Prime Minister. Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said at a press conference that Beijing is willing to take advantage of the trip to “improve political mutual trust”, deepen practical cooperation and “open a new chapter” in the “healthy and stable” development of bilateral relations.
Guo recalled that Chinese President Xi Jinping had a telephone conversation with Starmer in August 2024 and met with him in November during the G20 summit in Rio de Janeiro, contacts that “put bilateral relations on the path to improvement”. The visit to China, the first by a British head of government in eight years, takes place between Wednesday and Saturday.
The Chinese diplomatic spokesman stressed that China and the United Kingdom, as permanent members of the UN Security Council, have common interests in maintaining communication and strengthening cooperation in an international scenario marked by instability.
During the visit, Starmer will be received by Xi and will hold meetings with Chinese Premier Li Qiang and the chairman of the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress, Zhao Leji. In addition to Beijing, the British leader will travel to Shanghai. According to Guo, both sides will address bilateral relations and issues of common interest.
The spokesperson also highlighted that the current British Labor government has expressed its desire to develop a “coherent, lasting and strategic” relationship with China and to promote dialogue and cooperation between the two countries.
Asked about information regarding a possible tightening of British scrutiny over Chinese activities in the United Kingdom, Guo limited himself to reiterating that strengthening exchanges, increasing mutual trust and deepening cooperation “responds to the interests of both countries and the world”.
Starmer's visit comes at a time of readjustment of British foreign policy towards China, after years of distancing under conservative governments, with London seeking to relaunch economic ties with Beijing, a strategy that coincides with the cooling of its relations with Washington after Donald Trump came to power.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 23:59:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines searches for missing people in ferry sinking that killed 18 people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/27/filipinas-procura-dez-desaparecidos-no-naufragio-de-ferry-que-causou-18-mortos/</link><description>Ten people remained missing yesterday following the sinking of a ferry traveling towards the island of Jolo, in the south of the Philippines, with 344 people on board, of which at least 18 died.
Search and rescue operations remain ongoing following the sinking of the MV Trisha Kerstin, said Philippine Coast Guard (PCG) spokeswoman Noemie Cayabyab in an interview given yesterday on radio station DWIZ 882, broadcast by the maritime authority on the social network Facebook.
The sinking occurred on Monday at around 1:50 a.m. near the northeast of Baluk-Baluk island in the island province of Basilan on the southwest coast of Mindanao island, according to authorities.
The vessel departed the port of Zamboanga City at around 9:20 pm on Sunday and was heading to Jolo island in the Sulu archipelago, the PCG's Southwest Mindanao division explained.
Cayabyab clarified yesterday that the number of passengers on board totaled 344 and not 359 as initially announced, as 15 people did not board. “316 survived, 18 died and ten are still being sought by the joint search and rescue team, made up of several government agencies and private vessels”, said the spokeswoman.
Basilan authorities released a list of the people on board the vessel identified so far, all of whom are Filipino nationals.
According to the register, at least 216 adults, 63 students and six minors were traveling on the ferry. Among the dead is a six-month-old baby.
Maritime accidents in the Philippines cause dozens of deaths every year, the majority in shipwrecks caused by bad weather, non-compliance with safety standards, poor equipment maintenance or overloading. The most serious accident in the recent history of commercial shipping occurred in the Philippines in 1987, when the vessel Doña Paz sank in the waters of Leyte after colliding with an oil tanker, causing the deaths of 4,341 people.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 23:57:48</pubDate></item></channel></rss>