<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/mais-de-1-800-detencoes-em-operacao-anti-burla-na-asia-que-incluiu-macau/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Government reviews low game recipes for this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/governo-reve-em-baixa-receitas-de-jogo-para-este-ano/</link><description>The proposal of change to this year's budget presented yesterday by the Executive Board provides for a reduction in revenue and an increase in expenses. The government provides that the game's gross revenues are 228 billion patacas, instead of the 240 billion that were enrolled in the first budget presented at the end of last year.
 
The Executive Board presented yesterday a proposal to change the budget to 2025 that reviews the forecast of game revenues for this year. The government now predicts that the gross casinos revenues are in the 228 billion Patacas, instead of the 240 billion that were registered in the budget presented in December last year by the government led by Ho IAT SENG.
The executive justified this overhaul with the performance of the game industry below expectations in the first five months of the year. Between January and May, the casinos invoiced 97.7 billion of patacas.
This new forecast of game revenues implies that casinos make monthly 19 billion patacas on average. So far, the average has been around this value, and May has exceeded 21 billion. It is recalled that tax revenues from the game industry represent more than 80% of all of the MSAR tax revenues.
At the budget review press conference, Daisy Ho in Mis, a subdirector of the Finance Services Directorate (DSF), said that the government adjusted the figure of revenue after several factors were analyzed, such as the “uncertainty of the global economy” and the “change of visitors consumption habits”. Recently, both the head of the executive and the secretary for the Economics and Finance of the MSAR have warned of the possibility that economic indices fall short of the expected.
 
Revenues shrink, expenses grow
 
The total amount of revenues registered in this new budget is 116.5 billion Patacas, while the previous budget referred to revenues of 121 billion.
This budget review also provides for an increase in expenses throughout this year. Previously, the expenses registered had 113 billion patacas and now they are 116.2 billion. This increase is due to the construction of the University of Macao campus in Hengqin and the investment in research and scientific and technological development, explained the government. The new UM HENGQIN campus will cost 1.75 billion to MSAR coffers throughout this year. The six -year project has a global budget of 8.4 billion.
With the new amounts of revenues and expenses, the budget balance shrinks significantly from 7.7 billion to about 300 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:35:20</pubDate></item><item><title>China industrial activity retreats to the lowest level since September 2022</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/actividade-industrial-da-china-recua-para-nivel-mais-baixo-desde-setembro-de-2022/</link><description>China's transforming industry activity has fallen in May to the lowest level since September 2022. Data expose the impact of the trade war began by US President Donald Trump.
 
China's transforming industry activity has fallen in May to the lowest level since September 2022, according to the Purchasing Managers Index (PMI) released yesterday by the Caixin newspaper. The data expose the impact of the trade war began by the president of the United States, Donald Trump.
This indicator, prepared by the Standard &amp; Poor's (S&amp;P) Financial Notation Agency (S&amp;P) and used by many international investors as a reference to analyze the transforming sector of China, fell from 50.4 points from April to 48.3 in May - the first contraction recorded in eight months.
A value above the 50 points threshold indicates activity growth compared to the previous month; Below this value, it signals contraction.
The result also below all estimates of analysts inquired by Bloomberg agency, which provided, on average, an expansion of 50.7 points.
The data was even weaker than the official reading of the PMI, released on Saturday, which pointed to a contraction of the transforming industry, although at a slower pace, after the postponement of new tariffs have partially unlocked commercial flows.
“The offer and demand of the transforming industry have decreased by external demand,” wrote Wang Zhe, a CAIXIN INSIGHT GROUP economist, the newspaper -affiliated investigation unit in a statement. "The main macroeconomic indicators showed a marked weakening at the beginning of the second quarter," he added.
The inquiry, more oriented to private and exporters, reveals a process of adjustment by Chinese manufacturers, after China and the US have agreed a 90 -day truce in the ongoing trade war.
The drop in new orders was accompanied by a decline in industrial production, according to the report. Companies reduced purchasing activity and staff levels, although the feeling about future production has shown signs of recovery.
The caxin economist also warned of the fact that China's main macroeconomic indicators were revealing a negative trend since the beginning of the second trimester: “the downward pressure on the economy has increased significantly from previous periods.”
China now faces not only contrary winds of an internal nature, but also a “growing uncertainty” in global trade, Wang stressed.
Internally, the country remains under the weight of deflationary risks, aggravated by a profound crisis in the real estate sector, which has affected both investment and consumption.
In this context, Wang recommended the adoption of additional measures to stimulate internal demand, namely through the increase in the available income of families. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:35:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Synergy power formalizes candidacy for legislative elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/poder-da-sinergia-formaliza-candidatura-as-eleicoes-legislativas/</link><description>The power of synergy returns to this year's legislative election race. The group, represented by the current deputy Ron Lam, collected about 400 signatures and presented yesterday to the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), the request for recognition of the constitution of the application committee.
Ron Lam, vice president of the Synergy Association, indicated that the team decided to re-apply for elections for expecting to continue to be the most effective communication bridge between the government and society, reflecting public opinions in the Legislative Assembly and helping to promote governance work.
To journalists, the deputy admitted to noticing “deep changes” in the social environment in recent years. "There is a failure in terms that the government hear the opinion of citizens, which leads to policies not to match the real needs of the population and meet the needs of social development," he said.
"We have to respond to the requests of residents. We cannot do what we want, we must do what citizens want us to do," he said. Ron Lam said he was aware of the problem of access to employment in Macao, namely from young professionals. According to the official, the least positive prospects for employment are still affecting the desire for local consumption, a problem that the government should make more efforts to solve.
Regarding the application list, Ron Lam said the team does not yet have a final decision and needs more time to study the subject, so he doesn't know if he will be a list of list again.
Ron Lam admitted yesterday that his performance in the Legislative Assembly "fell short of expectations" and apologized to voters, but said he tried to "do the best." The deputy added that in the future, the team will maintain the same attitude and “persist in order” to serve Macau.
It is recalled that the period of constitution of this year's Legislative Application Commission will end on Friday. In addition to the power of synergy, and the New Hope, represented by José Pereira Coutinho, more groups yesterday handed over to Caeal the subscription signatures, including the Promoter Union for Progress, linked to the General Union of Macao Residents' associations; The Good Home Alliance, linked to the General Association of Women; and Macau Creating People’s Heart Force.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:35:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Alexander Lukashenko arrives in China for a two -day visit</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/alexander-lukashenko-chega-a-china-para-uma-visita-de-dois-dias/</link><description>Belarus President Alexander Lukashenko, yesterday arrived in China for a two-day surprise visit, during which he should meet with his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping. President Belarusso is already in the Chinese capital, where he will remain until Wednesday, the news agency Bielarrussa Belta said. The visit was not announced in advance by the authorities.
Quoted by Belta, the Belarus Ambassador in China, Aleksandr Chervyakov, said some of the main issues to be discussed during Lukashenko's visit are “the modernization of the Belarusian economy, based on Chinese technology”, and “bilateral cooperation in mechanical engineering, carperia, chemical industry and other sectors”.
The trip is also an opportunity to “evaluate and review the provisional results of cooperation work” between Minsk and Beijing, the diplomat said. "China remains a key strategic partner for us, as it has always been," he added.
Lukashenko visited China in February 2023, when he stated that “expanding contacts with China is a priority of Belarus foreign policy” and criticized, along with his Chinese counterpart, sanctions against Moscow by the invasion of Ukraine.
In December of the same year, President Belarussian again moved to China, a sign of the good relations that Beijing and Minsk currently maintain.
Increasingly isolated from Europe and the rest of the West due to its authoritarian drift and its policies regarding immigrants, Lukashenko's government has recently turned to allies like Beijing and Moscow.
His visit also has as its backdrop the negotiations between Russia and Ukraine for a ceasefire in a war where Minsk has been accused by Kiev of being a Moscow's accomplice, and for which Beijing has kept an ambiguous position.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:35:45</pubDate></item><item><title>China accuses USA of breaking agreement with “extreme suppression” measures</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/china-acusa-eua-de-quebrar-acordo-com-medidas-de-supressao-extrema/</link><description>Chinese authorities accused Washington of violating a deal to temporarily reduce customs rates with “extreme suppression” measures such as restricting semiconductor exports and nullifying visas to Chinese students.
 
Beijing accused Washington yesterday of violating an agreement reached in May to temporarily reduce customs rates with “extreme suppression” measures, such as restricting semiconductor exports and nullifying visas to Chinese students. "Geneva's consensus was achieved based on mutual respect and consultation equality. China has implemented it responsibly and in good faith. However, the US implemented unilateral and unfounded restrictions," said Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Lin Jian.
China, who said he had presented a formal protest, urged Washington to "correct his wrong actions" and "respect the harsh consensus." "The use of pressure and coercion is not the correct way to deal with China," said Lin.
Beijing said on Monday, through his Ministry of Commerce, that since the commercial pact was sealed on May 12, Washington has adopted new measures that "seriously undermine" the commitments made, including the suspension of sales of software used in the manufacturer of semiconductors, new controls of chips used in artificial intelligence systems and the recent revocation of visas for Chinese students, a measure that China described as "discriminatory."
The two powers had agreed a three -month tariff truce, with the US reducing their rates from 145% to 30% and China from 125% to 10% in an attempt to open the door to a wider deal.
However, tensions have increased in recent days, with new restrictions imposed by Washington and a fall of about 20% in US imports of Chinese products in April.
Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent acknowledged last week that negotiations are stopped and said that a call between Trump and his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, could break the impasse.
White House Economic Counselor Kevin Hassett said on Sunday that there is still no scheduled conversation between the two leaders, although they expect them to talk about trade next week. Beijing, however, answered yesterday that he has no "any information" about a possible call.
The growing commercial frictions come to join an atmosphere of political and strategic distrust, also reflected in the recent changes of impressions at the Shangri-LA security forum in Singapore, where the head of the Pentagon accused China of wanting to disturb balance in Asia. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:36:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho lowers the bar and admits only to elect a deputy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/coutinho-baixa-a-fasquia-e-admite-so-eleger-um-deputado/</link><description>José Pereira Coutinho formalized yesterday the candidacy of the “New Hope” list to the Legislative Elections of MSAR, which will take place on September 14. Without revealing whether it will be Rita Santos or herself to head the list, Coutinho said it will not be easy to elect two deputies.
 
Pereira Coutinho presented yesterday to the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) the Committee on the application of the electoral act of September 14 by the list "Nova Esperança", which had 500 signatures - the minimum limit was 300.
In the formalization of the candidacy for the next elections, Coutinho told reporters that it would not be easy for the list to be able to elect two terms, as happened in 2021 with the election of the president of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) and Che Sai Wang.
"It's hard [to elect a second candidate] because there will be more lists and the lists are strong; traditional lists have a very important weight because they have a great financial capacity," he said, adding that "the goal is to have a voice in the Legislative Assembly, that would be a very satisfactory result."
Rita Santos will be part of the list, but Coutinho still did not want to announce which of the two will be the head of theist. "We are still ultimately the chain of the list," he said.  It is recalled that the ATFPM announced in August last year that Rita Santos would be part of the lists, not indicating what position. In October, Rita Santos suspended her mandate as a counselor of the Portuguese communities, under the justification that she was already preparing the legislative elections.
Coutinho also complained of “unfair competition” by the other lists in the process of raising signatures for the constitution of the application committee. According to the president of the ATFPM, some elderly will have been error in error by other associations when they intended to renew Macau Pass to benefit from the consumption stimulus plan, inadvertently signing the other lists application committee. "Many of our friends and associates, for ignorance and thinking they were signing a document for formalities to change the cards, signed other lists. Those who four years signed our list had already signed by another list," he lamented.
"These elections must be cleaner, more full, and that there is not so much comezain, gifts and carriages to take people to vote," he said, instituting the authorities to be aware of these situations.
These will be the first legislative elections after the revision of the electoral law to the Legislative Assembly, which provides for the removal of candidates considered by the authorities as insufficiently “patriotic”, without the right to appeal. Asked if he fears that any element of his list will be disqualified by the State Security Defense Commission, Coutinho stated that "the fact that he is critical does not mean that he is not patriot."</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:32:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao is lacking hotel rooms and solution will have to pass hengqin, says Francis Lui</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/macau-tem-falta-de-quartos-de-hotel-e-solucao-tera-de-passar-por-hengqin-diz-francis-lui/</link><description>Francis Lui, president of Galaxy Entertainment Group, warned that Macau lacks hotel rooms, which can prevent the region's economic growth. Game operator CEO says the solution to the problem will have to go through hengqin.
 
Macao is lacking hotel rooms and Hengqin could be the solution, Francis Lui defended. Galaxy Entertainment Group's president and CEO said at a press conference with Hong Kong journalists that new political measures are needed to facilitate the development of mountain island to solve the problem.
“As Macau changes to a more model -oriented model and event, the issue of hotel rooms should be resolved,” said Francis Lui, quoted by the South China Morning Post newspaper. For the Galaxy head, the increase in the number of visitors and the growing search for hotel establishments makes it “urgent” to solve this situation.
It is recalled that, according to data from the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), there are currently about 48,000 hotel rooms in Macao. Last year, the region received a total of almost 35 million visitors. According to the Galaxy official, Macau needs at least 15,000 hotel rooms, especially hotel units below $ 1,000 in Hong Kong per night.
Lui suggested that improving hengqin development promotion measures would cause hotel capacity to increase and, consequently, help to achieve the objective of economic diversification of the region. Hengqin medium price hotels would allow visitors to stay overnight, but Macau came to conventions, concerts and games, proposed.
The official suggested facilitating the passage of the border several times to visitors, as well as reducing the time needed to pass the border using technologies such as facial recognition. These measures would also allow Hengqin authorities to take advantage of Macau's 35 million visitors to boost their economy, Francis Lui added.
Lui also pointed to the group's efforts on diversifying his business and betting on non-game elements, such as entertainment, hotel and conventions, giving the concerts of South Korean singer G-Dragon, who acts on the Galaxy Arena on June 6 and 8, as well as Jacky Cheung, between June 20 and July 5.
Francis Lui is also president of the Real Estate Promoter K. Wah International, listed on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, and, at the press conference, said that, in this sector, the activity in the neighboring region has improved since last year, anticipating that the situation is even better "as the city consolidates its position as an international commercial and financial center."</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:33:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Movie “Metamorphosis” today presents the resilience of Portuguese rural communities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/filme-metamorphosis-apresenta-hoje-a-resiliencia-das-comunidades-rurais-portuguesas/</link><description>António Luís Moreira's documentary “Metamorphosis” will be presented today at the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery at 18:30, under the “June, Portugal month” program. This event marks the first time the film is screened in Macau, after opening in Portugal in July last year.
The project focuses on the history of three women living in three villages of the Board of Góis schist-Aigra Velha, Aigra Nova and Comareira-and a man who fights for the recovery of cultural traditions in Portuguese rural areas, growingly unpopulated. Over the course of 79 minutes, the film weaves a reflection on topics such as identity, social changes and the ephemerality and fragility of human life.
“Focusing on the deconstruction of conventional social norms, metamorphysis highlights how personal and collective identities evolve in the midst of changeable realities; it offers a convincing analysis of rural life, memory and tensions between tradition and modernity,” Rui Cunha Foundation describes in a statement.
Parallel to the feature film documentary, the project also includes a homonymous book by photographer Carmen Serejo, with a preface signed by the poet Jorge Velhote.
In less than a year, the film participated in several Portuguese and international competitions and was even a winner at the Luleå International Festival Festival of Sweden, Filmnzen International Competition of Chicago, the Best Hollywood Day Short Film Festival 2025 and Portugal Indie Film Festival of Cascais.
António Luís Moreira was born and grew up in Lisbon, where he studied-cultivated painting at the Lisbon School of Fine Arts and Engineering at the University of Lisbon Institute (IST). Despite having done several video works, including 3D animations, “Metamorphosis” is his first documentary film work of feature film.
Today's session at the Rui Cunha Foundation will make available subtitles in English. Admission is free, although it is subject to available places.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Exhibition “The Slazing and Curious Travel” inaugurates tomorrow at CCCM and explores connections between Europe and Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/exposicao-as-espantosas-e-curiosas-viagens-inaugura-amanha-no-cccm-e-explora-ligacoes-entre-a-europa-e-macau/</link><description>The pair of artists, Cheong Kin Man and Marta Sala, revisits the family migratory stories, Macao and Poland, and joins Deborah Uhde to explore, in the exhibition “The Slazing and Curious Travel”, the different transfronist exodos and the links between Europe and Macau.
“Celebrate differences and use Macau as a symbol of this opening,” says Cheong Kin Man, in a summary way. Partners in life and work, Macao's artist from Poland based on Berlin based on his personal, family and professional universe, combining it with Deborah Uhde, Germany, to explore, through art and visual anthropology, historical and cultural exchanges between masters and Europe. Titled “The Slazing and Curious Travel” - The Title of German Translation, in 1671, of Fernão Mendes Pinto's book “Pilgrimage” - The Exhibition, with the curated by Lorena Tabares Salamanca, opens the doors tomorrow, at 5 pm, at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in Lisbon, and the final point unveils some of what you can see there.
The trip begins with a well -known work by Cheong Kin Man, but now redesigned by the artist in collaboration with Marta Sala. In 2008, as part of his degree in Portuguese Studies at the University of Macau, the artist completed a project on the Macanese diaspora, which resulted in the documentary “or Mun Ian, Macaenses - 35 interviewees, 35 identities”. “Here, in this exhibition, we have gathered some of these interviews and fear them in languages ​​such as Arabic, Tibetan and Ukrainian dialect,” he reveals, explaining that the work in CCCM has two layers. "On the one hand, we have the Macanese to speak, especially in Portuguese, but also in Cantonese, about Exodus; on the other, these interviews are subtitled to different languages ​​and are automatic translations," explains the artist.
For Cheong Kin Man, subtitling, using artificial intelligence, also reflects a point that is important for him. "It's important to see how some languages ​​continue not to be available through this technology, as translations have many mistakes," he says, explaining: "Tibetan letters are wrong or, in the Arabic, for example, should not have score and have." Accompanying these interviews are still two books, which contain the automatic translation of the content of the interviews to Polish. “For example, in automatic translation, if you are a woman who is talking, AI will change to men,” says Marta Sala.
 
Deborah Uhde and family connection to China
 
How did Deborah Uhde join Cheong Kin Man and Marta Room in this work? “Last year we visited different places in Portugal and the idea of ​​joining an exhibition came up,” he reveals. One of his pieces here dates back to an artist book, he produced last year, but which is arranged here differently. He was broken in different postcards, created using artificial intelligence, based on a true letter sent by his grandfather, when he moved to China [Tsingtao] in 1904. “A postcard wrote to his parents, who were in Germany,” he recalls. Later, when Deborah's sister studied in China, her grandfather handed her this postcard. “It's part of the family archive, I only took some short excerpts,” he says.
However, the artist also prepared another work, inspired by a replica of Globe Dias Longobardi, 1623, a play by Jesuit priests Manuel Dias Júnior and Nicoló Longobardi, who signed him with the Chinese version of their names, on display at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center Museum. “I made 3D impressions on this object and created a new version - they are all 3D models frames, often using a four -color system to reproduce all colors and pass the idea of ​​movement to the globe,” he explains.
In this exhibition, the artist brings the works “Blind Blind Points Slices”, “Atlas of Mental Juggling”, “Chromosferes” and “Corpoteca”.
 
“Revelation”, an installation for the Macau Biennial
 
One of the highlights in this exhibition is the installation “Apocalypses”, a work with several textile pieces conducted at the invitation of the Macao International Art Biennial two years ago. "The work exposes the story of the migration of the Poland's Marta family," says Cheong Kin Man. "My great -grandmother, who was Russian, left with my polaco great -grandfather, who had left Vilnius, and was working at Transiberian. They ended up settling in Bogotol, Czarist Russia," says Marta.
It is this same story that is evident in "Revelation". “I put here the clothes of my family members who have died,” says Marta. "Here is part of a dress, which belonged to my grandmother, his mother [great -grandmother] was a seamstress," he adds. Among the various textile pieces that are there, there is still a "T-shirt of his father, born in Poland, near Krakow, whose parents were from another city and they had also changed."
The remaining pieces are part of the artist's collection, which transports from different sites or cities where he has passed, whether Krakow, Katowice or Berlin. A work -laden work, which also includes a kind of fictional language, used in a parallel universe, based on a work that the couple is preparing with over 700 pages, with fictitious ideograms. “There is a story, a tension between AI and humans,” says Cheong Kin Man.
 
When reality and fantasy come together
 
The authorship of Cheong Kin Man and Marta Sala, one of the works, entitled “The Utopia compass”, is a textile installation that includes 12 pieces arranged in a circle, as if it was a compass, and joined by bamboo structures. With the colors used to evoke a poem by a poet from Macao, Sin Iok Cheong, this work uses mixed techniques and includes various details. “An important piece is the one that has a Chinese soldier and my father, dressed as a casino employee together, with a red line separating them,” says Cheong Kin Man, explaining that it is an allusion to his father's true story. “In 1979, my father and another group of people came to Macao de Zhongshan,” he recalls. The father was eventually able to reach the territory, the swim, after being hidden in the mountains, although he was almost intercepted by border guards.
Already in the territory, the father ended up working in the art of ivory and, in the 1980s, when this craft became forbidden, became an employee of a casino. “And he met your mother in an ivory studio,” adds Marta, who points to one of the 12 works, where there is an image of her.
Among the various works that are there, in “The Utopia Compass”, there are several references to Michael Boym's book, “Flora Sinensis”. In fact, when looking at this piece, literary and artistic evocations are mixed with reality. “Here we have a katowice tree and building, where I was born, my grandfather was a carpenter,” says Marta. In the works that the couple of artists brings to CCCM, art mixes with the former social housing buildings of Fai Chi Kei, historical references to the Democratic Poland, elements of Chinese pop culture or images of wars that happen in different parts of the world.
The exhibition “The Slazing and Curious Travel” is sponsored by the Colombia and Poland embassies in Lisbon, as well as support from the Ministry of National Culture and Heritage and the Adam Mickiewicz Institute of Poland, Orient Foundation, Goethe-Institute Portugal and Poland Institute of Poland.
The exhibition has the same name as the Cheong Kin Man and Marta Sala show that took place in 2024 at Kunstraum (Gallery) of the Confucius Institute of Nuremberg and was sponsored by the Oriente Foundation.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Two Japanese citizens murdered in northeast China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/dois-cidadaos-japoneses-assassinados-no-nordeste-da-china/</link><description>Two Japanese citizens were killed in Dalian, northeast of China, in another fatal attack against Japanese in Chinese territory, the newspaper Nikkei Asia yesterday reported. According to the Japanese newspaper, which cites sources from the Japan embassy in Beijing, police already detained a suspect in Chinese nationality. The two victims were male.
The Japan Consulate-General in the neighboring city of Shenyang was informed by the Chinese authorities on May 25 that the two citizens had been murdered, and a commercial dispute was pointed out as a motivation of the crime.
The incident follows the fatal stabbing of a 10-year-old Japanese student in Shenzhen, Southeast China in September, and a knife attack last year in a Japanese school stop in Suzhou, east China, where a Chinese woman was killed and a Japanese mother and child were injured. Two Chinese citizens condemned by fatal stabbing in Shenzhen and Suzhou were executed earlier this year.
These cases raised concerns about increasing feeling against Japan in the neighboring country. Tokyo asked Beijing to guarantee the safety of his citizens in China.
The death of the Japanese boy in Shenzhen coincided with the day the “Incident of Mukden” or “918 incident” was celebrated, a historical event that marked the beginning of the Japanese invasion of China in 1931, a particularly sensitive date in relations between the two countries.
September 18 is known as 'Humiliation Day' in the Popular Republic of China. Relations between the two countries have deteriorated in recent years as China has become more assertive in territorial disputes in the region and Japan has reinforced security ties with the United States and its allies.
A Japanese government source said, however, that the Dalian murders were motivated by "a business-related grudge" and that "they had no political motivations, nor were they triggered by anti-Japan sentiment."</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:36:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Big Health industry will be “motor for future economic growth,” says Tai Kin IP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/industria-de-big-health-sera-motor-para-o-crescimento-economico-futuro-diz-tai-kin-ip/</link><description>Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, participated in the opening ceremony of the International Big Health Forum of the “One Rota” initiative, which took place yesterday at Wynn Palace. The ruler gave a speech at the time to underline the importance of this industry in the context of government efforts to diversify the region's economy.
The secretary began by remembering the words of Xi Jinping when his visit to Macao in December last year, when he asked the region to take advantage of its unique advantages as a bridge between China and Lusophone countries, as well as countries throughout the initiative ‘a track, a route ',' 'injecting new dynamism into technological innovation and industrial development'.
Thus, according to Tai Kin IP, "Big Health industry is a focus of world care and a new engine for future economic growth." This is “one of the priority industries to promote proper economy diversification” and the government will “reinforce the capacity for technological health innovation and expand international cooperation”, said the secretary, highlighting the forum inaugurated yesterday as “an important attempt in the“ One Rota ”initiative, centered on technological innovation and cooperative development in the Big Health industry”.
Tai Kin IP said that in recent years, "Macau has established a solid base in areas such as traditional Chinese medicine and health sciences, with high -level scientific research results to continually emerge, having gradually formed an innovative ecosystem with its own characteristics of Macao." The ruler highlighted the joint creation of the Sino-Portuguese Conjunto Laboratory in Artificial Intelligence and Public Health Technologies in the initiative ‘A Range, a Route’ as "a significant milestone" in this context, demonstrating "the crucial role of Macao in international scientific cooperation."
The promotion of industrial diversification, reiterated Tai Kin IP, is "a key element for the sustainable development of Macau's economy." “In the future, Macau will maintain an open attitude, closely collaborating with partners from various sectors and fully valuing their linguistic, cultural and geographical advantages to jointly boost innovation in health technologies, with a view to consolidating the bases for the development of the 'Big Health' industry,” promised the "Big Health 'industry." and sustainability ”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:36:18</pubDate></item><item><title>China announces that it will continue to extend exemption policy of visas to more countries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/china-anuncia-que-vai-continuar-a-alargar-politica-de-isencao-de-vistos-a-mais-paises/</link><description>China said yesterday that it will continue to extend its visa exemption policy to more countries, highlighting the recent inclusion for the first time from Latin American countries, including Brazil. "We will continue to optimize our entry policies, widen the number of visited countries, and to invite more international friends to try China's quality consumer products, services and consumer offers," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said at a press conference.
Since June 1, citizens of Brazil, Argentina, Chile, Peru and Uruguay can enter China without visa up to 30 days, as part of a pilot initiative announced during the last Latin American and Caribbean Community (Celac) community.
With the entry into force, on June 9, of the exemption of visa to the citizens of Saudi Arabia, Oman, Kuwait and Barém, the number of countries with access to China with visa exemption will increase to 43. Policy has also encompassed Portugal since last year.
This expansion reflects Beijing's commitment to a “high -level opening” and the construction of an “open world economy,” said Lin.
The spokesman stressed that entry facilitation measures “are already producing concrete results”: in the first quarter of 2025, more than nine million foreigners entered China, an increase of more than 40%, compared to the same period last year.
In addition, more than 18,000 new companies with foreign investment were created in China between January and April, a homologous increase of 12.1%, according to official data cited by Lin.
Beijing believes these policies will help boost tourism, reinforce ties with partner countries, and project a modern and accessible image of China after years of border restrictions due to Covid-19 pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:35:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao and Portugal receive second edition of “NIS Caixa Pis” on June 7</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/macau-e-portugal-recebem-segunda-edicao-do-dinis-caixapiz-no-dia-7-de-junho/</link><description>The presentation of the new edition of the project “Dinis Caixapiz”-a box that brings together various didactic content in Portuguese for a children's audience-will take place this Saturday in Macau, at the Consulate General of Portugal, and in Lisbon, at the Book Fair. Both events have interactive activities designed for children and families.
 
Sílába - Educational and Literary Association will launch the second edition of the “Dinis Caixapiz” Children's Literary Project on June 7, Saturday, Portugal and Macau.
In Macao, the new edition will be presented in the Garden of the Consulate General of Portugal at 15:00, as an integral element of the cultural program “June, Portugal's month at MSA”. In addition to the presentation of the new content, interactive activities are also planned for children and families.
On the same day, Portugal will also receive a presentation session at the South Auditorium of the 95th Lisbon Book Fair, at 12:00 pm local time (19:00 in Macau), at the invitation of the Portuguese Association of Booksters (APEL). Also in this event will take place collaborative games, in which young participants are invited to invent a story while illustrator Aline Mendes transforms keywords into drawings.
In a statement sent to the newsrooms, the syllable states that the simultaneous presentation of the initiative on two different continents reinforces “the role of Macao and Portugal as a cultural union between the Portuguese communities around the world”.
The “Dinis Caixapiz” project includes the quarterly signature of a box with children's books, a magazine and a selection of physical and digital materials that aim to arouse the “intellectual curiosity” of children, develop knowledge about the history and culture of Portugal and Macao and promote the taste for reading and the Portuguese language.
The 2025 boxes are subordinated to the “literary games” theme, including the inclusion of reasoning games and linguas “to stimulate critical thinking” and an audio-book narrated by “known voices from the literary world”, which can be accessed by reading an ‘QR code’. Concern about sustainability has also been reinforced in this latest version, with a cutable box and pages made on seed paper that can be planted after read.
“Dinis Caixapiz” is intended for readers between the ages of five and 12, Portuguese teachers and families looking for cultural and educational activities outside the school context. This year, the selection of books included in Caixa was in charge of Elisabete Rosa-Machado, founder of Independent Publisher Poets and Dragons Society; Helena Alves, Manager at Leya Group; and Maria Elisa Vilaça, educator and artist.
In parallel to the quarterly box, the syllable ensures that it will continue to develop “creative writing workshops, reading clubs, renowned authors, illustration workshops, book fairs and book donation programs”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Child subsidy plan starts on July 15 and benefits born between 2022 and 2027</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/plano-de-subsidio-para-criancas-comeca-a-15-de-julho-e-beneficia-os-nascidos-entre-2022-e-2027/</link><description>The new children's support plan in Macau will start on July 15 and the candidacies will be open the next day. The government announced yesterday that children born in 2025 to 2027 will be beneficiaries of the subsidy and will receive a installment per year, in the amount of 18,000 patacas, for three years. Children born between 2022 and 2024 are eligible to assign one to three installments. This year, the executive foresees a budget of 270 million patacas for this plan.
 
The government yesterday presented the new “Childhood Assistance Subsidy Plan” which provides for the attribution of an 18,000 patacas subsidy, in annual installment, for children up to 3 years of age. The Executive Board concluded the discussion of the respective administrative regulation and announced that the document will come into force on July 15, and the children of the children will be able to submit the candidacy from July 16.
According to André Cheong, spokesman for the Executive Council, the granting of the subsidy is intended for children born from 2025 to 2027 and holders of the Macao Permanent Resident Identity Ticket, which may receive a total of three annual benefits from the subsidy.
Children born in the years 2022 to 2024, one to three annual benefits of the allowance depending on their age, taking into account the “need to create children born before 2025”, the executive said.
Hon Wai, president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), explained at a press conference that, in this case, children born in 2022 will be entitled to a subsidy, those born in 2023 may receive two, while those born last year will have three installments. He also pointed out that the eligibility of children to the subsidy is analyzed according to the year of birth and not the month, that is, children born in any month from 2022, until 2027, will be beneficiaries.
According to statistics and census services data, more than 11,600 babies were born in Macao in the last three years, ie 4,344 in 2022, 3,712 in 2023 and 3,607 in 2024, and the government predicts that about 3,500 babies are born in 2025. Thus, it is estimated that a total of 15,000 children will benefit by this year and this year's plan budget is 270 million Patacas.
 
‘Online’ applications
 
Authorities indicate that the application of application will be “very easy” and any of the child's progenitors can place the request by electronic via the application of a “single account” mobile phone, and the deadline to submit the candidacy cannot exceed June 30 of the year following the birth of the child.
And on January 1 of the following year of subsidy, if the child continues to meet the respective requirements and has been verified by IAS, he remains automatically as a beneficiary and without having to proceed again to the respective formalities.
The subsidy is assigned by bank transfer. For the new applications, the subsidy will be paid within 60 days from the day following its approval, while for existing eligible applications the payment will take place in the 2nd quarter of the year of assignment.
 
Encourage birth
 
André Cheong reiterated yesterday that the subsidy plan is provisional in nature and expects to help parents in the care of children, as well as encourage birth. "It is expected to provide some economic support to families with children, to meet additional expenses arising from the satisfaction of the strict requirements regarding the raising of children, relieving some financial charges of their own," he said. The Secretary for Administration and Justice also said the measure will have a "positive effect" on increasing the number of births.
The government, however, did not predict the effectiveness of the measure in birth, nor the possible continuity of the plan in the future. "After three years we will see how the result is to be able to respond. We could not make any estimate regarding the continuity or optimization of the plan," he said.
 
Continuity of the checks?
 
At the same press conference, the Secretary for Administration and Justice was once again asked about the cash reimbursement, due to the company's concern about the eventual cancellation of the plan in the future, after the government decided to impose a new 183 -day stay restriction on Macau for the reception of checks.
André Cheong pointed out that pecuniary reimbursement, although not a permanent measure, is an “important government policy for the well-being of the population”. "It is an important measure to increase the sense of belonging, happiness and gain of citizens, so the government will surely hear the public's opinions to improve the plan," he reiterated.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:34:19</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 1,800 arrests in anti-burrel operation in Asia that included Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/04/mais-de-1-800-detencoes-em-operacao-anti-burla-na-asia-que-incluiu-macau/</link><description>More than 1,800 people were arrested on a operation, which included Macao, against networks dedicated to fraud and squads set up in Asia, Hong Kong police said yesterday. The operation, which involved authorities from Hong Kong, Macau, South Korea, Thailand, Singapore, Malaysia and Maldives, successfully intercepted funds in the $ 20 million networks, said the chief superintendent of the Hong Kong Police Commercial Crimes Department, Wong Chu-Yue. Police action targeted online purchases and telephone scopes, as well as investment and employment frauds. The detainees are between 14 and 81 years old and almost 33,000 accounts were frozen, Wong said.
In March, a financial director in Singapore was deceived through fake videos, by someone who went through the executive director of a multinational. The victim transferred $ 499,000 to Hong Kong, said assistant director of the Singapore Police Anti -Freed Command, Aileen Yap, adding that through transionic cooperation, the money was recovered. A United Nations report in April found that transnational groups of organized crime in East and Southeast Asian are spreading fraudulent operations around the world. According to the report issued by the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime, for several years the groups proliferated in the southeastern Asian continent, especially at the borders of Cambodia, Laos and Myanmar, as well as in the Philippines, transferring operations from one place to another to escape the police. The centers of the schemes set up in Myanmar, Cambodia and Laos are known to attract people to work, using false arguments. Victims of online burlas and fraud also include workers used in operations that face threats, violence and poor working conditions. Employees are often forced to financially explore people around the world, and many are arrested in virtual slavery.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 05:35:45</pubDate></item></channel></rss>