<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/servicos-de-procriacao-medicamente-assistida-tem-tempo-de-espera-demasiado-longo-diz-leong-sun-iok/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Sam Hou Fai highlights national security in first review of Beijing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/sam-hou-fai-destaca-seguranca-nacional-no-primeiro-balanco-a-pequim/</link><description>The Chief Executive, who finished his mission in Beijing, revealed that he had presented to the Chinese President, Xi Jinping, the work related to national security defense throughout the year, including the detention of the former deputy, Au Kam San, and the holding of legislative elections. Sam Hou Fai thanked the Central Government for the “full recognition” of the work and promised to work to follow Beijing’s instructions.
The work carried out to defend national security and strengthen communication with the Central Government were the highlights in the report presented by Sam Hou Fai to the Chinese President, Xi Jinping, during his official mission in Beijing. The Chief Executive returned to Macau yesterday after meeting with Xi Jinping, expressing gratitude to the Chinese leader for the “full recognition” of the work of the government team.
Sam Hou Fai highlighted that it was his first presentation of a work report to Beijing, which is paying “deep attention” to the development of the Macao SAR. Speaking at a press conference yesterday, Sam revealed that the working report covers areas including the priority given by the Government to safeguarding national security.
According to Sam Hou Fai, the Government has “systematically implemented” tasks within the national security framework, drafted relevant laws and legal regulations and increased the public's political sensitivity.
"A former deputy of the Legislative Assembly was arrested, in accordance with the law, suspected of endangering national security. The principle of 'Macau governed by patriots' was comprehensively implemented. The elections for the VIII Legislative Assembly were concluded", detailed the Chief Executive. It is recalled that Au Kam San, a former legislator and also a Portuguese citizen, was arrested at the end of July, being the first case to be charged under the Macau State Security Defense Law.
Sam Hou Fai also assured Beijing that the general jurisdiction of the central power is being respected and safeguarded, with the Macao SAR Government maintaining enhanced communication with the central authorities regarding key policies, decisions and developments.
To the Central Government, the Chief Executive also emphasized the “healthy and orderly development” of the gaming industry in Macau, and said that all satellite casinos in the territory will be closed by the end of the year. “Gaming concessionaires are urged to further expand customer sources abroad and implement non-gaming investments,” he stressed.
With his dedication to the development of Hengqin since assuming the role of Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai indicated that he has strengthened the partnership between Macau and Hengqin.  He added that investments by gaming and leisure companies in Ilha da Montanha are considered as investments not related to gaming in Macau provided for in the gaming concession contracts in the city.
VOICES FOR 680 THOUSAND RESIDENTS
 
At a time when the first year of the 6th Macau Government is about to end, Sam Hou Fai was yesterday asked about his assessment of his performance, but the government official considers that “the most authoritative judgment lies with the 680 thousand residents of Macau and all sectors” that contributed to local development.
Sam, however, highlighted his gratitude to President Xi and the Hong Kong and Macao Affairs Office of the State Council for their recognition and support. “I would also like to thank the general public of Macau, in particular the patriotic associations that love Macau, for working together with the Government in implementing the policies”, he highlighted.
Noting that next year the Government will give priority to economic diversification and increasing administrative effectiveness, Sam Hou Fai expressed full confidence in the future and assured that the Government will advance all work in accordance with Xi Jinping's guidelines and instructions.
Government leaders guarantee implementation of Beijing’s “instructions”
After the presentation of Sam Hou Fai's work in Beijing, the holders of the main Government positions reacted with commitment to the implementation of the “instructions” given by the Central Government, articulating the development of Macau with China's 15th Five-Year Plan.
Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Administration and Justice, assumes that he will promote better local development, with work to deepen the reform of public administration, promote electronic governance and improve the performance of service operations.
Regarding actions in the legal area, Wong Sio Chak indicates that he will improve the legal system, deepen exchanges with the outside world and reinforce work coordination with Hengqin, in order to create better conditions for economic diversification.
The development of the economy was also in focus for Tai Kin Ip, who promises dedication in the area of ​​tourism and emerging industries. The Secretary for Economy and Finance also states that there will be more support for small and medium-sized companies, as well as promoting cooperation with Portuguese-speaking countries.
The Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, in turn, highlights that the authority is committed to improving the level of public security management and to “effectively prevent and mitigate various types of risks”, implementing the defense of national security.
O Lam, Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, aims to improve the training system and build a “cluster of top qualified professionals that combines international competitiveness and Macau’s own characteristics”.
Regarding the Transport and Public Works portfolio, Secretary Raymond Tam assures that he will be focused on promoting the construction of infrastructure in the territory, optimizing urban planning and reinforcing environmental protection, in order to transform Macau into an intelligent, ecological and livable city.
In addition to the secretaries, the Commissioner against Corruption, Ao Ieong Seong, says she is committed to raising the level of integrity in Macau society and supervising the exercise of powers. Elsie Ao Ieong, commissioner of Audit, Leong Man Cheong, general commander of the Unitary Police Services, and Adriano Marques Ho, director of the Customs Service, also highlighted their determination to work on following the “central instructions”. The Public Prosecutor's Office, Tong Hio Fong, highlighted the modernization of the work of the Public Prosecutor's Office and its capacity for legal protection, as well as the safeguarding of public interests and defense of the rights and legitimate interests of vulnerable groups.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:06:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Global Tourism Forum held in Harbin raises Macau's position on the World Tourist Map</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/forum-de-turismo-global-realizado-em-harbin-eleva-posicao-de-macau-no-mapa-turistico-mundial/</link><description>The 11th edition of the Global Tourism Economy Forum (GTEF), one of the main events in the sector organized by Macau, took place for the first time outside the territory, in Harbin, Heilongjiang province. The forum, which took place from 15 to 17 December under the theme “New Quality Productive Forces”, brought together more than a thousand participants and tourism ministers from various countries, with the aim of promoting Macau's image as a global tourism and leisure center and exploring synergies with other regions in the interior of China.

The Global Tourism Economy Forum (GTEF), the international tourism platform created under the auspices of the Macao SAR Government, marked a new chapter in its 11-year history by holding its 11th edition outside the territory, in Harbin, in the Chinese province of Heilongjiang. The event, which took place between December 15th and 17th, brought together leaders from the global tourism industry under the theme “New Quality Productive Forces: Boosting the Global Tourism Economy”, with the stated purpose of raising Macau's international profile and exploring new dynamics of regional cooperation.
At the opening ceremony, the Secretary for Economy and Finance and executive president of GTEF, Tai Kin Ip, who represented the Chief Executive, highlighted that Macau continues to take advantage of its unique advantage of “having the support of the Motherland and being connected to the world”. He reaffirmed the territory's positioning as “One Center, One Platform and One Base” and highlighted the holding of the forum in Harbin as an “important milestone” that reflects the irradiation capacity of the GTEF platform and highlights the potential for tourism development at a national level.
The forum was attended by high-level figures including vice-president of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference and president of GTEF, Edmund Ho; the secretary-general of UN Tourism, Zurab Pololikashvili; and Heilongjiang governor Liang Huiling. The debates focused on four main themes: Ice and Snow Economy and Industrial Innovation; Cultural Empowerment and Brand Building; Leadership in Investments and Project Development; and Opportunities for Cross-Border Collaboration and Cooperation.
This edition of GTEF also reinforced the forum's role as a catalyst for trade and cooperation agreements. Throughout its history, GTEF has facilitated the signing of more than one hundred memorandums of understanding (MOUs) between different international tourism stakeholders. These agreements have been “instrumental” in promoting the advancement and sustained growth of the sector, creating concrete bridges between the provinces and cities of China and countries around the world in areas that go beyond tourism, also covering culture, economy and commerce, according to the organizing entity.
Parallel to the sessions in Harbin, discussion panels were organized in Macau, broadcasting the main debates live. This initiative aimed to increase the participation of local industry and foster collaboration between the two regions. An “Exclusive Macau Session – Macau Tourism Promotion Seminar” was also held, chaired by the director of Tourism Services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes. In this session, the Government's efforts to promote “1+4” economic diversification and deepen the integration of the “tourism+” concept were detailed, with sector representatives sharing innovative initiatives.
The choice of Heilongjiang as the headquarters was not random. The province and Macau have distinct but complementary tourism resources, and in March this year they signed several cooperation memorandums to strengthen collaboration in areas such as economy, commerce, science and education. The holding of the GTEF in Harbin aims to reflect the Macao SAR Government's strategy of fully integrating itself into national development, expanding the forum's influence and exploring synergies between snow tourism in the north and Macau's multifaceted offer.
Since its creation in 2012, GTEF has established itself as an international platform of reference, having already established partnerships with more than 86 countries and regions and generated a media value of more than 600 million US dollars. The 2025 edition was organized by the People's Government of Heilongjiang Province and the Global Tourism Economy Research Center, with the Macao SAR Government as the founding entity and UN Tourism as a partner.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:04:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau received more tourists until November than in the entire year 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/macau-recebeu-ate-novembro-mais-turistas-do-que-em-todo-o-ano-de-2024/</link><description>The director of Tourism Services said that the territory received 36.5 million visitors between January and November, more than in the entire year 2024. Macau received 34.9 million visitors last year, 23.8% more than in the previous year, but still far from the record, 39.4 million, set in 2019.

Macau received 36.5 million visitors between January and November, more than in the entire year 2024, revealed the director of Tourism Services (DST). According to the Chinese-language newspaper Ou Mun Iat Pou, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes told journalists on Tuesday that the goal is to close 2025 with 39 million visitors.
Macau received 34.9 million visitors last year, 23.8% more than the previous year, but still far from the record, 39.4 million, set in 2019, before the covid-19 pandemic.
In Harbin, capital of Heilongjiang province, in northern China, Senna Fernandes highlighted that the number of international visitors has recovered to around 80% of pre-pandemic levels. The leader was speaking on the sidelines of the 11th edition of the Global Tourism Economy Forum, which was held for the first time outside Macau.
In August, Senna Fernandes set a target of more than three million international visitors in 2025. In the first ten months of the year, Macau received almost 2.97 million tourists from abroad, 14.9% more than in the same period in 2024.
Citizens of Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Bahrain and Oman will no longer need a visa to enter the city from July 16th.
Senna Fernandes promised to seek cooperation with different provinces and cities in mainland China to find new ways to attract more international visitors to Macau. The leader highlighted that the current visa-free transit policy for foreign travelers creates “new opportunities for cooperation” with more Chinese cities, in addition to the Greater Bay Area.
Senna Fernandes recalled that the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for 2026 foresee the opening of two Macau delegations in Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia and argues that they will be “important points of development in the future”. The LAG, presented at the end of November, foresees the opening of a delegation in Malaysia and also highlights the focus on tourists from Portuguese-speaking countries as a priority.
Despite the increase in the number of tourists, the average consumption of each visitor in Macau, excluding casinos, fell by 9.5% in the first nine months of the year, compared to the same period in 2024.
At the beginning of May, DSEC pointed to the “change in the consumption pattern of visitors” as one of the main reasons for the 1.3% drop in Macau's economy between January and March. It was the first time that the territory's Gross Domestic Product shrank, in year-on-year terms, since the end of 2022, when the region began to lift restrictions due to the covid-19 pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:03:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Government will launch counseling program for individuals with gambling addiction</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/governo-vai-lancar-programa-de-aconselhamento-a-individuos-com-dependencia-de-jogo/</link><description>The program should begin to be implemented in the first quarter of 2026, focusing on areas close to casinos. The Institute of Social Action (IAS) guarantees that the measures aimed at reducing gambling addiction have been “effective”, as revealed by the most recent data: between January and September, the number of individuals affected by gambling addiction fell by around 30% compared to the same period last year.

The Government will launch a pilot night-time counseling program for individuals potentially affected by gambling addiction in the first quarter of next year. The news was announced by the head of the Department of Prevention and Treatment of Gambling and Drug Addiction at the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Cheang Io Tat, in statements to the newspaper Ou Mun.
According to the official, the program will consist of concentrating social workers in community areas, such as parks or streets close to entertainment venues and casinos, in order to facilitate their interaction with residents or visitors potentially affected by gambling problems. On-site professionals will be responsible for providing relevant information to the population and identifying cases that require assistance, mobilizing the appropriate resources and departments so that these situations are detected and monitored early.
The most recent data from the central registration system of individuals affected by gambling addiction disorder, between January and September, reports 112 new individuals suffering from this condition. Quoted by the newspaper Ou Mun, Cheang Io Tat notes that this number represents a decrease of approximately 30% compared to the same period last year, being equivalent to the values ​​recorded in 2019.
Telephone advice lines also reported a decrease in the number of requests for assistance, with 1,800 calls received during the first three quarters of 2025. Requests for assistance were mostly made by non-resident players over 30 years of age, corroborating a trend of change in the profile of people addicted to gambling in the territory. Analyzing data from recent years, especially after the lifting of pandemic restrictions, it appears that individuals seeking professional assistance are increasingly older and, for the most part, do not hold a Resident Identity Card.
Cheang Io Tat notes that the decrease in cases reported to the IAS “reflects the effectiveness of recent efforts to promote responsible gambling”, as well as “an increase in tourists’ willingness to seek help”.
The official also adds that the organization has already collected data from a survey on the participation of young people in Macau in different types of games, which is scheduled to be released to the public in the first quarter of next year. In addition to traditional games of luck and chance, the survey also covers other types of games aimed at a younger population, such as “surprise boxes”, claw machines or other entertainment available in entertainment venues in Macau.
Cheang Io Tat hopes that the survey will allow us to consolidate “a basis” for subsequent prevention work, by allowing a more in-depth understanding of young people's perceptions of gambling and the prevalence of this type of disorder in younger generations.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:05:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Neighborhood Styles</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/estilos-de-bairro/</link><description>Have you ever walked into a trendy barbershop or hairdresser and been intimidated by the walls full of hair wax ads and the penetrating gazes of tattooed stylists, instantly feeling “fashion anxiety”? Don't worry.

On almost every corner in this city, there are always some well-lit quick haircut services in the neighborhood, waiting to give you a new and clean look in just a few minutes and for just a few patacas. These “neighborhood quick-cut foundations” are essentially the “Cha Chaan Teng” of the hairdressing world.
Imagine an uncle with a perfectly groomed “egg pie” hairstyle waiting for customers inside. This is just the basic scenario. The true masters often appear with the most impressive looks – like the “Beard Guy”, Master Fai, a barber who lives up to his name with a white beard covering his face and a head of gradient brown hair that makes him look like a mighty lion.
“I love doing hairstyles, whether they are common, strange or wonderful,” says Master Fai. He remembers how, in the past, people specifically went to the salon to get their hair done for banquets and dinners, both men and women.
“Do young people think that rainbow-colored hair is something new?” laughs Master Fai as he trims his client's faded hair, his hand holding the round brush firmly.
“In the 80s, for banquets, I rocked the Pompadour hairstyle and managed to make women's buns so high that they had to slide sideways to get into taxis!”
The barbers' own hairstyles are equally extravagant; one could even describe them as performance art. They are your best advertisements. Even with the years on their faces, they still welcome customers with a vibrant and welcoming energy.
Another master in the store, Master Keng, is the perfect visual representation of “hair standing on end.” The stark contrast between his shaved scalp and the mop of short, gray curls on top is truly striking — it's as if he's ready to receive cosmic radio waves from outer space at any moment. You are unlikely to see another person on the street with this hairstyle.
Here, there are no fancy titles like “artistic director”, just practical masters who rose through the ranks from “shampoo boys”. They learned the trade by interning with senior barbers in salons when they were young and have now gone on to serve their neighborhoods.
“Times are different,” says Beard Guy Fai. "Simple and quick has replaced formal and elaborate. Quick cuts are the trend now. It used to take two hours to do a hairstyle, now it only takes ten minutes."
Another elderly barber, “Godfather” Ieong, sports a much more modest hairstyle. He has been a barber in his neighborhood for over 60 years. Cutting hair isn't just something he's done his entire life; Even in retirement, he still occasionally comes to the barbershop to get a few cuts, a true master whose skill speaks for itself.
The barbershop is filled with old-style equipment: hairdryers for styling and conditioning, as well as hair curlers that look exactly like the landlady's from the Hong Kong film Kung Fu Hustle.
If you want to try the retro styles of the 70s, the old master's eyes will instantly light up. "Do you know who Farrah Fawcett is? Women back then loved her look!"
Younger generations may not recognize the name, but 50 years ago she played a private detective on the American TV series Charlie’s Angels. Her blonde curls were a classic icon of the 70s, and her hairstyle became famous as the “Farrah Fawcett flip”, characterized by long, layered hair with “wings” or bouncy waves that framed the face, created with a blow dryer and a round brush. A look full of life and bold beauty.
Neighborhood businesses are focused on efficiency and being practical. Typically, a barber handles the entire haircut process. At peak times, the entire barbershop can serve up to 60 people per day.
Although the barbers' appearance can be a little sloppy, these veterans not only create stylish cuts, they also provide meticulous service with a warm, friendly approach. There may not be an Instagram-worthy wall, but there are always students popping in after class for a flawless haircut; There is no champagne service, but the ladies bring their own thermoses and chat about family matters while they wait.
The hairstyle culture of the 1980s is vividly portrayed in Hong Kong TV dramas. The ATV series Barber Shop from that time portrayed this scene perfectly — everyone sporting voluminous, stylish hair and treating haircuts as an essential part of life.
At this time, cutting your hair was not just a matter of personal hygiene, it was also a social ritual. A young man starting his career would take a “mature and sober” approach to his job interview; A heartbroken girl entered the barbershop, demanding to “erase the traces of that shameless guy”.
These days, when you walk into a quick cut salon, you may see fewer of these dramatic and extravagant hairstyles. But the essential nature of the haircut as a regular ritual has never changed. The buzz of old-time barbers' hair clippers continues — easing summer boredom for students or giving a fresh air to office workers facing the day ahead.
Quick cuts do not debate the philosophy of style nor do they discuss schools of aesthetics. They simply help everyone start from scratch, get ready and then hit the busy streets again, ready to face the day in style!


G!NN!E, Macau Closer</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government approves deal for the only ‘satellite casino’ that will not close</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/governo-aprova-negocio-do-unico-casino-satelite-que-nao-vai-encerrar/</link><description>The Government announced yesterday the approval of the acquisition by the concessionaire SJM Resorts of Royal Arc, the only one of the 11 'satellite casinos' that will continue to operate after the end of the year.
According to an order published in the Official Bulletin, the authorities received, on November 11, a request from SJM and the company that owns the hotel where the Royal Arc is located to approve the deal. “This transmission aims to maintain the continuous exploration and operation of the existing casino (…), which operates as a satellite casino, transforming it into a casino belonging to the gaming concessionaire”, said the note.
The process involved opinions from the casino regulator, the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate, and the Tourism Services Directorate, which is responsible for hotels, said the order from the Secretary for Transport and Public Works.
Raymond Tam said that the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services and the Land Commission gave the green light to the deal, partly because “there is no indication that the transfer is requested for speculative purposes”.
On Monday, SJM announced, in a statement sent to the Hong Kong stock exchange, that the concessionaire's shareholders had approved the deal at an extraordinary general meeting.
On November 20, the company had announced an agreement to acquire the company that owns the hotel where the Royal Arc is located for 1.75 billion Hong Kong dollars.
Nine of Macau's 11 'satellite casinos' have already closed. The last to close its doors, on December 9th, was Fortuna, with more than 550 employees. The tenth, Landmark, which has 1,169 workers, will close on December 30th.
SJM highlighted that all employees of 'satellite casinos' with resident status in Macau and directly hired by the company have guaranteed employment in other casinos. Other local workers “are invited to apply for related vacancies” within the group, “with priority for hiring” and with conditions equal to those they had.
The DICJ promised to cooperate with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs to ensure compliance with the guarantees given by the concessionaires, namely “the relocation of all aforementioned workers”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:02:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Chip manufacturer MetaX debuts on the Shanghai stock exchange with an appreciation of 700%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/fabricante-de-chips-metax-estreia-se-na-bolsa-de-xangai-com-valorizacao-de-700/</link><description>Chinese graphics chip manufacturer MetaX debuted on the Shanghai stock exchange, reaching a valuation of 755%. The company's shares opened at 700 yuan per unit, well above the subscription price set for the initial public offering of 104.66 yuan.

Chinese graphics chip manufacturer MetaX debuted yesterday on the Shanghai stock exchange, reaching a valuation of 755%, reflecting investors' enthusiasm for local alternatives to Nvidia and the Chinese commitment to technological self-sufficiency.
The company's shares opened at 700 yuan per unit, well above the subscription price set for the initial public offering (IPO) of 104.66 yuan. At around 10:30 local time, the securities rose by 755%.
MetaX placed more than 40 million shares on the market, raising the equivalent of 596 million dollars (507 million euros), in the fifth largest operation of its kind in mainland China this year. The second largest was led by chip manufacturer Moore Threads, which raised around 1.131 million dollars.
According to the local press, MetaX's strong performance was driven by the enthusiasm generated by the recent debut of Moore Threads, whose demand from investors exceeded the number of shares available by 2,751 times. In the case of MetaX, the ratio was even higher: 2,986 times.
In addition to the stock market appreciation, both cases reflect the Chinese Government's efforts to ensure technological self-sufficiency, a strategic priority in the face of the trade war with the United States and the restrictions imposed on the export of advanced semiconductors to the Chinese market, which forced Nvidia to reduce its presence in China.
In recent days, the Chinese press reported that Beijing will be rejecting Nvidia's H200 chips – more powerful than those previously authorized by Washington – in favor of national solutions, such as those developed by MetaX.
Founded in 2020 by former AMD engineers, MetaX will use the funds raised to finance research and development (R&amp;D) activities for high-performance graphics cards, including products aimed at artificial intelligence applications.
Its main 'chip' for general computing, the C600, is expected to go into production soon, after being announced in July. The next generation, C700, is still in the development phase.
Despite the strong growth, MetaX, like Moore Threads, continues to record losses, expecting to reach the financial break-even point only in 2026. Even so, in the first three quarters of this year, the company quadrupled its turnover. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 22:58:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Deaths in the ongoing clash between Thailand and Cambodia already exceed those in July</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/mortos-no-confronto-em-curso-entre-tailandia-e-camboja-ja-ultrapassam-os-de-julho/</link><description>The armed conflict between Thailand and Cambodia in the border region left at least 52 people dead, a number that exceeded the number of victims of the July clashes, which killed 50 people, according to a report updated yesterday.
Thailand's Internal Security Operations Command raised the number of Thai soldiers killed to 19 and kept the number of civilian deaths at 16. Cambodian Defense Ministry spokeswoman Maly Socheata counted 17 civilian deaths, including a child.
The conflict arises from an old dispute between the two countries over the sovereignty of territories close to the common border, which extends for approximately 820 kilometers and was mapped by France in 1907, when Cambodia was part of French Indochina.
Phnom Penh said yesterday that Thai forces had “intensified attacks” at certain points along the border in recent hours and emphasized that they had carried out new bombings with F-16 fighter jets.
In addition to the armed conflict, the two neighboring countries are fighting a war of numbers: Cambodia avoids releasing information about soldier deaths, while Thai authorities claim that there are more than 500 casualties on the opposing side.
Last week, Cambodian authorities dismissed reports of soldier deaths reported by Thailand.
The Thai Ministry of Defense, in turn, alluded to an “information war” also underway, local media reported yesterday.
The new wave of crossfire, which both sides accuse each other of having started, broke out on December 7, with the 11 days of conflict already surpassing the five days of violence in July by almost a week, which ended after the mediation of several countries, led by Malaysia and including the United States.
North American President Donald Trump boasts of having put an end – albeit temporarily – to hostilities between the two countries in an agreement signed on October 26, and intervened again in the conflict, without apparent success, after its resurgence. “[Trump] should ask Cambodia to stop firing first at Thailand, because Thailand has never fired first,” said Thai Prime Minister Anutin Charnvirakul, according to local media, after a telephone conversation with the American leader last week. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 22:57:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese tourism in Japan slows down in November despite all-time high in arrivals</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/turismo-chines-no-japao-desacelera-em-novembro-apesar-de-maximo-historico-de-entradas/</link><description>The arrival of Chinese tourists to Japan slowed down in November, amid diplomatic tension between Tokyo and Beijing, despite the archipelago having registered a record number of foreign visitors, according to official data released yesterday. The total number of international tourist arrivals in November was 3,518,000, an increase of 10.4% compared to the same month in 2024, indicated the Japan National Tourism Organization (JNTO).
Among the visitors, 562 thousand came from mainland China – a year-on-year increase of 3%, but well below previous months. In October, Japan had received 715 thousand Chinese tourists and, in September, 775 thousand – growth close to 20% year-on-year. “In addition to the demand for travel to Japan slowing down at this time of year, the Chinese Government warned the population to avoid traveling to the country”, said JNTO, highlighting that the year-on-year increase was also due to the greater supply of seats on flights.
The slowdown coincided with the recommendation issued by Chinese authorities following statements by Japanese Prime Minister, Sanae Takaichi, about Taiwan, which reignited diplomatic tensions between the two countries. Even so, between January and November, China remained the main source of tourists to Japan, with 8.7 million visitors, followed by South Korea (8.4 million).
In the first eleven months of 2025, Japan received 39,065,600 international visitors – 17% more than in the same period of the previous year –, already surpassing the record of 36.87 million registered in 2024 and approaching the target of 40 million by the end of this year. The continued growth of tourism has fueled a national debate about the impacts of mass tourism, with some conservative parties demanding new restrictions on the entry of foreigners and stricter rules to preserve coexistence in local communities. Among the data highlighted by JNTO is the 53% increase in the number of Mexican tourists in November, totaling 20,700, while in the year to date they have already exceeded 183 thousand – 31% more than between January and November 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 22:56:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesian operators explore Macau and Hengqin routes taking advantage of new transit visa</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/operadores-da-indonesia-exploram-rotas-de-macau-e-hengqin-aproveitando-novo-visto-de-transito/</link><description>A delegation of ten representatives from the Indonesian Travel and Tourism Agencies Association was in Macau and Hengqin, from 14 to 18 December, for a five-day familiarization visit. The aim was to experience first-hand the new opportunities created by the 240-hour visa-free transit policy, implemented in November, which allows citizens from 55 countries to enter Mainland China through the Hengqin Border Post.
The visit, organized by the Tourism Bureau (DST) in cooperation with the Hengqin economic development authorities, focused on promoting “multi-destination” tourist itineraries that combine Macau, Hengqin and other cities in the Greater Bay Area. Indonesia is currently the sixth largest tourist source market for Macau, with more than 163 thousand visitors in the first ten months of 2025.
In Macau, the delegation visited attractions such as the Historic Center, the Grand Prix Museum and the W Macau Hotel, attended the “Macau 2049” show and the “Iluminar Macau 2025” event, and participated in a custard tart workshop. The gastronomic component included tasting local, Halal and Portuguese dishes. The visit continued to Hengqin, where tour operators personally experienced visa-free entry procedures at the border post and visited attractions such as Chimelong International Ocean Resort and Traditional Chinese Medicine Cultural Experience Center. The trip ended with the return from Baiyun Airport in Guangzhou.
This initiative is part of DST's broader strategy to attract international visitors, which has already included participation in fairs in Indonesia and promotion campaigns in Jakarta this year. DST, in a statement, said it hopes that this direct experience will encourage Indonesian operators to create and promote tourist packages that include Macau, contributing to the territory's positioning as a tourism and leisure center and to the synergistic development of tourism in the Greater Bay Area.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:02:43</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAL says that hiring TNRs only serves to meet local work needs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/dsal-diz-que-contratacao-de-tnrs-serve-apenas-para-suprir-carencias-do-trabalho-local/</link><description>The Directorate of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL) guarantees that the hiring of non-resident workers (TNRs) in the territory only happens when the local workforce is insufficient. According to the organization's president, Chan Un Tong, authorities have closely monitored the processing of applications for TNRs and ensured that priority is given to hiring resident workers.

The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) reiterated that the hiring of non-resident workers (TNRs) only happens when local resources are insufficient, in order to fill the needs of the local labor market. In response to a written question from deputy Leong Hong Sai, the director of DSAL, Chan Un Tong, stated that the authorities have been monitoring the job matching processes and ensuring that Macau companies give priority to residents.
In the interpellation sent to the Government, Leong Hong Sai highlighted the need to find a balance between hiring TNRs and local workers, safeguarding the interests and rights of both. The deputy noted that, although hiring TNRs is often a “relevant option to satisfy the demand for human resources”, it is imperative to ensure the protection of residents and their “labor rights and interests, salary level and stability”. “I hope that the authorities will pay attention to the current development of human resources and potential gaps in the non-resident workers regime, presenting viable solutions as soon as possible”, he stressed.
In the first of three questions addressed to the Government, deputy Leong Hong Sai begins by asking what the authorities' plans are for implementing “dynamic control mechanisms”, with the aim of “monitoring the principle regarding the limit number” of TNRs. This topic is explored further in the following question, which asks “how the authorities will, on a global basis, monitor and prevent (…) local workers from being subject to unjustified dismissal or having their rights and interests weakened in terms of access to employment”.
Finally, the Residents' representative gives voice to a complaint made by some residents he heard, according to which some companies set age limits for hiring and choose to hire non-residents at the expense of middle-aged people. “How will the authorities guarantee that, after completing their professional training, residents of all age groups are able to find a job?”, he asks.
In the response published on the Legislative Assembly (AL) page, the director of DSAL asserts that the organization “has strictly complied with the principle that the hiring of TNRs serves only to make up for the insufficiency of local human resources” by monitoring job matching in the region and the inclusion – mandatory – of a series of weighting factors.
Among the important factors in the assessment of requests are “the law and policies, economic development in general, the supply and demand for human resources in different sectors, the size and operational situation of the requesting entities, existing workers and the hiring situation of resident workers”. Furthermore, whenever residents show interest and meet the necessary requirements for a certain position, priority should “always” be given to their hiring. The number of TNRs will later be adjusted depending on local workers.
Referring to the second question from deputy Leong Hong Sai, the head of DSAL says that, if a resident worker is dismissed without just cause due to the hiring of TNRs, the authorities' action is to “initiate proceedings and revoke, in whole or in part, the hiring authorizations”. In this situation, the injured worker may also file a complaint with DSAL.
Chan Un Tong also draws attention to the “Integrated Professional Training Platform”, launched around two months ago on an experimental basis. Since then, around one hundred training courses have been made available to more than a thousand users of the application, accessible through the Macau Single Account. As this is a platform still in the optimization phase, the director of DSAL informs that opinions and suggestions from the public are currently being collected to reinforce its “size and efficiency”, while at the same time continuing to “provide support to residents who need employment or change jobs”.
On a final note, Chan Un Tong reaffirms that the Government “will continue to closely monitor the evolution of the Macau employment market” and organize various support measures, such as professional training courses and certification projects.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:05:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines considers using UN convention to extradite former deputy from Portugal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/filipinas-ponderam-usar-convencao-da-onu-para-extraditar-ex-deputado-de-portugal/</link><description>The Philippine government has said it is considering using a UN anti-corruption treaty to locate and extradite former congressman Elizaldy Salcedo Co, who Manila authorities believe is in Portugal, it was revealed this week.

The former deputy, better known as Zaldy Co, is the subject of an arrest warrant for alleged involvement in the scandal of “ghost projects” for flood control infrastructure.
Dozens of construction company owners, government officials and elected representatives across the archipelago are accused of embezzling funds or executing substandard projects.
On November 24, the Government announced the arrest of eight employees from the Ministry of Public Works and Roads, accused of being linked to the so-called “ghost projects”.
The most prominent figure, Zaldy Co, fled the country and released videos accusing Philippine President Ferdinand Marcos Jr. of being one of the main beneficiaries of corruption schemes. Marcos Jr. classified Zaldy Co's campaign as an example of “fake news”.
On December 1, Philippine Interior Secretary Jonvic Remulla said he believes Zaldy Co is in Portugal. “There are suspicions that he has a Portuguese passport obtained many years ago”, he explained.
On Monday, presidential press secretary and undersecretary Claire Castro said that Manila is studying a proposal from Senator Panfilo Lacson to appeal to the United Nations Convention against Corruption (UNCAC). “We can explore UNCAC, as it has international cooperation mechanisms, but this will depend on the country,” said Castro, reading a statement from the Secretary of Foreign Affairs, Maria Theresa Lazaro.
“Countries are obliged to provide, as applicable and in accordance with national law, the broadest possible mutual legal assistance to each other,” it added. The arrest warrant for Zaldy Co was issued by the Sandiganbayan, a special anti-corruption court.
In mid-November, Marcos promised that at least 37 senators and members of the Philippine Congress, as well as several construction workers allegedly linked to the scandal, would spend Christmas in prison.
Among the suspects are allies and opponents of Marcos, such as Martin Romualdez, cousin of the Philippine President, or Senator Bong Go, close to former Philippine leader Rodrigo Duterte, both of whom denied the accusations.
At stake are 9,855 drainage control projects, valued at more than 545 billion Philippine pesos (eight billion euros), which should have been built since Marcos takes power in mid-2022.
In September, Philippine Finance Minister Ralph Recto admitted that, since 2023, 118.5 billion pesos (1.75 billion euros) may have been embezzled. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 22:57:56</pubDate></item><item><title>The common chair</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/a-cadeira-comum/</link><description>There is a place where everyone sits, but few remember sharing it. A common place, which unites several bodies with the same purpose. It is in the barber's chair that we are all the same thing, summed up at the core of an inert piece of a protein called keratin, which under the hands of whoever cuts it, completes the union of a momentary partnership. It is in the common chair that a slightly intimate contact becomes a healthy routine of sharing and communion between strangers. A simple but infinite act… If it were possible.
Between the impersonal facade of a beauty salon and the cold glow of a quick-cut salon, there is that familiar light that insists on rotating forever. The barber's tricolor pole. An ancestral symbol whose colors, the red of the blood, the white of the bandages and the blue of the veins, tell the story of a profession that was once medicine, surgery and even dentistry. Today, in the neighborhood barbershops that still survive, the mission is different, but no less crucial: they are a safe haven for a community and a craft that gentrification has failed to swallow. It is the body's mechanics that leave the soul with a new shell.
These men, heirs of a lineage that goes back to the barber-priests of Ancient Egypt, are more than technicians. They are informal chroniclers of the neighborhood. They know their clients by name, they know about their lives, their work, their families. His chair, often a classic model based on those once used during the American Civil War, which could appear in a museum, is a privileged listening post.
The social function of the barbershop is a ubiquitous element in the history of humanity. They shared their function as places of debate with the hot springs and public baths in Plato's Greece. In Rome, visiting the barber was almost like a ritual, a daily routine. In the dark periods of the Middle Ages, they operated as health posts just around the corner. And who doesn't remember that recurring cinematic image? From the creators of African-American Jazz in communion in the barbershops of their neighborhoods, who were later replaced by the hip-hop masters of the 90s. Safeguarding spaces during times of segregating hallucinations.
This vocation of a public square on a reduced scale survives today, untouched by the digital world. Places where news circulates by word of mouth, the issues of the day are dissected without filters, and advice is given with the frankness of those who share the same territory. All under a simple but infinite act, if it were possible...
While the beauty sector becomes increasingly standardized and impersonal, these barbershops remain bastions of direct, unfussy service. There is no conceptual decoration for social networks, but there is the confidence of the student who goes there after school. No inflated shampoos are offered, but there is the familiarity of the customer who brings their tea and talks about their daily lives.
The job requires confidence, knowledge and an arsenal of tools that have changed little in decades: scissors, machines, razors. The latter, an instrument that in many places only a licensed barber can use, an echo of the times when they were also surgeons. And that's what they need, nothing more. The rest is the attitude of those who know that if they cut too much, there will be no turning back.
In the famous “Barber Paradox”, the logical question of who shaves the barber, curiously mirrors the unique role of these hair workers in the community. These figures take care of the image of others, trimming not only their hair, but also their insecurities, offering a moment of care and conversation. And who takes care of them? There comes the altruistic pleasure of leaving someone else in a little better spirits. A simple but infinite act. Indeed.
The hum of the cutting machines is the sound of a fresh start, whether for the student who wants to enter the holidays fresh or for the worker who needs a renewal of spirit. These houses are not lost in theories about aesthetics. They fulfill a practical and deeply human function: helping each person leave there lighter, tidier and ready to face the world outside. In the common barber's chair.
More than a business, these barbershops represent the resistance of original humanism in the face of aseptic massification, places where tradition and community meet, creating a refuge against the erosion of the unique character of urban neighborhoods.
Because, after all, tradition is not measured by tools or store design, but by the solidity and strength of human contact. In the common chair, we are all the same, together in sharing a simple act, in the hands of an infinite craft.  But after all, who shaves the barber, if the barber only shaves those who don't shave themselves?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Medically assisted reproduction services have too long waiting times, says Leong Sun Iok</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/17/servicos-de-procriacao-medicamente-assistida-tem-tempo-de-espera-demasiado-longo-diz-leong-sun-iok/</link><description>Deputy Leong Sun Iok called on the Government to reinforce the efficiency and speed of the “Medical Assisted Procreation Treatment Co-payment Program”, in order to provide a more useful and personalized service to older couples.
This program, remember, was launched in December 2024 with the aim of supporting infertile couples in Macau. The plan stipulates that couples who meet the requirements undergo a preliminary clinical assessment, and are then redirected to an external infertility consultation at Hospital das Ilhas.
“This represents a significant step for Macau in supporting birth rates”, points out the deputy, in a written question sent to the Government. However, factors such as excessive waiting times and the high costs of some services have been identified as the biggest weaknesses of this system, which is thus unable to meet the characteristics of a significant portion of the population.
Leong Sun Iok emphasizes that, “for older couples, time is an extremely crucial factor”, which is why he calls for an increase in resources and manpower at Hospital das Ilhas. It also suggests that processes be adjusted to optimize service capacity and shorten waiting times, allowing couples in need to benefit from the program “in an effective and timely manner”.
On the other hand, the frequent impossibility of immediately transferring the embryo to the woman's uterus implies the use of cryopreservation services. These are services that “involve substantial costs” as they are calculated over a six-month cycle – unlike what happens in the interior of China, where only the actual months of cryopreservation are counted.
The deputy's suggestion involves calculating the costs of services based on “real months of use”, thus determining the treatment cycle according to the actual number of “transfer” procedures used.
According to data released by Macau Union Hospital, more than a thousand users were attended to in external reproductive assessment consultations between February and December. The month of July was marked by the availability of the intrauterine insemination (IUI) service, which already has 57 cases – including “some” that resulted in successful pregnancies.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 23:01:46</pubDate></item></channel></rss>