<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/propostas-de-macau-ao-orgao-consultivo-politico-chines-abordam-servicos-medicos-na-ilha-da-montanha/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>China suspends imports of cattle meat from three Brazilian factories</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/china-suspende-importacoes-de-carne-de-bovino-de-tres-fabricas-brasileiras/</link><description>China temporarily suspended imports of beef from three Brazilian factories, announced yesterday the government of Brazil, ensuring that the decision will not affect bilateral trade relations.
The General Administration of China Customs has performed a series of “video audits” in the affected units and detected that they do not fulfill all import requirements established by the Asian country, explained the Ministry of Agriculture and Livestock in Brazil, in a statement.
The companies, whose names were not disclosed by the folder, have already been notified and are “taking corrective measures” to meet the demands of the Chinese body, according to the Brazilian government.
China is the main destination of Brazilian beef exports and the largest commercial partner in the South American country. Brazil's Minister of Agriculture and Livestock, Carlos Fávaro, denied in the same statement that the three suspended factories may have repercussions on the close business relationship between the two countries.
“Today, Brazil has 126 qualified plants. When we took over [the government in January 2023], we had 12 suspended plants. We resumed these 12 and opened 43 more from the 55 of this total of 126, ”he added.
The Secretary of Agricultural Defense, Carlos Goulart, said they will continue to talk to private exporters and the Chinese authorities to "resolve the questions raised and resume exports of these units."
Brazil, one of the world's largest animal protein suppliers, ended 2024 with a record production of 31.57 million tons of beef, pork and chicken, as well as record exports of 10.26 million tons, according to official data.
Since 2009, China has been the main commercial partner in Brazil, with bilateral trade from nine billion dollars (8.3 billion euros), in 2004, to 157.5 billion (144 billion euros), in 2023. Brazil plays, in particular, an important role in China's food security, composing more than 20% of the country's agricultural and livestock imports.
The second world's second largest economy feeds nearly 19% of humanity with only 8.5% of the planet's arable land. By comparison, the Latin American country has almost 7% of the arable land to 2.7% of the world's population.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:01+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China advances with more policies and subsidies to increase birth rates</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/china-avanca-com-mais-politicas-e-subsidios-para-aumentar-as-taxas-de-natalidade/</link><description>Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang announced yesterday the implementation of policies and subsidies to increase birth rate and solve China's demographic problem, whose population has been decreasing for three consecutive years.
 
At the opening of the Annual Plenary Session of the National Popular Assembly (APN), China's top legislative agency, LI said that the government will “provide subsidies for child care” at a time when the high children's education costs are one of the main obstacles cited by Chinese couples to have children. "We will vigorously develop integrated children's care and kindergarten services," Li said, adding that the "offering inclusive child care services will be increased."
During reading the government's work report, I Li Qiang, which set the goal of China's economic growth to 2025 by “about 5%”, stressed the importance of “promoting home support services to the elderly and“ reinforcing care for dependents ”.
He also indicated that “the progressive postponement of the legal age for the reform”, a plan already advanced by Beijing in recent years, “will be implemented with prudence”.
It is estimated that by 2035 more than 400 million Chinese will be over 60 years old, representing about one third of the population, with the consequent negative impact on the country's workforce and economy.
China registered a decline of the population in 2022, 2023 and 2024, the first contractions since 1961, when the number of inhabitants decreased as a result of the failure of the great leap industrialization policy in front and the followed hunger. The country registered 9.54 million births last year, slightly above 9.02 million recorded in 2023, the lowest value since 1949.
Despite the various policies announced by the authorities, both local and national, to try to create a “in favor of parenting”, local experts attributed the growth in the number of births last year to the fact that some families postponed their parenting plans between 2020 and 2022 due to the pandemic and the effect of 2024 being the year of the China Dragon, considered conducive to maternity.
Chinese delegates in APN will propose to make sex education mandatory in schools, create services to detect diseases that affect fertility in children without children, and incorporate the cervical cancer vaccine in the public system, due to its impact on female fertility.
Other possible proposals include widening insurance coverage for medically assisted reproduction techniques, prolongation of paternity leave or even reducing the legal age of marriage to 18 years (currently 22 for men and 20 for women), as well as the elimination of restrictions on the number of children, fixed in three from 2021.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:04+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>COVID-19 cases on the rise. Variant JN.1 will stay active in the coming weeks</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/casos-de-covid-19-em-ascensao-variante-jn-1-vai-manter-se-activa-nas-proximas-semanas/</link><description>Unlike influenza virus infections, which have been decreasing, health authorities warn that other respiratory viruses are in a growing trend. It stands out COVID-19, whose positivity rate went from 3.8% to 13.7% in a week. 
 
The flu virus is in a descending trend, currently being below the alert level. On the other hand, cases of coronavirus infection-more specifically, by the coronavirus JN.1 variant-continue to spread in the Macao region.
According to data provided by health services, the positive influenza virus detection rate has been decreasing, falling from 10.5% in the eighth week of the year (between 19 and 25 February) to 5.4% in the ninth week (between February 26 and March 3). Both weeks were therefore below the alert level, corresponding to 13.1%.
The positivity rate of the new coronavirus variant increased significantly from 3.8% to 13.7% in the same period. The detection of other respiratory viruses has also grown from eighth to ninth week, stressing the entering/rhinovirus (with an increase of 19.5%) and metapneumovirus (7.6%).
In a statement, health services predict that the new coronavirus “keep active in the coming weeks” and appeal to the population to reinforce precautionary measures - namely, through vaccination against the JN.1 coronavirus. High -risk groups (such as the elderly, people with chronic diseases or people with low immunity) should even reinforce protection with antiviral drugs within five days after infection, in order to effectively reduce the risk of severe illness and death.
Despite the increase in COVID-19 cases and the approximation of spring-the season most favorable to the spread of respiratory tract diseases-health authorities report that the general situation of respiratory infectious diseases in Macao is “stable, with the presence of a wide range of respiratory viruses, all admittedly endemic” and “with ordinary pathogenic agents”.
 
New case of collective infection by Covid-19
 
According to data available until Tuesday, March 4, in 2025 46 cases of respiratory diseases were recorded. Of these, 25 were caused by the influenza A virus, five by the influenza B virus and five by other breathing pathogenic agents, ten were "indeterminate."
The most recent case, making up the 46 cases, was notified to health services this Monday, being an episode of collective infection by the JN.1 variant. The situation occurred at the Harmonia Elderly Home, located at Avenida do Vale das Seac Pai Van butterflies, and affected six female users.
Since February 28, patients expressed symptoms of the upper respiratory tract, such as fever and nasal discharge, confirming covid-19 infection with a rapid antigen test. Patients are currently in a stable state without complications or serious diseases resulting from infection.
Health services recall that preventive measures against COVID-19 and other infectious diseases are similar: in addition to vaccination, the population is advised to follow a healthy and balanced lifestyle and maintain good personal hygiene. If symptoms arise, patients are advised to rest at home and seek medical advice as quickly as possible if symptoms get worse.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:52:58+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China announces an increase of 7.2% in the defense budget</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/china-anuncia-aumento-de-72-no-orcamento-da-defesa/</link><description>China announced yesterday that it will increase defense spending by 7.2%in 2025, in line with the previous year, in a context of geopolitical rivalry with the United States and tensions with Taiwan.
 
The budget was announced at the opening of the plenary session of the National Popular Assembly (APN), the Asian country's maximum legislative body. The increase is the same as last year and is far below the percentage values ​​of two digits of the previous decade, reflecting a general slowdown of the economy. The country's leaders set a GDP growth goal of about 5% for this year.
Beijing plans to spend the equivalent of 231 billion euros in defense - about three times less than Washington.
China's military expenses are, however, the second largest in the world, behind the United States.
This announcement comes after US President Donald Trump proposed in February a summit with Chinese President Xi Jinping and Russian President Vladimir Putin to negotiate a reduction in defense budgets of the three great powers. Beijing opposite that Washington should take over the initiative.
The announcement also comes at a time when Europeans are considering a large increase in military budgets, given Trump's disinterest in the transatlantic alliance.
China has argued that it has a "defensive" military policy and that the sole purpose is to preserve sovereignty - which implies, however, the potential achievement of areas considered national territory. This is the case of Taiwan, most of the southern sea islets - where Beijing recorded several incidents with the Philippines last year - and the Senkaku Islands - controlled by Japan.
In addition to having the largest permanent army in the world, China has the largest navy and recently launched the third aircraft carrier. The country has a huge reserve of missiles, fighters, war ships capable of throwing nuclear weapons, advanced surface ships and nuclear -powered submarines.
China also has a military base in Djibuti, in the horn of Africa, and modernized the Naval base of Ream in Cambodia, which offers it a semi -permanent presence in the Gulf of Thailand, facing the Southern Sea of ​​China.
To justify the increase in military expenses, Beijing stressed the need to improve the living conditions of soldiers, exercise or have better equipment.
“Expenses focus on technological update, restructuring forces, expansion of naval and aerospace capabilities” and “nuclear deterassion,” said Adam Ni, Australian analyst and author of the China Neican report. "It remains reasonable, especially because Europeans are also increasing their expenses in the face of Ukraine's Russian invasion and threats to European security," said Niklas Swanström, director of the Institute for Safety and Development Policy (ISDP), a Stockholm -based investigation organization.
Regarding China's economic weight, military expenses remain moderate. In 2023, they represented 1.67% of GDP. Far behind Russia (5.86%) and the United States (3.36%). "Although China's defense budget is increasing in absolute terms, it represents about 5%of total public expenses, well below the United States (9%) and Russia (more than 30%)," said Adam Ni, suggesting that China "is not developing excessive national resources to its militarization."
In terms of armament, China has “improved considerably, but is still late in the US Army in many respects, namely in terms of having its own stealthy strategic bomberfish,” noted James Char, professor at Nanyang University Technology in Singapore.
The United States has "an army designed to conduct operations abroad and have a global influence," Adam Ni said, but China intends "first of all to be a regional military power." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:02+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Firefighters advise population to pay attention to gas stoves</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/bombeiros-aconselham-populacao-a-prestar-atencao-aos-fogoes-a-gas/</link><description>After the fire on Monday, in the neighborhood of Tamagnini Barbosa, which will have occurred following a gas leakage, the Fire Department (CB) warns the population to pay “high attention” to the use of gas stoves.
"Citizens and sectors are expected to reinforce surveillance and prevention and do the safety matters related to the use and installation of gas stove appliances, in order to jointly ensure the safety of life and goods," says the CB in a press release released yesterday.
Firefighters also indicated that, from 2019, inspections were carried out to gas stove devices at home, together with residents' associations and organizations and community security heads. By February this year, 1,742 home inspections have already made. During the inspections, the safety specifications, the place of installation and the expiration date of the gas stove pipe were verified.
Inspections to gas stove devices performed at home are aimed at eliminating potential safety risks, but CB notes that, "due to privacy issues, many citizens do not want to coordinate and have a relatively negative attitude, because tasks on home inspections have not had satisfactory results."
Still, "CB has been striving to maintain close cooperation with residents' associations and organizations and community security heads, in order to constantly develop inspections to home stove devices in home, actively disclose information on public fire safety through various channels and strengthening safety awareness."</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:49:42+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM with profit in 2024 after four years of damage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/sjm-com-lucro-em-2024-apos-quatro-anos-de-prejuizos/</link><description>SJM Holdings game concessionaire announced a $ three million profit from Hong Kong in 2024 after unprecedented losses for four consecutive years.
In a statement sent on Tuesday to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, the company founded by the late game tycoon Stanley Hung Sun recalled that he had a loss of $ 2.01 billion from Hong Kong in 2023.
SJM casinos raised Hong Kong's $ 28.8 billion, 35.9% more than the previous year, while revenues did not play 22.9% to Hong Kong's $ 1.92 billion.
With the revenues to rise, the company registered an operating profit of $ 3.76 billion from Hong Kong, more than twice than in 2023.
Over last year, SJM was able to reduce total debt by 6% to Hong Kong's $ 26.5 billion at the end of December.
On January 22, the Fitch Ratings Financial Notation Agency maintained the SJM debt classification. Fitch said Grand Lisboa Palace forced SJM to accumulate a high level of debt.
The company said on Tuesday that Grand Lisboa Palace went from losses by 2023 to Hong Kong's $ 499 million operating profit last year.
The revenues of the new SJM venture more than doubled, reaching $ 6.58 billion from Hong Kong.
The mass market represented 82.4% of the company's casinos revenues, while the VIP game was a 9.3% slice.
The big bets, which in 2019 represented 46.2% of the revenues of Macao casinos, were affected by the arrest of the leader of the world's largest VIP betting company in November 2021.
The SJM said it will completely renew every room of Grand Lisbon, as well as increasing the number of rooms “by conversion of old areas reserved for junkets”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:49+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean deputy says Pyongyang is training more soldiers for the war</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/deputado-sul-coreano-diz-que-pyongyang-esta-a-treinar-mais-soldados-para-a-guerra/</link><description>The party deputy in power in South Yo Yong-Weon Korea said yesterday that 3,500 North Korean soldiers are being trained to integrate Russian forces on combat fronts in Ukraine. According to Yo Yong-Weon, who recently visited Ukraine, the North Korean military is currently doing preparation training in Russia's territory.
The South Korean politician cited, on the new Detachment of North Korea, a document by the maximum responsible for Kiev information services.   "About 3,500 North Korean soldiers are receiving ground adaptation training at five sites from the Far East of Russia and there is a possibility of forming a third detachment," Yu said in the press release issued today in Seoul.
In recent months, Pyongyang has transferred troops in two phases. The first contingent of about 11,000 soldiers was sent in October last year to Russia and a second group of 1,500 staff was highlighted between January and February.
According to Yu, the second group has already completed the adaptation training and is fighting on the front line in Kursk, Ukraine.
On February 26, Ukrainian information services indicated that about 400 North Korean soldiers were killed in combat. The same source also said that 3,600 North Korean military personnel were injured in combat.
During the recent visit to Ukraine, Yu met with North Korean prisoners.
Submission of troops and military material is part of the strategic partnership agreement signed between North Korean leader Kim Jong-un and Russian head of state Vladimir Putin in June 2024, which allowed the provision of North Korean weapons to Russia and the progressive incorporation of Pyongyang troops in the conflict.
Under the agreement, North Korea sent to Russia artillery, missiles and other conventional weapons used against Ukraine forces.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:56:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese government reiterates support to Macau and Hong Kong in improving the welfare of the population</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/governo-chines-reitera-apoio-a-macau-e-hong-kong-na-melhoria-do-bem-estar-da-populacao/</link><description>Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang has signaled support for Macau and Hong Kong in his economic development and the improvement of population welfare. He also expressed the hope of RAE to work for international exchange and national integration. In a work report presented at the National Popular Assembly, I Li Qiang also urged Macao to join the principle of governance by Patriots. The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, says he will lead society to learn the spirit of the “two sessions” and promises defense to national security.
 
Beijing acknowledged that it will give greater support to the improvement of the well-being of the population of Macau and Hong Kong and the deepening of international exchange and cooperation in the RAE, revealed Chinese prime minister, Li Qiang, at the opening of the Annual Plenary Session of the National Popular Assembly (APN).
According to the report on the government's work presented yesterday at the country's top legislative agency, Li Qiang, representing the State Council, also advocated the importance of promoting the integration of Macau and Hong Kong in the conjuncture of national development, as well as the economic growth of RAE.
The Prime Minister, while reading the report, again appealed to the “comprehensive, precise and unshakable implementation” of the 'one country, two systems' principles, 'Hong Kong ruled by their people' and 'Macau ruled by their people' with a high degree of autonomy.
It urged, however, to the special administrative regions to join governance only by patriots. "[We have to defend the Constitution, safeguard the constitutional order of the RAE, as established in the Constitution and Basic Law, implement the principles of 'Hong Kong governed by Patriots' and 'Macao governed by Patriots'," said the politician, highlighting the need to maintain prosperity and long -term stability of Hong Kong and Macao.
The third session of the 14th APN started yesterday and takes place until March 11, next Tuesday. Li Qiang announced in the opening session several policies and work goals for this year. In the part dedicated to RAE's affairs, compared to last year's, the report added the highlight to international exchanges and cooperation.
Still in the document Li Qiang talked about Taiwan and stressed that he “resolutely opposes the independence of Taiwan and the interference of external forces”, reaffirming that he is based on the principle of “one China” and the “consensus of 1992”.
In this case, it assumed the promotion of the “peaceful development of relationships between the two sides of the Strait”, including “improving the system and policies to promote exchanges and economic and cultural cooperation” and “deepen integration and development” between the two sides of the narrow.
 
Sam Hou Fai thanks support from the central government
 
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, expressed his gratitude to the Central Government for the attention and support of the MSAR and ensured that it will, together with all sectors of the community, study and implement the spirit of the “two sessions”, APN and the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC).
Present yesterday at APN's opening session in Beijing to “learn the important spirit” of the government's work on Li Qiang's work, Sam Hou Fai highlighted, in a press release, the determination to take advantage of the opportunities brought to Macau for the “advance of Chinese style modernization” in the country.
“The Government of MSar will follow the provisions of the central government to deepen the comprehensive reform to translate the spirit of the 'two sessions' into practical actions. Through the reinforcement of interdepartal coordination and political articulation, it will increase the effectiveness and level of governance, ”he said.
Sam Hou Fai reiterated, by the way, the effort in promoting economic diversification and building a higher level opening platform to the exterior, in order to effectively enhance Macau as an interlocutor between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
According to the statement, Sam said he was still committed to following the instructions given by Chinese President Xi Jinping during his visit to Macau late last year, continuing to implement, unshakable, comprehensive and accurately, the principle 'one country, two systems'. He indicated that the MSAR should also continue to safeguard the sovereignty, security and interests of the country's development, "since national security is the fundamental principle for" a country, two systems, "he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:53:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibition “The Legend of Tea Song” celebrates 25 years of the Macao Chinese Tea Association</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/exposicao-a-lenda-do-cha-song-celebra-25-anos-da-associacao-de-cha-chines-de-macau/</link><description>On March 9, the Center for Culture and Performative Arts Cardinal Newman receives the exhibition “The Legend of Song Tea: Old Jian Zhan Cups and Tianmu Cups”. Celebrating the 25th anniversary of the Macao Chinese Tea Association, the event highlights the cultural inheritances of the Song dynasty and the evolution of the art of preparation, with emphasis on the iconic “Jian” and “Tianmu” cups. A rock on history and beauty surrounding the millennial traditions of the Chinese continent.
 
The Macau Chinese Tea Association invites the general public and tea culture enthusiasts to the inauguration of the unprecedented exhibition entitled “The Legend of Song Tea: Old Jian Zhan Cups and Tianmu Cups”. The event, which includes workshops, will take place at the Cardinal Newman Culture and Performative Arts Center, located on the Walk Country, and will start at 11 am on March 9th. This initiative will mark the association's 25th anniversary, highlighting the rich cultural heritage linked to tea during the Song Dynasty of the ancient Imperial China.
The exhibition is not limited to celebrating the history and impact of tea on Chinese culture, but also presents the famous Jian and Tianmu cups, both known for its superior quality and unique aesthetics. Coming from the city of Jianyang, in the province of Fujian, Jian cups are admired for their ability to highlight the taste of tea and the diversity of patterns that can result from the burning process.
Visitors will have the opportunity to discover the story behind the Tianmu cups, with an origin linked to the Holy Monte Tianmu in southwest China. Known as “heavenly bowls”, these precious ones were adopted by Japanese monks who, impressed by their beauty and usefulness, brought them back to Japan, where they became an essential part of the Japanese tea ceremony.
The legend of tea Song begins with the Song Dynasty, which covered the period between 960 and 1279. Recognized as one of the most prolific times in China's history. During this period, the country attended a large cultural flowering and advanced technological progress in the domains of agriculture, textiles, metallurgy and ceramic. The famous five furnaces - Guan, GE, Ru, Jun and Ding - signed China as a power of world porcelain. More than a mere drink, tea acquired a unique prestige, especially with the evolution of preparation methods that turned the drink from the old boiling method of tea powder, emerged in the Tang Dynasty, to the way to “beat” the leaves to create a different texture in the drink, which characterized the Song era.
Among the innovations, we highlight the evolution of tea tools, which went from 24 utensils in the Tang Dynasty to just three main ones in the Song era: the tea bowl, the beater and the hot water kettle. This simplicity not only reflected a stylistic change, but also a new way of enjoying tea, promoting a more Zen and refined experience.
Emperor Huizong, famous for his love for art and ceramics, left a significant legacy. It served as an inept military leader and corrupt political boss, but was the author of the only treaty written by an emperor about the tradition of tea, entitled “The Great Treaty on Tea”, praised the cultivation and preparation of tea of ​​his time, highlighting the black enamel tea cups known as “hare hair cups”, produced in Jian'an. These precious artifacts have gained a special place in the hearts of tea lovers, becoming national treasures in Japan.
The show “The Legend of Tea Song” is an exhibition that can be seen as an invitation to reflect on how this ancestral drink remains a bridge between cultures and eras. The event will be divided into three parts, one starting at 11am, where the lecture will introduce the “Tianmu Cup Secrets”, to the first 30 subscribers on the association's official page. The other two sessions also have vacancies limited to only 10 people each. The Japanese tea workshop is scheduled for 3:30 pm and the second workshop, titled “The Seven Techniques for Making Emperor Huizong's Song Tea”, will start at 16h. Registration and participation is free.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government admits to review requirements for assignment of subsidies to caregivers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/governo-admite-rever-requisitos-de-atribuicao-de-subsidios-a-cuidadores/</link><description>In response to an interpellation of Deputy Wong Kit Cheng, who reflected on the need to expand the reach of subsidies to people with disabilities and their families, the government did not exclude the hypothesis of reviewing some of the criteria for attributing social support. Although in Macau there are about 2,500 people with serious and deep disabilities, until April 2024 only 260 families had been aimed at government support.
 
The Government of the MSAR admits to review some of the requirements of assignment of subsidies to caregivers of elderly and people with disabilities, taking into account the current economic context of the region.
In response to a written interpellation presented by Wong Kit Cheng, deputy to the Legislative Assembly of MSAR, Hon Wai, the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), began by remembering that the subsidy for caregivers "is just one of the numerous subsidies in cash" that the government attributes to "needy" families of people with disabilities.
Among the other forms of support available to eligible families include, for example, subsidies and pensions for the elderly and invalid, as well as the “permanent support mechanism” for families with economic difficulties. "If these families do not have sufficient economic resources to meet their basic needs, they may require subsidy from IAS," he added.
Currently, to benefit the support, families must meet the “basic requirements” and pass the assessment test of the financial situation of the household. Given the concerns of Deputy Wong Kit Cheng, which suggested not to include the value of heritage in the application requirements to include a larger number of beneficiaries, Hon Wai recalled that these criteria are indispensable “for the purpose of assessing the economic aggregate situation (…), in order to ensure that the target beneficiary of that subsidy is a family with low income”.
Still, the government admits to consider some of the requirements in the face of generalized economic pressure in Macao that affects, above all, the most disadvantaged social layers. This revision will apply, in particular, on the “amount of the subsidy, the total monthly income from the household and the maximum limit of active values”.
In parallel, the president of IAS continues, "the requirement for 'habitual residence' will be considered within the scope of caregivers in order to create a similar or closer life environment for Macao residents residing in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin."
Hon Wai guarantees that the MSAR government “will continue to focus primary care about the provision of different support services” to caregivers' families, in particular the economically needed, “in order to alleviate physical and psychological pressure” to which they are subject.
The same responsible explained that the revision of the measures, when implemented, will come together with the other efforts already in force to meet the needs of these demographic groups, including free health care, rehabilitation training and temporary reception services. There are also support programs and resource centers specifically aiming at caregivers, in order to provide “emotional support and counseling”.
Since December 2023, the “Pilot Project of the Subsidy for Caregivers” formally became a permanent measure, ensuring the assignment of subsidies to four types of recipients who need continued third party care in their daily lives: permanent bedridden, people with intellectual disabilities, people with autism and people with severe or deep motor disabilities.
The government's response is followed by a written interpellation presented by Wong Kit Cheng, deputy to the Legislative Assembly of the MSAR, where it expressed apprehension with the current economic context in Macao and its impact on the most needy families. In the document, the deputy drew attention to the fact that the plan had only 260 families until April 2024, leaving no “effective support” other “special patients” who, although “need care 24 hours a day” do not fully fit the program criteria, such as people with autism or children with special needs.
According to statistical data from the Institute of Social Action, cited by the deputy, until December 31, 2024 were in Macao 578 people with deep and deep intellectual disabilities and 1,911 people with severe and deep physical disabilities.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:54:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing warns that it will resist until the end if they continue with trade war</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/pequim-avisa-que-resistira-ate-ao-fim-se-eua-continuarem-com-guerra-comercial/</link><description>China warned yesterday that it will “resist until the end” if the United States “insists on harming Chinese interests,” in response to the new customs imposed by Washington on Asian country products.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian reiterated at a press conference that Beijing "firmly opposes" the US decision to use Fentanil as an excuse for applying more rates on Chinese exports. "If the US really wants to solve the problem of Fentanil, they should negotiate with China based on equality, respect and mutual benefit," said the spokesman.
Lin Jian said he had not seen the Chinese embassy statements in the United States, which China is "ready for any kind of war," but insisted that Beijing made its position clear. "We urge the US to abandon its intimidation tactics and to return to the right way of dialogue and cooperation as soon as possible," he concluded.
The Chinese executive defended in a white book on the fentanil released the day before, which took rigorous measures against production and fentanyl trafficking and its chemical precursors.
The Chinese government also stated that it has actively promoted the construction of a traceability system using new technologies to monitor any links to production, transportation, importation and exportation of these drugs.
Trump said 90% of death consumption deaths in the US is due to Fentanil. Washington argues that opiates arrive through Mexico and Canada, but whose precursors come from China.
In his first presidency (2017-2021), Trump has already had a tense relationship with Beijing, imposing several rounds of about $ 370 billion (346 billion euros) annually, which China responded with rates on US exports.
Washington announced this week the duplication for 20% of rates on Chinese products, which led Beijing to respond at 10% and 15% rates on US agricultural imports.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:01+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Proportion of the elderly in the face of the total population has grown the pique in the last 10 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/proporcao-de-idosos-face-a-populacao-total-cresceu-a-pique-nos-ultimos-10-anos/</link><description>Over the past 10 years, the proportion of the elderly population of Macau compared to the total population has risen the pique. In 2014, the elderly were only 8.4% of the total population; By the end of last year, the share of the population over 65 already corresponded to 14.6%.
 
In the last decade, the population of Macau has been considerably older. The idea is confirmed by the region's demographic statistics released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), which show that the population over 65 is equivalent to 14.6% of the total.
According to the data available on the body's electronic page, analyzed by the end point, in the last ten years a bump has been registered in the proportion of the elderly. In 2014, only 8.4% of the population was considered elderly, which reveals an increase of more than six percentage points.
At the end of 2023, the proportion of the elderly was 14%. This year, the elderly population exceeded the young population for the first time. Over the past ten years, there has been a gradual increase in the slice of the elderly population, and the only decrease went from 2020 to 2021.
In 2024, the proportion of young people, from zero to 14 years, was 12.5% ​​of the total population, also show DSEC data. In the previous year, this proportion was 13.2%.
DSEC data also reveal that Macao's total population consisted of 688,300 people at the end of 2024, with a slight growth of 0.7% in annual terms, “mainly due to the increase in the number of non-resident workers,” explains the body. The female and male population represented 53.7% and 46.3% of the total population, respectively.
The local population was, at the end of last year, 568,700 people, lowering 0.4%in annual terms. The number of household aggregates in Macau totaled 205,000, another 600 in annual terms.
In 2024, 3,607 undead were registered (105 less, in annual terms) and the birth rate dropped 0.2 permitting points to 5.3 per thousand. Last year there were also 2,477 deaths (minus 504, in annual terms). The mortality rate dropped 0.8 permit points to 3.6 per thousand. Analyzing by previous causes of death, the highest death number was due to malignant tumors (937), corresponding to 37.8% of total deaths, followed by deaths from heart (362) and pneumonia (268), representing 14.6% and 10.8% of the total deaths, respectively.
As for the movements of the population, in the year of reference there were 3,677 individuals from the interior of the newly arrived China to Macao holders from Single Holiday (plus 260, in annual terms), 64.8% of which were female. In 2024 there were 1,074 individuals to whom a new residence permit was granted in Macao (another 196, in annual terms), mostly from Hong Kong (364).
DSEC also accounted for 3,187 marriages in 2024 (19 more, compared to 2023) and the nuptial rate equivalent to 4.6 per thousand, less 0.1 points of allowance. The median of age to the first marriage of men (31.4 years) and women (29.7 years) increased both 0.2 years. There were 1,361 divorces (another 62, compared to 2023) and the divorce rate stood by 2.0 per thousand, plus 0.1 points.
In the fourth quarter of 2024 alone, 987 number of undead were held, plus 77 compared to the third quarter of 2024. The number of deaths corresponded to 611, plus 13, in quarterly terms, with the three main causes of death tumors (237), circulatory diseases (168) and respiratory tract diseases (49). In the quarter under analysis there were 1,232 individuals from the interior of the newly arrived China to Macao holders from the unique safe conduct (another 358, compared to the third quarter of 2024) and a new residence permit was granted in Macau to 286 individuals (minus 31). 873 marriages were registered, plus 221, in quarterly terms.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Alfredo Cunha: Portraits of a transition continent on display at Rota das Letras</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/alfredo-cunha-retratos-de-um-continente-em-transicao-em-exposicao-no-rota-das-letras/</link><description>Light and Fight. Part of the 14th Macau Literary Festival - Rota das Letras, the new exhibition of photojournalist Alfredo Cunha celebrates 50 years of the independence of African Portuguese -speaking countries, in its 50 years of photographic career. With images from countries such as Angola and Mozambique, the show, cured by João Miguel Barros, is organized on five topics that explore the independence process of these rapidly growing nations. The presentation enriches the festival through photography, promoting a dialogue on cultural identity and historical memory, without limiting itself to words.
 
The 14th Macao Literary Festival, which runs from March 21 to 30, stands out for its theme centered on poetry, its various forms of expression and, this year, the celebration of the 50th anniversary of the Independence of African countries of Portuguese Language. The series of events provides a unique platform for reflection on literature and culture, and increasingly the poetry that is found in the contrasts of photography.
This year the festival includes an exhibition of the renowned Portuguese photojournalist Alfredo Cunha. Titled “New Independence”, the show brings together a selection of 52 carefully selected images of your file, captured over nearly five decades and offer a graphic testimony of independence processes in several African nations.
Immortalized by his photograph of Salgueiro Maia during that iconic Thursday, Alfredo Cunha, born in Celorico da Beira and born in 1953, began his career in professional photography in 1970. His professional career includes collaborations with several newspapers and news agencies, and his position as official photographer Mário Soares and António Ramalho eas. Over the years, Alfredo Cunha has become a reference in photojournalism in Portugal, having documented historical events of unique relevance, from the events that gave rise to the Cloves Revolution, the conflicts of the colonial war and its reminiscences. His works are recognized not only for aesthetic quality, but also for their ability to capture the essence of the crucial moments that shaped the contemporary history of Portugal and their former colonies.
As stressed in statements to the end, the photographs exhibited in Macao cover a wide range of places and events. “They are Africa photographs taken in Angola, Guinea, Mozambique, Cape Verde, Sao Tome and Principe and Timor, photographed between 1973 and 2019,” explained Alfredo Cunha. This selection would not only be a photographic exercise, but a trip through collective memory, a record of the complexities and challenges of the political and social transitions experienced by the various peoples and nations involved, highlighting their trajectory in search of autonomy and cultural identity, after 500 years of colonization.
The curator of the exhibition, João Miguel Barros, emphasized the magnitude of this work. “This exhibition is a challenge that I think will be fabulous, and it is a project that I have been working on for some time with the photographer too,” said Barros. The initial idea was to perform a great exhibition, which was postponed due to logistical issues, but this sectoral version offers a new perspective on a theme that is contemporary and timeless, and is a special images selection. "Alfredo is one of the great Portuguese photographers, with over 50 years of career celebrated ... and the starting point was basically the 50th anniversary of independence," said the curator.
João Miguel Barros divided the exhibition into five themes: “places”, “weapons”, “matches and new arrivals”, “people” and “rituals”. This structure not only categorizes photographs, but also offers a narrative that connects the various dimensions of the colonial and postcolonial experience. "It is a little more conceptual and was based on this subdivision that this exposure of new independence was built," he said, emphasizing the intention to provide visitors with a profound understanding of contexts and meanings behind images, in the already recognized style of Cunha, with high contrast and all black and white.
The importance of presenting this exhibition in Macau is except by Alfredo Cunha, who mentioned: "Macau is a part of China where Portuguese is still spoken, and the importance of China in all areas, namely cultural, cannot be ignored." This linguistic and cultural connection makes the exposure particularly relevant to the territory, offering a space for reflection on the unprecedented stories of African independence and its direct relationship with the Portuguese presence.
The exhibition will be inaugurated on March 21, in tune with the official opening of the festival, in the old slaughterhouse of Barra, and will be exposed throughout the event, allowing visitors to immerse themselves in the visual narratives proposed by Cunha.
Alfredo Cunha will not be present during the opening, but this necessary dialogue about history, colonialism and new independence will have the presence of the curator, João Miguel Barros, during the opening. A unique opportunity for Macao audiences to connect with the visual narrative of one of the most significant Portuguese photojournalists, while celebrating literature and poetry as forms of resistance and cultural expression.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Surplus of public accounts falls almost a third in January</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/excedente-das-contas-publicas-cai-quase-um-terco-em-janeiro/</link><description>Macao finished January with a public account surplus 32% lower than in the same month of 2024, especially due to a slowdown in the game's recipes. The surplus set out at 3.68 billion patacas, according to the latest online data by finance services.
In addition, it was the first year since 2020, at the beginning of the pandemic, that the territory was able to keep accounts on positive land, something required by the basic law, without transfers from the financial reserve.
The main reason for the reduction in surplus was a 20% drop in current revenue, to 8.39 billion patacas, due to taxes on the game, which represented 85.7% of the total.
Macao's game revenues fell 5.6% in January, compared to the same month of 2024, to less than 18.3 billion Patacas despite the New Year Lunar, a high time for tourism.
In January, Macau collected 7.5% of the projected current revenue for 2025 in the region's budget, which is 112.6 billion patacas.
In early December, the Macao Study Center and the University of Macao Economics Department foresaw that revenues should be smaller than the government's estimated: 111.8 billion patacas.
The surplus of the territory shrunk despite the public expense designed 7% in January, to 72 billion patacas, mainly due to investment in infrastructure, which fell to less than half.
The Macao Government spent 594.6 million patacas under the administration's investment and expenses plan, 52.9% compared to January 2024. On the contrary, current expense increased by 8.2% to 4.12 billion patacas, mainly due to a 12.9% rise in social support and subsidies given to the population.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:48+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation dynamizes discussion about “The Book of San Michele”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/fundacao-rui-cunha-dinamiza-discussao-sobre-o-livro-de-san-michele/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation presents today, at 18:30, a session of the Reading Club of the Association of Friends of Macau entitled “The Book of San Michele”. The event focuses on the namesake book of Swedish physician and writer Axel Munthe, who became one of the most read works of the twentieth century after publication in 1929.
The conversation will be coordinated by Natália Santos and Rui Rocha and held in Portuguese, with free admission. In a press release, the Foundation states that all members and interested parties are invited to participate in the discussion and share questions and impressions about the work.
"The Book of San Michele" (or "The Story of San Michele" in the original English) fuses autobiographical and fictional elements of the author's own memories, with the backdrop of Anacapri's Italian village. It is, moreover, deeply dichotomous in all its aspects, as the Rui Cunha Foundation note highlights: “It contains drama and humor, it is sarcastic and sentimental, literary and journalistic, true and false; In other words, as full of contradictions as its author. ”
In the press release, the book is summarized as "a mixture of stories of medical practice [of the author], namely medicine and death, as well as personal reflections on the fragility and spiritual magnitude of human existence, their devoted love for animals and various encounters, both humble and illustrious people."
Doctor, psychiatrist, naturalist, philanthropist and writer, Alex Munthe has established friendship relationships with various celebrities and members of the European elite, highlighting, in particular, the proximity to Swedish royalty. He died at the age of 91 at the Stockholm Royal Palace, as the Court's official guest.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing with ambitious goal for GDP, but insufficient budgetary support, analysts say</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/pequim-com-meta-ambiciosa-para-pib-mas-apoio-orcamental-insuficiente-dizem-analistas/</link><description>The purpose of growth set by the Chinese authorities for this year, of “about 5%”, is ambitious, but the increase in the budgetary deficit will be insufficient to prevent the economy from recovering, warned analysts.
 
“Chinese politicians have maintained an ambitious goal for the actual GDP growth [Gross Domestic Product], but are more cautious in their predictions for nominal growth and inflation. And although they have announced an increase in fiscal support, the degree of flexibility is more moderate than it seems, ”wrote Julian Evans-Pritchard, an analyst at Capital Economics consultant, in a report.
The expert said he was skeptical about the possibility that the announced measures avoid a slowdown on growth in 2025, marked by "contrary winds in the international scenario and the absence of a more pronounced change in public expenses to support consumption."
After reserving a record percentage of expenses for investment in 2024, Beijing now seems to turn more to consumption, "though nothing extraordinary", equivalent to $ 41.3 billion (38.5 billion euros) in obligations to finance the government's "renewal plan" for appliances or electronic, the analyst noted.
Hong Hao of Chinese active manager Grow Investment Group, noted that this year's official report is what most often mentions the word 'consumption' in a decade, but Evans-Pritchard pointed out that authorities “are not having a considerable impulse” in the form of reflection (the artificial stimulus of the state economy, usually to exceed a recession).
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang said yesterday that the objective of economic growth for the current fiscal year is “about 5%” for the third consecutive year, and that the fiscal deficit will be increased at a percentage point to 4%as part of government efforts to relaunch recovery.
Despite the “largest increase in decades” in the ratio between deficit and GDP, Evans-Pritchard estimated that, taking into account other factors, the actual increase in expense will be about 1.5%, lower than previous flexibility cycles such as 2015 (2%) and 2020 (3.6%).
Cited by Bloomberg Financial News Agency, Charu Chanana of the Saxo Markets Stock Exchange Trading Platform, said the objectives revealed by Li “are within expectations” and show that the authorities are still “keeping ammunition for later”, an analysis that deserved the agreement of Lee Homin, from Swiss Bank Lombard Odier, who believes Beijing could adjust the objective of the year of the year, when it becomes clear the impact of Washington's customs imposed on goods from China.
The latest projections of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the World Bank (BM) point to Chinese GDP growth of about 4.5%after growing 5%in 2024, driven by extra effort by the authorities at the end of the year. However, the capital Economics doubts that China has grown 5% last year, as official numbers indicate, and argues that this rate was, in fact, about 4.4%.
Evans-Pritchard pointed out that the goal for inflation, which went from 3%last year to 2%, is the lowest since 2003, and noted that "it is unlikely that the Popular Bank of China [Central Bank] do everything necessary to bring" the indicator back to this level: "a lower goal suggests some official acceptance of the current deflationary environment."
The expert also referred to the official promise of maintaining the Chinese currency exchange rate, Yuan, "usually stable to an adaptable and balanced level": "It is a repetitive language and does not exclude new depreciation at some point this year, especially if the US -imposed rates continue to increase."
The weak internal and international demand, associated with the risks of deflation, insufficient stimuli, a profound real estate crisis and the lack of confidence of consumers and the private sector are some of the causes pointed out by analysts to explain what is happening in the world's second largest economy. This joins the intensification of the trade war with the US after Donald Trump's return to the White House. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:55:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao proposals to the Chinese political advisory agency address medical services on Mountain Island</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/06/propostas-de-macau-ao-orgao-consultivo-politico-chines-abordam-servicos-medicos-na-ilha-da-montanha/</link><description>Macao representatives in China's leading political advisory body are aware of the medical service between the territory and the mountain island. Alvis Lo, director of health services, asks to make it easier to share the use of medicines and vaccines between the two locations, while businessman Frederico MA proposes the creation of a great bay acupuncture training center. Several members of the Chinese people's political advisory conference have also suggested a system for residents of Macau and Hong Kong to volunteer in Guangdong.
 
Alvis Lo, a member of Macao at the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), advocates measures to make the use of medicines and biological preparation easier, such as vaccines, from Macao in Hengqin.
The director of health services also considers that the Macao government should create an interdepartal coordination mechanism to simplify the process of approving hengqin drug transport, with the aim of benefiting the lives of Macao residents living on Mountain Island and “contributing to an environment similar to life in Macau” on the other side of the border.
The third session of the 14th CCPPC is taking place in Beijing, to which Macao deputies in this Chinese political advisory body have submitted several proposals. Quoted by the newspaper or Mun, Alvis Lo pointed out that there are many challenges and obstacles to the convergence of health services between Macau and Hengqin, such as the differences between medical technology standards and drug use standards between the two locations. "The procedures are always complicated to widen the vaccines used in Macau for use in Hengqin, due to the need for coordination between various departments in the interior of China," he explained.
In his document presented to CCPPC, Alvis Lo said he hoped there will be a mechanism for transfringing delivery for clinical medical purposes, assuming biosafety, by creating “closed circuit”, point to point ”or“ white list ”of medicines and vaccines, in order to help develop collaboration between the continent's medical institutions and Macau.
Frederico Ma, president of the Macau Commercial Association, believes Macau should take advantage of his international connection to “build a solid channel for the dissemination of Chinese medicine culture to the outside world”. In this case, it is expected that an “International Center for Acupuncture Training of the Great Bay” in Hengqin will be created.
The entrepreneur also suggested launching acupuncture training courses using translations and publications of teaching materials in English and Portuguese of traditional Chinese medicine.
On the other hand, several members such as Lam Lon Wai, Ia Teng Pio, IP Sio Kai, Alvis Lo, Kou Kam Fai, Chan Wa Keong and Fanny Vong submitted a proposal about voluntary activities to take residents from Macau and Hong Kong to participate in Voluntary Activities in Guangdong in the future.
The group considers that the development of social organizations in Macau has a long history and local volunteer services cover a wide range of areas, so they want to promote the model of volunteering in Macao in the cities of Bay.
The other proposals play on topics such as the Water Supply Guarantee from Zhuhai to Macao, Higher Education of Local Institutions in Hengqin and the businesses of Macao's small and medium enterprises.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06T04:54:57+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>