<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/a-guerra-entre-a-russia-e-a-ucrania-paz-ou-impasse-continuo/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Timorese presidency of ASEAN in 2029 is “great responsibility”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/presidencia-timorense-da-asean-em-2029-e-grande-responsabilidade/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Timor-Leste, Xanana Gusmão, stated yesterday that the Timorese presidency of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), scheduled for 2029, is a great responsibility and will define the perception that the region will have of the country. "This is a great responsibility for our nation and for all our people. We must ensure that we live up to the trust placed in us by our regional partners", stated Xanana Gusmão.
The leader of the Timorese executive was speaking at the first meeting of the National Council for the ASEAN Presidency Organization (ACNOC), held at the Ministry of Finance, in Dili. "Presiding over ASEAN is not just about hosting meetings. It is a test of the State's ability to coordinate, define priorities, budget and execute with discipline", highlighted Xanana Gusmão. "In 2029, our performance will define how the region will perceive Timor-Leste for the next generation. In 2029, the eyes of the world will be on us. It will be, by far, the biggest international event we have ever held", highlighted the Prime Minister.
The Council of Ministers approved in early February the creation of the National Council for the Organization of the Presidency of Timor-Leste of ASEAN in 2029.
This National Council is a central inter-ministerial coordination body responsible for strategic guidance, planning, monitoring and supervision of all preparatory work and the implementation of the ASEAN Presidency. “At this first meeting we decided and approved our action plan for 2026 and also chose the sectors that need to define their leadership to lead the process and the respective committees”, stated the deputy minister for ASENA Affairs, Milena Rangel.
According to Milena Rangel, Timor-Leste's preparations will cover protocol issues, the definition of the country's theme, infrastructure, communication, hospitality, among other aspects. Timor-Leste became a member state of ASEAN in October last year.
ASEAN was created in 1967 by Indonesia, Singapore, Thailand, Malaysia and the Philippines, which currently holds the presidency of the organization, and was later joined by Brunei Darussalam, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar and Vietnam.</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 22:37:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping congratulates Kim Jong-un on re-election as leader of North Korean ruling party</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/xi-jinping-felicita-kim-jong-un-por-reeleicao-como-lider-do-partido-norte-coreano-no-poder/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday congratulated his North Korean counterpart, Kim Jong-un, on his re-election as general secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea, while also highlighting the “friendly relations” between Beijing and Pyongyang.

Xi highlighted in his message that Kim's re-election reflects the "great confidence and sincere support" of the "party, the Government and the people of North Korea", according to the state agency Xinhua, stressing that the party's ninth congress, held at a stage he described as "crucial", is of "important significance".
The Chinese leader also expressed the desire for North Korea to use the occasion as a starting point to boost its political and economic agenda.
The congratulations come one day after the Workers' Party re-elected Kim on the fourth day of the congress, in a session in which, according to the North Korean agency KCNA, the “radical” improvement of the country's military deterrence stood out, with nuclear forces as its central axis.
Xi stated that China and North Korea are “friendly socialist neighbors who support each other” and maintained that maintaining, consolidating and developing bilateral ties is Beijing's constant policy.
The Chinese President indicated that, in a “complex and volatile international situation”, he is “willing” to “strengthen well-being and friendship” between China and North Korea and to “contribute positively to the promotion of regional and global peace, stability, development and prosperity”.
Although both sides have highlighted the improvement in bilateral relations in recent years, Xi did not attend the military parade marking the 80th anniversary of the Founding of the Workers' Party of North Korea, celebrated last October.
The fact that Xi did not attend that North Korean parade, when Kim went to Beijing last September to participate in the Chinese military parade commemorating the 80th anniversary of the end of the Second World War in the Pacific, may highlight limits still present in bilateral relations.
China continues to be North Korea's main trading partner, a country with which it shares a border of more than 1,400 kilometers, in a scenario marked by international sanctions on Pyongyang and growing North Korean military cooperation with Russia.
Kim Jong-un was re-elected general secretary of the Workers' Party at an extraordinary congress, as expected, the official North Korean news agency KCNA reported. The decision was taken “in accordance with the unshakable will and unanimous desire of all delegates” present at the congress, according to the state agency.
The congress, which normally takes place every five years, is the party's most important meeting, a major political event that traditionally reinforces the regime's authority and can serve as a platform to announce political changes or leadership shakeups.
Since the previous congress, in 2021, North Korea has continued to develop its nuclear arsenal and carried out multiple tests of intercontinental ballistic missiles, violating the prohibitions of the United Nations (UN) Security Council.
Pyongyang is subject to several rounds of sanctions over its nuclear weapons programs. The North Korean economy has been stagnant for years and food shortages are chronic.
The Kim dynasty has ruled the country with an 'iron fist' since its founding in 1948, with Kim Jong-un succeeding his father and grandfather. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 22:38:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho wants Macau to be more attractive to visitors</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/coutinho-quer-que-macau-seja-mais-atractiva-para-os-visitantes/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho presented a written statement to the Government asking for measures to reinforce the attractiveness of Macau as a tourist destination, in order to reduce the number of day trippers and increase the average number of nights spent in the region. According to the deputy, the flow of tourists received during concerts or other large events is an opportunity to promote cultural tourism in its various aspects, such as art or gastronomy.

José Pereira Coutinho drew attention to the paradox between the growing number of visitors to Macau and the average number of nights spent in the region, which remains low. In a written statement sent to the Government, the deputy calls for the creation of measures aimed at retaining tourists in Macau and strengthening the city's attractiveness, particularly through the promotion of local culture.
In the message sent to the Executive, Coutinho begins by noting “the substantial increase in large-scale events” in the territory, which include “concerts, seminars, exhibitions and excursions”. Despite the growing tourist flow – which, in fact, reached a new maximum in 2025 –, the average night stay continues to correspond to less than two nights per person.
“This situation derives from the absence of effective measures to justify longer stays”, argues the deputy, highlighting that a longer stay in the region would imply greater investment in accommodation, food, transport and “other non-gaming expenses”.
According to the most recent report released by the Tourism Services Bureau (DST), visitors from mainland China continued to dominate Macau's tourism market in 2025, constituting 72.4% of total visitors. In another table made available by the organization, it is possible to observe that more than half of last year's visitors were daytrippers – that is, they entered and left the city on the same day.
José Pereira Coutinho recognizes the phenomenon of visitors who make “light trips for a day or a night just to play in casinos, leaving aside leisure or cultural tourism”. On the other hand, many international tourists (or those “from the distant provinces in the interior of the continent) also choose to spend the night in the city of Zhuhai, which offers luxurious hotels at prices lower than those in Macau. This is the case of the recently opened Hyatt Regency, located “hundreds of meters” from the border that separates the two regions.
According to the deputy, Macau is also incapable of competing with the attractiveness of other cities in the Greater Bay Area, often appearing as “a quick stop on a broader tour” of cities such as Hong Kong, Shenzhen or Guangzhou.
Based on the problems presented, Coutinho concludes the interview with three questions addressed to the Government. In the first, the deputy and president of the Macau Public Service Workers Association (ATFPM) asks what measures are planned to “retain visitors at the end of concerts and large festivities”, preventing them from being “redirected” to the borders.
In addition to this type of visitor being essential for the survival of many small and medium-sized businesses, their visit to the region also constitutes a valuable opportunity to spread local culture. In this regard, Coutinho questions what measures have been developed to “promote the unique Portuguese-Chinese heritage through thematic routes, art festivals, music, in-depth gastronomy (not just pastéis de nata) and historical-artistic houses”.
Finally, the deputy questions the Government about the measures planned to facilitate the issuance of “multiple visas that include more days of stay in the Macao SAR, in addition to passing through Hong Kong and Guangdong province in a more integrated way”. Coutinho also proposes that Macau's tourist circuits present alternatives to gaming tables, including places such as the NAPE lakes, the fishermen's dock in Coloane or night markets.</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 23:53:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Government scrutinizes 'dark web' for threats to critical infrastructure</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/governo-escrutina-dark-web-em-busca-de-ameacas-a-infraestruturas-criticas/</link><description>The Cybersecurity Incident Alert and Response Center is monitoring the 'dark web' to identify threats targeting Macau's critical infrastructure. The revelation appears in the government's response to a question from deputy Chan Lai Kei, who warned of the significant increase in cyber attacks in the territory.

The Government detailed, in response to a question from deputy Chan Lai Kei, the measures currently in force to protect Macau's critical infrastructures against cyberattacks. Among the actions highlighted is the constant monitoring of the 'dark web', where the Cybersecurity Incident Alert and Response Center (CARIC) collects information on potential threats, such as the leakage of passwords to access computer accounts or the identification of existing security vulnerabilities. This information is then used to require operators to take appropriate preventative measures.
The response, signed by the head of the Office of the Secretary for Security, Lam In Sang, follows an interpellation presented on December 5, 2025, in which deputy Chan Lai Kei highlighted the escalation of risks in cyberspace, with official data indicating that the average daily number of attacks and computer espionage actions increased from around 1,850 in 2020 to approximately 6,300 in 2024. Chan Lai Kei He also warned of new emerging threats, such as the malicious use of artificial intelligence (AI) through technologies such as Deepfake, which he considers “one of the most complex, real and serious security challenges”, also recalling that the recent amendment to the Cybersecurity Law of the People's Republic of China, approved in October 2025 and coming into force on January 1, 2026, reinforces the need to monitor AI security risks.
In addition to surveillance on the 'dark web', CARIC has implemented other protection measures since its entry into operation on December 22, 2019. Weekly, it communicates blacklists of malicious IP addresses detected in cyberattacks or espionage actions to operators of critical infrastructures. The center also issues accurate alerts on software and hardware vulnerabilities worldwide, urging operators to install security updates. Periodically, it carries out risk analyzes to help entities identify latent vulnerabilities and dangers, requiring the optimization and correction of systems.
On the issue of regional cooperation in combating complex cybercrimes, the government response indicates that Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau have already established cooperation mechanisms at various levels. In the field of prevention and investigation of fraud and computer crimes, the Judiciary Police's Anti-Scam Coordination Center maintains direct communication channels with cyber police units and anti-fraud centers in the other two regions, allowing the timely exchange of information and rapid action on payment cessation measures. In cases of great complexity, cooperation may take the form of a joint investigation task force.
Regarding the possible revision of the Macau Cybersecurity Law (Law No. 13/2019) to align it with recent national legislative changes, the Government stated that the Cybersecurity Commission has been studying and discussing the legal diplomas of Mainland China, such as the Data Security Law and the Personal Information Protection Law. Under the leadership of this committee, CARIC will continually review the implementation of local law and, based on the evolution of Macau society, will timely assess the need to make changes, developing specific plans to improve the legal framework in the area of ​​cybersecurity.
The data revealed in the interpellation show the scale of the challenge faced by the authorities. In 2024 alone, 291 alerts were issued to critical infrastructure operators, an annual increase of 36 percentage points, and there were 38 reported incidents, 22.6 percent more than in the previous year. Of these, 12 were confirmed cases of cyber attacks, representing an increase of four cases compared to the same period last year.</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 23:54:25</pubDate></item><item><title>“Classics on Strings” brings together Macau Orchestra and international virtuosos for a night of masterpieces</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/classicos-em-cordas-une-orquestra-de-macau-a-virtuosos-internacionais-para-noite-de-obras-primas/</link><description>On March 14th, at 8pm, the Grand Auditorium of the Cultural Center will host a concert that will take the public through the best of the symphonic repertoire for strings. “Clássicos em Cordas” is the result of a partnership between the Cultural Institute, the Macau Orchestra Society and SJM Resorts, and will be directed by violinist and conductor Julian Rachlin, in a performance featuring violist Sarah McElravy as a guest soloist. The opening will be one of Beethoven's most dramatic works, the Coriolanus Overture, op. 62. This will be followed by Mozart's Sinfonia Concertante in E-flat Major, K. 364, a piece that establishes a dialogue between the solo violin and the solo viola, with orchestral accompaniment. To close the night, the Macau Orchestra will perform Symphony No. 3 in A Minor, op. 56, “Scottish”, by Mendelssohn, a work that evokes the landscapes and imagery of the Scottish Highlands.
The concert takes on a special character due to the quality of the guest artists. Julian Rachlin, born in Vienna, is an unmissable name on the international music scene. With a career spanning more than three decades, he has collaborated with the most prestigious orchestras in the world. In addition to his career as a soloist, he has established himself as a renowned conductor, having been Principal Guest Conductor of the Royal Northern Sinfonia, in the United Kingdom, and directing groups such as the Oslo Philharmonic and the Munich Philharmonic. At his side will be Sarah McElravy, a Canadian violist recognized for her technique and for a career that took her to the main stages of Europe, America and Asia.
The “Clássicos em Cordas” concert lasts approximately one and a half hours, including an intermission, and is part of the Macau Orchestra Concert Season 2025-26. Tickets are on sale at the price of 300, 250, 200 and 150 patacas, at the Macau Online Ticket Office.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>South Korea and Brazil elevate bilateral relationship to “strategic partnership”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/coreia-do-sul-e-brasil-elevam-relacao-bilateral-a-parceria-estrategica/</link><description>South Korea and Brazil agreed to elevate bilateral relations to the level of “strategic partnership”, at a summit held in Seoul between the presidents of the two countries.

South Korea and Brazil agreed yesterday to elevate bilateral relations to the level of “strategic partnership”, at a summit held in Seoul between South Korean presidents, Lee Jae-myung, and Brazilian, Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva. “We have decided to elevate our bilateral relationship to a ‘strategic partnership'”, announced Lee, at a press conference after the meeting. The South Korean President explained that the “South Korea-Brazil Five-Year Action Plan”, adopted yesterday, will serve as an integral roadmap in areas such as politics, economics, practical cooperation and exchanges between citizens.
Among the main results of the talks, he highlighted the push to resume negotiations for a trade agreement between South Korea and Mercosur, as well as the signing of eleven memorandums of understanding in sectors such as SMEs, health, agriculture, space, defense and aviation.
In economic matters, the two countries agreed on the need to expand mutually beneficial cooperation and supported the prompt resumption of negotiations for a trade agreement between South Korea and Mercosur.
Lee highlighted that the regulatory cooperation agreement in the health sector will allow South Korean cosmetics, currently popular in Brazil, to reach a greater number of consumers.
In the field of agriculture, three agreements were signed focused on food security and strengthening cooperation in cutting-edge agricultural technologies, with a view to the sustainable development of rural economies.
The South Korean President recalled the attempted launch of the South Korean Hanbit-Nano commercial rocket at the Alcântara Space Center in December and expressed the expectation that it will be successful in the future, while also highlighting cooperation in aeronautical supply chains and the aspiration to move towards the co-development of new generation civil aircraft.
The two countries also committed to promoting student exchanges, teaching Korean in Brazil and audiovisual co-production.
In turn, Lula da Silva recalled that Brazil is home to the largest community of Korean origin in Latin America, with around fifty thousand people, and that K-pop, soap operas and South Korean cuisine have millions of consumers in Brazil.
Brazil is South Korea's main trading partner in South America, while, according to the Brazilian President, Seoul is the South American country's fourth trading partner in Asia. "The energy transition opens up new opportunities for productive complementarity. Critical mineral chains offer broad possibilities for adding value. There is room for cooperation in high technology, such as semiconductors and artificial intelligence", highlighted Lula about the areas of opportunity.
The Brazilian leader further explained that he informed Lee “that the completion of sanitary procedures to export Brazilian beef could benefit South Korean consumers”.
Lula also valued the firmness and resilience of both democracies in the face of recent coup attempts that both countries suffered, in reference to the actions of their respective predecessors in power, Jair Bolsonaro and Yoon Suk-yeol.
The Brazilian President will leave South Korea this Tuesday. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 22:38:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Four years of war without military advances or political setbacks</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/quatro-anos-de-guerra-sem-avancos-militares-nem-recuos-politicos/</link><description>Four years after the Russian invasion, the fate of the war in Ukraine remains locked in the uncertainty of the ongoing trilateral meetings, which have not yet produced a way out of the battlefield stalemate and intransigence of the parties.

The last round of talks ended on Wednesday in Geneva with progress, according to Kiev, and without lengthy comments from Moscow, and an agreement to continue the dialogue, promoted by US President Donald Trump since his return to the White House just over a year ago.
However, Russia continues to not give up the regions it claims in Ukraine, which insists on not giving in to its territorial integrity, which has already been attacked by Moscow since 2014 with the annexation of the Crimean peninsula and its support for separatist uprisings in the provinces of Luhansk and Donetsk, which make up Donbass.
After 1,460 days since the beginning of the invasion, Russian forces occupy almost all of Lugansk and almost 80% of Donetsk, but last summer they failed in a vast operation to capture this province in its entirety, including the strategic city of Pokrovsk.
Moscow's troops also partially occupy the provinces of Kherson and Zaporijia, in the south of the country, where they have maintained control of the largest power plant in Europe since March 2022, whose destination has become another hot spot in peace negotiations.
The Russian army also has military pockets in northern Ukraine, in Sumy and Kharkiv, where they sought to recover Kupyansk, another strategic city that has already experienced both sides of the conflict, but whose recapture by Moscow, announced in November as a great military victory and a sign of Kiev's weakness, has not been confirmed.
Russia made the biggest advance in Ukraine last year, although below the gains achieved in 2022 and equivalent to just 1% of the territory, meaning that less than a fifth of the country is under Russian occupation, including Crimea and the other areas under its rule since 2014.
In the opposite direction, in 2025 the Ukrainian army expanded 125 square kilometers in Kharkiv and 55 kilometers in Dnipropetrovsk (central-east), two regions where the peace plan proposed by Washington foresees Russian withdrawal.
Already last week, another 200 were added in Zaporijia, in the largest portion of territory recovered by Kiev since the failed counteroffensive of 2023, taking advantage of the interruption of the Starlink satellite Internet service to the Moscow military.
However, Ukraine continues to suffer large-scale air attacks on a daily basis, particularly against energy infrastructures, leading to prolonged blackouts in the middle of winter and accusations from Kiev and its allies about the use of cold as a weapon of war against civilians.
The Ukrainian President, Volodymyr Zelensky, has repeatedly questioned the willingness of his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, to accept a ceasefire and, as a sign of “difficult negotiations” and a strategy of dragging the Kremlin, noted, in the aftermath of the last meeting in the Swiss city, that the working group discussing the military model of a possible truce made more progress than the group responsible for the political framework.
At the same time, he tries to avoid antagonizing the United States and the negotiating rush, after Trump warned that he wants to close an agreement by June, before the US mid-term elections in November, and that his Ukrainian counterpart has to “move” at the risk of losing “a great opportunity”.
In response, Zelensky warns that the normalization of relations between Washington and Moscow cannot be achieved at the cost of Ukraine's sacrifice, alluding to a bilateral meeting, on the sidelines of the Geneva talks, between North American and Russian envoys, in which Kremlin representative Kirill Dmitriev discussed the prospect of business worth 14 billion dollars.
As a precursor to the relaunch of the peace process, Trump received Putin, in August, in Alaska, followed by an intense diplomatic journey promoted by North American envoy Steve Witkoff and Trump's son-in-law, Jared Kushner, until reaching the current format of trilateral negotiations.
Direct dialogue between Russians and Ukrainians has not occurred since the first days of the war, although the two sides never stopped communicating with each other, which allowed the release of thousands of prisoners of war and the return of soldiers' bodies, but slow results in the recovery of children and adolescents deported from the occupied territories to Russia.
Although most of the content of the summit in Alaska remains unknown, Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov has already referred to a supposed step back in relation to a proposal that Moscow would be ready to agree to.
The White House's original 28-point plan envisaged the handover of Donbass in exchange for Western security guarantees to prevent new Russian aggression, but it was in the meantime revised and reduced by Kiev, together with the main European allies, who rebelled against a proposal that they interpreted as a capitulation by Kiev, as it contemplated most of the Russian demands.
Despite being present in Geneva, but absent from the central negotiating table, the European NATO countries have sought to compensate for the USA's departure from the stage in political, financial and military support for Kiev, while also being initially excluded by the Kremlin from being part of a possible structure that ensures security guarantees, which should be supervised by Washington.
After four years of a conflict that has already caused hundreds of thousands of casualties in both countries, Russia frequently returns to the “root causes” argument that it uses to justify the military invasion, referring to the expansion of NATO close to its borders and an alleged Russophobic feeling in Ukraine, a country that in 2022 urgently needs to “denazify”, that is, change the regime.
Zelensky continues to be pressured by Washington, but against the opinion of European partners, to hold elections, which should have taken place in 2024 but were postponed without a date due to the imposition of martial law in force, leading Putin to consider him an illegitimate leader. In response, the Ukrainian President conditions the scheduling of elections to the ceasefire that the Kremlin has so far refused and only “when all necessary security guarantees are in place”.
There may still be a referendum at stake, if Kiev negotiators end up accepting an agreement that involves territorial issues and changes to the Constitution, but polls indicate that this is not an option for the majority of Ukrainians. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 23:53:32</pubDate></item><item><title>FDCT visits technology companies in Macau and Hengqin</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/fdct-visita-empresas-tecnologicas-de-macau-e-hengqin/</link><description>Since the beginning of the year, the Fund for the Development of Science and Technology (FDCT) has carried out a list of visits to several technological companies in Macau and in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin. The objective was “to deepen knowledge about the evolution of research and development (R&amp;D) and its application, as well as to identify the development needs expressed by company representatives”, indicates the organization in a statement released yesterday.
The aim is, therefore, to “boost the transformation of the results of scientific research and its industrialization, contributing to the development of adequate diversification of Macau’s economy”.
The FDCT team visited an environmental technology company in Macau, focusing on observing progress in R&amp;D and the effects of applying technologies such as recycling and reuse of waste oils, as well as box-culvert desilting with a remotely controlled cleaning robot. Furthermore, the FDCT visited Macau technology companies based in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, in order to monitor the development of R&amp;D projects in the areas of biotechnology and nanomaterials, among others.
The organization also says that, in the first two months of this year, the FDCT opened applications for a set of financing programs, covering areas such as scientific and technological cooperation between Guangdong and Macau, innovative business research and development and scientific research and innovation, among others. The number of applications received increased by around 50%, compared to the same period of the previous year. Of these, the Financing Plan for Innovative Company Research and Development received a total of 40 applications, “which reflects the growing investment of local companies in the field of scientific and technological innovation”, says the FDCT.</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 22:40:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Court accuses former Philippine President of personally selecting assassination targets</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/tribunal-acusa-ex-presidente-filipino-de-selecionar-pessoalmente-alvos-de-assassinato/</link><description>The deputy prosecutor of the International Criminal Court yesterday accused, at the beginning of hearings for a possible trial, former Philippine President Rodrigo Duterte of having “authorized assassinations” and “personally selected” targets, which the Defense denies. Deputy Public Prosecutor Mame Mandiaye Niang said these “confirmation of charges” hearings, during which judges will decide whether 80-year-old Duterte will stand trial, are “a reminder that the powerful are not above the law.”
Duterte, who governed the Philippines between 2016 and 2022 and is currently accused of crimes against humanity over his anti-drug policy, did not appear in The Hague and will be absent throughout the week, after the court approved, on Friday, his request to renounce his right to appear. Niang accused Duterte, first as mayor of the southern city of Davao and then as President of the Philippines, of playing a “central role” in the extrajudicial executions of alleged drug traffickers and users. “Mr. Duterte authorized murders and personally selected some of the victims,” said the deputy prosecutor. The former Philippine leader denies the accusations, his lawyer, Nicholas Kaufman, told reporters before the hearing, in which he will also present his arguments. The former Philippine President "firmly maintains [the proclamation] of his innocence", stressed the lawyer, adding that Duterte "personally defends his legacy firmly. The hearing will last four days, after which the court will have 60 days to issue its decision.
The former head of state, accused of three crimes, was arrested in Manila on March 11, 2025, during the government of his successor, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., and taken to the Netherlands that same night, where he remains detained in prison in Scheveningen. The first accusation refers to Duterte's alleged involvement as an accomplice in 19 murders committed between 2013 and 2016, when he was mayor of Davao, one of the main cities in the Philippines. The second charge relates to 14 assassinations of alleged “high-value targets” between 2016 and 2017, when Duterte was President. The third charge refers to 43 murders committed in the Philippines during “clearance operations” between 2016 and 2018, targeting suspected drug users or traffickers. Niang said the homicides alleged in this case represent “only a fraction” of the actual number of people killed. Human rights groups believe that extrajudicial killings linked to Duterte's anti-drug campaign have led to the deaths of tens of thousands of mostly poor people, killed by police and vigilante groups, often without any evidence of drug involvement. The Philippines withdrew from the International Criminal Court in 2019, following Duterte's decision, but the Court ruled that it maintained jurisdiction over alleged crimes committed in the country between 2011 and 2019. The Defense appealed this decision.</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 22:40:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong court upholds conviction of 12 pro-democracy activists</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/tribunal-de-hong-kong-ratifica-condenacao-de-12-activistas-pro-democracia/</link><description>The Hong Kong Court of Appeal yesterday rejected appeals filed by twelve pro-democracy activists, who sought to overturn their convictions or reduce their sentences for conspiracy to subvert state power.

The court's presiding judge, Jeremy Poon, ratified the sentences handed down in the first instance in the largest trial to date under the National Security Law, and confirmed the acquittal of one of the 47 defendants, concluding that the unofficial primaries held in July 2020 constituted a “lethal weapon” designed to win a majority in the Legislative Council, systematically veto public budgets and force the resignation of the head of the Executive.
Jeremy Poon classified the plan — devised by former law professor Benny Tai — as an “abuse of power”, prohibited by article 22 of the Basic Law, and rejected as a mitigating factor the alleged “impossibility” of success, given the “political volatility” triggered by the mass anti-government protests of 2019.
The movement sought to impose five demands: withdrawal of the extradition law to mainland China, annulment of the classification of demonstrations as “riots”, release of detainees, independent investigation of police violence and enforcement, and the holding of elections through universal suffrage. The court premises were heavily protected by a hundred agents, who installed barricades and road controls in the surrounding areas.
The judge-president's decision was heard by a dozen Western diplomats present in the room, where the accused appeared calm, greeting family members and supporters. The magistrate validated the 118 days of trial between February and December 2023, rejected complaints for “excessive judicial intervention” and highlighted the duty of legislators to align public funds with the general interest.
Three first instance judges declared 14 guilty at the end of the process, proving the respective accusations, and a further 31, who admitted the same. The sentences ranged from four years and two months to ten years imposed on Benny Tai as leader of the movement.
The initial ruling considered the strategy a conspiracy to “severely undermine” the Executive, citing 2020 statements by a senior Chinese official about “anti-Chinese forces”, which aimed to paralyze the legislative branch through budget vetoes.
Among the applicants are former deputies Helena Wong, Lam Cheuk-ting, Raymond Chan and Leung Kwok-hung; former councilors Clarisse Yeung, Kalvin Ho and Tat Cheng, and activists Gwyneth Ho, Owen Chow and Gordon Ng. Activist Prince Wong also failed to reduce her 53-month prison sentence. So far, 18 convicts have served their sentences.
The case has drawn criticism from Western countries and non-governmental human rights organizations, who consider the National Security Law an instrument against dissent. The law provides for penalties of up to life imprisonment and grants broad police powers. Since its entry into force, more than 300 arrests and the dissolution of organizations have been recorded. Hong Kong authorities argue that the agreement made it possible to re-establish stability in the territory. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 22:39:25</pubDate></item><item><title>The war between Russia and Ukraine: peace or continued stalemate?</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/23/a-guerra-entre-a-russia-e-a-ucrania-paz-ou-impasse-continuo/</link><description>Four years ago, on February 24, 2022, Russia launched a “special military operation” against Ukraine. This large-scale invasion by land, air and sea followed a limited military operation in 2014, when Russia seized the important Crimean Peninsula, home of the Russian Black Sea Fleet, and parts of the eastern provinces of Luhansk and Donetsk. The aim of the February 2022 invasion was to overthrow the pro-Western government of Volodymr Zelensky and install a pro-Russian government in a residual vassal state.  The invasion was a violation of the United Nations Charter, two bilateral treaties between Ukraine and Russia signed in 1991 and 1994, the 2004-2005 Minsk Agreements, and numerous laws of war. In just a few weeks, European, North American and several Asian countries launched very severe economic and financial sanctions against Russia, temporarily sending the Russian economy and currency into a precipitous fall. Russia quickly became more isolated than it had been since the Stalin era some 70 years ago. Numerous embassies, including most North American and European countries, maintained only a skeleton staff as political relations deteriorated. The war in Ukraine is the most dramatic breach of the European security order since the Second World War.
The military front was divided into two parts: first, a blitzkrieg-type campaign of Russian offensives and Ukrainian counteroffensives in 2022 and 2023, and second, a war of attrition from 2024 to the present.  Using superior aviation, tank, artillery and troop resources, Russia was able to seize large areas of eastern Ukraine, capturing most of the rich Donbas region, the northern coast of the Sea of ​​Azov and Crimea, which had already been taken before. In the March 2022 lightning offensive, Russia conquered around 115,000 km², but in August and September Ukraine's counteroffensives retook 35,000 km² in the provinces of Kharkiv and Kherson. By the end of 2023, the 1100km front was at an almost complete stalemate. Russia had the advantage in troop numbers, which allowed it to launch attacks in human waves along the front line. However, the lack of training of Russian recruits, the poor tactics of their officers and widespread corruption at all levels meant that the offensives petered out. In turn, Ukraine has erected an effective defense-in-depth strategy, incorporating multiple lines of trenches, dragon's teeth (anti-tank obstacles), mines, artillery and drones, preventing Russia from making significant gains. Russia's objective has been to take over the entire Donbas region, an objective that has not yet been realized. Their offensives have been slower than the failed major Allied offensives of World War I, averaging just 15 to 70 meters per day. Approximately 20% of the heavily fortified Donbas remains in Ukrainian hands, including the key cities of Pokrovsk, Chasiv Yar and Kupiansk, with a total population of 300,000.
Both countries suffered huge casualties, but especially Russia. To date, Russia has suffered around 1.2 million casualties, including around 325,000 deaths. Ukraine suffered around 600,000 casualties, including 150,000 deaths. Approximately 200,000 Ukrainian civilians are dead, injured or missing, including approximately 20,000 Ukrainian children who Russian forces have abducted and taken to orphanages across Russia. Several observers have commented that Russian casualties will increase to a rate of 50,000 per month by summer. As several military historians have observed: “No great power has suffered anywhere near the same number of casualties since the Second World War.”  For example, Russia has had about 17 times more deaths than it suffered in about 10 years of war in Afghanistan. Russia's casualties forced it to offer potential soldiers huge cash bonuses worth $50,000; high wages; if imprisoned, release from prison and subsequent full pardon; recruitment of 10,000 soldiers from North Korea; as well as hundreds of “volunteers” from various African countries.
In 2024, Russia increased its drone and missile attacks, including ballistic missiles, against Ukrainian cities and towns. After a months-long siege, in February 2024, Russia seized the city of Avdiivka, in Donbass. Russian forces then attempted to take Pokrovsk, an important logistics and transport hub, using infantry, artillery, Iranian-made Shahed drones and glide bombers. Over the past two years, Russian forces have attempted to seize the rest of Donbas. Today, Russia controls about 120,000 km², about 20% of Ukraine in the northeast, east and south, including the territory seized in 2014. Russia has proven to be highly innovative in developing drones, electronic warfare, artillery and glide bombers.
Having failed to win the war militarily, in the last two years Russia has changed strategy to conduct a war of attrition — taking the war to the Ukrainian people to make them suffer so much that they would welcome an end to the war at any cost.  Russia conducted an air campaign using Shahed drones, ballistic missiles, artillery, glide bombs and aircraft to destroy Ukraine's infrastructure — energy, transportation and military-industrial targets. Every night, hundreds of drones and missiles rain down on Ukraine's cities and towns, spreading fear, destruction and casualties. Ukraine's energy system has been particularly targeted, leaving the country to meet only around 60% of its electricity demand. This has caused prolonged blackouts, where people across Ukraine — in cities, towns and villages — spend several hours a day without heat, hot water, electricity or gas during a harsh winter when temperatures often drop to -20°C.  People’s apartments are cold and dark, with few public “heating points” available. Every night, air raid sirens sound as people leave their apartments to take refuge in air raid shelters. Russian-occupied Ukraine is no better off, with frequent blackouts, an unstable and hated leadership installed by Russia, abducted children, political repression, suppression of Ukrainian identity, famine, widespread unrepaired damage and high unemployment.
After two years of “wartime boom”, the Russian economy is showing signs of strain. Industrial production and consumer demand declined. Inflation and interest rates are very high. In cities and towns, there is a serious shortage of labor, as young males are at the front of the battle. Economic growth has slowed to less than 1% as foreign investment remains limited. Approximately 40% of the Russian budget is dedicated to war, leaving little for health, education, housing, social welfare and infrastructure repair. The combination of high inflation and low economic growth created “stagflation”, a very unhealthy condition. Russia is heavily dependent on China as its trade has increased to around $250 billion, around 34% of Russia's total trade. Russian oil now accounts for about 75% of China's oil imports, providing Russia with valuable hard currency. China has significantly increased exports to Russia of computer chips, machine tools and radars. In both Russia and Ukraine, there has been a decline in popular support for the war, which appears to have no end. A generation of young men has disappeared forever. From this perspective, what are the prospects for peace?
Two-day US-mediated talks in Geneva between Ukraine and Russia ended on Wednesday, February 18, without results. Both Moscow and Kiev described the negotiations as difficult. Both sides have exactly opposite and maximalist demands. Ukraine is willing to cede some temporary losses of territory, but, crucially, it will not cede to Russia the 20% of Donbass that Russia has not conquered but wants. Ukraine wants control of the Russian-controlled Zaporizhzhia nuclear power plant. Russia insists that there be no foreign troops in Ukraine after a ceasefire that could prevent a new Russian invasion; while Ukraine insists on the presence of NATO troops, with strong US air support. For both sides, the war is existential. Ukraine declares that it is fighting for its existence as an independent nation, with its own identity and path. Putin and his supporters do not believe that there should be a Ukrainian state, that Ukraine was a “creation of Lenin and the Bolsheviks”. Ukrainians fear that the volatile Trump will step aside if they do not grant peace on his terms, which are very pro-Russian. Trump stated that Zelensky is preventing peace, while Russia “wants a deal”. While Ukraine does not receive direct military aid from the US, as it did under Biden, it does receive critical military intelligence reports. It also benefits from the right of European nations to purchase American weapons and then supply those weapons to Ukraine.
Unless Ukraine is forced to agree to Trump's terms, which are akin to a surrender, the war will almost certainly continue until one side is too exhausted to sustain it. Unless more severe sanctions are enacted, particularly secondary sanctions against countries that buy Russian oil, Putin will continue, as he clearly does not care about the huge number of victims in his country. Without further suffering, Putin will continue to delay negotiations and fight. Ukraine has no choice: fight or die, at least as a nation. Therefore, this author believes that the war will continue for at least another two years, but probably without any US involvement.</description><pubDate>2026-02-23 22:41:28</pubDate></item></channel></rss>