<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/pop-mart-macao-citywalk-atrai-visitantes-aos-bairros-comunitarios-ate-ao-final-do-verao/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Housing Price Index rose 0.6%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/indice-de-precos-da-habitacao-subiu-06/</link><description>Between February and April this year, the global housing price index was 203.6, registering a 0.6%increase compared to the period between January and March.
The Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) says that this climb “mainly due to comparison of the previous period has been relatively low, resulting from the high number of transactions of autonomous fraction of buildings under low average price construction in January”.
The building price index (221.4) lowered 0.1%compared to the previous period, however, the building price index (214.6) increased by 2.6%, add DSEC data.
As for the price index of built housing, the Macao Peninsula (209.2) fell 0.5%, in relation to the preceding period, however, that of Taipa and Coloane (269.9) ascended 1%. In terms of the year of building buildings, the price rate of built housing belonging to the level of over 20 years has dropped 1.5%, compared to the previous period, however, the rate of the lower level or equal to 5 years grew by 1.1%.
In terms of useful area of ​​autonomous fractions, the level of dwelling price rates of less than 50 square meters of useful area and the level index from 75 to 99.9 square meters rose 2.4%and 1.1%, respectively, compared to the previous period, however, the level of 100 square meters or greater than 0.8%.
In the period under analysis, the global housing price index decreased 8.3%compared to February to April 2024. It is noteworthy that the Macao Peninsula Housing Price Index and the Taipa and Coloane index decreased 8.6%and 7%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau wants to deepen exchange with Guinea-Bissau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/macau-quer-aprofundar-intercambio-com-a-guine-bissau/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai was on Thursday with Umro Sissoco Embaló, president of Guinea-Bissau. During the meeting, the chief executive stressed that Macau and Guinea-Bissau can deepen exchange and cooperation in the domains of health, education and youth.
The chief executive stressed that China and Guinea-Bissau maintain a good relationship, highlighting the establishment of the strategic partnership last year. The leader of the local government stressed that the VI Ministerial Conference of the Macao Forum successfully held last year, "contributed to a broader and higher level perspective between China and all Portuguese -speaking countries" and ensured that "Macau will continue to perform its advantages of a center, a platform and a base well."
Sam has also promised that MSar will continue to assist Guinea-Bissau in full leverage the commercial cooperation platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, “promoting and supporting companies from both countries to reinforce investment and mutual cooperation, to help Guinea-Bissau transform their potential to the level of development engine”.
At the meeting, the Chief Executive made a point of stating that “the principle‘ a country, two systems ’was successfully and lastly and lasting in the field, and remarkable results in the political, economic, social and welfare of the population has been achieved”, also noting that the Government of MSA is committed to “preserving and transmitting local history and culture, transforming Macao and mutual learning platform between culture eastern and western, and in a high importance tourism and leisure center in the Asia-Pacific region ”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Leong Wai Man highlights Macau's potential to become the “city of East Asia Culture”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/leong-wai-man-destaca-potencial-de-macau-para-se-tornar-a-cidade-de-cultura-da-asia-oriental/</link><description>Macau welcomed the 23rd Cultural Cooperation Meeting of the Greater Delta of Rio das Pérolas, bringing together representatives of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. During the meeting, the president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Leong Wai Man, presented the recent efforts of the three regions in order to strengthen collaboration in cultural areas. The event promoted exchanges of talents, joint projects and discussions about the international projection of Chinese culture.
 
On June 5 and 6, Macao was the scene of the 23rd edition of the Greater Delta Cultural Cooperation Meeting of Rio das Pérolas, bringing together representatives of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. The main objective was to deepen collaboration bonds in cultural areas, promoting the exchange of experiences and the joint development of projects.
During the meeting was present the president of the Cultural Institute, Leong Wai Man, who highlighted the advances in cooperation between the three regions, highlighting the importance of state support and the mechanism of the joint work committee of “a base”. According to the ruler, efforts have resulted in the promotion of Chinese culture, the exchange between civilizations and the sustainable evolution of local cultural industries. The official also expressed her intention to position Macau as “East Asia Culture City”, with the aim of facilitating the participation of cultural organizations in international events and strengthening the projection of Chinese culture globally.
The meeting was attended by various personalities, including Huang Xizhong, from the Guangdong Department of Culture and Tourism, and Raistlin Lau Chun, Undersecretary of Culture, Sport and Tourism of the Hong Kong government. About 110 participants from different regions participated in the discussion of topics related to the exchange of talents, museum actions, immaterial cultural heritage, public libraries and creative cultural industries.
Work sessions included specific discussions on the exchange of talent in performative arts, partnerships in cultural programs, museum cooperation and immaterial heritage, as well as joint actions in the cultural industry. Future planning foresees the realization of several joint activities, thematic exhibitions and exchanges in the cultural area, as well as expanding collaboration in the promotion of artistic events between the three regions.
According to the IC statement, Macau intends to consolidate himself as a multicultural platform that contributes to the integration between civilizations, standing out in the promotion of Chinese culture, being mentioned as a “basis of exchange and cooperation for the promotion of multicultural coexistence, with the predominance of Chinese culture”. The strategy is to transform Macau into an opening bridge abroad, promoting cooperation and exchange of knowledge between “Chinese civilization and the western world”.
Since its inception in 2002, the Greater Delta Cultural Cooperation Meeting has promoted the union of regions in the cultural area. The 2003 cooperation agreement between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau has been the basis for continuous exchange activities, with the aim of raising the quality and reach of cultural actions in the region. The next meeting is scheduled to take place in Guangdong.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing asks Paris to reinforce “mutual trust” and respect for “fundamental interests”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/pequim-pede-a-paris-reforco-da-confianca-mutua-e-respeito-dos-interesses-fundamentais/</link><description>China and France should “reinforce mutual strategic trust” and “respect the fundamental interests” of each, said Wang Yi. The Chief of Chinese diplomacy has expressed the hope that Paris "opposes to the interference of the NATO" in the affairs of Asia Pacific.
 
China and France should “reinforce mutual strategic confidence” and “respect the fundamental interests” of each, said Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi in a recent telephone conversation with French homologist Jean-Nooel Barrot.
During the call, which took place on Friday and whose details were published by the Xinhua news agency, Wang stressed the need to “reinforce interpersonal, cultural and educational exchanges” between the two countries, in order to “promote healthy development” relationships between China and France, as well as between Beijing and the European Union (EU).
Chinese diplomacy chief has expressed the hope that Paris “opposes the interference of the swim” in the affairs of Asia Pacific and stressed that China and France “must jointly defend multilateralism and safeguard free trade, as well as oppose unilateral intimidation practices”, in reference to the trade war triggered by the president of the United States, Donald Trump.
Barrot, in turn, said that relations between France and China “are increasingly important,” in the face of global “growing uncertainty”, and noted that his country considers the Asian giant as a “friend and partner”, according to the statements cited by Xinhua.
The promotion of interpersonal and cultural exchanges between the two parts “will send a strong open signal, which is of great relevance today,” said Barrot, stressing that France “opposes commercial and tariff wars” and is willing to “properly” resolve economic and commercial friction.
The call was made two weeks after a telephone conversation between Chinese president, Xi Jinping, and his French homologist Emmanuel Macron, who insisted on the need for “equitable conditions” of market access to both countries to companies in both countries.
Equal access to the Chinese market is a longtime requirement from the European Union, which regularly complains that the Asian giant companies have more facilities on European soil than European ones in Chinese territory.
In addition, Paris and Beijing have been in disagreement since last year because of the threats of Chinese retaliation against French products, essentially brandy, as well as the role of France in the imposition of European tariffs on Chinese electric car imports, which, according to the EU, benefit from Chinese state aids. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:55</pubDate></item><item><title>This year's elections will be the least crowded ever</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/eleicoes-deste-ano-vao-ser-as-menos-concorridas-de-sempre/</link><description>There are nine lists that should compete for this year's legislative elections. Never the number of interested in being part of the Legislative Assembly (AL) was so low. In 2021, 19 lists initially presented their candidacy, although five of them were later disqualified by the authorities, on the grounds that candidates did not defend the basic law or were not faithful to MSAR.
 
A total of nine lists formalized their candidacy for the legislative elections of 14 September to the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), the body reported on Friday, the last day for the request for recognition of the constitution of the candidacy committee.
The lists will also be analyzed by the State Security Defense Commission, which may disqualify some of the candidates. The decision on the final verification of the candidates will be released until July 15.
The nine lists that formalized their candidacy for these elections are: The Union of Macau-Guangdong (UMG) of the Jiangmen community; the Association of United Citizens of Macao (ACUM), from the Fujian community; Power of synergy; Promoter Union for Progress (UPP), from the General Union of Macao Residents Associations; the Good Home Alliance of the General Association of Macao Women; the Union for Development (UPD), of the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom); The Nova Esperança, from the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM); the mutual help grassroots; and a list linked to the association of the life promotion of citizens and economics, which competes for elections for the first time.
In addition to these nine candidacies for direct suffrage, Caeal also received six candidacies for indirect suffrage. It is recalled that, in addition to the 14 seats in the hemiciclo for deputies elected by direct suffrage, that is, by all certified residents, there are also 12 places in AL to deputies elected by indirect route, that is, by a restricted number of associative leaders linked to certain sectors. In addition to these, there is still place for seven deputies appointed by the chief executive.
 
Never has direct suffrage had so few candidacies
 
The nine lists that will compete this year by 14 places in AL through universal suffrage reflect a significant decrease compared to previous electoral acts and is the minimum recorded since the establishment of the MSAR.
In the 2021 elections, for example, 19 lists were initially formalized, and five of them did not go to votes after Caeal disqualified dozens of candidates, mostly pro-democracy. Under the authorities, the candidates disqualified in the 2021 elections did not advocate the basic law and were not faithful to MSAR. This will have led to abstention to the four -year elections to rise, having been the highest ever: 57%.
In the 2017 elections, 25 lists competed and the abstention rate was 42%. In 2013, 20 lists were votes, in 2009 there were 16, in 2005 competed 18 and in 2001 there were 15 lists.
This year's elections will be the first legislative elections after the revision of the electoral law to the AL, which provides for the criminalization of incitement to abstention. In addition, the new law stipulates the removal of candidates considered by the authorities to be insufficiently “patriotic”, without the right to appeal.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:25:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai promises more opportunities and a more favorable environment for students</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/sam-hou-fai-promete-mais-oportunidades-e-um-ambiente-mais-favoravel-para-os-estudantes/</link><description>The government will provide more opportunities, a larger stage and a more favorable environment for students, promised Sam Hou Fai. At the undergraduate ceremony of students at the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must), the chief executive asked young people to tell “the history of Macau”.
 
The chief executive attended the undergraduate ceremony of the students of the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must), where he gave a speech underlining the importance of the institution and local talents.
In the speech, Sam Hou Fai stated that “the now and the near future are critical periods for the full boost of the construction of a strong nation and national rejuvenation through modernization to the Chinese style”, asking students to apply their skills “to help deepen exchanges and cooperation between Macao and the interior of China”, contributing “to the high quality development of the big-ball, Guangdong Hong Kong-Macau and for the high quality construction of 'a track, a route' ”. In the speech, the leader of the local executive said you hope that young people will "well" the story of Macao.
Sam has promised that the government, in collaboration with all sectors of society, "will provide more opportunities, a larger stage and a more favorable environment for students and the young generation develop their talents, work, create their own businesses and realize their aspirations."
It will also "pay attention and persistently support young people to grow healthy, well formed and achieve success, ensuring that the spirit of patriotism and love Macau continues to be transmitted from generation to generation, and that the cause of" one country, two systems "be taken further." The chief executive also said that the executive will "support the growth of young people in an environment conducive to their success."
Sam Hou Fai also recalled that the government aims to build a university city of International Education of Macao and Hengqin and accelerate the creation in Macao, hubs of qualified tolls of top international level, “so as to equip fleets and provide a strong basis to constantly open new horizons of 'one country, two systems'”.
Sam also stressed that "young students are the most energetic group, entrepreneur and fighter for their dreams; they have the hope of the nation and the future of the country." “I hope all students will follow the pace of the New Age and walk with the homeland, they have great inspirations and dreams, worry about the fate and position of our nation, assume responsibilities and take actions with courage, reinforce solidarity and cooperation, perform their own personal development within the scope of the practice of 'a country, two systems' with macao, and realize, and realize Its life values ​​in boosting the great cause of national strengthening and national rejuvenation, letting your youth persistently shine in the construction of a beautiful Macao and in the provision of service to our great homeland, ”concluded the boss.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:24:25</pubDate></item><item><title>They justify the occision of stray animals with “epidemic diseases” and “serious injuries”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/iam-justifica-occisao-de-animais-vadios-com-doencas-epidemicas-e-ferimentos-graves/</link><description>In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) ensures that it will reinforce cooperation with animal protection associations to reduce the number of stray animals in Macao, while ensuring only animals that represent a risk to public health or have serious injuries. The body's response does not answer, however, to several questions presented by Ron Lam, such as the pilot project's point of situation to “capture-e-be-to-go” (CED) and the exact number of deaths from natural causes in Coloane's municipal kennel.
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) has announced that it will reinforce cooperation with animal protection associations and continue to develop measures to reduce the number of stray dogs and cats in Macao. The body's statements are contained in a document of response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, issued in April, in which he accused the government of not having effective policies to deal with the problem of stray dogs in the region.
The deputy's interpellation, divided into three points, was beginning to emphasize the growing number of stray dogs in various parts of the territory, including public roads and high road circulation on Taipa Island. Under the “Capture-E-Doptar” (CEA) program, the 1,086 animals collected from the streets by 2024 (30% more than in the preceding year and 65% more than in 2022) were then made available for adoption, in a strategy that Ron Lam considered “not satisfactory” and lacking “light goals and concrete policies”.
"Many animals were only adopted by animal protection associations, even with no room to welcome them, or adopted by people for fear of animals to be slaughtered," he said, citing the project "capture-being-to-go" (CED) project presented by the government itself in 2022.
In the response text, the AMI does not refer to the CED program and is poisoned with another sense, ensuring that the strategies currently ongoing correspond to “the guiding principles of the World Animal Health Organization, being also widely [recognized] by animal protection associations and society, which allows it to effectively protect animals and, at the same time, balance public interests, to achieve the objective of public health and public health”.
Despite the growing number of stray dogs in Macao, AMI ensures that “it continues to reduce and control the number of bastards from its source” through the CEA program and also the improvement of reception facilities and the streamlining of sensitization actions for animal adoption and sterilization. The next steps to be adopted undergo the reinforcement of “cooperation with animal protection associations, addressing various optimization measures for reducing stray animals (…), continuing to promote adoption instead of purchase and seeking adequate adopters for animals,” says the chairman of the Board of Directors for Chao Wai Ieng.
 
Old data were removed to “facilitate consultation”
 
At the second point of the interpellation, Ron Lam drew attention to the lack of “transparency” of the statistical data present on the Macao Animal Health Inspection Page, under AMI, which after a recent update has concealed the information prior to 2023. Also the way data is classified has changed: the total number of captured animals now appears by the “microchip” categories or microchip ”or microchip categories “No microchip”, no indications of animal species, and the categories of “adopted animals” and “claimed animals” were merged into a single group.
"With a view to fulfilling the principle of transparency of information that the Government of MSAR has been emphasizing, AMI should again carry the full records of previous years and publish more statistical data from the past, and more completely, so that the public can know the current situation and the tendency of the evolution of animals in Macao," said the deputy.
Regarding this point, AMI clarifies that the “reorganization and optimization” of the page occurred at the beginning of 2025 with the purpose of “optimizing management and improving the viewing mode of the website, in order to facilitate their consultation by citizens”. The page is now structured to show “more citizens' subjects more clearly”, having “reclassification” of old statistical data and merging “similar items such as the adoption and complaint of animals” in a single category.
 
Slaughter to diseases or serious injuries
 
At the last point of the government's interpellation in April, Ron Lam mentioned the exponential increase of animals slaughtered in recent years, which nearly tripled between 2019 and 2024. Remembering that, according to the Animal Protection Act, the slaughter should occur only “in the last resort”, the deputy questioned the AMI on what the fundamentals for the slaughter of 119 cats and 311 dogs that died in Macau (430). He also questioned how many animals died of natural causes at the facilities of the Coloane Municipal Kennel, a statistic that is not on the body's page.
Given this topic, Chao Wai Ieng stresses that some of the animals collected under the CEA program reveal health problems or injuries due to their wild condition, never having been subject to "to any vaccination against epidemics or medical care." Although AMI veterinarians provide “proper examinations and treatments for all stray animals”, some may eventually die due to health problems. The body also emphasizes that there is no “period of permanence” for animals that remove from the streets, making it implicit that it does not slaughter animals for reasons of overcrowding of the facilities.
On the other hand, animals that have contracted “high transmissibility epiziotic diseases or have serious injuries that make them inadequate to be adopted” require more strict measures to “control risks of spreading epidemic diseases and safeguard the welfare of animals”. In these cases, dogs and cats “undergo medical examinations and evaluated by two AMI veterinarians and, after confirmation of the leadership, humanitarian means are used to end their life.”
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:23:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Police investigates almost 100 workers on suspicion of illegal work at a concert</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/policia-investiga-quase-100-trabalhadores-por-suspeita-de-trabalho-ilegal-num-concerto/</link><description>Authorities are investigating about a hundred non-resident employees of a concert held Saturday at the Galaxy Arena, suspected of being illegal workers. The 96 involved worked at a South Korean rapper G-Dragon Merchandise Session, which she played in Macao in the last three days. Two responsible for the event were also taken to the squad and the police said they are following the case.
 
A police operation warned of almost a hundred workers on suspicion of being illegally working at a concert at the Galaxy Arena. A total of 96 non-resident officials underwent police inspection and two responsible for the event were taken to the investigation squad.
The detention occurred on the second day of the three-day concert series by South Korean singer and rapper, G-Dragon, in Macao, namely at a Merchandise sales session on the eve of his performance.
According to a press release, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) held, at 10:30 am, a joint inspection to the concert, as part of a “local employee and non-residents of the event” in the Merchandise of the Concert.
The CPSP revealed that it "investigated the identity of 96 non -local workers" and "taken two responsible to the squad." "The incident is still being investigated," said the authorities, ensuring that "if there is a violation of the law, it will deal with the case under the law."
It is recalled that the K-Pop rapper has played in Macao in the last three days following his latest worldwide tour, “übermensch”, marking the singer's return to the territory eight years after the debut concert at Cotai Arena (current venetian Arena) in June 2017. G-Dragon is also part of the Big Bang, a South Korean boybands, being the South Korean, being group leader.
The news about the arrest of the alleged illegal workers was widely shared on social networks, where some reports denounced chaos on site due to the operation. According to fan reports, who wanted to purchase Merchandise from the artist, were temporarily prevented from leaving the scene during the police operation and, after detention, left only less than five employees to "manage a crowd of thousands of fans."
According to the presentation of the show on the Galaxy Ticketing page, the event is organized by TME Live, Tencent Music, the Chinese technology conglomerate company TME LTD. including concert digressions, music festivals, musical ceremonies, among others.
G-dragon concert tickets in Macao were sold out in minutes after being put for sale. In addition to publications on social networks for resale and purchase of tickets, there were also part-time employee recruitment announcements on online platforms in the interior of China, namely in the “Xiaohongshu”, known as “Little Red Note”. The ads claimed to hire merchandise salespeople with a base salary of 200 patacas per day and could receive more in commissions.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:21:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Public officials of DSCC and AMI sentenced to arrest by slogans and illegal access to data</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/funcionarios-publicos-da-dscc-e-do-iam-condenados-a-prisao-por-burla-e-acesso-ilegal-a-dados/</link><description>Two civil service workers were sentenced to the arrest penalty for burla crimes, following a company in 1.4 million patacas as compensation for vacancy in a land acquisition. The case was detected by the commissioner against corruption in 2022, in which an employee of cartography and registration services will have illegally accessed to data from the internal system, and cooperated with an worker from the Institute for municipal affairs in the practice of the slopping.
 
The Base Judicial Court (TJB) sentenced an employee of the Board of Cartography and Registration Services (DSCC) to four years in prison, after illegally obtained internal information on the registration of properties and defrauding, in collusion with a worker from the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), a company in 1.4 million patacas in a case of purchase and sale of property.
The sentence of the criminal case was issued last Friday, according to which the DSCC employee is involved in the commission of considerably high, abuse of power crimes, as well as the crime of inaccuracy of the elements provided for in the Law of the Declaration of Heritage and Interests. Quoted by Radio Macao in Chinese language, he was applied to the Iam employee of a three -year prison, with a suspended four -year sentence for burla crimes.
The case was discovered by the Commissioner against Macao's corruption (CCAC) in 2022 and, according to the body's report of activities this year, the DSCC worker, at least between 2015 and 2019, will have illegally accessed the internal system and obtained, without proper authorization, data related to the registration of land and the building's building registration.
The CCAC investigation found that the individual will have revealed the data to a friend, who exercised real estate activity, so that he acquired land and made profits.
In addition, the court indicated that the DSCC employee established a company, on behalf of a family member and without a due statement to the Administration, in order to exercise mediation and sales mediation activities and remodeling works. In this case, in a purchase and sale of land, the two convicts had falsely stated that they were the possessors of a building located on Rua dos Mercadores, in the mud, and required the buyer in question the payment of compensation to vacate it.
The same worker will also have hidden his identity in the exploration of a coffee, without fulfilling the duty of declaration of assets and interests by civil servants.
Following the judgment of the grassroots court, the services involved reacted to the case and left the guarantee to sensitize employees to comply with the law.
DSCC assured to attribute “great importance” to the court's judgment, and also ordered “employees to reinforce their awareness of compliance with the law and discipline, and pay attention to their conduct and personal behaviors, and to strive to form a team of full employees and dedicated to the public”, can be read in a press release.
The body reiterates that it will not tolerate any violation of law and discipline and take disciplinary measures in accordance with the law. In turn, AMI said that a disciplinary proceedings against the worker concerned to hold their behaviors will be filed.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:22:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing says discussions with EU about electric vehicle prices are in the final phase</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/pequim-diz-que-discussoes-com-ue-sobre-precos-de-veiculos-electricos-estao-na-fase-final/</link><description>Negotiations between China and the European Union (EU) on minimum prices for electric vehicles “entered the final phase, although they still require efforts from both parties,” said a spokesman for the Chinese Ministry of Commerce.
 
According to the spokesman, at a meeting last Tuesday in Paris, Chinese Minister Wang Wentao and European Commerce Commissioner, Maros Sefkovic, maintained a "professional and in-depth discussion" on electric vehicles, which represented a large step towards an "adequate resolution of the question."
"The European part has proposed to explore new technological pathways and China will evaluate the viability of these legal and technical proposals," said the spokesman, quoted in a statement from the Ministry of Commerce. "Both parties instructed their teams to redouble efforts to find a mutually acceptable solution, in accordance with the respective legal regulations and the rules of the World Trade Organization (WTO) in order to properly resolve their commercial differences," he added.
Last October the rates of up to 35.3% on imports from the EU of electric vehicles from China, approved by the European Commission.
The community executive applies 35.3% rates to Chinese manufacturer Saic (MG and Maxus, among other brands), of 18.8% to Geely and 17% to BYD for a maximum period of five years.
The Asian country responded with provisional taxes on Brandy, after threats from an investigation into dairy imports and pork from the EU.
With regard to the case of Brandy, the Commerce spokesman assured that French companies and associations voluntarily presented “price commitment requests” to the Chinese party, “and the Chinese investigating authorities have reached consensus on the key terms of this commitment”. "China is reviewing the full text of the price commitment and, if approved, it is expected to issue a final announcement with this text before July 5," he said.
During his stay in Paris, the Chinese Minister of Commerce also defended Beijing's export of rare land, arguing that it is a “common practice at international level”.
However, according to the Commerce spokesman, China attributes “great importance” to “European concerns” in this matter and is willing to establish a “green channel” for export requests that meet the requirements in order to accelerate their approval. "Minister Wang expressed his hope that the European party also acts with reciprocity, adopting effective measures to facilitate, protect and promote legal trade from high-tech products with China," said the spokesman.
Since April 2, as part of the tariff climbing with the US, Beijing has imposed a new license regime that requires foreign companies to request authorizations to export the mentioned minerals (Samarius, Gadolinium, Terbian, Discretion, Lutécio, Scândio and Itrian), alleging national security reasons.
Controls are especially harmful to the sectors that most need these materials, because China concentrates about 49% of world reserves and processed 99% of the heavy rare lands used in 2024.
In late May, China hinted - publishing and then removing an article in the official press - the possibility of softening these controls to European companies, something that experts interpreted as a possible approach with Brussels in the face of growing tension with Washington. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.06.09</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/ponto-fatal-2025-06-09/</link><description>Negotiations between China and the European Union (EU) on minimum prices for electric vehicles “entered the final phase, although they still require efforts from both parties,” said a spokesman for the Chinese Ministry of Commerce.
 
According to the spokesman, at a meeting last Tuesday in Paris, Chinese Minister Wang Wentao and European Commerce Commissioner, Maros Sefkovic, maintained a "professional and in-depth discussion" on electric vehicles, which represented a large step towards an "adequate resolution of the question."
"The European part has proposed to explore new technological pathways and China will evaluate the viability of these legal and technical proposals," said the spokesman, quoted in a statement from the Ministry of Commerce. "Both parties instructed their teams to redouble efforts to find a mutually acceptable solution, in accordance with the respective legal regulations and the rules of the World Trade Organization (WTO) in order to properly resolve their commercial differences," he added.
Last October the rates of up to 35.3% on imports from the EU of electric vehicles from China, approved by the European Commission.
The community executive applies 35.3% rates to Chinese manufacturer Saic (MG and Maxus, among other brands), of 18.8% to Geely and 17% to BYD for a maximum period of five years.
The Asian country responded with provisional taxes on Brandy, after threats from an investigation into dairy imports and pork from the EU.
With regard to the case of Brandy, the Commerce spokesman assured that French companies and associations voluntarily presented “price commitment requests” to the Chinese party, “and the Chinese investigating authorities have reached consensus on the key terms of this commitment”. "China is reviewing the full text of the price commitment and, if approved, it is expected to issue a final announcement with this text before July 5," he said.
During his stay in Paris, the Chinese Minister of Commerce also defended Beijing's export of rare land, arguing that it is a “common practice at international level”.
However, according to the Commerce spokesman, China attributes “great importance” to “European concerns” in this matter and is willing to establish a “green channel” for export requests that meet the requirements in order to accelerate their approval. "Minister Wang expressed his hope that the European party also acts with reciprocity, adopting effective measures to facilitate, protect and promote legal trade from high-tech products with China," said the spokesman.
Since April 2, as part of the tariff climbing with the US, Beijing has imposed a new license regime that requires foreign companies to request authorizations to export the mentioned minerals (Samarius, Gadolinium, Terbian, Discretion, Lutécio, Scândio and Itrian), alleging national security reasons.
Controls are especially harmful to the sectors that most need these materials, because China concentrates about 49% of world reserves and processed 99% of the heavy rare lands used in 2024.
In late May, China hinted - publishing and then removing an article in the official press - the possibility of softening these controls to European companies, something that experts interpreted as a possible approach with Brussels in the face of growing tension with Washington. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand closes tourists two borders with Cambodia due to tensions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/tailandia-fecha-a-turistas-duas-fronteiras-com-camboja-devido-a-tensoes/</link><description>Thailand has temporarily closed two of its border posts with Cambodia to Thai and Cambodian tourists, in a context of mutual tensions, after the death of a Khmer soldier in a recent border confrontation.
The soldier was killed on May 28 during a shooting in a place known as “Emerald Triangle”, a common border zone between Cambodia, Thailand and Laos. Thai and Cambodian armies agreed to soothe the tensions the next day, but Phnom Penh decided to keep their troops in the area despite bangacoque removal requests.
On Saturday, the Thai royal army took control of the "opening and closing" of all border passages with Cambodia, invoking a "threat to the sovereignty and security of Thailand."
In a statement, the authorities of the Thai province of Chanthaburi (east) explained that they had “temporarily suspended” the passage of Thai and Cambodian tourists in two permanent border posts.
However, they specified that trade was not affected and that Cambodian workers were still allowed to enter Thailand.
Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Defense, Phumtham Wechayachai, considered, in a statement, "deeply unfortunate" statement that Cambodia has "rejected" the proposal to remove their armed forces.
On Monday, Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet announced that the Kingdom would file a complaint to the International Court of Justice (TIJ) regarding its former border conflict. Manet added that the border conflict is "fed by small extremist groups in both countries," which could lead to new clashes.
Cambodia and Thailand have long been in conflict on the stroke of their border of more than 800 kilometers, largely defined by agreements celebrated during the French occupation of then Indochina.
In 2011, clashes around the Preah Vihear Temple, classified as a world heritage by UNESCO and claimed by both countries, caused at least 28 dead and tens of thousands of displaced people.
Although the TIJ has attributed to Cambodia the contested zone below the temple in 2013, the layout of other areas continues to oppose Bangkok and Phnom Penh.
Thailand indicated that next week, the Border Delimitation Committee will meet to try to solve the problem.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong USA AI to predict Alzheimer's risks through retina images</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/hong-kong-usa-ia-para-prever-riscos-de-alzheimer-atraves-de-imagens-da-retina/</link><description>A Hong Kong Health Center has developed a system that uses Artificial Intelligence Technologies (AI) to predict the risk of Alzheimer's disease through retinal image analysis, a pioneering advance in the world.
 
The system does not invasively analyze images from the background of the eye, detecting early changes in blood vessels and retinal nerves that may be related to Alzheimer's disease, allowing to identify potential risk cases years before clinical symptoms.
Humansa Medical Center, a longevity-centered health center, has developed the system in collaboration with I-Cognitio Sciences, an ophthalmological technology company at the Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK).
The artificial intelligence of i-cognitio has been validated with a vast data set, which includes nearly 13,000 eye background images of 648 patients diagnosed with Alzheimer's and over 3,000 individuals with normal cognition.
A study published in 2022 in Lancet Digital Health, demonstrated that artificial intelligence technology developed to detect Alzheimer's risk reaches a precision of 80% to 92% in multiethnic populations from various countries.
Dementia affects about one third of people over 85 in the Asia Pacific region, according to recent data. In Hong Kong, dementia affects 10% of the population over 70 years old and Alzheimer's disease is responsible for more than half of diagnosed cases.
Scientific studies underline that up to 45% of cases of dementia could be avoided or delayed through early interventions, stressing the importance of early detection to mitigate the impact of dementia on the population.
However, conventional cognitive tests and brain structural imaging have limited accuracy, while advanced methods such as amyloid pet and cerebrospinal fluid analysis are invasive and less accessible to the general population.
In this context, this study has developed a model based on deep learning with an approach that promises to offer “a simple, low -cost and poorly laborious solution” to identify potential patients in community environments and provide adequate accuracy and sensitivity.
In an effort to highlight AI relevance in the diagnosis and health care of the brain, Vincent Mok, director and founder of I-Cognitio, highlighted the fundamental role of the retina as a window to the brain.
According to Mok, "through non -invasive eye photography, it is possible to identify changes in retinal blood vessels and retinal nerves linked to Alzheimer's disease."
The expert explained that these changes in the retina may manifest themselves 10 to 15 years before Alzheimer's clinical symptoms are evident, which represents a crucial opportunity for early intervention. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:53</pubDate></item><item><title>New President of South Korea and Trump agree to solve tariff negotiations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/novo-presidente-da-coreia-do-sul-e-trump-concordam-em-resolver-negociacoes-tarifarias/</link><description>South Korea's new president Lee Jae-Myung has maintained a telephone conversation with his US homologist Donald Trump on Friday night during which they agreed to resolve negotiations on customs rights. During the conversation of about 20 minutes, the first since Lee took office, Trump has congratulated the new counterpart in Seoul for his electoral victory, while Lee stressed that the alliance between South Korea and the United States remains the basis of Seoul's foreign policy, said South Korean presidency spokesman Kang Yu-Jung in a statement. "Both leaders have agreed to work to quickly reach a mutually satisfactory deal" about tariff negotiations between South Korea and the United States, the presidential office said, adding that "for this purpose, they agreed to promote a tangible result in the conversations at work."
Lee's first conversation with Trump took place two days after the new South Korean president was taking office, ending months of political and diplomatic uncertainty after the dismissal of Yoon Suk-Youol, following a failed imposition of marial law.
Lee assumed the South Korean presidency at 6:21 pm, after the electoral agency confirmed his victory at the polls in a plenary session. Belonging to the Democratic Party (PD), so far in the opposition, Liberal Lee has taken office immediately, without the usual period of transition, following the elections anticipated by the dismissal of former President Yoon Suk-Yeol.
Lee won the South Korean presidential elections with 49.42% of the votes, compared to 41.15% of his main competitor, Kim Moon-soo, from the conservative party of Popular Power (PPP) and Yoon's political heir.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Children's Arts Festival returns with programming from July to August</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/festival-de-artes-para-criancas-de-macau-regressa-com-programacao-de-julho-a-agosto/</link><description>The 2nd International Arts Festival for Children of Macao takes place again, strengthening itself as an initiative aimed at promoting culture and creativity among younger ones, with a varied programming, which includes shows, interactive activities, film sessions and over 35 workshops. The event brings together national and international productions, offering different options for different age groups.
 
A month of cultural events for the little ones. The 2nd International Festival of Children will be held between July and August, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC), with the support of the Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture. The wide program includes a diversity of events, including shows, workshops, cinema sessions and field activities, directed to different age groups.
The program includes the Ballet “Cinderella”, from the BRNO National Theater Ballet, Czech Republic, with music by Sergei Prokofiev and choreography of Markéta Habalová. Returns Slava Polunin's “Slava’s Snowshow” show, which combines visual theater, classical music, artificial snow and large balloons. The theater “Bebeethoven”, from Portugal, features a musical experience that combines Som and Light, inspired by Beethoven's “Sonata to Luar”.
The theme “East-West Meeting, Asia in Harmony” is reflected in the presentation of South Korea's “Poli Pop” multimedia theater, which turns a children's space into a digital playground through projections, live music and moving scenarios. The play “One Day at the Space Station” presents an interactive narrative in space, with multimedia effects and robotics elements.
The program also includes productions from the IC 2024-2026 Performative Arts Productions, such as “Chong Chong's Hamsters”, Puppets Theater, with video, sound and narrative elements, which addresses life and death-related topics.
As part of activities, art fields for children and families are planned, including creativity workshops and night visits to the Macao Museum. The Macao Children's Film Festival features five screening sessions, including films such as “Where The Monsters” and classic animations live, with outdoor screenings and promotional activities.
The program includes over 35 music, theater, painting and dance workshops, intended for various ages. Some activities are directed to children with special needs, with specific activities and guidance by specialized professionals. Some activities imply additional costs and require early registration.
Tickets for shows and activities will be available from June 11 at 10am through the “Enjoy Maca Ticketing” service and associated platforms. Registration for workshops opens on June 6 at 10am, through Macao One Account's “Activity Applications” portal, with limited vacancies and, in some cases, additional costs.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Chinese vice-prime minister in London to debate with the US</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/vice-primeiro-ministro-chines-em-londres-para-debater-com-os-eua/</link><description>Chinese vice-master-master, he Lifeng, will lead the Chinese delegation in commercial negotiations with US representatives next Monday in London, the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs said.
In a statement quoted by the Spanish news agency Efe, the Chinese Foreign Ministry indicated that he Lifeng will visit the United Kingdom from June 8 to 13 “at the invitation of the British government” and take advantage of its stay in the country to participate in the “first meeting of the China-United States Economic and Commercial Consultation”.
He, very close to China President Xi Jinping, was in charge of leading the commercial negotiations held last month in Geneva with US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, who ended with a tariff truce between the two powers.
The announcement was made a day after US President Donald Trump anticipated that the meeting on US and China commercial delegates, agreed on Thursday in a telephone call with Xi Jinping, will take place on Monday in London.
The conversation between the two leaders occurred after last week Trump accused China, without giving details of violating the bilateral tariff pause agreement reached in May after the meeting in Geneva.
Beijing answered arguing that it was Washington who violated the deal by imposing new chip restrictions and the cancellation of visas for Chinese students announced the week before.
Both countries had started a tariff climb the day after Trump's announcement in early April of their so -called “reciprocal” tariffs, imposing at least 10% on all products entering the United States, regardless of their origin.
Chinese products were subject to a 34% surcharge, in addition to the 20% imposed on the fight against fentanyl trafficking, an opiate that is causing a serious health crisis in the United States, and the customs rights before Donald Trump's reelection.
Beijing retaliated with equivalent rates, which led to a customs war with Washington, reaching 125% and 145%, respectively, about the products of each country, causing a strong slowdown between the two giants.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong rules out tariff retaliation that compromises its “successful DNA”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/hong-kong-descarta-retaliacao-tarifaria-que-comprometa-o-seu-adn-de-sucesso/</link><description>Hong Kong Chief Executive John Lee said the tensions between Beijing and Washington will not make the city adopt retaliation measures, which would compromise their “successful DNA” and free port zone status.
In an interview with Hong Kong South China Morning Post, on the third anniversary of his administration, Lee said his government prepared "contingency plans for the worst scenarios."
He also assured that he is trying to counteract the impact of customs customs imposed by US President Donald Trump, China, who also affect the Special Chinese administrative region, despite the regime "one country, two systems."
Hong Kong leader reaffirmed that the metropolis will maintain its Porto Livre statute and excluded the possibility of retaliation against the US, even if relations between Beijing and Washington deteriorate. Lee has rejected that this attitude is “passive”, defending the strategy as a way of preserving Hong Kong's economic status.
According to the Hong Kong Basic Law, the region will maintain its role of customs territory independent of China and will not impose rates unless the law sets the opposite, consolidating the position of Porto Livre.
Lee also stated that in the two years left of her term, the Hong Kong government will intensify market diversification measures for the benefit of local companies, reducing their exposure to the United States and encouraging expansion to "blue oceans" in high potential economic regions, such as Southeast Asian and Middle East. "With 180-190 global economies, opportunities are vast. We are talking about reorienting strategies, developing new abilities and forging strategic alliances," he said, stressing the need to consolidate Hong Kong's position as a world financial and commercial center in the face of geopolitical tensions.
The United States is the second largest export market in Hong Kong, with a volume of $ 37.9 billion (33.2 billion euros) in goods in 2024, led by telecommunications equipment and parts followed by computers, precious stones, jewelry, semiconductors and valves and electronic tubes.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 07:27:27</pubDate></item><item><title>“Pop Mart Macao Citywalk” attracts visitors to community neighborhoods by the end of summer</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/09/pop-mart-macao-citywalk-atrai-visitantes-aos-bairros-comunitarios-ate-ao-final-do-verao/</link><description>The “Pop Mart Macao Citywalk” project was inaugurated last Friday in the leisure zone of Pai Kok Street in Taipa. The tourist attraction of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) consists of the installation of characters from the Chinese brand Popmart - Baby Molly, Crybaby, Dimoo and Labubu - in various parts of the city, as a way to attract visitors and stimulate the economy of Macao community neighborhoods.
The opening ceremony featured a mega-institution of the seven-meter-high labubu character, which will remain exposed to “present the macanese and Portuguese delicacies” of the site, according to an STD statement. Speaking at the time, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes said that the project aims to reconcile the various dimensions of Macao, from the historical neighborhoods and the gastronomic culture to the new “intellectual property trends (PI)”, reinforcing the interest of tourists and visitors around the world in the multifaceted character of the region.
The initiative extends all summer, with an end scheduled for September 21st. In addition to the great attraction of the character Labubu, in the mud, the public can also see a four -meter dimoo installation in Saint Agostinho Largo, representing the gelatoria of Macao; An unprecedented Baby Molly installation on the sidewalk of São Lazaros Church, which intends to lead the public to buy typical memories; and Crybaby's “fun facilities” at Luís de Camões Square, drawing attention to the typical macao snacks.
During the tourist campaign period, the Ritz building, in Largo do Senate, will provide a “base pop” with the activity program, a zone to take photographs and a pop-up sales zone. A large -scale installation to take photographs from the “Mega Space Molly Egg Tart”, in its first exclusive macao edition, will also be present at the site.
The project also includes a four -phase consumer draw, with four limited edition awards for Popmart's four most popular characters. Visitors who take pictures in any of the five places where the characters are installed and share them on social networks are also entitled to a limited edition thematic post.
In parallel, a minimum consumption of one hundred patacas in any Macau store automatically enroll users of MPay, Alipay, True Money and Touch ‘N Go Ewallet portfolios in another draw with Popmart memories, as long as payments are made by these electronics.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>