<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/restricao-no-envio-de-encomendas-da-china-para-os-eua-tera-impacto-limitado-em-macau/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Macao International Parade scheduled for March 23</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/desfile-internacional-de-macau-agendado-para-dia-23-de-marco/</link><description>The Macau 2025 International Parade will take place on March 23 this year, the Cultural Institute (IC) said yesterday, taking the opportunity to invite the local artistic and cultural associations, schools and institutions interested in participating in this event to present proposals until the February 15th.
In this edition, the parade aims to reinforce the concept of “love, peace and cultural integration” and also disseminate the spirit of “symbiosis, innovation and harmony” of the city of East Asia, encouraging participating teams to “express creativity and to demonstrate the charm of Macao's integration and cultural innovation ”.
This year, the parade route will start in the ruins of S. Paulo and ends at SAP SAI VAN Square. Participating groups can participate in the four -sport parade, including “Parade theme”, “Artistic Group Parade”, “Large Artistic Facilities Parade” and “Special Planning Parade”.
Several extension activities will be held before the international parade. Groups can choose to register in the mode of “street art groups”. According to the IC, this year's parade will be opened and/or ended by international artistic groups, and the artistic groups may sign up for the opening and/or closing shows.
The IC points out that, since the first edition, in 2011, “the parade has invited performance arts groups around the world to ally with local artists so that, with their distinct costumes and styles, they provide Macau residents and tourists A cultural and cheerful environment, highlighting the unique landscape of the historic center of Macau, spreading the concept of 'love, peace and cultural integration' and promoting the interaction and exchange of arts and culture ”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timorese government wants to create more conditions for the formation of young people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/governo-timorense-quer-criar-mais-condicoes-para-formacao-de-jovens/</link><description>The Secretary of State for Vocational Training and Employment of Timor-Leste, Rogenta Araújo Mendonça, asked the government yesterday to create spaces for the formation of young thymorenses appropriate to the needs and demand.
 
Speaking to journalists, at the end of the Council of Ministers, Rogério Araújo Mendonça, said that, currently, the training spaces available in Dili, namely in Caicoli and Becora, are neither sufficient nor adequate, for the formation of young people, either to work temporarily abroad or in the country.
"Today at the Council of Ministers we discuss with the prime minister and other ministers support and search for larger spaces for investment in training, especially to prepare young people for opportunities in Australia, South Korea and Japan," said the ruler.
According to Rogelo Araújo Mendonça, at the meeting was guided to the State Secretariat of Land and Property to, together with the State Secretariat of Vocational Training and Employment, to identify available places and in good condition.
The objective, according to the Secretary of State, is to ensure that young people have access to adequate infrastructures that benefit them.
The ruler pointed out that the formation of young Timorese must be aligned with the demand of the international market, giving examples. "If there is a greater need for professionals in the area of ​​construction, SEFOPE should prepare young people with training in this sector," he said. "If there is greater demand in the hotel area, we also have to create national quality hotel training centers to respond to the needs of the domestic and external markets," he concluded.
 
Timorese government expects project from a new airport terminal until March
 
Timor-Leste Transport and Communications Minister Miguel Manetelu said yesterday that he hopes to receive until the end of the first quarter of this year the project for the construction of the new Nicolau Lobato International Airport Terminal in Dili. “We signed a contract with a consortium of Japanese consultants to finish the design. I asked them that, before the end of the first quarter, they will present the design to be approved and advance with the construction, ”he told Lusa Miguel Manetelu.
The Minister of Transport and Telecommunications signed on Monday a contract for the provision of consultancy services with a Japanese consortium to elaborate the project for the construction of the new airport passenger terminal, which also has the support of the Japan government.
For the minister, the “first step” to accelerate the construction of the new passenger terminal is the completion of the project, which aims to modernize the airport and ensure greater compliance with passengers and compliance with international security and operation standards Airport.
In addition to the new passenger terminal, the Timorese government announced in August that it will also advance with the rehabilitation and expansion of the country's main airport track, in a process that will take place in three phases.
The first foresees the increase of the runway from 1,850 meters to 2,150, the second provides for the construction of another 400 meters towards the sea and the third an expansion of another 500 meters in the opposite direction of the sea. The project will be funded through a loan to the Asian Development Bank, with the support of the governments of Japan and Australia, as well as by the State Budget. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:25:15+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Recorded case of influenza infection</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/registado-caso-grave-de-infeccao-por-gripe/</link><description>Health services were notified last Tuesday to a serious influenza infection case. The case was detected in a 69 -year -old woman, resident of Macao, with chronic diseases.
On January 14, the patient resorted to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center for having symptoms of cough and vomiting, having been diagnosed with bacterial pneumonia and undergoing hospital hospitalization for medical treatment. On January 30, symptoms got worse and had fever and shortness of breath. On February 1, laboratory examination revealed positive reaction to the presence of influenza A virus, having been diagnosed with flu, with pneumonia complications.
The patient required mechanical fan respiratory assistance and her clinical condition improved after treatment. Last Monday, the patient ceased to need support by mechanical fan, being currently considered stable. The patient was not vaccinated against seasonal flu for this year, and their family members with whom cohabite did not have any indisposition, notice health services.
Health services warn that the influenza virus in Macau is active and has arrived the peak of flu, appealing to residents to reinforce prevention. “Residents who have not yet been vaccinated against influenza, especially pregnant women, children, the elderly and those with chronic diseases, which are more likely to suffer serious complications or death after influenza virus infection, should be vaccinated with As soon as possible against the flu, ”the health authorities say.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:24:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The borders between the West and the East of Henry Ma</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/as-fronteiras-entre-o-ocidente-e-o-oriente-de-henry-ma/</link><description>The exhibition “Searching”, by artist Henry Ma, will be inaugurated in Macau on February 11. The show will present about thirty sketches to Chinese paint, reflecting the artist's self -exploitation journey. MA, with rich academic background, will display works that represent significant stages of their creative process, inviting the public to explore their intersection between western and eastern art. Visits will be possible until March 11.
 
The Creative Macau gallery inaugurates on February 11, between 6.30 pm and 8:30 pm, the latest collection of works by Henry Ma. The exhibition “Searching” emerges as an important milestone in the artist's career, reflecting his deep journey of self -exploration through art. The show brings together about thirty sketches to the china ink, all performed outdoors in recent years. For ma, each work represents not only a moment of inspiration, but also a stage of its process of artistic development.
Since returning to Macao in the early 1980s, after completing his academic background at the Faculty of Fine Arts of Canada, MA has been a driving force in promoting art in the region. For years, he has devoted himself to the organization of exhibitions to other artists, now his turn to present his screenships, exposing a set of works that, according to his own, are not masterpieces, but reflexes of their phases of search and improvement. “I recognize that there is still a lot to improve,” says MA, revealing a willingness to continuous learning.
Many of their artistic attempts initially sought a fusion between Western techniques and the tradition of Chinese calligraphy, but not all results were satisfactory. With this, Ma decided to return to his roots, rediscovering the outdoor design. Its practice began with fiber pens on handcrafted paper, before evolving to the use of china ink on rice paper. This experimentation process allowed you to better understand the relationship between ink and water, a crucial step in improving your techniques that, consequently, improved their expressiveness in painting.
The exhibited pieces are thus invitations to contemplation and reflection not only on the work itself, but also about the artist's own path and his creative process, according to MA, a continuous “search”. The inspiration that led to the title of this exhibition.
Henry Ma has a long academic background, including PhD in Archeology and Museology from the University of Beijing and a Master in History from the University of Jinan. In addition to his artistic career, he taught in various institutions, such as the University of Science and Technology of Macao. He is also the author of an academic publication entitled “An Investigation on the Blue and White Porcelain of the Ming Dynasty discovered in Macao”, as well as several academic articles that exploit the intersection between art and history.
Thus, the “Searching” exhibition is not only a collection of works, but a narrative about the artist's constant evolution, a testimony of his commitment to deepen his artistic understanding and a reflection on the interaction between Western and Eastern art. For visitors, it will be a unique opportunity to enter the world of an artist who continues to look for, experiment and evolve, thus inspiring others to embark on their own creative journeys through their vast experience in curatorship and history. The “Searching” exhibition will be available for visits until March 11 at the Creative Macau gallery at the Macao Cultural Center.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Lecture on intellectual property scheduled for March 1</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/palestra-sobre-propriedade-intelectual-marcada-para-1-de-marco/</link><description>On March 1st will be held the lecture “Unraveling the PI industry: how to master its operations and legislation”, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC), in the auditorium of the Macao Art Museum.
The lecture will feature the participation of Rosia, founder of an intellectual property authorization agency (PI) known in the interior of China. Rosia has over 10 years of business experience in management and creativity industry. He is experienced in the area of ​​PI creation, PI, Marketing and Promotion Operations Management, Cultural and Creative Products Development, Brands Development, Authorization for Commercial Purposes and Event Management, having collaborated with more than 30 PI owners and known artists in the interior of China, including there The Fox, Luo Xiaohei, Dooro Bear, Lucky Cat and Zhu Xiao PI, etc., thus having a vast practical experience in the industry.
Rebecca LO, lawyer who works in the PI authorization area, will also participate in this lecture. It has experience in intellectual property legislation and in the management of intellectual property portfolios, including in the request, registration and pledge of registered/design/patent, PI guarantee financing and treatment of objection/revocation/invalidation, defense of Intellectual property rights, legislation related to the commercialization of intellectual property rights and wording of commercial agreements related to intellectual property rights.
The two speakers will share legal knowledge about PI marketing and authorization strategies, as well as PI trade, describing some cases of PI. “IC encourages Macao's cultural and creative industries to develop in the sense of professionalization and industrialization, and hopes that giving lectures directed to the sector can help more PI creators and interested in creating PI improve their professional knowledge In the context of the legislation related to the operations and authorization of PI ”, reads the press release of the body.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:24:56+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao bank profits fall 21.3% in 2024 for lower value in 14 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/lucros-dos-bancos-de-macau-caem-213-em-2024-para-valor-mais-baixo-em-14-anos/</link><description>Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas by 2024, a drop of 21.3% and the lowest value in the last 14 years, show data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM). According to the body, the main reason for reducing profits was a 18.3% drop in interest margin, the difference between loan revenues and deposit expenses.
 
Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas by 2024, a drop of 21.3% and the lowest value since 2010. According to official data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the main reason For profit decrease, it was a drop from 18.3%to 16.1 billion patacas, on the interest margin, the difference between loan revenues and deposit expenses.
This after the AMCM approved three descents of the main reference interest rate in the last three months of 2024, the last of which a 0.25 percentage points, introduced on December 19, following the US Federal Reserve.
The loans, the main source of revenue from the worldwide banking, decreased 7.2% compared to the end of December 2023, settling at 1.01 billion of patacas.
On the contrary, deposits with Macau banks increased 4%to 1.27 billion of patacas in late 2024, AMCM said on Monday.
The Banking of the MSAR was over 2023 with a profit of 6.14 billion patacas, 53.5% less than the previous year.
Macao has two currency broadcasters: the local Chinese state bank branch Banco da China and the National Bank Overseas (BNU), which belongs to the Caixa Geral de Depósitos group. BNU announced in November net profits of 444.2 million patacas in the first three quarters of the year, a 3.4%homologous decrease, in part due to the “prevailing environment of interest rates”.
Malpated credit increased by 30.3% in 2024 to 56.1 billion patacas, the highest value since AMCM began compiling this data in 1990, still during the Portuguese administration of the territory.
Overdue loans accounted for 5.5% of Macao banks loans, more than 1.6 percentage points than at the end of 2023. A percentage that reaches 6.9% in the case of credit to institutions or individuals outside the region.
The European Banking Authority, the EU regulatory agency, for example, considers that banks with at least 5% of bad loans have “high exposure” at risk and should establish a strategy to solve the problem.
Still, the percentage of bank credit overdue in Macau is far from the 25.3% record reached in mid -2001, in the middle of the world economic crisis caused by the outbreak of the speculative bubble of companies linked to the internet. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:28:44+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deepseek launches recruitment campaign with high salaries to respond to demand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/deepseek-lanca-campanha-de-recrutamento-com-altos-salarios-para-responder-a-procura/</link><description>JOB
 
The Chinese Artificial Intelligence Platform (IA) Deepseek announced yesterday a recruitment campaign with offers exceeding $ 150,000 a year after achieving worldwide success at its launch.
The company has published at least 37 employment offers for various advanced technology positions, the best paid of which is the deep learning researcher, with an annual salary of about 1.12 million yuan (148,000 euros), according to the Business Journal Securities Times.
Deepseek currently has 150 employees, against about 1,700 from OpenAi, the main American competitor and the most used AI model to date.
According to the newspaper, the company intends to recruit the best talents finished leaving the Chinese universities, for which also launched an offer of scholarships in the main fields of AI, with daily financial compensations far superior to the usual internship and lunch And even dinner are subsidized.
With staff reinforcement, the technology company seeks to respond to the exponential growth of users since launch and improve and stabilize the service, which has suffered interruptions and technical failures allegedly due to the influx of consultation, even more intense due to the Lunar New Year, period in which much of the Chinese population was on vacation.
Deepseek caused a major excitement in the global AI industry after the launch a few weeks ago from its V3 model, which will only have been developing and cost less than six million dollars. On January 20, he released the latest version, called R1.
Launched in 2023 by the Chinese investment fund High-Flyer Quant, DeepSeek is open source and offers 95% cheaper services than OpenAi's O1 model. However, the great attention it generated - was the leader of Apple devices in the United States - also translated into criticism, as the application refuses to comment on some issues related to China.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:28:00+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Urban Practice of Macau wins silver prize at French Design Awards</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/urban-practice-de-macau-conquista-premio-de-prata-nos-french-design-awards/</link><description>Urban Practice (UP), a group of architects and designers based in Macao, won the Silver Prize in the interior design category/exhibitions, pavilions and exhibitions in the French Design Awards 2024. The award -winning proposal aims to preserve and promote world heritage de Macao, having been presented in the context of a public tender organized by the Cultural Institute in 2022.
French Design Awards, organized by the International Awards Associate (IAA), are an international prestige competition that recognizes excellence in the areas of architecture, interior design, products and packaging. This recognition underlines UP's ability to create innovative projects that have a positive and sustainable impact, both local and internationally.
The project for the Macao World Heritage Pavilion is not limited to being a space for display, but rather a point of cultural interaction that highlights Macao's uniqueness as UNESCO World Heritage. Located on D. Belchior Carneiro Street, the pavilion rises near emblematic historical monuments, including the ruins of São Paulo and Fortaleza.
The main architect, Nuno Soares, underlined the project's central intention: “This approach mainly aimed to preserve and highlight Macao's world heritage to a wider audience. With the ambition to celebrate the story of Macao, a key element of the project is the vertical patio with a top wall wall made with local mud, material once used in the old wall of the city that crosses the project site. ”
By choosing materials and technologies, the team bet on sustainable principles and best preservation practices. One of the central elements of the pavilion is the vertical patio, which is adorned with a local mud wall, a traditional material that, in other times, made up the city's walls.
In addition, the UP organized the spaces respecting the altitude of the terrain and preserving centenary trees and vegetation, implementing universal design principles that ensure accessibility and harmony with the surrounding environment. With a design that incorporates the latest technologies and interactive resources, the space was designed to maximize the visitor's experience.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Number of non -resident workers grew 3.3% last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/numero-de-trabalhadores-nao-residentes-cresceu-33-no-ano-passado/</link><description>At the end of December last year, there was a total of 182,542 non -resident workers in Macao, which means a 3.3% increase compared to the 176,661 non -residents recorded in 2023. This is the highest number since the beginning of the beginning of pandemic. The percentage of the migrant population from the interior of China remains highlighted as the most representative, now representing 66.3%.
 
The number of non -resident workers continues to increase after the end of pandemic restrictions. According to data from the Public Security Police Corps now available on the Electronic Page of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), in late 2024, there was a total of 182,542 migrant workers in Macao, ie more 3.3 % compared to 2023, when they were registered in the territory 176,661 not residents.
Last year, by the way, the peak of the number of non-residents had reached since the beginning of the pandemic. In 2019, when the restrictions were not yet felt, the number of migrants was over 196,000. The following year, this number dropped to 177 thousand and in 2021 it was 171 thousand. In 2022, the largest descent was given in the number of migrants, having been registered less than 155 thousand.
Of the more than 182,000 current workers, the largest slice remains that of migrants from the interior of China. In 2023, the continent migrants represented 68.5%, and last year the percentage dropped to 66.3%. Filipine non -residents remain the second largest population, now representing close to 17%.
At the end of December last year, there was also 8,261 not residents of Vietname; 7,418 of Indonesia; 4,314 of Myanmar; and 3,776 of Nepal, for example. The data also show that there were 127 US non-residents, 109 from the UK and 97 Canadians.
Among the total of non -residents registered last year, almost 30% works in the business of hotels, restaurants and the like. In 2023, the percentage of workers not resident in the hotel or restoration area was less than 28%.
The data released now on the DSAL website also show that, throughout 2024, the authorities approved a total of 158,316 from 194,588 BlueCard requests. These numbers are still lower than 2023, when 224,575 'Bluecards' were requested and approved 174,504. The previous year, 154,726 requests had been authorized after 183,592 requests had been received.
Last year's approved requests are mostly for non -specialized non -resident workers (146,086). Also authorized were 4,841 requests for specialized migrants. There were also 7,386 approved requests for housework.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:27:42+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Diagnosed malaria case</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/diagnosticado-caso-de-malaria/</link><description>The Conde de São Januário Hospital Center diagnosed an imported case of malaria in a 40 -year -old tourist tourist who works in Nigeria. According to health services, this is the second registered case of malaria in Macau since the beginning of the year.
On January 24, the day of return to the interior of China, the man began to have symptoms such as fever, diarrhea and abdominal pain, and symptoms were relieved after administration of medicines. On the 30th, he had low fever again, having resorted to a medical institution in the interior of China. Last Monday, he entered Macao and, due to the persistence of symptoms, resorted to the urgent service of the public hospital, where he was diagnosed with malaria and was admitted to in-depth treatment.
Currently, the patient is in a stable state, and the family members with whom he traveled did not have any similar symptoms.
Health services explain that malaria is a severe and fatal infectious disease, caused by a protozoan of the gender plasmodium, and is classified into four types: plasmodium vivax, plasmodium falciparum, plasmodium ovale, plasmodium malarie. Malaria is transmitted through the female bite of an infected mosquito (of the genus Anopheles). Malaria is not transmitted among people, however, through infected blood transfusion or infected blood products, organ transplantation or syringes sharing with infected people can also be transmitted to malaria. It can also be transmitted through pregnancy or childbirth, that is, from the mother to the fetus and the mother to the newborn.
The incubation period of the different species of parasite plasmodium varies, and symptoms usually appear 7 to 30 days after the bite of an infected Anopheles mosquito, the incubation period of some patients can last several months or even more. Symptoms include intermittent fever, chills, sweating, headaches, fatigue, muscle pain, etc., while complications include anemia, liver and renal failure, seizures, unconsciousness and coma. Malaria is potentially fatal if not treated in time. Currently, drugs are effective in treating malaria and early diagnosis and treatment are essential for healing malaria.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:24:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese Toyota registers a 3.9% profit increase between April and December 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/japonesa-toyota-regista-aumentos-de-lucro-de-39-entre-abril-e-dezembro-de-2024/</link><description>Toyota Motor Corp. Net profit of 4.1 billion yen (25.7 billion euros) between April and December 2024, an increase of 3.9% in annual terms, the car manufacturer announced yesterday. Sales growth, driven by hybrid models and a weaker yen, contributed to the increase.
Toyota, the world's largest car manufacturer in sales volume, registered an operating profit of 3.67 bilions of yen (23.125 billion euros) in the months under analysis, less 15.25% than in the same period of 2023.
Japanese sales revenues increased 4.85% in annual terms to 35.67 billion of yen (22.42 billion euros) between April and December, the first nine months of Japanese fiscal year.
Toyota has increased the prospects for annual operational profits, although quarterly yields were below estimates, due to a break in sales and global production, indicating that it provides a faster pace of activity later.
The car manufacturer foresees a profit of 4.7 billion yen (30 billion euros) for the fiscal year ending in March, above its previous perspective of 4.3 billion yen (27 billion euros), According to a statement released yesterday.
Analysts predict, on average, 4.8 billion of yen, considering that the strong demand for gas-electrical hybrid vehicles in the United States pays up weaker sales in Japan and China.
Toyota sold 10.8 million cars in 2024, a slight drop from the 11.2 million it put in the market the year before, but enough to protect its position ahead of Volkswagen AG as the world's largest car manufacturer for Fifth consecutive year.
Although Tesla Inc., Byd Co. from China and other companies are taking the lead in the sale of battery -fed electric vehicles, Toyota has adopted a different approach, maintaining its focus on gasoline and hybrid vehicle production.
The capital expenses of the Japanese giant, namely investments in personnel and growth areas, along with better cost competitiveness and profitability, are reflected in the magazine forecast, the company said.
Toyota is also investing in increasing the production capacity of electric vehicles and has revealed plans to establish a subsidiary in Shanghai, China, where it will initially employ about 1,000 people. The goal is to produce 100,000 electric vehicles annually under the Lexus brand from 2027.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:31:39+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lunar New Year's holidays brought 1.3 million visitors to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/feriados-do-ano-novo-lunar-trouxeram-13-milhoes-de-visitantes-a-macau/</link><description>Macau received almost 1.31 million visitors during the eight days of New Year's holidays, less 3.5% compared to the same period last year. The daily average of entry is, in this case, in more than 163,000 tourists, number below the expectations of the authorities of an average of 185 thousand visitors per day. The data released yesterday indicate that 76% of the total tourists came from the interior of China, while 17% were from Hong Kong.
 
The number of people who visited Macao during the Lunar New Year's holidays registered a 3.5% break from last year's same period. Almost 1.31 million visitors arrived at the territory during the so -called Golden Week of the Chinese New Year, between January 28 and February 4, the authorities advanced yesterday.
Statistical data is provided by the Public Security Police (CPSP) body and were published on the website of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), indicating that almost 163,700 tourists per day entered the region.
The calculation is below the expectations of STD. It is recalled that Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of the body, said in the middle of last month that she expected a daily average of 185,000 visitors during these holidays.
The Lunar New Year period is traditionally a high time for trips, and many go to their hometown to meet with families, but also take advantage of the holidays to travel. Generally speaking, the day of the day before, as well as the first days of the New Year, are the most important days to join with the family. According to the lunar calendar this year, the first day of the year was celebrated on January 29.
According to data, the 28th, 28th and 30th of January were those who suffered a drop in the entry of visitors in Macao, registering an annual decrease of arrivals at 35%, 19%and 21%, respectively, with the reception of 79 Thousand, 132 thousand and 173 thousand visitors in these three days.
January 31 was the day the territory welcomed more tourists, with 219,000 people visited Macau, plus 9.1% compared to last year. It was thus a record of arrival of tourists in one day since 2019 and also the second largest in Macao history.
The authorities also revealed that of the total of tourists, just over one million (76.3%) of visitors came from the interior of China, which represents an annual reduction of 3.2%. 231,000 tourists came from Hong Kong, occupying 17.6% of the total weight of arrivals, a number that fell 8.9% over the identical period of last year.
The data report that 38.4% entered the siege gates, the main border with mainland China. Another 24% arrived in the territory by the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge, a 55.5 kilometers infrastructure. Only 4.3% of tourists entered Macao through the airport.
The Lunar New Year is one of the three tall times for tourism and the Macao casinos, along with the 'golden weeks' of Labor Day and China National Day on October 1. Game revenues in the region fell 5.6% in January, compared to the same month of 2024, to less than 18.3 billion patacas, below analyst expectations.
As for the number of movements at the various border stations, CPSP said that 4,918,000 entries and exits between January 28 and 4 February were registered, with a daily average of 614,000 crossings, which represents an increase of 0.6% compared to the same period last year. The stations of the doors of the siege, the Delta Bridge and Qingmao were the most used by passengers.
According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, CPSP spokesman, Lei Tak Fai, considered that public order in Macau was "good" during the Lunar New Year and the border passage was "quiet". CPSP has implemented multitudes control measures near the São Paulo ruins on six occasions. In addition, 15 cases against taxis were filed for non -compliance with regulations, and 11 cases of illicit exploitation of the taxi service. Authorities also received 220 noise complaints, of which 32 resulted in a fine.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:29:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China records 2.3 billion trips during holidays</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/china-regista-23-mil-milhoes-de-viagens-durante-feriados/</link><description>Lunar New Year
 
China registered 2.3 billion interregional trips between January 28 and February 4, the Lunar New Year period, according to official data published yesterday.
The National Immigration Administration also reported yesterday that 7,671 million continental residents entered and left the country during their holidays, another 5% compared to the same period last year.
Residents of Hong Kong, Macao and Taiwan who traveled totaled 5,737 million, an increase of 5.6% compared to 2024, plus 958 thousand foreigners, more 22.9% of those registered during last year's holidays.
China expects about nine billion interregional trips before, during and after the holidays, known as 'Chunyun', between January 14 and February 22.
According to the Chinese government, the volume of rail and air passengers is expected to exceed 510 million and 90 million, respectively, although road trips represent most of the flow.
The Asian country exceeded 8.4 billion interregional trips during the 2024 Chunyun, although Beijing's predictions for this year to exceed nine billion, a value that was not reached due to bad weather, which caused delays and cancellations in transportation services and infrastructure problems in various regions.
On January 29, millions of Chinese welcomed the serpent's year and took the holidays to meet their families or travel inside and outside the country.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:28:07+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Special Representative on Violence Against Children Visit Dili in March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/representante-especial-da-onu-sobre-violencia-contra-criancas-visita-dili-em-marco/</link><description>The special representative of the United Nations Secretary-General on Violence against Children, Najat Maalla M'Jid, will visit Timor-Leste in March as part of the commitments made by the Timorese authorities to strengthen child protection.
According to the statement of the meeting of the Council of Ministers, yesterday, Najat Maalla M'Jid will be in Timor-Leste between March 3 and 5 at the invitation of the Institute for the Defense of the Rights of Children (Indica), following the first Global ministerial conference to eradicate violence against children last November in Colombia.
At the meeting, the Deputy Prime Minister Coordinating of Social Affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, and the president of Indica, Dinorah Granadeiro, presented the national commitment to eliminate violence against children. “The commitments made by Timor-Leste include the approval of the Youth Justice Law by 2026, the integration of child protection in educational policies, the reinforcement of specialized justice for children and the professionalization of social workers in the area”, can be read in Notice of the Council of Ministers.
Timor-Leste, according to the statement, also provides for expanding environmental education programs, increasing the budget for child protection services and creating legal staff for online safety and limiting access to alcoholic beverages and tobacco. “The implementation of a national plan to eradicate violence against children and an information management system for children's protection policies are other Timor-Leste commitments, presented in November at the Colombian meeting.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:25:16+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities justify a new record of suspicious transactions with resuming casinos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/autoridades-justificam-novo-recorde-de-transaccoes-suspeitas-com-retoma-nos-casinos/</link><description>The number of suspicious transactions recorded in Macao casinos reached a new record by 2024 due to the recovery of the economy and tourism, the territory authorities said.
 
According to data released by the Financial Information Office (GIF), the six casino operators in Macau submitted, in total, 3,837 participation of suspicious transactions of money laundering or terrorism financing in 2024, more 11.8% than the previous year. "This increase was mainly due to economic recovery and the significant increase in the number of visitors arrivals in 2024," said the GIF in a response to Lusa questions.
The cabinet also mentioned the "continuous investment of resources from the entities of complaining entities in the detection of suspicious transactions."
In 2024, the game sector in Macao raised a total of 226.8 billion in revenues, more 23.9% than the previous year. The territory last year received 34.9 million visitors, 23.8% more than in 2023.
Casinos denounced transactions involved questions such as “conversion of chips without or with minimal play activities, the conversion of tokens in the name of third parties [or] the exchange of money/cash conversion,” added the GIF.
In June, China announced that it has dismantled three clandestine banks linked to the illegal money exchange in Macao, which would have made annual profits of about $ 1.5 billion from Hong Kong.
In 2024, the GIF received a total of 5,245 appearances, and 73.2% came from casino dealers, while 20.9% came from banks and insurers and 5.9% from other institutions and entities. Referenced sectors, including pledge, jewelery, real estate and auction houses, are required to communicate to the authorities any transaction equal to or greater than 500,000 patacas.
Of the total of 5,245 appearances, the GIF last year 142 suspicious transactions to the prosecutor for investigation, 26 more than in 2023.
Asked by Lusa about the reasons that led to the overwhelming majority of suspicious transactions, the GIF made no comment.
In March 2022, an annual US State Department report designated Macao as one of the main points of worldwide capital bleaching.
According to the annual GIF report, Macau was the only member of the Asia-Pacific group against the laundering of capital that complied with “all 40 international standards” on the prevention of money laundering, terrorism financing and proliferation of weapons of destruction in mass.
The GIF signed agreements for the exchange of information with 33 countries and territories, including the Portuguese Judicial Police Financial Information Unit, in 2008, the Central Bank of Timor-Leste Financial Information Unit in 2018 and in 2019 , the Brazilian financial activity control board and the Cape Verde Financial Information Unit. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:28:44+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand cuts energy on the border with Myanmar to combat Burla Computer Science</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/tailandia-corta-energia-na-fronteira-com-myanmar-para-combater-burla-informatica/</link><description>Thailand cut electricity at five points on the Myanmar border. The measure aimed to combat cyber fraud centers in Burmese territory, which in recent years have created regional security problems.
 
Thai authorities decided to cut electricity yesterday at five points on the Myanmar border to combat cyber fraud centers in Burmese territory, which in recent years have created regional security problems with thousands of victims.
Following an order announced by the Thai government on Tuesday, the authority for Thailand's electricity production applied the order in the areas where it identified telephone and 'online' circumstances and where there are also suspicions of victims of human trafficking, allications with false job offers.
The measure, which includes internet and fuel cutting, will have restrictive effects on drinking water in these locations, although the public broadcaster Thai PBS states that several of these centers have electricity generators, so it is not yet known to what extent this decision It will affect criminal groups.
Bangkok reiterated that this is a security measure against transnational crime and is just the beginning of a policy to eradicate the scourge, now with the help of China.
This is also one of the points on the agenda of Thai Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra, on an official visit to Beijing, which began yesterday.
Computer fraud centers, including those located in the Burmese city of Shwe Kokko and the KK Park complex, near the border with Thailand, received more attention after the abduction of Chinese actor Wang Xing, who raised safety concerns in the country that received fence 36 million foreign tourists in 2024.
The actor traveled to Bangkok in early January, attracted by a false job offer, and was taken by a criminal group to the Burmese side, where he was rescued after several days missing. Following the episode, the Thai government hardened speech and actions in an attempt to relieve concerns and protect tourism, one of the country's main sources of performance.
Cutting the supply of electricity also arises following an unusual request from the Myanmar Military Junta - in power after a coup in February 2021 - through an editorial published in the official media, in which it asks for help to countries neighbors in the fight against these groups.
According to the figures presented in the article, the Burmese regime deported more than 53,000 Chinese involved in online burla centers between October 2023 and late January 2024. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:31:39+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>End of tariff exemption in the US threatens Chinese platforms Shein and feared</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/fim-de-isencao-tarifaria-nos-eua-ameaca-plataformas-chinesas-shein-e-temu/</link><description>The elimination by the United States of tariff exemption for low -value products from China can threaten the business models of Chinese E -commerce groups Shein and Tempu, yesterday said analysts cited by the Jornal Financial Times.
 
United States President Donald Trump imposed an additional 10% rate on imports from China over the weekend and said the tariff exemption on products of less than $ 800, purchased directly by consumers and sent through the service Postal, would stop applying.
On Monday, the United States Customs Authority stated that its agents would now have to formally verify and determine the content of all orders sent by China's mail. This measure could increase the costs of Chinese e -commerce companies, whose US growth has been partially driven by efficient deliveries of cheap products produced in China. "The impact will be much bigger than just a few packages," said Henry Gao, law professor at Singapore Management University, quoted by the Financial Times. "Everything that comes from China will be retained because of this," he said.
Shein and rival Temu, who sell clothes and other articles at low prices, have grown rapidly from the Covid-19 pandemic and were probably responsible for more than 30% of customs of customs rates that arrived in the US, regulatory. , he pointed out a report from the US Congress in 2023. According to US customs, about four million orders are processed every day.
US Customs and Protection data showed that the average value of requests was about $ 50, with a total of $ 47.8 billion in eligible goods sent in the first three quarters of 2024.
Trump's measure comes at a time when Chinese companies face increasing scrutiny in Western markets, accused by local competitors and unfair competition regulatory entities.
Shein executives, who intend to enter the London Stock Exchange with an assessment of about 50 billion pounds, argued that their products will remain competitive due to their strategy of adjusting production volumes due to demand.
The elimination of exemption occurs at a time when Trump also announced new rates on products from Canada and Mexico. These were suspended after Trump spoke to the leaders of these countries. The rates about China came into force on Tuesday and Trump is expected to talk to Chinese leader Xi Jinping in the coming days.
The US e-commerce company Amazon sought to counteract the threat of cheap Chinese suppliers, launching the “Haul” brand, which offers products for less than 20 dollars with delivery times between one and two weeks. "The closure of this gap is favorable to Amazon," said Andy Wu, an associate professor at Harvard, adding that the company "would buy a thickness to make the most of its logistics system."
The exemption was designed to reduce the charges of customs employees, eliminating the need to inspect all small shipments, and allowed US companies and consumers to avoid going through a long customs process when less valuable articles matters.
However, these measures have faced more and more opposition, which led former US President Joe Biden to propose a hardening of the rules for Chinese imports at the end of last year, while the European Union proposed the suppression of exemptions to Orders of less than 150 euros, according to Financial Times.
 
China firmly opposes the rates imposed by Washington
 
China said yesterday that it resolutely opposed to increasing customs imposed by the United States about its products and appealed to dialogue after revealing a series of retaliation measures on Tuesday.
"China expresses its profound dissatisfaction and is resolutely opposed to US measures," Chinese Foreign Foreign Ministry spokesman at a press conference said. "What we need now is not a unilateral increase in rates, but a dialogue and discussions based on mutual respect," he added.
Beijing also announced new restrictions on critical metal exports used in sectors ranging from mining to aerospace industry. "The measures taken by China are a necessary action to defend their rights and legitimate interests," said the Chinese spokesman.
 
BOX
 
Chinese bags reopen mixed after a new chapter in the trade war with the US
 
China's financial squares yesterday recorded a mixed evolution in the resuming of negotiations, after being closed during the Lunar New Year's holidays, which coincided with the aggravation of the trade war between Beijing and Washington. The Shanghai Exchange lost 0.36%in the morning negotiations, while the Shenzhen scholarship won 0.44%. Hong Kong, who won 2.83% on Tuesday, fell 0.69% until the middle of the session.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:28:09+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SCM Hostel organizes activities and exhibitions in celebration of the year of the serpent</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/albergue-scm-organiza-actividades-e-exposicoes-em-celebracao-do-ano-da-serpente/</link><description>The SCM Hostel and the Circle of Macao Culture Friends (CAC) are organizing a series of activities, exhibitions and a party to celebrate the serpent's Chinese New Year, which will take place on February 12, at 6:30 pm, in space of the SCM hostel itself. The ceremony and party mark the beginning of the new lunar year under the theme “Serpent” and will be an opportunity for the community to gather to celebrate Chinese traditions.
The event will include a variety of activities, such as the exhibition “Beauty Inheritance: Chinese Cheongsam Exhibition”, a root -shaped button -shaped workshop, a wishes and a love tree, and live music and Some festive delights. In addition, CAC invited Caligraph Master Choi Chuen Heng to attend the event and present his art on display.
The Chinese Cheongsam exhibition is a joint initiative between CAC and the Hong Kong Design Institute, and will feature 16 traditional Cheongsam pieces, a type of female Chinese clothing that is inspired by the Qizhuang, the Ethnic Clothing of the Manchu people, highlighting the essence of culture and artisanal ability of Chinese ethnic groups. Visitors will be able to try traditional clothes and take photographs to keep as a memory.
The frog -shaped button accessory workshop will be held in eight sessions, between 15h and 20h, each lasting half an hour, and will allow participants to create their own accessories using the paper folding technique, such as earrings, such as earrings technique and necklaces. The event is free and works in order of arrival.
The opening ceremony of the Chinese Cheongsam exhibition and the Chinese calligraphy exhibition will take place at 6:30 pm on February 12, and the exhibitions will remain open until March 16 and February 23, respectively. All activities are free and open to the public.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China rejects Trump's proposal to expel inhabitants from the Gaza Strip</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/china-rejeita-proposta-de-trump-de-expulsar-habitantes-da-faixa-de-gaza/</link><description>MIDDLE EAST
 
China yesterday expressed its opposition to the proposal of US President Donald Trump to expel the inhabitants of the Gaza Strip and reiterated their defense of the solution of two states to the Israelo-Palestinian issue. “We oppose the forced displacement of residents of the Gaza Strip. China expects all parties to accept ceasefire and return to a two-state political solution, ”Lin Jian Ministry spokesman said at a press conference.
Trump said on Tuesday that Palestinians have no choice but to leave the Gaza Strip because the place is uninhabitable, and insisted that he wants Jordan and Egypt to welcome them.
The Chinese spokesman added that the parties involved should "put the Palestinian question on the right track." "This means an agreement based on the" two -state solution "that aims at lasting peace in the Middle East," he warned.
Beijing has repeatedly affirmed that Palestine should be “fully” recognized as a state in the United Nations and will insist on solving two states to ensure “peaceful coexistence” between Israelites and Palestinians.
China also expressed its support for the “fair cause of the Palestinian people to restore their rights and legitimate interests”, and their employees held several meetings with representatives of Arab and Muslim countries to reaffirm this position or to try to advance the conversations of peace.
Trump stated that at the Palestinian enclave "everything is demolished" and that the inhabitants of Gaza "would be happy" to leave if they had the opportunity to do so in a "pleasant place with pleasant borders."
Since 1967, Israel has built about 160 illegal colonates that host more than 700,000 Jews in the occupied West Bank and East Jerusalem. The Israeli state also claims the sovereignty of the whole city of Jerusalem, whose eastern side was captured in the 1967 war, occupied militarily and unilaterally annexed in 1980.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:27:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Restriction on sending China orders to the US will have “limited impact” in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/06/restricao-no-envio-de-encomendas-da-china-para-os-eua-tera-impacto-limitado-em-macau/</link><description>The CTT suspended yesterday the sending of small packages and orders to the United States. The US postal service had announced the suspension of the reception of orders from the interior of China and Hong Kong. The impact on Macau is “limited,” the CTT-Macau said. However, the suspension was brief and the US post office said last night that they will restore orders in question. They even revealed that the initial decision is related to Donald Trump's new policy of putting an end to a tax exemption arrangement, which was used by Chinese retailers, such as Shein and Temu, to send low -value orders to the US .
 
The Directorate of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT -Macau) admitted that there is some impact on Macao due to the measure of the United States to suspend the reception of orders from the continent and Hong Kong, however, this impact is, for the now, “limited”. , he assured. "The measure has, for now, limited impact on Macao, and more information will be announced later," said the CTT-Macau yesterday in statements to Radio Macao in Chinese language. In a statement, CTT announced yesterday the suspension of sending small packages and orders to the United States.
The United States Postal Service (USPS) announced on Tuesday night, local time, that it was “temporarily” to accept orders from the interior of China and Hong Kong, and the measure has immediate effect “until new order ”At a time when the trade war between Washington and Beijing intensifies.
However, USPS has retreated in its position yesterday morning and said it will continue to accept international orders from mainland China and Hong Kong.
According to its initial statement, USPS said the measure does not affect “the flow of cards and normal mail”, but only orders for low value products that previously benefited from exemption from fees.
USPS, although not clarified the reason for the initial decision, said it was related to the new customs tariffs imposed on Tuesday and the elimination of the minimis exemption, and covered articles of less than 800 dollars, which may not be subjected to inspections.
"USPS and Customs and Protection of Borders are working closely to implement an efficient charging mechanism for the new tariffs in China, in order to ensure the least possible disturbance in orders," the service said in an updated statement .
United States President Donald Trump increased customs rates on imports from China by 10%after having retreated in the plans to charge Canada and Mexico. Beijing responded with retaliation measures, including 15% rates on imports of coal, liquefied natural gas, agricultural equipment and other US goods.
The vast majority of goods sent from China arrive outside the mail system, but Trump's order specifically eliminated a tariff exemption for low -value products, purchased directly by consumers and sent through postal service.
USP's initial measure was able to block or delay orders made through Chinese Electronic Trade Platforms Shein and Temu, but also from the American Amazon.
Exemption from fees on buying low value articles has greatly benefited from the two Chinese platforms and Amazon: the number of rates exempt from rates has increased by 600% in the last ten years, reaching 1.36 billion orders last year, against almost almost 140 million in 2015.
According to a report published in June 2023 by the US Congress Committee on China, the two Shein companies and stared together represented more than 30% of all orders sent daily to the United States under the “minimis” arrangement, while almost half Of all packages sent to the “minimis” shelter come from China, according to the report.
Following the announcement, the actions of the Chinese Electronic Trade companies traded on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange fell yesterday: JD.com toppled 5.25% and Alibaba ceded 1.6%.
Orders entering the US under the “minimi” policy may not be subject to restricted control in US customs, which have had a significant impact on the US consumer market, which led to unions and legislators of country to insist on the adoption of response measures.
Reuters previously reported that Chinese suppliers use tax exemption to export chemical materials to Fentanyl through orders for low -cost goods, Washington had accused Beijing of not being doing enough to lock the flow of fentanyl, one, one Dangerous synthetic opiate for the US.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06T06:30:14+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>