<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/numero-de-toxicodependentes-registados-sofreu-aumento-de-244/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Most Chinese university students devalue marriage and children, says study</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/maioria-dos-estudantes-universitarios-chineses-desvaloriza-casamento-e-filhos-diz-estudo/</link><description>The Institute of Psychology of the Chinese Academy of Sciences points out that more than half of Chinese university students do not consider relevant marriage and paternity. In China, the fertility rate continues to fall and, according to local analysts, is located in about one child per woman, placing China above only South Korea in this indicator.
 
 
A report published yesterday by the Institute of Psychology of the Chinese Academy of Sciences indicates that more than half of Chinese university students do not consider relevant marriage and paternity.
The document, which is part of a national report on the development of mental health in the period 2023-2024, is based on inquiries to about 56,000 university students.
According to the results, 51.8% of the students inquired indicated that marriage was not important to them and 59.4% said the same about having children.
The differences between genders are notorious: the number of young women who claim that love is not important is 26% higher than their male colleagues. In the case of marriage, the difference between the two groups was 38%, while to have children the difference reached 35%, in both cases with women to give less importance.
According to the study, published by the China Official Journal of Daily, students of less wealthy means tend to postpone or give up the idea of ​​having children due to the difficulties of getting a stable job and obtaining financial security. Women also consider the possible effects of motherhood on their career opportunities.
The children of troubled marriages, according to the study, tend to avoid constituting a family. Students whose parents have a high level of education reveal a greater tendency to postpone or renounce children, possibly influenced by values ​​centered on personal development, according to the study.
The authors of the report suggest the introduction of contents on personal relationships in educational curricula to foster a vision based on equality and respect, as well as economic policies of support, such as housing, parenting and education subsidies, and public welcoming children and advice on family relationships.
China, who gave the title of most populous nation in the world to India in 2023, according to the UN, abolished the only child policy in 2016, but the fertility rate continues to fall and, according to local analysts, is about one child per woman, placing China above only South Korea in this indicator.
Chinese couples cite the high cost of a child's education and the priority given to their careers as some of the factors that prevent them from deciding to have children. According to official statistics, the number of marriages in China was 6.1 million by 2024, the lowest since 1980.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>“It's a song more exploratory than the one that is on the records”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/e-uma-musica-mais-exploratoria-do-que-aquela-que-esta-nos-discos/</link><description>He was never in Macau or in mainland China, but knows that in the territory there are those who hear his music. In partnership with the Noyb Association (None of Your Business), Portuguese multi-instrumentalist and composer Bruno Pernadas, is about to start his “The Greatest Bay Area Tour 2025”, which will take place from June 12 to 15, in Shenzhen, Macau, Zhuhai and Hong Kong, and states, in an interview with the final point, which will be more exploratory concerts with Original themes. About the show at MSAR, which takes place on June 13, under Portugal Day celebrations, Portuguese and Portuguese communities, reveals that it will play a theme with influences of fashions of Ribatejo or Alentejo, bringing a smell of the European country to the public present.
 
 
 
With a career for over a decade such as guitarist, composer, producer and singer, which records are most comfortable?
In the composition. In the jazz area or makeshift music, improvising is a kind of real -time composition. When he was a child and teenager, he was a more guitarist. When I had my first instrument, my first desire was soon to create music, even though I still don't know how to play a new instrument - I was 10 or 11 years old. It was not learning a repertoire, but to create, even not knowing what I did.
 
It also makes composition for cinema and television. It was even the author of the soundtrack of series like "glory". Is it a very different creation process from the composition of your own music?
It is different and is different from production for production. Still now I finished a movie and it was a completely different process from the others I did. It varies because there is no official way of doing things or rules. We really have to guess what people are thinking, through references, conversations, our own analysis of the film. I don't think it's very easy.
Why is it difficult?
If we have no different resources to be able to create something completely different, or if the director wants something different and we can only do… but there are also a lot of people who, when he invites certain composers, already know the record in which these musicians and composers work. My experiences, in general, have always been positive.
 
What movie is this that end now? Can you reveal?
I can say it's a Galician movie of a director/documentary filmmaker, and that this is your first fiction.
 
Was this one of those difficult cases?
In this case it was not difficult, because I quickly realized what he wanted, what was the kind of sound he wanted to associate with the movie, through the references he gave me and through the songs he used in the first montages. For example, there was a movie called “Patrick”, filmed in Paris and Portugal, Sertã, which is from Gonçalo Waddington, which I made the song - was the only soundtrack I edited, is available online, you can listen to streaming services - and it was the easiest project. It was also done with a long time, which gave to work. I made music for a quintet of ropes and other wind instruments and, both the production and the director and the director assistant, loved the music the first time they heard. It was really a case of those in which the stars were aligned. They loved all the pieces and it was this song that I recorded with a set. The person who recorded was used to recording orchestras and the sound was amazing, because I had the opportunity to see the movie several times at movie festivals and, whenever I saw, thought: We really managed to do something amazing!
 
As for composition for your music, is it a freer process?
Yes, it is completely free and does not use the same instrumentation. The last album was the first album I used a string quartet in my work. I had already used it other times more for cinema, but on a record of mine I had never used it.
 
From jazz to folk, going through pop, MPB or electronic music, there are several musical genres where you browse. Do you feel closer to any of these styles?
No, I have no great barriers or boundaries in the way of listening to music and thinking about music, since I was a child. There are people who confuse them on a record, like in mine, that the songs are very different from each other. But then I think: When you are listening to radio, no one complains that one song is different from the other. It is the predisposition. They know they are in that context and got used to listening to music like that. It is like the duration of the themes: People got used to hearing small themes, because the radio forced them because it came from an ancient story where the singles could only have three minutes. People got used to listening to three minutes music only in a pop music context. The way of listening to music is the same. Since I was a child, I have collected cassettes and CD's with collections. I have always enjoyed collections. I remember that when I started studying jazz, I had jazz collection and this, for some colleagues, was a very strange thing because they were used to listening to the albums of those musicians all jazz and I chose the songs I liked the most. People asked me: How is it possible to listen to music like that? For me, it's very natural. In these issues related to the duration of the themes and the various styles within the same album, for me it makes no confusion at all. It's something I am used to. By the way, I discovered the themes of The Beatles, because my older sister did the same with The Beatles records: she chose the songs she liked best. When I finally heard some records in their original order, it has no longer made sense for me, because it was used to the other [order], in which everything was mixed.
 
But when do you make your albums a guiding thread? Is there a story?
Yes yes. This connection is something in which I invest a lot of time and usually the records have no stop between the songs. The first album does not stop - if there is [pause], there is a second in the middle. I think about albums like movies, not like cinema music. I think of discs as a director thinks of a movie, in space and has an ensemble that works with it, just like I work with the musicians. I already write to think of those people - if it's that musician playing, I'm already writing to think about him. I see myself from operating this production.
 
Is the driving thread never the musical style?
No, but I worry a lot about the connection from one theme to another. The latest album [“Private Reasons” was the hardest to join the pieces, because there were very pop pieces and then there were others closer to exotic music. It was the most complicated.
 
In this tour of China, what will it take? What is in the alignment that can already reveal?
In the concert that I will solo, do not play any songs of the albums. It's like another project. But I'm thinking of joining the alignment two or three themes of the “Worst Summer Ever” album, edited in 2016. It's a completely different concert - aesthetically, but also because I'm alone. I've had the opportunity to do it in Portugal and went very well. Sometimes I do it alone, sometimes I do with a colleague of mine who arrived from the Netherlands and is here in Portugal, who will play with me later in Japan, at the Portuguese Fair.
 
Are they original themes?
These are original new themes, which I have never recorded, but maybe it may happen. There is a video recording, but I never recorded these songs. Whenever people are listening is a kind of "it's here, right now, now."
 
China is a debut. What expectations you have and what you have thought, considering the public of each of the cities you are going to play?
In the case of Japan it was easier the first time I went and even went with a large ensemble at the time. It was easier, because there was a lot of interest there, curators, programmers and record stores in my music. I wasn't sure how the public would react, but I knew there were many people who bought the records. In Macao, there are some people who know my music, but in the case of Japan, it was a surprise-the first time we played, the concert was at 7 pm and I remember going to the room and it was 15 minutes to 7pm and nobody was. I thought, "Well, it was good to travel here across the world, but it's going to be a little flop, no one is there to see the concert." But then, at the right time, it was full. The space was completely crowded and the concert was an experience from another world. I know the same will not happen in China, because, statistically, there are fewer listeners and the concert will be different, but there was never a concert of these that they had not liked. Of course it depends on the public too. It is a song more exploratory than the one on the albums. There is more improvisation. Regarding concerts in China, the only thing I didn't want - and I don't want to do it in other places either - is to play a very large place, that is, in very capable show or auditoriums. If it is justified, yes, but I prefer to make this concert solo, in smaller places, where I am closer to people.
 
Produced a record from a Japanese band. Is there a possibility for this to happen in China too?
In China no, but in Korea yes. We haven't closed the process yet.
 
In China, there will be several concerts in different cities and then goes to Japan to play on June 17 in Osaka and June 18 in Tokyo. In Japan will you have a different alignment?
It is possible that some songs are part of it, but it is another alignment.
 
This is not the first time it plays in Japan. What will be again over the previous concerts?
I will play in Duo [with musician José Soares] this time. A concert is at Expo Osaka, framed in the context of the Portugal Pavilion, at Expo, which has been there since February and will be until October, and have been there huge Portuguese from various areas. For the videos I have followed, there is a lot of desire for the public who is at the fair to watch the concerts. I know it's in an outdoor space, but it's different. It is completely different. The other concert will also be in duo and will be with some Japanese artists [The Hatch] - they organized and we will make a concert to socks. In the other years I went, I always played at the same festival, which is the fruue and the fruiezinho. It is possible to go back to Japan, until next year, already in the context of the new album, to play in the frue. For now, none of this has been marked.
 
The concert in Macao will be in the context of the celebrations of Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese communities. Will the alignment and the songs that take to the concert bear this?
Yes, exactly. There is a theme, which I will play, which is a kind of a suite and, in the midst of this suite, there are several minications, as if they were several fashions, as if they were fashion of Ribatejo or Alentejo - melodic motifs of fashion. In other contexts it could be confused with music from Mexico or other places, but if it is a Portuguese listening, you will realize that it really comes from this place. I also heard a lot of fado when I was a child and I always liked it - I still like it! I always like to listen to certain singers and this side of the Portuguese tradition will be at the concert right now.
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
H</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hong Kong inaugurates world mediation center “at the level of the Hague Court”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/hong-kong-inaugura-centro-mundial-de-mediacao-ao-nivel-do-tribunal-de-haia/</link><description>The first non -western headquarters of an important world legal organism, the International Organization for Mediation (Iomed) in Hong Kong, is inaugurated today. John Lee, head of the Raehk executive, indicated that the institution will have a status “equivalent to that of the International Court of Justice” in The Hague.
 
 
Hong Kong today inaugurates the first non-western headquarters of an important world legal organism, the International Organization for Mediation (Iomed), at a time when Beijing seeks to impose itself as an international dispute resolution center.
Hong Kong Executive Chief John Lee indicated on Tuesday that the institution will have a status “equivalent to that of the International Court of Justice” in The Hague, which “will reinforce the city's international position, attract economic benefits and improve the rule of law,” the EFE news agency wrote.
The leader of the region has stated that the Center will facilitate Hong Kong's commercial and economic cooperation with international partners, especially the countries of the Chinese infrastructure project known as a new silk route, "creating more business opportunities."
In a reaction to the creation of Iomed, China's main diplomatic representative in the neighboring region of Macau stressed that it will be the first center “specializing in international dispute resolution”.
China's Foreign Ministry Commissioner in Macao, Liu Xianfa, who was speaking at the opening of a Sino-Lusophone Forum at the University of Macao, said that the inauguration reflects Beijing's desire to be "a positive force for the peaceful development of humanity."
Iomed's inauguration ceremony will be attended by Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi and high representatives from about 60 countries, as well as delegates from about two dozen international organizations, including the United Nations.
Iomed's creation was proposed in 2022 by China and about 20 nations and, after intense negotiations, it was decided that the headquarters would be located in Hong Kong.
The body will be the first intergovernmental international entity dedicated exclusively to the resolution of international disputes through mediation, defending the principles of the United Nations Charter in a context of growing global tensions and challenges to traditional conflict resolution systems.
The new institution is born in a context in which mechanisms such as the World Trade Organization Differential Resolution System and international investment arbitration face criticism for long procedures, high costs and inconsistent results.
Sebastián Contin Trillo-Figureoa, Asia-Europe's analyst, told the EFE agency that the creation of Iomed "is a masterful move from China, consolidating his" soft power "[diplomatic and cultural power] strategy without generating open resistance."
The expert pointed out that "this movement demonstrates China's ability to identify and occupy niches in the international system, highlighting an institutional construction similar to the Asian infrastructure investment bank, which reflects a strategic approach to expanding its global influence."
"Geopolitically, the absence of rejection by Western countries reinforces the perception that China has performed an effective diplomatic operation. The apparent US passivity before Chinese leadership in international institutions suggests a lost opportunity to counteract Chinese discourse as moral and civilizational power," he added.
Trillo-Figureoa noted that "in a world of increasing tensions," mediation "may be more significant than several United Nations initiatives, which face ideological and bureaucratic limitations, thus consolidating the role of China as a central actor in global diplomacy."
The analyst stressed that, for Hong Kong, the initiative is "the most relevant" approved by local and national authorities since the entry into force of the National Security Act in 2020. It reinforces the position of the region "as a legal center and exceptional service provider for large companies and multinationals."
The Deputy Secretary for Hong Kong Justice, Horace Cheung, indicated that the organization's headquarters could open at the end of 2025 or early 2026.
"It will significantly raise Hong Kong's international image as a global center for mediation and bring multiple benefits, including improvements in the economy, political status, cultural influence and international impact," he said on social networks.
Cheung pointed out that Hong Kong Statute as a mediation center "can attract more international organizations, non-governmental organizations and academic entities, thus generating more job opportunities."</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Association accuses Macau of wanting to limit journalism to the instrument of propaganda</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/associacao-acusa-macau-de-querer-limitar-jornalismo-a-instrumento-de-propaganda/</link><description>The Society of Journalists and Professionals of European Communication in Asia (JOCPA) says that the Government of Macao that "redefines journalism", transforming it into a "instrument of state propaganda."
 
An association of media professionals told Lusa to be concerned about statements from the Macao government that they seek to “redefine journalism (…) as a state propaganda instrument”.
Hours earlier, the secretary for MSAR Security, Wong Sio Chak, defended at a press conference that, in addition to journalists, "all people have a duty to tell Macau's story well."
A statement that “signals a worrying change in the sense of a more restrictive environment” in which journalism is seen “not as a pillar of democratic accountability,” warned the president of the Society of Journalists and European Communication professionals in Asia (JOCPA).
"Macao's current administration has increasingly given priority to narrative security and control over transparency and journalistic independence," Josep Solano lamented.
"The fundamental duty of journalists is not 'to tell a good story', but to look for the truth, to hold the powers responsible and to report the facts - even when they are uncomfortable," said the JOCPA. "Journalism that only echoes official narratives is no longer journalism," the group added in a statement.
Josep Solano demonstrated "particular concern" about the reference to statements by Xia Baolong, head of Beijing, who told local businessmen who should "tell the story of Hong Kong, Macao and China to the world."
"These guidelines, if interpreted as normative expectations for all communicators and" media professionals ", sketch the boundaries between journalism and state propaganda," warned the JOCPA.
Wong Sio Chak argued that journalists “are no exception” to the duty to comply with the law when asked about the arrest of two reporters at the door of the Legislative Assembly on 17 April. "When journalists are detained and the official speech suggests that they should align with the prescribed narratives, the result - intentional or not - is an intimidating atmosphere for the independent press," said Josep Solano.
Authorities should “avoid actions that can be perceived as punitive or intimidating in relation to the media”, defended the president of the JOCPA.
This, because, "even if the intention is not to repress," the result will be "to instill caution, fear or self -censorship among journalists - particularly those who cover sensitive or critical issues," said Solano.
"Freedom of the press is not an exception, but a fundamental principle in any system based on the rule of law. The law must protect the press, not to be used as a weapon against it," the JOCPA warned.
The president admitted that in Macao "laws are being used in ways that seem to want to aim or intimidate press members."
The jocpa also called on to the government of Portugal to "express its concern on this matter, even if the individuals involved are not Portuguese citizens." "This gesture would reaffirm its commitment to the universality of human rights and freedom of expression," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:27:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Insulae</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/insulae/</link><description>The expression Roman house will bring to the imagination of people a large house with a garden inside, a source in the middle, columns, painted walls, decorative mosaic on the floor, among other refinements. This is Domus, the house of Dominus. In Conímbriga there is only the gardens and some columns, which, however, were rebuilt, of these domus that once belonged to the Roman aristocracy of Western Lusitania.
The word Dominus, which will be known to those who studied Latin or once went to a Latin mass, derives from Domus, one of the Latin words to designate home. Thus the domain is the [man] of the house; The suffix -inus denotes possession, so Gallina 'chicken' is Gallus 'rooster'.
In Portuguese, Dominus gave two words, owner and gift, the latter fell into disuse, but still applies to members of the nobility and high clergy, E.G. D. Duarte de Bragança. The Portuguese Terms Owner and Dom point to one of the semantic characteristics behaved by the word Dominus, someone with economic power and status.
The word gift, as a form of respect, is, in common language, replaced by sir of Senior Latin, a word that originally means exactly this, senior or older, as opposed to Junior or younger; Senior and Junior still use today to distinguish father and son when both have the same name. Thus, when we say Mr. D. Duarte, we are, in fact, saying Lord Duarte is, by the way, what occurs when the election of the Pope is announced where the word Dominus is repeated in the formula of Habemus Papam. If we take as an example the announcement of the election of Benedict XVI, ‘Annuntio vobis gaudium magnum, habemus papam, eminentissimum ac reverendissimum dominum dominum iosephum, sanctae romane ecclesiae cardinalem ratzinger’, the correct Portuguese translation would be 'advertisement of great joy, we have papa, the very eminent and the papa Most Reverend Lord D. José Ratzinger, Cardinal of the Holy Roman Church '. Sometimes, in the past, to differentiate the dominus 'sir' form from the Dominus 'gift' form, the second was written.
The word dominates, the wife of Dominus, gave in Portuguese owner, who serves to designate the owner of anything - the owner of the corner coffee -, a form of respect - the Dona Maria do Café da Esquina - and the title noble –d. Maria Pia, Queen of Portugal.
If the word Dominus moved into the common language, the word Domus did not have the same fate, and was replaced in popular language by the Latin word. While Domus referred to the house of Dominus, someone of economic power, holder of slaves and land, the ordinary people lived in humblest houses or even in huts, hence the word home, which in Latin means exactly that, hiller. The rule, which obviously has exceptions, is that the word that passes to the common language, and hence to the Romance languages, is the one that is most used by the people.
The term Latin Domus gave in Italian, Duomo, a word used to refer to the local Cathedral, il Duomo, and the Englishman who, through the medieval Frenchman Domme, was imported from the Italian to refer to the typical summit of the Italian cathedrals.
 
Apartments for Rent in Rome
In ancient Rome, the home of the people had different shapes and sizes depending on not only the economic power of each, but also the area where it was inhabited.
Around the first century of our era, the population of Rome exceeded one million inhabitants, thus becoming in the most populous city in the ancient world. After two thousand years, Rome has less than three million inhabitants. The metropolitan zone of Rome is about four and a half million inhabitants, but it is made up of several satellite cities that serve as a dorm for those who work in the Italian capital.
The Roman Empire has achieved its maximum extension in territory and population around 117, the year of Trajan's death (53-117, Emperor since 98) with the conquest of Dacia, where it is now part of Romania today. By this time, the population of the Empire will have reached, about 75 million inhabitants. After the fall of the Empire, the European population would only reach similar numbers in the mid -thirteenth century again. Black plague (1347–1351) decreased by 30% to 60% of the European population, depending on the region. At the entrance of the fifteenth century, the population of Europe had fallen to about 45 million inhabitants and would only return to the pre-heavy values ​​in the mid-16th century.
Back in Rome, as expected, such a high population density causes housing problems. Obviously, the Romans could no longer live in their traditional ground floor homes. Most of the population within the urban perimeter of the city lived in insulae, which were no more than a multi -storey apartment blocks. Roman insulae are the first civil housing structure known in history and their traces can be found in Rome, Pompeii, Herculaneum, and Antiqua Optia.
In the ground floor of the insulae were the Tabernae, or stores. Although in Portuguese Taberna refers to an establishment where drinks and food is served, in Latin Taberna is a store that sells whatever, from books to clothing. For the Romans, our taverns were Thermopolia, establishments where you could eat and drink. The second floor of the Tabernae, a kind of mezzanine, could be used as a warehouse or tabernary accommodation. Between the ground floor and the first floor, the ceiling was usually vaulted in brick and concrete, which the Romans already knew and used.
The first floor was where the most expensive apartments were, with high ceilings, walls and decorated ceilings, windows and balconies. As priced were descended, consequently it is on the superior floors of the insulae that the poorest lived, where there was no running water or sewage. [The Romans already had running water, sewage and, in certain more luxurious domus, until central warming that propagated on the ground and inside the walls.]
The insulae, that is, the apartments, varied in size and quality, with apartments that were no more than a tiny room without window. The plant of the floors could be modified with wood partitions according to the needs of the moment. At first one could also add floors at the top to increase the number of insulae to rent. Many insulae were organized around a central courtyard and even accommodated more than 350 people, and many of these insulae were virtually vertically tin neighborhoods where the noise, confusion, to get and out of people, family disputes and neighbors reign.
With the progressive increase in the number of insulae, mainly caused by the arrival in Rome of people from all parts of the Empire, and the number of floors of these, Emperor Augustus (63 BC AD, Emperor since 27 BC), the first to legislate on this matter, determined that the insulae could not exceed 20 meters.
Wood, being a cheap and easily adaptable material, abounded the insulae, which considerably increased the danger of both fire and collapse. In a letter to his Attic Friend, written in the year 45, Cicero complains about the collapse of two stores that had rented: ‘Duae Tabernae Meae Cum Aedibus Incommodissime Sunt Dirutae, Reliquae Concidunt. Itaque nec drivers iam ulli nec coloni, ne musesm ’, that is,‘ two stores I had, for my bad luck, collapsed along with the buildings, the others go the same way! That is, the employees, the tenants, were all, they were not even rats! '
The fires in the insulae were frequent because the poorest had no kitchen, and when trying to cook in their tiny rooms, they eventually set fire to the entire building. The fire, once started, there was no way to escape him, especially on the upper floors. In this context, Juvenal satirizes the bad luck of those who lived on the top floor: ‘nam si gradibus trepidatur ab imis, | Ultimus Ardebit Who Tegula Sola Tuetur | The rain, Molles Ubi Reddunt Ova Columba ', that is, ‘If sounds the alarm on the floors below, the last to burn is the type that, between him and the rain, has only one tile, where doves, without giving anything, lay their eggs.'
The fires in the city of Rome were very often; In fact, there were several fires every day. As such the City of Rome has created a kind of fire brigade, that is, employees paid by the city entirely dedicated to erasing fireworks.
The great fire of the year 64, in the reign of Nero (37–68, emperor since 54), lasted almost nine days and completely destroyed ten of the fourteen districts of Rome. Pictured as a madman, Nero appears in Hollywood movies at the window of his palace reciting poetry and playing Lira as he sees the city that burns. This image is mainly due to the Tacitian historian (56-120) who, in his life of the twelve Caesars, refers to a rumor that existed at the time that it was Nero who had the fire set forth in order to create space for its new palace, Domus Aurea. At the time, however, the fault was attributed to Christians and thus began the great Neronian persecution of Christians.
Following this fire, Nero reduced the height of the insulae to 17 meters, also having the width of the streets so that it was more difficult for the fires to spread to neighboring buildings. Among other anti-innant measures adopted, it was also determined that there should be a counterfog space or brick wall among the buildings.
As with any densely populated modern metropolis, life in the city of Rome was not easy, especially in the neighborhoods and suburbs where the humblest people lived. Suburra, a precarious neighborhood behind the Caesar Forum, became so famous for its unhealthiness and decay that the word suburris became synonymous with social decay and crime.
 
A Man’s House is His Castle
Rome was the target of successive immigration vacancies of people and people who came to Urbe, looking for better luck, attracted by the imagined charm of the largest city in the world, or to do business - Roma was, after all, the financial center of the world of the time. This immigration that began with the establishment of the Empire is responsible for many of Rome's demographic problems.
Today, the capitals and large cities in Europe are assisting similar demographic problems, caused not only by migratory phenomena, but also by a phenomenon that was unknown to the Romans, massive tourism.
Since a week or two, at Barajas airport in Madrid, passengers have to prove that they will actually travel so that the airport has become one of the favorite places, if so, the homeless. There are, in fact, whole families living in the airport waiting zones.
This happens at the same time that, in several Spanish cities, the people begin to manifest against the exponential increase in price and the scarcity of housing thanks to tourism. These manifestations began in the Canary Islands, which, incidentally, live almost entirely from tourism. There the people went massively on the street to claim the right to live in their own land. It followed him Barcelona, ​​where tourism also represents a significant slice of local performance.
What is behind these demonstrations is that houses and apartments prefer to rent tourists through platforms such as Airbnb instead of making them available to the long-term local lease market. This has led several people in the Canary Islands - people who have a job, such as high school teachers - to have to live in their cars or in leased caravans because they can't find housing, sometimes, not even a quarter, since everything that exists is reserved for tourism that can pay much more than the local population.
These cases, by the way, give voice to one of the most glaring problems we assist today, the people who work, but who have to live on the street or in public spaces, such as airports or trains stations, or, lucky, they have to depend on the favor of friends, colleagues or family members.
The homeless phenomenon, including those who have work, is one of the problems that does not stop growing and for which there is no solution. In Portugal this phenomenon can be seen, for example, at Gare do Oriente, in Lisbon. The area where the bathrooms are located is covered with homeless, many of which are emigrants, who will sleep refugees from the weather.
Much has been said lately about emigration and I imagine much more will be said in the near future. Immigration is a cyclical problem that, now and then knocks on us at the door. At the end of the Roman Empire, we had a massive migratory flow, also caused by people who came looking for better living conditions, which we refer to as barbaric invasions and who was responsible, at least in part, for breaking the power structures of the time.
Europe has suffered various migratory flows throughout its history, for example, in the thirteenth century, when many of its citizens left the fields to the cities, or in the nineteenth century, when, especially in England and Germany, the cannon meat needed to keep the industrial revolution on the suburbs of large cities into centers of material and moral misery.
Portugal, in the sixteenth century, also found arms with problems derived from migration and emigration; If, on the one hand, many left the field to come to Lisbon, where the money swept in front of the broom, others abandoned the kingdom and their families to try their luck in the new Portuguese territories in Tre-Mar. One of the consequences of this male -mainstanding population was the scarcity of specialized labor in Lisbon at a time when money abounded.
The difference between these migratory flows of the past and the immigration of these days is that we see the consequences in movie movies or television series while we have to deal with them in our everyday life.
In the campaign that preceded the last elections in Portugal, whose final results we will know today, the immigration topic was quite crowded. What is the result of so much discussion, it is to see, but whatever the position people and politicians have about this phenomenon, behind immigration are people. Or well that the entry of these people are entry into the country or well that, who lets them enter, do their position. What cannot be accepted is that these people continue to enter Portugal and then live on the street or in public spaces as if they were abandoned dogs. We cannot allow our parks, trains stations and other public spaces to become a kind of living cemeteries to which the most minimal dignity is denied to them. Beyond the enormous cruelty this represents, in the face of our inability, as individuals, to do whatever it is to put it to this, when trying to escape the depression that this situation causes us, in the end we are used to leading our lives, as if those people were not there. The indifference that will necessarily result from this process and which is no more than a form of resistance and safeguarding our sanity, will necessarily also lead to our own dehumanization. We risk becoming islands, or Latin, insulase, isolated and oblivious to others, something that goes deeply against our Mediterranean and Christian nature that we inherit from the Romans.
 
Insulae
From the Latin word insula derives the Portuguese island, from Spanish Isla and the French île. The Latin word insula is better represented phonetically in the near-island or peninsula of Portuguese.
The Roman insulae to which we referred to in this article were blocks, if we want to say, of apartments, or insulae in the plural, each apartment was an inlance in the singular. The building that supported these apartments was designated as an insulae, ie, set or cluster of 'insets'.
Why does the designation insulae? First, let's look at the word apartment, which we use today. This word means exactly the same as it is inserted, as it denotes the isolated and isolator character of the space in which it is lived. Apartment comes from separating, which means to put aside or separate from the others. At first, apartment was the word reserved for part of the palace where the king and royal family led their private life, apart from the eyes of the other members of the Court. Now the insula is exactly this, a form of isolation of others within a space shared by many people. In these spaces full of strange people, people found their islands of refuge, or, to use a more modern, privacy word, in the midst of the confusion of a rome overlife with people.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:28:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Registered failure at Taishan's nuclear center</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/registada-falha-na-central-nuclear-de-taishan/</link><description>A failure at the Taishan Nuclear Center led to the activation of the emergency generator and to workers' inspection work, although no damages are recorded or escapes. The incident happened days after a Macau delegation visited the site and ensured the intention to reinforce cooperation with Guangdong in the response to incidents in nuclear centers.
 
 
The Taishan Nuclear Center in Guangdong noted a connection failure that forced the interruption of energy and automatic emergency diesel engine.
The incident was reported yesterday to the Unit Police Services (SPU) by the Guangdong Province Nuclear Management and Emergency Commission Office, in compliance with the “Cooperation Agreement in the Guangdong Nuclear Central Emergency Emergency Management between Guangdong and Macau” signed by both parties in 2018.
According to the Chinese authorities, the incident happened when Taishan's nuclear central unit 1 performed the change of the transformer assisted by panel to the factory transformer and caused a connection failure that delayed the junction of the gate, leading to automatic activation of the emergency diesel engine. The supply of electricity was resumed after the central workers perform inspection actions on site to ensure the safety of operations.
In a statement, the SPU stress that unit 1 maintained the “safe and stable” operation during treatment, and no damage was recorded in the three safety barriers or escapes of radioactive substances. “Taishan's joint nuclear power company has in accordance with the successful supervision and control entity and will start feedback from internal experiences,” he says.
The occurrence was classified as a level 0 operational incident, as it did not have threats to the safety of the central, operational personnel, neighboring population and adjacent environment. In the same statement, SPU clarifies that level 0 “serves essentially for the correction of deviations and return of experiences” and is not part of the International Nuclear Accident Scale (Ines), which classifies events from level 1 to 7.
The detailed descriptions of the situation can be consulted on the Taishan's joint nuclear energy website on the “Operational Incidents” page of the “Nuclear Security Information” tab.
 
Macau wants to reinforce response to nuclear incidents
 
Last Friday, four days before the succeeded, Macao authorities visited the Taishan Nuclear Center and held a meeting on Guangdong-Macau cooperation for the response to incidents in nuclear power plants.
Wong Sio Chak, the secretary for the Security of MSAR, pointed out that since the cooperation agreement was signed, "both parties have maintained narrow communication and cooperation and have effectively implement the agreed content and continually reinforce information sharing."
During this annual meeting, Wong Sio Chak said he hoped the exchange and cooperation between both parties could continue to deepen and extend to all aspects in the area of ​​nuclear emergency, such as 'on-site' visits to nuclear centers, vocational training courses and thematic lectures, “in order to raise nuclear risk prevention awareness and the capacity of nuclear emergency treatment of service staff. competent from Macau ”.
In turn, Zhang Shaokang, head of the Guangdong Province Nuclear Emergency Management Committee and Guangdong Province Popular Government's deputy governor, has ensured that the two regions “will further reinforce the exchange and promote the construction of nuclear emergency response capacity, promoting continuous reinforcement of nuclear emergencies between Guangdong and Macao”.
The bilateral cooperation mechanism was signed on January 8, 2018 by the governments of Guangdong and MSAR province in Zhuhai, with the aim of creating an effective response capacity for potential incidents that may occur in the nuclear centers of Taishan and the surrounding regions.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:26:12</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Portugal are “old friends who share the same ideals,” says Lam</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/china-e-portugal-sao-velhos-amigos-que-compartilham-os-mesmos-ideais-afirma-o-lam/</link><description>In a speech given at the opening ceremony of the Think Tanks Forum between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, the secretary for social affairs and culture argued that Macau should act as a “connecting link” between China and the Lusophone community, as well as taking responsibility for “spreading to the world” the stories of Macao and China.
 
 
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, has pointed out that she intends to enhance the role of Macao as a platform for connection and exchange between Portuguese -speaking countries and China, consolidating her “unique character” as a confluence point of oriental and western cultures.
In the opening speech of the Think Tanks Forum between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, which took off yesterday at the University of Macao, the ruler began to remember an old Chinese proverb: "Those who share the same ideals do not see distances like barriers." Likewise, and despite the large geographical distance, the “friendly relationships” between both countries have made it from the “ancient times” of the sea silk route to the current economic, commercial and cultural exchanges. "China and Portuguese -speaking countries are old friends and good friends who share the same ideals," he said.
LAM revealed that this year's edition of the Forum, subordinate to the theme “Achieving Consensus on Global Development, joining efforts for world modernization”, focuses on two main topics: “Sharing experiences on modernization processes in various countries” and “joint vision of the course for modernization”. The intention of the ruler is that the debates carried out by participants allow us to understand how to achieve advantages and mutual benefits and contribute to the sharing of the “Chinese -style modernization path” with Lusophone countries.
"As a witness, a participant and beneficiary of Chinese modernization, Macau has the responsibility to publicize the history of Macao and the history of China," said Lam. In turn, the Chinese side is willing to "adopt an even more open stance" in the deepening of relations with Portugal, namely in the domains of trade and investment, academic investigation, cooperation between "Think Tanks" and of increasingly frequent cultural exchanges.
Macao status as a bridge between two worlds was intensified at the end of last year, with the visit of Xi Jinping to Macau and several speeches in which the Chinese president described the region as "a very important window for the abroad." The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture considers that the recognition of Macao's strategic position accentuates the territory's “responsibility” to assume itself as a center of confluence of ideas and union between different civilizations, as contemplated in the beginning “one country, two systems”.
The opening ceremony of the Think Tanks Forum took place yesterday at 9:30 am at the University of Macao Ho Yin Convention Center (one). In addition to the Chinese representatives and the Government of MSAR, the event also brought together experts and academics from eight Portuguese-speaking countries: Portugal, Brazil, Angola, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Mozambique and Timor-Leste.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:28:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Pecuniary reimbursement starts on July 15 and excludes those who were not in Macau for 183 days</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/comparticipacao-pecuniaria-comeca-a-15-de-julho-e-exclui-quem-nao-esteve-em-macau-durante-183-dias/</link><description>The government has introduced a new requirement to this year's pecuniary reimbursement plan to exclude residents who have not been in Macao at least 183 days throughout 2024. The regulation provides, however, several exceptions to this requirement. The amount of the amount begins on July 15. André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice, reiterated yesterday that pecuniary reimbursement is not a permanent measure and the government now aims to focus on financial resources in people who “have a narrow connection with Macao”.
 
 
This year, the attribution of the monetary reimbursement will start on July 15 and the government came this year to add a new condition on the permanence in Macao. The holders of the resident identity ticket must have been in the territory at least 183 days throughout 2024 to be eligible for the reception of the amount.
The Executive Board presented yesterday the administrative regulation of the pecuniary reimbursement plan for this year, which provides, at the same time, exceptions to the new requirement.
According to the document, “to pay special attention to certain groups of people”, there are three types of individuals who are exempt from verifying the time of stay in Macau, including those who have not completed 22 years of age last year and any of their parents are able to receive the monetary reimbursement; and those who are receiving the disability pension or disability allowance.
The Executive, having as reference the provisions on the central social security regime, still establishes eight reasons, for those outside Macao, so that their absence is justified.
These reasons comprise the course of the course of higher education recognized on site; hospital hospitalization; have a domicile in the interior of China when they have been 65 years of age or, having not been 65 years old, health reasons justify it; the provision of work outside Macao to an employer enrolled in the Social Security Fund; the provision of work outside Macao, when responsible for the subsistence of members of their household, who have a domicile in Macao; the exercise of official functions; HAVE HOUSE IN HENGQIN, work on site or higher education course or not higher education, recognized on site; and work in the cities of mainland China integrated in the Great Bay. In this sense, residents living and work in Hong Kong are not covered.
In this case, people absent from Macau due to any of the eight reasons may require counting the period of stay in Macau to receive the amount.
 
Amount remains the same
 
This year's checks on checks remains unchanged, and each permanent resident will be assigned ten thousand patacas and to the non-permanent six thousand patacas. Residents can see if it is eligible for checking checks through the application of a single account or the official electronic page of the pecuniary reimbursement plan.
As for residents who are classified as having not met the requirements, but are outside Macao for legally planned reasons, they may submit the application to the Social Security Fund (FSS) between June 18 this year and December 31, 2028. FSS will appreciate the request and assign the amount within one month after its approval.
According to the calendar of the amount of the amount, the reception by automatic transfer happens between July 15 and August, while the reception of the letter with the check will be completed between July 22 and 13 August depending on the date of birth.
 
“It is not a permanent benefit system”
 
André Cheong, spokesman for the Executive Council, reiterated yesterday the nature of the monetary reimbursement as a “temporary measure”, but not a permanent benefit system. Also Secretary for Administration and Justice therefore dismissed the possibility of creating a permanent mechanism that associates the attribution of checks with the budgetary surplus.
At yesterday's press conference, André Cheong recalled that the government has since 2008 implemented the pecuniary reimbursement plan in response to the impact of the financial crisis on the economy of height, as well as to alleviate the pressure of inflation in resident lives. He explained that this year introduced changes to the regime hoping to attribute public resources to residents who “have a narrow connection with Macau”.
"The purpose of the plan is to assist [financial] to residents. This does not change even now new requirement. Residents also face economic problems, as the geopolitical environment is not optimistic," admitted the secretary.
He added that in Macau there are also “difficulties and problems in the community economy and local consumption” although inflation is not on the rise. "This money can help residents and, on the other hand, after receiving the value, can spend it on local consumption and promote the economic development of the community. This is the purpose of the plan," he said.
 
Without advance budget and number of beneficiaries
 
However, the government said it does not yet know the number of beneficiaries, as well as the estimated value that can save after the imposition of Macau's new permanence requirement to the plan, since "it is difficult to estimate at this time."
André Cheong stressed that, according to the data provided by the ID managers, the number of owners of the Macao resident identity ticket surrounded the 753,000 by the end of last year, but "it is still difficult to estimate how many of them meet the 183 -day permanence requirement in Macao."
Already the amount saved also "it is difficult to calculate", however the secretary assured that this money will be used to improve the welfare of the population and promote community economic development, rather than going to the financial reserve.
The secretary also pointed out that the government has heard opinions "from different sectors of society", including advisory bodies, associations and media, but also "paid attention to comments on social networks." Thus, he considered that the public “fully participated in the debates” although a public consultation was not organized.
The requirement for Macao's permanence should be for next year, said André Cheong, ensuring that the government will continue to listen to society on the subject.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:29:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Towards a new realism in US foreign policy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/rumo-a-um-novo-realismo-na-politica-externa-dos-eua/</link><description>When US Vice President Jd Vance gave the main speech at the US Naval Academy Diploma ceremony in 2025, he outlined the main characteristics of the new US foreign policy, which may be considered a new realism in the development of US foreign policy under Donald Trump's second administration.
While the first part of his speech congratulated the Naval Academy graduates, the second part delineated their ideas about US foreign policy under the Trump administration (see: Transcript of Jd Vance’s Class of 2025 Commissioning Ceremony Speech - Capital Gazette).
First of all, Vance stated that the US entered a "very dangerous era," which means that it has realized that the world is entering a multipolar world, although it has not used the term multipolar. Vance added that President Trump's recent visit to Qatar, Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates meant "the end of an approach of decades on foreign policy" which, in his opinion, was "a break with the precedent established by the [US] founding parents." Vance admitted that US supremacy in the world is now challenged by other countries following the collapse of the former Soviet Union, adding that "for a brief period, we were a pairless superpower." But Americans, according to Vance, did not believe that any foreign nation could compete with the US.
Secondly, Vance criticized the previous US foreign policy, as Washington "had a long experience in [his] foreign policy that changed national defense and maintaining [US] alliances for building nations and interference with foreign countries, even when these foreign countries had very little to do with fundamental American interests." He added that what Americans are seeing is a "generational change in politics with profound implications." Specifically, if the US intervenes in the affairs of any country, this intervention will have to be effective.
Thirdly, Vance denied the myth that economic integration would make other countries, such as China, increasingly similar to the US. He noted that "many of us believe that economic integration would naturally lead peace, making countries like the China Popular Republic more like the US." In short, Vance believes that economic integration and globalization would not make countries developing, including China, more like the US. Nor does it think that this economic integration leads to "peace."
In fourth place, Vance criticized the previous US leaders who closed the idealistic theme of making "the world converge into a uniform set of secular and universal ideals, regardless of culture or country, and those who did not want to converge, well, our political decision makers would aim to force them by all necessary means." It is interesting to note that Vance is a realist who points out the failure of the previous US foreign policy of promoting Western -style democracy in other parts of the world. If so, it is understandable that the second Trump administration has removed its support from pro-democracy and transnational organizations in the US.
Fifth, Vance stated that the Trump administration reversed the previous foreign foreign policy adopted by the US government. The US, according to Vance, should return to "a strategy based on the realism and protection of our fundamental national interests." As such, it is understandable that the Trump administration defended a reciprocal tariff policy for many countries, including China, although recently both Washington and Beijing have made mutual concessions to reduce their reciprocal and retaliatory tariffs.
In sixth place, Vance stated that when US military power is used, it must be used effectively and accurately, such as US forces acted against the Hethis who attacked US ships.
In seventh place, although the US maintains its dissuasive policy, this dissuasion represents a "principle -based foreign policy" with "a red line." In other words, the new US foreign policy is a policy of principles “with objectives, with superior force, superior weapons and the best people in the world”.
In eighth place, Vance considered China, Russia, and other emerging nations such as "serious threats" that are "determined to defeat" the US "in all domains, from the splee to the low orbit of Earth, our supply chains and to our communication infrastructures." As such, the US should use the "right tools" effectively when "we send our troops to war."
In ninth place, to maintain the US technological advantage, Trump administration is investing in innovation and rationalizing the acquisition of weapons. The use of cutting -edge technology will be a necessity in US efforts to achieve their advantage and technological sophistication.
In tenth place, Vance has appealed to the Navy and, of course, to all the Armed Forces, to use new equipment, new systems and new technologies during the new era when US supremacy in the world has already been dealt with. As such, the US should develop its modernization, which includes not only tactics and tools, but also a better education and better military mission, in which military officers can sacrifice their lives.
The main points discussed in Vance's speech point to a new standard of realism in US foreign policy. In the past, especially for many years after the collapse of the former Soviet Union, the US has adopted a foreign policy to promote democracy and American -style values ​​in other parts of the world, but this foreign policy is now seen by Trump administration, especially since some countries refuse to absorb or adopt this democratic system and values. After the collapse of the former Soviet Union, US leadership, at least before the second Trump administration, considered military intervention necessary in some countries, but for the second Trump administration this approach was ineffective. As Vance argues, military intervention has to be accurate, effective and directed.
Vance's perspective reveals a change in US foreign policy, stressing the importance of adapting to a rapidly mutated global panorama. He stressed the need for the US to recalibrate their strategies and to focus on their fundamental national interests rather than involved in widely building exercises that often produce limited results and dilute American power.
The appeal to a realistic approach to international relations is in line with Vance's criticism of the policies of previous administrations. He stressed the importance of effective and accurate military interventions, advocating disciplined use of force that protects American interests without unnecessary involvement. This strategic pragmatism marks a removal of idealistic views that previously influenced the US external commitments.
In addition, Vance's observations underline the growing importance of technological innovation in maintaining US competitive advantage. The investment of the Trump Administration in Advanced Military Technology and the simplification of weapon acquisition processes aims to reinforce the country's defense capabilities and ensure their superiority in critical domains.
Vance also stressed the importance of adapting to this new era, investing in technological advances and simplifying weapon acquisition processes. His observations underline a change to a more pragmatic and strategic approach to US foreign policy, stressing the need for accuracy in military interventions and safeguarding fundamental national interests. This represents a removal of the most idealistic and expansive strategies of previous administrations, favoring a concentration in practical and measurable results. Defense of a reciprocal tariff policy and investment in technological innovation by second administration Trump further enhances Washington's commitment to maintaining and reinforcing US supremacy in an increasingly competitive global landscape.
Vance stressed that maintaining technological advantage is crucial for the US to stay ahead of its competitors. By focusing on innovation and modernization, Trump administration aims to increase the efficiency and effectiveness of the Armed Forces, ensuring that they are well equipped to face any emerging threats.
The new Tonic in “Modernization”, which encompasses new equipment, systems and training, is crucial for adapting to a world where US dominion is no longer unconnected. In addressing the threats placed by emerging powers such as China and Russia, Vance stressed the need for a foreign policy based on principles and supported by a higher force and strategic clarity. He acknowledged the determination of these nations to challenge US supremacy in various spheres, from the low terrestrial orbit to the global supply chains. Therefore, the US should use the correct instruments and strategies to effectively combat these threats and safeguard their interests.
The move to a tripolar world, led by the US, China and Russia, requires a deeper understanding of global dynamics and the implementation of policies that reflect this new reality. Vance's view of a more realistic and focused US foreign policy is indicative of the broader changes that are occurring in Trump administration as it seeks to navigate the complexities of a multipolar world.
The deterrent, however, has a “red line,” as Vance emphasized.
Most importantly, Vance's speech showed that he sees a triplar world led by the US, China and Russia, although he did not use the term triplar world. In the circumstances when US supremacy has been questioned, Vance appeals to the need to improve military technology and to use the most sophisticated technology in US modernization.
In a way, Vance criticized US foreign policy during the Joe Biden administration, although the Biden government has noticed the challenges of China and Russia and has decided to invest in US infrastructure projects and developments. However, the second administration Trump raised the "American first" policy to the highest level. Reciprocal tariffs, the desire to put Gronelândia under the US sphere of influence, and the renewed emphasis on US maritime investment illustrated a sense of urgency from the Trump second administration to stop or reverse the US decline trend.
Vance's observations about China were interesting, considering Beijing as a "serious threat" to the US.
However, perhaps has been neglected another perspective on China, that is, China, as a weak country between 1840 and 1940, may have a geopolitical mentality not only to recover delay in the West, but also sees military modernization as an imperative parallel to the construction of the great wall under the Qin dynasty to move against foreign forces attacks. In other words, the defensive aspect of China's modernization, including military and economic aspects, was perhaps swept under the rug by many people who see it as a "threat." The issue of perception remains a fascinating aspect of observing the way US leaders see China's rapid rise in recent years.
In short, Vance's speech is a good indicator of the new US foreign policy realism. If the late Henry Kissinger was considered a US foreign policy realist, Jd Vance's thinking pointed to the features of new realism, where US intervention in any other country in the world has to be more effective and more targeted than before, the American First Policy is demonstrated in US reciprocal tariff policy compared to other countries, the emphasis on US supremacy contestation is A awareness that the world is now tripolar with the rise of China and Russia, and the renewed emphasis on the development of advanced technology in the US is indicative of Washington's perception that containment and involvement with China and Russia (or commitment policies in relation to China and Russia) are new US external policies under the second Trump administration.
 
SONNY LO
Author and Teacher of Political Science
This article was originally published in English at Macau Newsagency/MNA</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:28:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Postpartum and Chinese culture</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/pos-parto-e-a-cultura-chinesa/</link><description>After childbirth, Chinese women follow a series of traditional practices known as “Zuò Yuèzi” 坐月子, which translated to the letter means isolation where both mother and baby are strongly advised against home.
Postpartum isolation, popularly known as a “seated month”, consists of the thirty-day postpartum period where, with the purpose of helping the recent mother in the process of recovery, body strengthening and welfare in general, is advised to rest, avoid any kind of more demanding activity and to comply with a series of millennial customs.
The Chinese believe that everything that is done within thirty days after delivery is directly related to the quality of health in the future. Food and diet care includes “hot” foods such as chicken soup, bone broth and plenty of ginger. "Cold", bitter and raw foods are advised against. It is quite common the practice of “bandaging”, known as “Bao Bei” or “Yao Ding”, which consists of applying a special range more than ten meters long and about 30 centimeters wide in the waist.
In the first half of the isolation period, hygiene is done solely with a towel plunged into a mixture of hot water, alcohol and salt, and washing hair in these early days is considered a huge act of madness. After the initial period, bathing care has special relevance in traditional Chinese postpartum practices, being prepared with medicinal herbs, ginger, aromatic plants and always with hot water. It is strictly advised against exposure to the cold, especially at the ends of the body (head, hands and feet) and thus the woman moves with warm clothes, avoiding air conditioning environments and chains. Chinese tradition values ​​family presence and support during the postpartum period, however, the only visits and aid considered to be welcome are that of the newborn's grandparents involving a hundred percent in baby care and housework.
It is important to emphasize that such traditions may have variants depending on the region and family beliefs and that new generations are more flexible regarding compliance with isolation period practices.
In an increasingly globalized world, it is fascinating to observe how different cultures address as significant moments of life as the birth of a child. Regardless of culture and beliefs, the melody of dedication, compassion and sacrifice unites mothers around the world, as if in a timeless dance of unconditional love, involving the newborn in a cloak of care and tenderness. In this antithesis of practices and traditions we find the beauty of a universal language that breaks borders, maternal love.
 
Francisca Beja
Interior design and architecture project manager</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:28:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of registered toxicode dependents increased by 24.4%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/30/numero-de-toxicodependentes-registados-sofreu-aumento-de-244/</link><description>Last year, the number of toxicode dependents in the Central Registration System of the Institute of Social Action (IAS) increased by 24.4% to 148. Seven of the registered toxicode dependents were under 21 years old. The most consumed drug continued to be Ice, show the data released yesterday by the authorities.
 
 
The total number of toxicode dependents recorded in Macau was, last year, 148. This number reveals an increase of 24.4% compared to the previous year. The data were released by the Institute of Social Action (IAS) at the plenary session of the drug struggle committee that took place on Wednesday.
The press release about the meeting, released yesterday afternoon, says that of the total of 148 individuals in the central registration system, seven were young people under 21. Authorities also indicated that Ice remains the most consumed drug by registered toxicode, representing 26.3% of the total. Consumers of cannabis are followed, which correspond to 11.1% of the total. IAS also states that over 80% of toxicodependents have consumed drugs in Macau and more than 70% in relatively hidden places, ie at home or friends and hotels.
The authorities also pointed out that, in the future, the work of optimizing the central toxicodependent registration system will be developed, namely the questionnaire that is done, the participation system, the collaboration of the service units and the periodic conduct of thematic studies.
Hon Wai, president of IAS, said at the time that, “with the drug-related problems, they become increasingly complicated, the challenges posed on the work against drugs are different from previous years,” adding that the commission “continues to present opinions and suggestions, in order to support the government of the MSAR not only in the definition and implementation of the general anti-drug policy plan, but also in the increase of the increase in the increase of cooperation between drug combat services, in order to guarantee the security of society. ”
In addition, “considering that society has been concerned about the harm caused to young people for the use of new drugs in electronic cigarettes”, the working group has invited health services to organize thematic sessions in order to address the change in smoking control law. Opinions, after being organized and analyzed by the Commission, will be sent to the competent services as references to the amendment of the law.
Still, in the crime report for the first quarter of this year, released on Wednesday, Wong Sio Chak pointed out a decrease in drug-related crimes from 15 to 12 cases in the first three months, "continuing to maintain a low-rate occurrence trend," he said. In this context, the Secretary for Security stressed that the Executive Board has already completed the discussion about the legislative project, which provides to add to the table attached to Law 20 new substances regulated by the United Nations, as well as four other types of substances that are not yet subject to control, including “space oil”. Wong Sio Chak expects the diploma to be analyzed and considered in June by the Legislative Assembly.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 04:25:14</pubDate></item></channel></rss>