<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/os-papiros-de-herculano/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Macao Ideas holds sales session of “Macao Quality Products” between February 20th and 27th</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/macao-ideas-realiza-sessao-de-venda-de-produtos-de-qualidade-de-macau-entre-20-e-27-de-fevereiro/</link><description>Macao Ideas's exclusive exhibition and sale session - “Macao Quality Products” will take place between February 20th and 27th at the Grand Mart Department Store Ltd. headquarters in Taipa. The event is organized by the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) and has the participation of ten Macao Ideas companies.
For eight consecutive days, more than a hundred diversified products will be available with the “Macao Quality Products” seal to “meet the purchasing needs of different customer groups”, as Ipim clarifies. These products include “crackers, snacks, pasta, swallow nest, dry shellfish, healthy tea, wines, health supplements, bath products and pet items”, and other categories.
In a press release, Ipim points out that this event will mark three “premieres”: “The launch in large supermarkets located in Macau's community neighborhoods for the first time, the availability of their products, for the first time, in the online stores of these supermarkets on the platform Food delivery and exposure and simultaneous sale of online and offline forms for the first time. ”
The session will also feature news that aims to reinforce the flow of visitors and curious, such as the “offer of gifts with check-in” and the opportunity to gain a “limited edition memory” when sharing “the indicated footage and taking photography in loco ”.
IPIM states that the exhibition and sale session last year obtained a “satisfactory result” and helped “facilitate contact with new clientele sources” by introducing products from exhibiting companies into Macao's large supermarkets. The organization concludes, therefore, that the series of activities launched by Macao Ideas "can support Macao companies in reinforcing the visibility of their brands and increasing their sales."
Macao Ideas, originally established by IPIM, brings together more than 100 Macao exhibiting companies and about 1,700 projected and/or manufactured products in the region.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:24:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China defends collaboration with Thailand and Myanmar in the fight against human trafficking</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/china-defende-colaboracao-com-tailandia-e-myanmar-na-luta-contra-trafico-humano/</link><description>China reaffirmed its intention to collaborate with Thailand and Myanmar in the fight against human trafficking networks after the Thai authorities began to repact Chinese citizens in captive by criminal groups.
 
“China follows its people -centered philosophy. It is a necessary choice to safeguard the common interests of the region's countries and respond to aspirations shared by their peoples, ”said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun at a press conference.
Guo stressed that China maintains close bilateral and multilateral cooperation with Thailand, Myanmar and other affected countries. “We have taken several measures to solve both symptoms and the deep causes of these crimes and work together to prevent criminals from crossing borders, with the aim of eradicating the problem of illegal online fraud and gambling,” he said.
The spokesman added that China will continue to take steps to “protect people's life and goods” and preserve exchange and cooperation with countries in the region. However, it avoided giving details about the identity of repatriated citizens, their health or the circumstances of their rescue. "For specific information, I refer to the competent authorities in China," he said.
Myanmar, Thailand and China yesterday began a large operation to repair hundreds of Chinese that were rescued from ‘Online 'burla centers, where they were allegedly kept in captivity.
The first group, made up of dozens of people, boarded a flight operated by China Southern Airlines, which took off from the Thai Sot (Northwest) airport around 11:30 to Xishuangbanna (southern China).
They crossed the border in the early morning under strong security, hiding their faces from the press.
About 16 flights are planned until Saturday, for about 600 people. The repatriation of all people in question may take weeks and no details have been announced about what will happen to them in China.
Thai Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra said on Wednesday that about 7,000 people were waiting to be released, while a representative of Karen's state border guard force (BGF), an ethnic militia, acting at Myanmar, Kyanmar. estimated the number by 10,000.
This operation comes after months of protests from China, as victims are mostly Chinese: forcibly employed in centers that make the internet. “Two hundred Chinese citizens involved in 'online' gambling, telecommunications frauds and other crimes were delivered this morning by Thailand, according to legal procedures, in a spirit of humanity and friendship between countries,” said the Myanmar Board, said, in a statement.
Mae Sot is only 10 kilometers, in a straight line of Shwe Kokko, a Myanmar city that built its prosperity based on a variety of trafficking activities, with almost total impunity.
Complex gigantic complexes where fraudulent activities are abounded in the border regions of Myanmar, considered lawless areas due to the civil war that slaughtered the country since the coup d'état of February 2021.
According to experts, mafia networks resort to force to employ predominantly Chinese labor, mostly through human traffickers, to perform fraud that generate thousands of millions of dollars a year.
In recent months, Beijing has intensified the pressure on the Myanmar Board, of which he is one of the main gun suppliers, to end these activities. According to a United Nations report published in 2023, fraud centers employ at least 120,000 people at Myanmar. According to the report, many of the victims were subject to torture, arbitrary detention, sexual violence and forced labor.
Many workers say they were attracted or deceived by promises of well -paid jobs, just to be kept in captivity because their passports were confiscated.
In early February, another Myanmar militias group delivered 260 alleged victims from a dozen countries, including Philippines, Ethiopia, Brazil and Nepal, to the Thai authorities. Many of them showed signs of physical violence, including a woman who had huge bruises on her arm and thigh and said she was electrocuted.
In early February, Thailand cut electricity supply to several Myanmar border regions, including Shwe Kokko, in an attempt to wage the increase in illegal activities. The kingdom wants to give security guarantees to Chinese visitors, who are crucial to their tourist sector. The fears of the Chinese increased with the abduction, in Bangkok, of a Chinese actor, which was forcibly taken to a Fraud Center at Myanmar, before being released in early January. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:21:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Neoliberalism, culture and mercantilization of the self</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/neoliberalismo-cultura-e-mercantilizacao-do-eu/</link><description>In the beginning it was the market, and the market was with God, and the market was God (neoliberal version of 1: 1-2 of the Gospel of St. John)
Neoliberal ideology is synonymous with globalization of markets outside the regulation of states and, as such, unable to produce a common space with rules of social game. Contrary to what neoliberal ideology states - that a free market economy, without any state regulation, will eventually produce economic and social justice - Thomas Piketty, in his book Le Capital Au Xxie Siècle (2013) states that neoliberal capitalism produces and It accentuates economic and social inequality, tends to enrich the owners of capital and impoverish all others. In fact, in no country neoliberalism was able to end poverty and reduce inequality.
Increasing inequalities since the 1980s, that is, since Washington Consensus that has delineated, through 10 rules, the characteristics of neoliberalism and differences between Western countries, on the one hand, and the United States as leader, on the other, coincide With the beginning of neoliberal policies started when Margaret Thatcher and Ronald Reagan came to power in 1979 and 1981, respectively.
The only form, second, Piketty, of decreasing the growing distance between rich and poor is the application of a global rate (valid across the planet) and progressive (who is richest pays more) to fortunes over one million euros. The departure to neoliberal capitalism would therefore be to foster some distribution, not of income, but of capital, through close international cooperation between states in this matter.
And what is most surprising is that the crisis was generated within the capitalist system itself, by the animal spirit of financial capitalism, using the expression of Keynes (1936) and “not because it was shaken by the opposition or resistance of social forces that He proposed to defeat ”(Hall, Massey, Rustin: 2013).  In fact, one of the great successes of neoliberal conservantism “has been the demobilization of the resistance of working classes to capital and successful co -optation of political parties originally created to represent the interests of the working class for the task of cogestion of the social and economic model”. (Hall, Massey, Rustin: 2013).
When journalists Le Monde, Françoise Fressoz and Laetitia van Eeckhout, in 2008 an interview with Michel Rocard and asked him if the state of Europe today announced the end of liberalism, he was concerned to distinguish liberalism from neoliberalism and replied:
 
Don't even think. And in the midst of a crisis, the left could avoid this kind of controversies. Historically, the liberals-Adam Smith (1723-1790), Thomas Malthus (1766-1864), David Ricardo (1772-1823) in particular-were moralistic, people who had a social thinking oriented towards the integration of human freedom in the organization of society. For none of them freedom was the right to do nothing, needed to be channeled by rules.
The current crisis does not question liberalism. On the other hand, the touch of death for ultraliberalism sounds, this criminal school of thought founded by Milton Friedman (1912-2006) who wanted to believe that the market balance is great and that the less rules we have, the more opportunities we will have to achieve the "Optimization". Permeated the American right and part of the European right. Fortunately, he spared the German-Christian Democrats and the French right, who was still very gaulist.
The long success of neoliberalism from the 1980s to our day has been ensured not only by the adherence of the great right -wing political formations to a new political project of world competition, but also for the porosity of the “modern left” to the great neoliberal themes, to the point To have the impression in certain cases - we think mainly in “blairismo” - from a total submission to the dominant rationality. We would find the same trend in the United States, where the "liberals" began to speak, think and act like the "conservatives."
In short, the most worked discourse in the plane of neoliberal ideology is that there is no alternative to the world except to adjust to the productive restructuring promoted by globalization. Revenue for this adjustment is deregulation, decentralization and privatization.
Deregulation means the minimum possible existence of laws that guarantee rights, which causes the end of social rights established in the context of the Welfare State. It is the end of labor guarantees, stability in employment and productivity gains. It is about leaving the free market to be the great regulator of social relations. Decentralization complements deregulation with state reform, which aims to delegate responsibilities to states/provinces and municipalities. Privatization completes the cycle because the state is detached from strategic sectors such as electricity, telecommunications, ores, oil, etc., effectively losing the possibility of developing economic and social policies.
There is today a consensus among economists in Western countries that a change of course is needed and that neoliberal ideas must be abandoned. Many economists from Europe have already abandoned the defense of the minimum state and begin to argue that the state must have the necessary dimension to ensure development. Also recently in the Guadian newspaper, November 28, 2024, Joseph E. Stiglitz, Nobel Prize for the Economy, Professor at Columbia University and former Chief Economist at the World Bank wrote:
 
40 Years of Neoliberalism have left the us with unprecedented inequality, Stagnation in the Middle of the Income Spectrum, and Declining Life Expectancy (Highlighted by Mounting “Deaths of Despair”). Stiglitz, in an August 2024 interview with Australian television ABC even said that "neoliberal Capitalism 'has contributed to the Rise of Fascism."
 
Neoliberalism and the commodification of self and emotions
An interesting analysis of a segment of neoliberal ideology should be the study of the social and individual consequences of neoliberal culture that was taking over the daily life of televisions, social networks, etc., with the public commodification of feelings and emotions, even the most personal and intimate. Neoliberal society has become a society of the spectacle, of socio-affective deregulation (beyond economic), the desubjectivation of the human being, in which everything can be a show in the good logic of theology and market liturgy. Currently social networks are for the most pathetic and shameless funeral compliments of loved ones or friends without any discreet and collected reserve of pain, to the most stunning manifestations of anniversary celebration of dating, marriage (publicly showing that everything is (well) (well) or even to manifestations of pain for widowhood and even for the television trivialization of human sexuality as a spectacle.
We have lived since the 1980s of the Washington Consensus Declaration to show that our private life must also be in line with the spirit of the “reality show” of the neoliberal society in which we live. Trump before he was a president was a presenter of a reality show, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa calls live to Cristina Ferreira's program starting by saying, "I interrupted a meeting here to talk to you."
That is, the concept of freedom was radicalized by neoliberalism. In other words, the concept of economic freedom in neoliberalism, that is, from the market that should command the lives of people deregulating social and labor laws, proposing the end of the social state, trying to privatize the essential and strategic functions of the state constituted -the exclusive foundation of all other forms of freedom. In the expression of Mozambican sociologist José Castiano, it includes the refraction of the subject and the “cultural” promotion of an era of free emotions, very well used by the emotional designers and the advertisers, the forefront of neoliberal capitalism, to consume everything, until what doesn't We want or we cannot, even the emotions of others: the girl with cancer, the reunion with the lost son, the actress Exchanged by another woman, the politician's photo with the homeless in a degraded neighborhood that should no longer exist in the middle of the century. XXI, etc. However, this is the reality of poverty, sometimes extreme in a democratic, Catholic, European country in which 40% of citizens live in poverty and therefore, 50% live close to extreme misery due to lack of effective social support.
But all this is commodified in a huge reality show in the taste of the dictatorship of Idiocia in the manner of Big Brother and other political actors and activities of public life.
Neoliberalism in its process of ideological construction thus assumed not only as a strong political and economic alternative for the exit of the capitalist crisis, but also as a “cultural revolution” in the way of thinking and living in society. Economic order and social order must be regulated only by the principles of free market, reducing to the least the harmful interference of the state.
Interestingly, the Woke culture, an expression that emerged in the African American community and meant “being alert to racial injustice,” probably coined by African-American novelist William Melvin Kelley in 1962 in an article in The New York Times with the title IF You're Woke, You Dig It, is also the neoliberal facet of a certain left and extreme left.
Currently the term Woke has become “synonym for liberal (neo) or leftist policies, which advocate themes such as racial and social equality, feminism, LGBTQia+movement, gender ideology, the use of neutral gender pronouns in language, the multiculturalism, vaccination, ecological activism and the right to abortion ”(BBC-Brazil, August 13, 2024), From 2020 becoming one of the central axes of life and the political struggle between the right and left of the western world, namely in the recent campaign for Trump's reelection by combating the so-called Woke Lefties (“wake leftists”) which, according to He, they practice “fascism of the extreme left” and are a threat to “family values”, but also to democracy, when they want to replace it with a tyranny Woke.
In a very recent book (the left is not Woke, 2023; 2024) Susan Neiman, an American writer and philosopher, argues that political movements exchanged the ideal of universalism for limiting tribalism. He also says that international solidarity was his watchword. This was exactly what distinguished it from the right, which did not recognize deep connections and only a few real obligations with anyone outside their own circle. Left turn to tribalism is particularly tragic, since the first anti -colonialist and civil rights movements openly opposed tribal thinking in all their forms. Tribalism is a dangerous game, such as the right and far-right they quickly realized, so their anti-wake political agendas have emerged with great visibility and electoral strength far right in Europe and the United States of America movements and in South America. This is one of the reasons why many political scientists claim that neoliberalism in all its facets has been destroying democracy as, by Example, the various authors of the book Neoliberal Capitalism and the Rising of Authoritarian Politics (2021). They explain why democracy is being destroyed; Neoliberalism has generated a crisis that expresses itself in the growing visible authoritarianism in divisionist and exclusionary policies, in popular political parties and political movements, the growing distrust of facts based information and news and reducing the accountability of state institutions.
Over the past four decades, democracy has radically changed to a market democracy, in which all aspects of human, non-human and planetary life are commodified, with companies becoming more powerful than states and their citizens. This is how neoliberal capitalism works at systemic level, punitive for people with old and new but punitive poverty profiles, also to nature and, and if not controlled, is the greatest threat to democracy and the sustainable planet.
 
Rui Rocha
Researcher</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:20:54+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste demands from Japan apology for invasion in World War II</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/timor-leste-exige-ao-japao-pedido-de-desculpa-por-invasao-na-segunda-guerra-mundial/</link><description>The Non-Governmental Organization Hak yesterday pointed out the 83th anniversary of the occupation of Timor-Leste for Japan during World War II, asking that country to make an apology to the families of abuse victims. “The Japanese invasion brought a lot of suffering to the Timorese people. About six thousand people died from the Japanese invasion, ”Hak's Lusa Marina Galucho Ximenes told Lusa.
On February 20, 1942, during World War II, Japan invaded Timor-Leste, still under the domain of Portugal, which had declared neutrality in the conflict.
The Japanese occupation took place following the entry of an Australian military contingent into the territory in December 1941, which eventually retreated and installing its base on the mountains.
According to Marina Ximenes, during the Japanese occupation of Timor-Leste, which occurred until 1945, many Timorese were forced to work and many women were victims of sexual abuse. "These victims and their families continue to demand that the Japanese government give them a formal apology and give them a reparation," Hak official said.
A survey conducted by the non-governmental organization identified 21 women victims of abuse and sexual exploitation, to whom an apology was not made or given compensation. Of the 21 victims, only remains alive Inês Magalhães, who resides in the municipality of Ermera.
Marina Ximenes also asked the Ministry of Education to integrate the Japanese occupation of Timor-Leste during World War II in the National Education Curriculum, which covers only history between 1975 and 1999. “We will continue to fight for truth and justice for victims who They have not yet received it from the Japanese government, ”said Marina Ximenes, recognizing the support for the development that has been given by Japan to Timor-Leste. “Japan has already recognized the victims in Korea. Why does it recognize Korea and not Timor-Leste? We will continue to wait for them to recognize the victims in Timor-Leste, ”he asked.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:26:43+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Development of low altitude economy can be “new point of economic growth”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/desenvolvimento-da-economia-de-baixa-altitude-pode-ser-novo-ponto-de-crescimento-economico/</link><description>At yesterday's plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Deputy Chui Sai Peng urged the government to consider developing the so -called “low altitude economy” as a form of economic diversification of the region. The first time in Hemiciclo as Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP said this area "can inject a new dynamic in the development of the proper diversification of the economy, forming a new point of economic growth."
The economy of low altitude is an economic activity that is based on low altitude airspace and is based on the general aviation industry, involving low altitude transport sectors, low altitude tourism, research and science education, entertainment and performance, among others, whose aircraft include drones and helicopters, etc.
Tai Kin IP recalled that in 2021 and 2022, a drone gala was organized shines on Macau ”and, on the other hand, since the launch of the technological companies certification program, by the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services, in 2023 , to date, five reference technology companies and 28 potential technological companies have obtained the qualification of certification, including those that mainly exploit the research and development of the drone system.
In response to Chui Sai Peng's oral interpellation, the secretary assured that “the Government of MSar will continue to optimize and launch support measures that respond to the needs of companies and are dedicated to the creation of a better development environment for companies Macao Science and Technology, including those involved in the economy of low altitude ”. Tai Kin IP also pointed out that this area "presupposes the existence of adequate laws and regulations that regulate aircraft air transport, including drones."</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:20:52+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai awaits suggestions and support from APN and CCPPC members to LAG</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/sam-hou-fai-aguarda-sugestoes-e-apoio-dos-membros-da-apn-e-ccppc-para-as-lag/</link><description>The first report of the Government Action Lines (LAG) is in the elaboration phase and the Chief Executive said the Macao representatives in the National Popular Assembly (APN) and the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Conference (CCPPC) continue to present “valuable suggestions” and “strong support” for the work in question.
Sam Hou Fai stated that, over the past few times, the team has been listening to “continuously and extensive” the opinions and suggestions of all sectors of Macao society about LAG, namely associations and organizations, which “ It has been very fruitful and deeply inspiring, ”he said. "On this basis, it will hear even more sectors and points of view, namely the patriotic associations that love Macau, for the preparation of LAG," he said.
Sam Hou Fai's statement was made at a dinner offered by the government to Macao deputies to APN and Macao members at CCPPC, which took place last Wednesday. In his speech, the government leader highlighted his hope that Macao representatives in these two Chinese political bodies may take into account their own advantages and specialties and needs in the new development in the next two national sessions to be held soon. “Making a greater contribution to the construction of a strong country, the revitalization of the nation, to the progress of Macao, to the development of Hengqin, as well as for a better life of Macao residents, being the 'good voice' of Macao” , he stressed.
It is recalled that the plenary sessions of the 14th APN and the 14th CCPPC are scheduled for 5 March and March 4 this year, respectively, in Beijing. Sam Hou Fai wished members “a fruitful trip successfully in the performance of functions” in Congress.
During dinner, on behalf of the government, the chief executive also paid a “high tribute” to all Macao elements in APN and CCPPC for “participation in the country's governance, promoting the development of Macau, for reflection on feelings and opinions of the people and the congregation of patriotic love ”. The press release also indicated that Sam Hou Fai also expressed “sincere gratitude” to them for the attention and support of his candidacy for the position of Chief Executive and in the organization of the new government.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:20:52+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Preventive Winter Operation resulted in more than 1,000 arrests</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/operacao-preventiva-de-inverno-resultou-em-mais-de-mil-detencoes/</link><description>Police authorities carried out a winter preventive operation between January 8 and February 7 this year, having mobilized 8,598 police officers and 651 police operations. A total of 41,953 individuals were identified, among which 1,140 were arrested and taken to the squadron for investigations.
In a statement issued by the Unit Police Services (SPU), the individuals taken to the police were involved in 365 cases, namely related to drugs, theft, theft, the provision of assistance to illegal immigration, illicit loan for play, exploration of exchange rate illicit for game, among others. Among them, 464 individuals were sent to the judiciary, 345 being subject to coercion or conviction measures, while 22 were arrested preventively.
The SPU revealed that 18 individuals were also intercepted in compliance with warrants of capture and detention issued by the judicial bodies, including 13 were sent to the prison establishment for immediate compliance with penalty.
In the same operation, a total of 500 non -resident individuals were sent to the Department of Border Control of the Public Security Police (CPSP) for due repatriation process.
This police work aimed to “guarantee a safe and quiet environment on the Chinese New Year 'court” and was carried out by the SPU, who coordinated the CPSP and the Judiciary Police (PJ), with the collaboration of customs services. (SA).
The SAs triggered, during the operation, action to combat smuggling, illegal immigration and counterfeit. In terms of activities related to parallel trade, 305 individuals were accused administratively in accordance with the Foreign Trade Act, and they were seized in the so -called tobacco, electronic cigarettes, alcoholic beverages, cosmetic products, fresh and living food, electronic products, plants on extinction roads, among others.
In the work balance, the SPU highlight that this year's preventive winter operation “fully reached the expected results” and police measures were “effective”, having contributed to the maintenance of safety and the stability of the social order of the territory . "With the increase in the number of tourists, the SPU will be aware of the situation of Macao's security, adjusting the police strategies and triggering preventive operations in order to maintain a stable and safe environment in the region," reads on notice.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:20:50+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Restaurant and retail turnover rises at the end of 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/volume-de-negocios-de-restaurantes-e-retalho-sobe-no-final-de-2024/</link><description>In December, restaurant and retail turnover rose 5.6% and 7.9%, respectively, compared to the previous month. Compared to the same month of 2023, the turnover of both sectors recorded respective 5.6% and 21.1%. The conclusions were released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services.
 
The volume of retail and retail sectors increased in December compared to the previous month of November, but decreased by last year's same period.
According to statistics revealed yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), based on a conjuncture survey to restoration and retail trade, the owners of the restoration reported in December 2024 a 5.6% growth in volume business compared to the previous month. Western restaurants were those that recorded the largest increase of 12.4%, followed by Japanese and Korean restaurants - grouped in a single category - and the Chinese (8.8%and 7%, respectively).
The interviewed retail volume also observed a 7.9% growth in the reference month. Regarding the volume of “Automobile Business, Watches and Knee Por, that of adult clothing, as well as cosmetic and hygiene products”, DSEC reports an increase of 18.6%, 16.4%, 15, 8% and 13.6%, respectively. In a press release, the body justifies the results of December - positive for all sectors, compared to November - with “Christmas holidays”.
Statistics become more negative when compared to the same period of the previous year. Restoration turnover descended 5.6% compared to December 2023, with special highlight for Chinese and Western restaurants, with a drop of 10.3% and 4.4%. Japanese and Korean restaurants, in turn, saw an increase of 10.9%.
Regarding retail trade, the interviewee's turnover fell 21.1% in annual terms, such as the business and jewelery businesses, the leather items and the warehouses and trinkets (with respective 31 falls, 31, 5%, 25.9%and 20.8%). Only the car business grew up to 2023, with an increase in the order of 36%.
Regarding predictions about the future, 44% of restoration owners interviewed projected that the turnover for January 2025 to grow in monthly terms due to Chinese New Year's holidays and festivities. It should be noted that the proportion of the Chinese owners and the owners of Western restaurants was 64% and 32%, respectively. In turn, about 17% of restoration owners anticipated monthly decreases in turnover for January.
36%of retailers were equally confident about monthly increases in turnover, especially retailers of warehouses and trinkets (50%) and leather items (43%), while 20%(43%) retailers (43%) Of the interviewees anticipated monthly decreases for January.
Regarding the index of business perspectives, which reflects the forecast of owners and retailers interviewed about the trend of monthly variation of business volume, it was found that both the branch of the economic activity of restoration (63.6%) Branch of retail trade (57.7%) were greater than 50. This means, explains DSEC, that “both the restoration owners and the interviewed retailers anticipated, In general, that business performance for January 2025 would be better than the month under analysis. ”
This inquiry was carried out to 229 owners of the restoration business and 161 of the retail trade business, corresponding to about 53.5% and 70.6% of the respective branches in 2019.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:24:38+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Influenza cases decreased, but the prevalence is maintained this month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/casos-de-gripe-diminuiram-mas-mantem-se-a-prevalencia-neste-mes/</link><description>Health services claim that the number of flu in's infections is falling slight, however, it can maintain “a certain degree of prevalence” later this month. The positivity rate of the influenza virus tests fell from the peak of the year 29.1% to the 13.4% registered last week, with an average of 82 patients with flu a day. Authorities warn that, in addition to the flu virus, spring is also time for prevalence of respiratory and gastrointestinal infectious diseases.
 
The influenza infection situation relieved in Macao after the Lunar New Year and the number of people with influenza similar symptoms in the emergency services of local hospitals is gradually decreasing. Health services, however, predict that the flu virus will continue to have “a certain degree of prevalence” in the community this February.
Last week, more than 1,200 people a day resorted to emergency, of which 82 were patients with flu -like symptoms, including 44 adults and 38 children. The number was reduced compared to that of the first week this year, which was considered the peak of flu in Macau, with 1,400 users in urgency per day and 130 patients with symptoms similar to the flu.
The influenza virus infection detection rate was 13.4% last week, less than a 29.1% peak recorded this year and last year's peak of 32.9%. "The peak of the flu in Macau was a little delayed compared to previous years, but did not exceed the level of the past," said Ieong Chon Kit, a doctor at the Center for Disease Prevention and Control, on the occasion of a press conference held yesterday.
Regarding the collective flu infection, 29 cases have been recorded so far this year, ie a decrease of 80.4% compared to the 148 cases recorded in the same period last year. The cases involved 206 people mainly in primary and secondary schools.
Authorities also said that the number of influenza cases in pediatrics is lower than the one recorded in the identical period of 2024. Wong Fong Ian, head of the Conde de São Januário (CHCSJ) Hospital Pediatric Service, revealed that this year were treated more of 400 cases with Tamiflu in pediatric emergency services, health centers and external consultations, less than in the years previous.
Flu Vaccination, on the other hand, reached the peak of 3,000 vaccinations a day at the beginning of the year and fell to about 1,000 more recently.
Health services held a press conference on the prevention of more common transmitted diseases in spring, where they stressed the tendency to reduce influenza cases, but highlighted the rise of cases of gastrointestinal viruses. “Until February 15, of the 82 samples of gastrointestinal viruses tested by the Public Health Laboratory, 37 cases of noroviruses and 22 rotaviruses were reported. Norovirus' positivity rate is considered high, ”said Wong Fong Ian. In addition, authorities also received 15 cases of collective gastroenteritis infection, which involved 178 people.
At the conference, Chang Tam Fei, ChCSJ Emergency Service Head, stressed that viruses and bacteria are “very active” in spring. "With changes in climate and moisture, it is necessary to pay attention to the storage of food at home for the prevention of infectious diseases," said the doctor, noting that, besides the flu, among prevalent infectious diseases are also respiratory and gastrointestinal diseases are diseases are .</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:21:51+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>3.65 million visitors entered in January, the second largest number of history</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/entraram-365-milhoes-de-visitantes-em-janeiro-o-segundo-maior-numero-da-historia/</link><description>The number of visitors registered an annual rise of 27.4% last month and exceeded 3.64 million entries, a volume that was the second largest in history after August, when there was more than 3.65 million of visitors. Most visitors continued to be tour, who do not stay overnight in Macau. Of the total, only 6.6% were international tourists. Visitors from South Korea, Philippines and Indonesia dominated the foreign tourist market, yesterday revealed the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services.
 
Macau received 3,646,561 visitors in January, which reveals a 27.4% growth compared to the same period last year. The data were advanced yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), showing that last month marked the second largest number of visitors in history, having only been exceeded by August last year, when 3 were welcomed 3 , 65 million visitors. The third month with the most tourists is now August 2019, with 3.62 million visitors.
The movement of visitors for last month also indicated that most visitors remain from the interior of China and tour, who do not stay overnight in Macao.
Among the visitors' arrivals only 6.6% came from abroad. The number of international visitors entrances totaled 241,131, plus 21% in annual terms. South Korea, Philippines and Indonesia were the main places of entrances origin.
DSEC analysis shows that the number of visitor entries of the Philippines (48,499), Indonesia (21,579) and Malaysia (11,982) ascended 42.2%, 54.6%and 9%, respectively, in annual terms. However, that of Thailand (9,992) and Singapore (7,874) decreased 26.6% and 11.3% respectively. There was also 2.2% less in the number of visitor entries from India compared to the same time as last year, which was moved in 6,648 people.
As for the Asian Northeast, the number of visitor entries from South Korea was 65,659 and that of Japan was 12,029, which increased 29.9% and 13%, respectively, compared to January 2024. In terms of visitors, Long -range, the number of visitors from the United States of America (12,367) had a 13.2%homologous increase.
2,75 million visitors from the interior of China entered January, which grew 33.8% in annual terms. It should be noted that the number of visitors with individual visa visited situated at 1.6 million (+44%), of which 111,000 were from “one entrance per week” visitors and 25 thousand were from “one one visa of multiple entries ”. The number of visitors with “group departures and exits” was over 13,000.
The number of visitors from visitors from nine cities of the Greater Bay River Delta was over 1.4 million, 37.9% more than a year ago. The number of visitor entries from Hong Kong (577,983) and Taiwan (77,163) grew, in annual terms, 5.8% and 28.8%, respectively.
DSEC statistics also indicate that the majority of entry of visitors are still tour, who do not stay overnight in Macao. The number of entrances of tour was 2,155,279 and tourists was 1,491,282, having recorded an annual increase of 45.6% and 7.9%, respectively.
The average period of permanence of visitors was a day, less 0.2 days compared to January 2024, "mainly to the homologous increase in the proportion of extensions compared to the total of visitors," the authorities explained. In concrete, the average period of permanence of the tour increased by 0.1 days to 0.3 days, and that the tourists remained in 2.2 days.
The DSEC added that the number of terrestrial visitors was set at 2.98 million (81.9% of the total), maritime by 385 thousand (10.6%) and by air at 273 million ( 7.5%), which translated an annual rise of 31.9%, 9.2%and 12.3%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:23:44+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The Portuguese brand in Hong Kong: a story of adaptation and influence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/a-marca-portuguesa-em-hong-kong-uma-historia-de-adaptacao-e-influencia/</link><description>An unprecedented project for Hong Kong highlights the importance of the different immigrant communities, which made the multicultural network that defines the safe haven of the former colony. A collection that dates back to the least appreciated past from European rule in Asia, the exhibition “Lush Stories” at the Hong Kong History Museum is, more than anything, a tribute to the positive fruits of this meeting point between empires. A mixed community that brought all the influences of Portuguese defaults around the world and today contribute to the projection of a small territory, in one of the most influential regions of the globe. No date to end, the permanent exhibition is one of the prominent destinations in the current Hong Kong cultural agenda.





Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho


The history of the Portuguese community in Hong Kong, now presented in a comprehensive exhibition at the Hong Kong History Museum (HKHM), is a valuable case study on resilience, adaptability and the importance of intercultural relations in the development of a society cosmopolitan. Inaugurated on November 27, 2024 and without closing forecast, until the next large -scale project, the exhibition “Stories Lusas - Stories of the Hong Kong Portuguese” is part of the first phase of a new series of installations within the existing exhibition Permanent Museum, entitled “Multifaceted Hong Kong Exhibition Series”, or “Series of Multifaceted Exhibitions on Hong Kong”.
Between objects donated or offered by the Lusa Community in Hong Kong, large -scale facilities and use of new technologies, such as “Projection Mapping” and interactive maps, the exhibition occupies a total of 10 rooms on the second floor of the museum and is the result of A collaboration between the Department of Leisure and Culture Services and HKHM.
The museum initiative of great wingspan gathers a vast set of artifacts, including historical documents, personal objects, photographs, works of art and descendants' testimonials, offering an in -depth look at the more than 150 years of Portuguese presence in the former British colony.
From the arrival of the early Portuguese from Macao in the mid -nineteenth century, to the present, the Portuguese presence in Hong Kong has been marked by a multifaceted contribution that has covered the economic, social, cultural and sports sphere. The analysis of existing documents and testimonies reveals a course of challenges and achievements, which deserves to be recognized and preserved as an integral part of Hong Kong's history.
The exhibition is structured to guide the visitor through the journey of the Portuguese community, highlighting its ability to adapt to local realities. The narrative begins with the arrival of the first Portuguese, mainly from the then Portuguese colony of Macao, entrance port for Canton trade, and details its gradual integration into the Hong Kong society.
A map of 1872, which illustrates the area around Graham Street, where is one of the oldest street markets in the city today, identifies that 18 of the about 100 dwellings were marked as Portuguese.
Current figures such as Francisco da Roza, former president of Club Lusitano, the city's oldest Portuguese social club, in an interview with Zolima Citymag in 2016, noted that there are currently many living traces of the Portuguese presence, but stressed that, after an integration Deep, most people would not identify him as Portuguese.
"We can track our ancestors to a small village near Lisbon, but I've been in Hong Kong for over 50 years, and my family has been in Macao over 300 years." Da Roza is one of the most avid protagonists of this new show, which has been in gestation since mid -2019, in search of, for the first time, highlighting a community that was once the largest foreign group in the city, even more populous than The characters in charge of the British crown.
The exhibition explores the challenges faced, such as linguistic and cultural barriers, difficulties in adapting living conditions and professional opportunities, illustrating how the community has overcome these obstacles and built a new life on new ground.
The spirit of unity and mutual support is a recurring theme in the show, so unique to a Latin culture that mixed with Indiana, African and Asian, in the various passages before the arrival of the Pearl River, reflecting the importance of social cohesion For the survival and success of a small community, already defined as Macaense, an ethnic group in itself. The exhibition details everyday life, the professions, the social clubs and the moments of celebration of the community, offering a vivid portrait of its evolution over the years.
One of the most significant aspects of the exhibition is the demonstration of the crucial role that the Portuguese played in Hong Kong's economic development. The experience in dealing with different cultures and languages, as well as the ability to establish trusting relationships, were decisive factors for the success of the Portuguese community in the territory.
Many of the historical documents present, authentic relics, illustrate the rise of prominent figures in the Portuguese community, highlighting their impact on sectors such as trade, finance and industry, such as Roza and his career as a prominent banker.
 
Roots and development: intermediation, entrepreneurship and loyalty
 
The Portuguese initially stood out as intermediaries between the British and the Chinese population, filling a crucial void in communication and translation. Dominating English, Cantonese and, for the most part, Portuguese, actuated as translators, accountants and civil servants, facilitating trade and administration of the then English colony. This intermediate function, which required a high degree of linguistic and cultural competence, contributed to the economic development of Hong Kong.
At the same time, the Portuguese did not hesitate to invest in their own businesses, creating companies that played an important role in the development of the colony. The impression industry, for example, was dominated by Portuguese families, such as Noronha and Xavier, who built lasting and renowned businesses. Portuguese entrepreneurship extended to other sectors, such as shipbuilding, commerce and bank, as well as the beginning of the innovative plastic toy market, so well known. Efforts that consolidated the presence of Portuguese descent entrepreneurs in the region's economy.
The Lusa community also demonstrated a strong sense of loyalty and patriotism, which manifested itself in its participation in the defense of the colony. During World War II, many Portuguese served on Hong Kong's voluntary defense body and, after the war, continued to support Civil Defense through voluntary organizations. This commitment to Hong Kong's safety and stability demonstrates its integration into local society and its desire to contribute to the common good.
 
Culture, sport and legacy: preservation and continuity
 
Portuguese culture, with its traditions, language and values, played an important role in the identity of the small Hong Kong region. The creation of social clubs, such as Club Lusitano and Club de Recreio, provided a space for conviviality, leisure and preservation of Portuguese culture. These clubs were important to the general population, as they offered opportunities for social life, sports and celebration of Portuguese traditions, marking an essential contact space to make an identity mesh of such a unique region.
Sport was another important factor in the cohesion of the Portuguese community, which maintained a crucial role until today. The Victoria Recreation Club, founded in 1849, became a popular meeting place for Portuguese swimmers, while the recreational club, founded in Kowloon, played an important role in developing local athletes. Figures such as Arnaldo de Oliveira Sales and Tony Cruz, legendary Jockey, stood out in the sports panorama, contributing to the recognition of the Portuguese community among a majorly English elite.
Despite the social and political transformations that have occurred in Hong Kong over the years, the Portuguese community has remained active and present in the city. The emigration of many Portuguese, especially after the 1967 riots, reduced the number of community members, but did not diminish their importance. Currently, the descendants of Portuguese continue to play a relevant role in various sectors of the Hong Kong society, from economy and culture to sport and politics. Figures such as Ray Cordeiro, the legendary DJ known as Uncle Ray, who kept the longest radio show in history from 1970 to 2021, when he decided to close the “store” at the age of 96. Joe Junior is another character of Portuguese descent who enchanted the population with his “Voice of Love”, voice of love, through romantic popular songs, which still sound to this day.
Continuing by the room maze of this chain shows, the visitor is surrounded by “flying” documents installed in the space, while Voices in Patuá explain recipes from the macanese kitchen that has as its background the immense projection of a world map highlighting the route of caravels through the oceans. It is in this scenario that the history of the Portuguese community in Hong Kong unfolds with a history of the search for integration, through its own resilience that reflects the Lusa international community and reflects on the importance of cultural diversity and adaptation. When we look at the past, we can see how the Portuguese community, already with various influences from the various colonies spread along the way to Asia, knew how to build a new life in a distant land, literally on the other side of the world, adapting to local realities and Contributing to the development of the colony, which, however, became one of the most influential cities in history.
What is carried out, among numerous interpretations, is the reality that the Lusitanian presence in Hong Kong is an example of how cultural diversity can enrich a society and promote understanding among peoples. The Portuguese heritage in the territory was, with this well -elaborated, enriched and preserved collection, not only as a testimony of the past, but as a reflection on the future, illuminating the way to a more inclusive and rich society in experiences and traditions. It is very important to the present, where the distancing between peoples and cultures is increasingly seeming to be the norm, in the cloud of conflicts of low international diplomacy, which is in the current political panorama.
By preserving the inheritances, it will be possible to ensure that future generations can learn from the history of multiple communities that set up a society and be inspired by their values ​​of resilience, adaptation and integration. It is a pertinent legacy, not just for the Portuguese descendants, but for humanity as a group, capable of building bridges between cultures and creating a stronger and more united community.
The Hong Kong History Museum initiative to create an exhibition about the Portuguese community aims to be a recognition of its importance and its contribution to the identity of the city. The preservation of memory, the result of a long, developing work for about 3 years, is fundamental to promote continuous intercultural dialogue.
The “Series of Multifaceted Hong Kong Exhibitions” also includes the exhibitions “Yau Tsim Mong - The Urban Transition and Community Bonds” and “Sojourning in Gold Mountain - Hong Kong and the Lives of Overseas Chinese in California”, which foster a similar role , of learning about the multiple faces of an urbanization dispersed through the Islands of a corner on the Asian continent, which one day decided to call themselves “fragrant port”.
The series of exhibitions is located in the 2nd floor exhibition gallery of the Hong Kong History Museum, located in 100 Chatham Road South in Tsim Sha Tsui. The opening hours are Monday, Wednesday to Friday, from 10h00 to 18h00; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays from 10h00 to 19h00. The museum is closed on Tuesdays (except holidays).</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Ratted President Yoon Suk-Youol's trial by insurrection</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/arrancou-o-julgamento-de-presidente-yoon-suk-yeol-por-insurreicao/</link><description>The trial against South Korea President Yoon Suk-Yeol, accused of insurrection for declaring briefly martial law in December, started yesterday, France-Presse news agency said.
 
The hearing began at the central court of the capital, Seoul, at 10:00, in the presence of the defendant, in a crowded room, according to an AFP journalist, present at the site. A strong police contingent surrounded the court building.
This process is independent of another, underway in the Constitutional Court, which must confirm or annul the dismissal of Yoon, voted by the National Assembly, the South Korean Parliament, on December 14.
Yoon Suk-Youol, 64, is accused of insurrection, a crime punishable by death or life imprisonment that is not covered by presidential immunity.
Arrested on January 15, after hiding for weeks at the presidential residence in Seoul, protected by the president's guard, Yoon was accused on January 26 and placed in pre -trial detention for six months, period after which it should be released if not not has been condemned until then.
The prosecutor accuses Yoon of “leading an insurrection,” although the defendant's lawyers claim that the accusations are not legal, arguing that he had the constitutional right to declare martial law.
The conservative leader plunged South Korea into political chaos on December 3 by declaring martial law and sending the army to Parliament in an attempt to silence him. She was forced to retreat six hours later when the deputies managed to meet emergency and vote against the special regime.
Yoon justified the action by saying that Parliament, dominated by the opposition, was blocking the adoption of the state budget. In a television speech, he said he intended to “protect liberal South Korea from the threats placed by the North Korean communist forces” and “eliminate the hostile elements to the state”.
Yoon remains officially as president while awaiting the verdict of the Constitutional Court.
Han Duck-soo, appointed interim president in December, before being suspended by the deputies, should testify at the hearing, as well as a former secret services official, Hong Jang-Won, and National Police Chief Cho Ji-ho, who It also faces criminal accusations in the case.
If the Court confirms the dismissal, early presidential elections will have to be convened within 60 days. Otherwise, Yoon will be reinstated in office, although it remains the subject of criminal accusations.
Most of Yoon's dismissal process was devoted to whether Yoon violated the Constitution by declaring martial law, a measure that can only be adopted when military intervention is necessary to preserve security and public order “In case of armed conflict or similar national emergency ”.
Yoon continues to be supported by a part of the popular power party, the most radical fringe on the South Korean right and influential evangelical pastors. Every Saturday, tens of thousands of supporters come together in Seoul to demand the politician's liberation and return to power.
These demonstrations are largely non -violent, but on January 19, a court of Seoul that had just extended Yoon's preventive arrest was invaded and looted by hundreds of presidential supporters. Since then, more than 60 people have been held related to this attack. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:26:29+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Project to take a slight meter to Qingmao will be “a big step”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/projecto-para-levar-metro-ligeiro-a-qingmao-sera-um-grande-passo/</link><description>Raymond Tam announced yesterday, in the Legislative Assembly (AL), that the study on the viability of the extent of the eastern east line to the Qingmao border post concluded that the project is viable, despite the various challenges. This will be “a big step,” said the secretary for transport and public works.
 
At yesterday's plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Raymond Tam said that the preliminary study on the viability of the east line extension of the mild to the Qingmao border post concluded that the project is feasible.
Still, between the doors of the siege and the Qingmao border post, "geological conditions are complicated and technically difficult," as the layout will pass through border stations and Dr Sun Yat Sen Municipal Park, the secretary stressed for transport and public works.
In September 2024, it was known that the study project on the extension of the East Line until Qingmao, a study that was awarded to the “China Railway Major Bridge Reconnaissance &amp; Design Institute Co., Ltd. (Macao Branch)” by 8.48 million patacas. A preliminary study was done for the construction of the tunnel using tunnel, subject to the extension of the east to west to the Qingmao border post.
“What we want is that the light meter line extends to Qingmao. We still have no name of the new post, but the line will extend to Qingmao. If we can achieve this goal, it means that we have taken a big step, ”said the ruler.
The theme was brought to the Hemiciclo by Leong Sun Iok, who asked the government what progress of the works of the East Line and how is the study of the conception of the West Line. During the discussion, most of the deputies' issues had to do with the transhipment problems of the light meter and the payment methods. The Secretary for Transport and Public Works asked the deputies to give time to the new government to solve these problems.
During the discussion, there were also those who asked that, after the passage of a typhoon through Macao, the restoration of the operation of the subway was more fast. Raymond Tam explained that the delay in recovering the service after the typhoons has to do with line safety checks, as objects may fall into the rails. The secretary also indicated that in the future, the government will be able to resort to technology to shorten the stopping period of the subway, using drones to find out if there are objects in the carris, saving human resources.
Regarding the commercial elements at the stations, the secretary indicated that at Barra da Barra the stores are all leased. "When developing other lines, we will consider using other models," added Raymond Tam.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:22:53+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The Chinese and the Western education system</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/o-sistema-educativo-chines-e-o-ocidental/</link><description>In a world in constant evolution and global competition, the education system plays a crucial role in the formation of future generations.
The Chinese education system is characterized by its patriotism and rigor, with an emphasis on memorization, discipline and intensive practice where, from an early age, students follow the routine of long hours of study and are often challenged by strict examinations. This approach has resulted in remarkable academic performance in the areas of exact science and standardized tests. During the academic year, classes are from Monday to Saturday and, before the first class of the week, students and teachers gather to the raising of the flag and singing of the national anthem.
In contrast, the Western education system values ​​creativity, individual expression and critical thinking. The classroom is often centered on the student, encouraging participation, discussion and problem solving. In order to prepare young people for the unpredictability of life and a constantly changing world, they are strongly encouraged to question, explore and test.
While the Chinese education system produces solid results in the term of academic performance, there has been a deficit of creativity and innovation by students. On the other hand, the Western education system tends to be criticized for lack of rigor and too focus on self-expression. The focus of the debate between these two educational systems should not be addressed in the comparison and qualitative classification, but rather in assessing the best practices of both. A hybrid approach that combines the rigor of Chinese teaching with an emphasis on the creativity of Western education. This could be the way forward, thus promoting a healthy balance between discipline and innovation, preparing the new generations to face the challenges of the future in a holistic way.
That, on this global stage of education, the future is to nourish this synergy, cultivating an environment where academic excellence goes hand in hand with creativity, where disciplines merge with individual expression. Awakening an intercultural educational system, where empathy, tolerance and mutual respect are fundamental principles, not forgetting that true success is achieved when a student shares his own voice with the world.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:20:56+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation in Hong Kong rises to 2% in January due to Lunar New Year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/inflacao-em-hong-kong-sobe-para-2-em-janeiro-devido-ao-ano-novo-lunar/</link><description>Inflation in Hong Kong accelerated in January, for the first time since August, due to transportation and food prices during Lunar New Year's holidays, it was announced yesterday.
 
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 2% in January, compared to the same period, said the Census and Statistics Department (CSD) of Hong Kong. In December, inflation settled at 1.4%.
In a statement, the CSD justified the acceleration, the first in five months, with "the price increases in round trip transportation and background and basic food prices due to the effect of the Chinese New Year."
The Lunar New Year, the largest mass movement in the world, is the main traditional party of Chinese families and takes place in January or February, depending on the lunar calendar. This year, he celebrated between January 28 and February 4.
The CSD also stressed that a 10% increase in the income of most residents in public housing in Hong Kong came into force in January.
A territory government spokesman argued that underlying consumer price inflation was modest in January and added that, overall, food prices "continued to record mild annual increases."
In a statement, the spokesman predicted that inflation "should remain moderate in the short term," but admitted that "uncertainties arising from geopolitical tensions and commercial conflicts deserve attention."
In early February, the new US President Donald Trump announced an additional 10% rate on Hong Kong and mainland China imports.
Inflation in China also accelerated in January, for the first time since August, due to the strong increase in family spending, at the time of New Year's holidays, contrary to persistent deflationary pressures.
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 0.5%in January, compared to the same period, reported on February 9 the National Statistics Office (NBS) of the Asian country. In December, inflation settled at 0.1%.
The temporary increase in consumption briefly checked the size of the deflait challenge that the world's second largest economy faces. The price of services increased by 0.9%, representing more than half of the total IPC increase, according to NBS.
The deflation in China factories extended for the 28th consecutive month, with a decline of 2.3%, remaining stable, compared to the contraction of the index in December. Domestic consumption is increasingly crucial and so the Chinese government has already advanced plans to increase public spending and reduce interest rates. Beijing's fear is that a rooted price cycle of pricing can bark household expenses and push companies to salary and discharge cuts. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:21:41+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>M+ Hong Kong M+ Moma and New York Moma sign first collaboration</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/museu-m-de-hong-kong-e-moma-de-nova-iorque-assinam-primeira-colaboracao/</link><description>The Hong Kong M+ Museum signed a collaboration agreement with the New York Model Museum of Modern Art, the first genre between the US institution and an Asian counterpart.
 
The alliance, announced yesterday by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper, appears amid growing geopolitical tensions between the United States and China.
M+ assured the newspaper that on Tuesday signed a memorandum of understanding with MoMA, to promote cooperation in areas such as research, curators exchange, conservation, programs and talent development.
The partnership happens in the midst of deterioration of relations between Beijing and Washington, exacerbated by the return to the US Presidency on January 20, from Donald Trump, which imposed an additional 10% tariff on Hong Kong imports and mainland China China imports .
Founded in 1929, MoMA houses a collection of nearly 200,000 pieces, which includes striking paintings in the history of art like 'The Night Star Van Gogh (1853-1890), and' Les Demoiselles d'Avignon 'by Pablo Picasso (1881-1973).
From March 15 to July 13, M+ will host the exhibition 'Picasso For Asia: The Conversation', which brings together more than 60 works by the Spanish artist, considered one of the most prolific and influential creators of the twentieth century.
M+joint curatorship, located in the West Kowloon Cultural District, and the Musée National Picasso-Paris in France, this exhibition will be the first to display masterpieces from the Parisian museum alongside pieces from a museum collection in Asia.
Among the prominent works that will be transported to the former British colony are 'The Acrobat' (1930), 'Figures by the Seaside' (1931), 'Great Great Nature with Pedestal Table' (1931), '' Portrait of Dora Maar '(1937) or' Massacre in Korea '(1951).
The Hong Kong government pointed to the recovery of tourism as essential for the region's economy. Authorities said the organization of this exhibition represents an important step in restoring the city's cultural landscape and attracting visitors from around the world.
The Hong Kong executive revealed a five -year tourism development plan, with the aim of almost duplicating the sector's contribution to Gross Domestic Product (GDP), from 2.6% in 2024 to about 5% by 2029.
The plan, presented at the end of December by the Secretary for Culture, Sport and Tourism, Rosanna Law Shuk-Pui, includes the implementation of 133 measures focused on the creation of projects that highlight the city's local and international characteristics.
Rosanna Law was appointed in early December by executive head John Lee Ka-Chiu at the first remodeling of the Hong Kong government, a neighboring city of Macau, since the former deputy commissioner of the police took office in July 2022, in the middle of pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government will study exchange of fractions in economic housing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/governo-vai-estudar-troca-de-fraccoes-na-habitacao-economica/</link><description>The Economic Housing Law may allow the holders to exchange fraction, depending on the typology they prefer. The news was given yesterday by Raymond Tam, the first time he went to the Legislative Assembly (AL) as Secretary for Transport and Public Works. The measure aims to encourage birth.
 
The first time he went to the Legislative Assembly (AL) as Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam said that the government will study the creation of a mechanism that allows the exchange of fractions within the Economic Housing Law.
The secretary who replaced Raimundo do Rosario at the head of the guardianship indicated that the permission to exchange fraction “is a short -term measure” to increase the birth rate. This future change will allow, for example, that a holder of an Economic Housing T1 that constitutes a family change to a larger home.
It is recalled that, according to estimates made in a report released in July by the United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Macau had had the lowest birth in 2024 in the world: 0.68 births per woman.
Asked about the subject by deputies Zheng Anting and Ella Lei, Raymond Tam indicated that the government is already studying this regime and will "consider everything cautiously taking into account the offer of fractions." “We don't want to divert from reality. Let's make all efforts out of this course, ”he said.
At the Yesterday's Plenary meeting, Zheng Anting recalled that, in the 2023 Economic Housing Contest, the largest slice of candidates was between 23 and 44 years old, “mostly at marriage, in the process of constituting family and having children , urgently needing a housing ”.
“Residents often focus on long-term development, and T1 fractions cannot meet marriage and procreation needs. The government must, taking into account the real needs of residents, proceed with the proper review of the Economic Housing Law, ”he said.
Raymond Tam also said that in future contests, the main typologies of the fractions will continue to be T2 and T3. In the last competitions for economic housing, T2 and T3 fractions represented about 80% of the total and T1 20%. As for the price of selling the fractions, the secretary indicated that this will still be studied by the government.
There were also deputies who asked the government to implement a permanent candidacy mechanism, but Raymond Tam did not commit to and only responded that "to achieve this goal, there must be several phases." "We will generally analyze and take into account soil resources, the speed of housing construction and the needs of the population," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:24:53+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Herculaneum papyrus</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/21/os-papiros-de-herculano/</link><description>Good news has always been a rare thing, but since SIC's new soap opera, 'Again in the White House', it premiered, it's harder to find than a diamond! Now, not even on the weekend we are spared an episode of the misadventures of this new kind of pregnant skinheads that march to the whistle of a creature that seems to have come out of a advertising poster of restorer Olex. The restorer Olex, if they remember, this famous tonic of our grandparents who was hidden behind the mirror of the riverhouse of the bathroom, did not restore anything, the people who had white hair, when applying the thing, were with the Hair, whatever the original color before the age knocked on the door, not loose, but yellow, exactly the same tone as the volunteer's hair to real estate agent for the gaza strip. Is the restorer Olex one of the products that Portugal still exports to the United States? And what repercussions could bring to the appearance of some Americans the increase in customs rates for the importation of European goods? We must continue to watch this exciting net-new to know.
Although even before the gain from Granelândia, this media saga already completely dominates all our screens, from time to time there is some space for one or another little news. One of them was the launch, another day, of DeepSeek that, for a day or almost two, actions climb, actions go down, put the world in semi-alvorço.
Artificial intelligence, which has long been in the shrink, also had to set aside to step to the saving rhetoric of the latest Messiah beyond seas, whose premonitory abilities even God would envy him if he walked by social -Media, although, be wary that on top of the programming is another, better and less depressing. Recently, however, AI has been news again.
With the exception of AI scientific use, for example, medical investigation, where its ability to process huge amounts of information in record time makes it possible to go important in the search for new disease therapies so far incurable, the news that normally hear coming from of this quadrant are not the best. Also the other day came to public another case in which AI was used to create false pornographic images of a public character who were later scattered anonymously over the internet. Another favorite of AI is its “academic” use where it gives titles to those who have no breath, but it is clever and, above all, if there is guita, while it serves as quick relief for pains of “consciousness” of whom, generous and Large hands, gives notes that beat the ceiling. Far will already go the days of the adagio 'quod natura non dat, salmantica non praestat, or, for those who do not know Latin, what nature does not give, the University of Salamanca does not lend, today you do not need to lend anything, sells If so, plastic, and it's not even that expensive!
But here is finally good news related to AI arrived; More than good, excellent!
 
Herculaneum
The image that accompanies this text must have already aroused the curiosity even of the most peaceful spirits. They will probably not be able to guess what it is, but do not feel bad about it, because when these things came to daylight in 1752, during the first excavations of what, because of these things, would be nicknamed Vila dos Papiros , no one knew what it was and is even fearing that some specimens were even burned, taken by mere pieces of charred wood. It is a charred papyrus roll. This roll is part of a set of 1,826 copies in different conservation states that were discovered in the ruins of Herculaneum, an ancient Roman city in the Campânia area of ​​Italy current.
We have all heard of the city of Pompeia - some will have already visited it - which was destroyed by an eruption of Vesuvius, and even had Hollywood movie honors and television series. Herculaneum, the Portuguese form of the Latin name, was the other Roman city of antiquity destroyed by the same eruption of Vesuvius in our era. Sun has solidifying and fossilizing the lives that previously existed there. Vesuvius is about fifteen kilometers south of the urban perimeter of Naples Moderna, Pompeii about ten kilometers south of Vesuvius and Herculaneum is halfway between Naples and Pompei, right in front of the volcanic cone, about six kilometers from the crater. Both Pompeii and Herculaneum were port cities, but with the advance of the eruption and over the years, both are now a certain distance from the beach.
It is thanks to two letters that Plínio, the young man (61-112), writes to Tacitus (56-120), his contemporary Roman historian, who know that both cities were destroyed by the eruption of Vesuvius in the year 79.
Although the city of Herculaneum came to the light of the day before Pompeii, more precisely in 1709, when inhabitants of the Italian village of Ercolano dug a well, his archaeological park is incomparably smaller than Pompeii that was rediscovered in 1748. One of the great problems of the Roman city of Herculaneum is that it is buried under the modern village of Ercolano, and as such, its excavation It would depend on the destruction of what over the centuries has been built over the Roman urbe.
As the city of Herculaneum was closer to Vesuvio, its carbonization and consequent extinction of oxygen were faster which led to its state of conservation than that of its south counterpart. Thus, in Herculaneum we find papyrus, wood, fabrics and even foods that have retained for over 1,600 years under the ashes and the Vesuvius volcanic mud.
 
Carbonized papyrus
The more than 1,800 papyrus that have so far been found have come to the surface in different vacancies and in different conservation states. In 1752 the first 21 papyrus were found, followed by eleven more in the same year. As the excavations went on more papyrus were found and in 1855 there were already the more than 1,800 we currently have, of which 341 are whole, that is, they have the same aspect as the image.
The problem of these papyrus is that their advanced state of carbonization associated with the time they were under the ground at the mercy of nature made us impossible to unfold. Different methodologies have been employed over the years, some more successful than others, but all extremely slow.
Some of these techniques even lead to the almost destruction of papyrus, as was the case with the method used by Camillo Padeni (1715-1781) which consisted of cutting the roll in half and then pelas the papyrus layer by reading. More successful was the technique used by Abbot Piaggio, curator of ancient manuscripts of the Vatican Library, which invented a machine to unfold the rollers. With the help of this machine it was possible, for the first time, unfolding an entire papyrus without being destroyed. The problem was that each day could only unfold a few millimeters; In all it took four years to unfold the entire papyrus.
 
The importance of papyrus
It is believed that at the lowest levels of the village still by excavating if they can find more papyrus rolls, and given the general state of conservation of Herculaneum, the possibility that more libraries could be discovered.
The village of papyrus in Herculano contains the only library in the Greco-Roman world that came to us intact. It is estimated that the approximately 1,800 rolls so far found can represent about 800 different literary works. The various books that have already been identified seem to be above all works of Epicurean philosophy written in Greek.
In order to understand the importance of this finding, let's see, as an example, the case of the great tragediographer poet. Although only seven of his works arrived to us complete, it is estimated, based on the titles we have in antiquity catalogs and excerpts from various works of their unknown cited in other authors, which will have written between ninety pieces. It is just an example of what happens to most Roman and Greek writers. In addition to lost works of known authors, there are also authors of which we only know their names since none of their works survived. Such is the case of several Athenian tragediographers who competed, alongside the great poets Ésquilo, Sophocles and Euripides, for the first prize in the great Dionysiacs, religious festivals we have already talked about in this column.
Crisypo, a Greek stoic poet, will have written, according to sources of antiquity, more than 700 works, all lost. All that was known to him were quotes in other authors. However, they have already been found among the papyrus of Herculaneum significant parts of two of his works, namely 'providence' and 'logical questions'.
It is believed that, most likely, this was the private library of philodemus, one of the most important epiculars of the first century BC, whose patron, Lucio Calpurius cesonin, was the father-in-law of Julius Caesar and probably the owner of this sumptuous village. It was customary among the Romans to have large libraries in their country houses, where they organized literary or philosopher and artists, watered with good wine and provided with the wealth of dead and living meat. The great poets Virgílio and Horace were part of the Cycle of Friends of Pisution and Philodemo, the latter also he poet.
The fear that a new rash of Vesuvius could bear Herculaneum and Pompei again led to in March 2016, a group of French, English and Americans academics to write an open letter to Times asking the excavations in Herculaneum, suspended since 2009 , if they restart, arguing that 'Another Eruption of Vesuvius May put the villa Beyond Reach Forever ’. The Vesuvius, who never really hampeth, has been erupting, for average, every twenty years since 1631, when his activity began to record. As the last eruption was in 1944, it is feared that the next may be of huge proportions and, in fact, the authorities have increased the perimeter of the danger zone.
 
The Vesuvius Challenge
It was clear that the methodologies so far used were derived from little gains; The process of text recovery was too slow, hard, and often fruitless as the opening of the manuscripts led to their destruction.
Since the principle of millennium that has been trying to unfold virtually by XPCT (X-Ray Phase-Contrast Tomography) and also its reading has made use of technology as the ink tends to disappear over time and,, Moreover, with the carbonization of the papyrus. Thus, the digitization of papyrus already unfolded has made use of technologies such as MSI (Multi-Spectral Imaging) and Swir HSI (Shortwave-Infred Hyperspectral Imaging) in an attempt to recover the lost texts.
After, in 2016, he unfolded virtually and read a roll of Hebrew scroll, Brent Seales, a Professor of Computational Sciences at the University of Kentucky, in the United States, in collaboration with Richard Janko, professor of classic Michigan, was able to , in February 2023, to read parts of a much-damaged Herculanean papyrus using X-ray technology and artificial intelligence. The resulting text was identified as part of a lost work about Alexander the Great and his empire.
That same year, with the financial support of Silicon Valley, was launched Vesuvius Challenge, a competition to decipher Herculaneum papyrus rollers using 3D X-Ray Software and Artificial Intelligence with a $ 700,000 prize.
In October of the same year, students Luke Farritor and Youssef Nader managed to develop virtually several layers of one of the rolls and identify the Greek word Porphyras 'purpura' without the roll being physically altered.
This result achieved scarce months after the launch of the contest was considered promising wisdom and new stages of the challenge were launched. Already in April 2024, Papirologists at the University of Pisa, using X-ray and infrared, were able to extract from one of the papyrus, information about the location of Plato's lost grave.
These results have only now appeared in the news because another Herculaneum papyrus has recently been unfolded virtually by technological means and thanks to artificial intelligence is now being read at Oxford University.
For the year 2025, five rolls were distributed by competitors this time with the aim of being read in full. If this objective is satisfactorily achieved, and if more papyrus are discovered with literary works of the classical world so far unknown, this could lead to a civilizational revolution only comparable with what happened in the Renaissance. The great challenge would then be knowing if, in the state when things are, with democracy rising the risk of becoming indistinct of authoritarianism, with the people apparently willing to deliver their freedom to the hands of people, until there is until there Very little, little recommended, we would be able to recognize the true civilizational and humanist value of such a discovery. Hopefully natural intelligence can still be worthwhile.</description><pubDate>2025-02-21T02:20:54+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>