<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/analistas-chineses-destacam-valor-estrategico-da-relacao-com-russia-antes-da-visita-de-xi/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Exhibition “Poetry in the Garden” celebrates the Portuguese language</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/exposicao-poesia-no-jardim-celebra-a-lingua-portuguesa/</link><description>The exhibition “Poetry in the Garden” is inaugurated tomorrow, an initiative within the Portuguese Day of Portuguese Language, which was celebrated last Monday. The exhibition, organized by IPOR, with support from Casa de Portugal and the Macau Forum, will be patent until the end of May at the Pai Van Seac Park. The exhibition will consist of 11 panels suitable for external environment. Each of the ten individual paintings will represent a poem from one of the nine Portuguese -speaking countries, and there is one in which a poet of the mashes will be represented.
The text of the poem will appear in its original language and its version translated to Chinese, in traditional and simplified characters. A brief biography of the writer will also be included in both languages ​​and will also figure a QR code with an audio file where one can hear a declamation of the poem and two other QR codes with the audio version in Chinese, one in Mandarin and one in Cantonese.
After the exhibition period in the garden, the panels will be converted into a traveling exhibition that will be displayed in higher education and non-higher institutions of the Popular Republic of China, as well as in Lusophony countries that are interested in welcoming it. “With this project it is intended to transform a garden of Macau into an outdoor literature gallery, accessible to the entire population, thus making known the poetic work of authors of nine countries and the region where Portuguese is one of the official languages,” says the statement issued by IPOR. “Poetry in the Garden” seeks to “bring poetry in Portuguese to meet the population of MSAR and its visitors”.
The exhibition has as its main objectives “to disseminate contemporary authors of Portuguese -speaking countries and their work, streamline Macau's public space in a creative way, to appeal interest in reading, book and Portuguese, value the pluricentrism of the Portuguese language and its variants, and also to give due recognition to the translators of the Chinese and Portuguese language”, says the organization.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:10:25</pubDate></item><item><title>President of Brazil goes to Russia and China in the midst of tensions in Ukraine and global trade</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/presidente-do-brasil-vai-a-russia-e-a-china-no-meio-de-tensoes-na-ucrania-e-no-comercio-global/</link><description>Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva visits Russia and China between May 8 and 13 when tensions between Ukrainians and Russians grow and the commercial war began by the president of the United States, Donald Trump. Lula da Silva embarked on Tuesday night to Moscow, at the invitation of Russian President Vladimir Putin, to participate this Friday, in celebration of the 80th anniversary of Victory Day, a date that marks Berlin taking by the Soviet Army in World War II. Between Thursday and Saturday, Lula will fulfill an official agenda in Russia, which includes a meeting with his Russian counterpart. The Brazilian delegation has several ministers, including Mauro Vieira, from Foreign Affairs, and the president of Parliament, Senator Davi Alcolumbre, and provides for signatures of documents in the areas of science and technology. On the agenda of the Brazilian head of state is planned a meeting with Putin and a meeting with the Prime Minister of Slovakia, Robert Fico.
In Russia, Lula da Silva will again try to position Brazil as a mediator of peace in the conflict initiated by the Russian invasion of the Ukraine territory in 2022 and to pass the sign of independence of foreign policy. As president of BRICS (group of emerging countries founded by Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa), the Brazilian leader has argued that the group participate in a possible negotiation for a peace agreement in Ukraine. The Russian government reported that Ukrainian drones launched attacks against the Russian capital on Monday and Tuesday, interrupting flights at four Moscow airports and several other places, raising the tension in the conflict. On Sunday, Lula da Silva will land in China for a state visit with an official agenda between May 12 and 13. The Brazilian president will meet with Chinese President Xi Jinping and attend the fourth meeting of the China-Celac Forum (Latin American and Caribbean Community). It will be the third state meeting with the Chinese leader since Lula da Silva returned to power for a third term. The last meeting took place in November 2024, when Xi Jinping was visiting the Brazilian capital.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:04:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy says hotel scarcity threatens Macau's competitiveness</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/galaxy-diz-que-escassez-de-hoteis-ameaca-competitividade-de-macau/</link><description>Galaxy leader warned yesterday that the shortage of hotel rooms could threaten the city's international competitiveness as a tourist destination.
Galaxy Entertainment Group president Francis Lui Yiu Tung said that "the issue of hotel rooms should also be addressed," as Macao casinos focus on events and middle -class gamblers.
In 2019 the great gamblers accounted for 46.2% of the total revenues of Macao casinos. But in the first three months of the year this segment, known as VIP game, was a slice of 25.1%.
Big bets were affected by the arrest of the leader of the largest vip betting company in the world in November 2021.
Francis Lui recalled that Las Vegas received 42.5 million visitors in 2019, before the pandemic began, and currently has “more than 155,000 hotel rooms”. "This is more than three times higher than Macao," lamented the businessman, although the city received more than 34.9 million tourists last year. And the number of hotel rooms available in the territory has been decreasing.
According to official data, Macao's hotels and pensions had, at the end of March 2025, with 44,000 rooms, 5.8% less than the same month last year.
As a result, the number of hotel establishments guests fell 5.4% in the first quarter of 2025 and about 59% of visitors arrived in organized excursions and spent less than one day in the city. "The search for accommodation will continue to overcome the offer in the coming years," warned Francis Lui. "If we cannot properly face the issue of accommodation of accommodation, the competitiveness of Macau (…), not only at the regional but also global level, can be harmed," warned the businessman.
Francis Lui admitted that the scarcity of land available in Macao is a challenge and pointed out as a possible “greater integration” solution with the neighboring special hengqin economic zone.
On the other hand, the operator said the six dealers should "join to protect Macao's leadership position, not competing in prices but in the quality of the customer experience."
According to data from the Macao Hotel Association, which brings together 47 local establishments, the average prices of the rooms fell 9.7% in homologous terms to 1,287 patacas in March.
Francis Lui spoke during the start of Global Gaming Expo Asia, the largest event in the game industry held in Macau, which will take place until this Friday.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:09:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Descent of economic indices is also harming lawyers, note aam</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/descida-dos-indices-economicos-tambem-esta-a-prejudicar-advogados-nota-aam/</link><description>Macao's fall in the economy has been affecting various activity sectors and lawyers are no exception. Oriana Pun, from the Directorate of the Macao Lawyers Association (AAM), suggested that the professionals of the sector take advantage of the opportunities of the great bay and hengqin, for example. At the press conference for the presentation of this year's Lawyer Day activities, AAM also indicated that the protocol with the Portuguese Bar Association remains in a water bath.
 
The descent of Macao's economic indices has also affected the region's lawyers, warned Oriana Inácio Pun, secretary general of the Macao Lawyers Association (AAM). "We know that the [economic] environment is damaging several sectors, namely that of lawyers," AAM official said at the press conference of presentation of this year's lawyer day.
In particular, he indicated lawyers linked to the real estate sector have been harmed by the fall in this area. "Just see the number of Scripture to know that it is certainly having a lot of impact," he said, stressing that "law firm not only depends on the real estate." The AAM official suggested that lawyers follow the political guidelines of this year's governance lines and take advantage of opportunities in the Great Bay, Hengqin and with Lusophone investors, in order to fulfill the role of Macao and Sino-Lirophone platform.
The number of lawyers in Macau has been stable over the last few years. According to the association's numbers, there are currently 457 lawyers and about 180 trainees. Of the total lawyers, 87 perform functions in the great bay.
Asked about the reactivation of the protocol between AAM and the Portuguese Bar Association, Oriana Inácio Pun said there is no news yet. "This depends on both parties, but we have not yet started negotiation in this context," said the official. This protocol, suspended since 2013, had mutual recognition of the qualifications of sector professionals and facilitated the entry of Portuguese lawyers in the Macao market.
 
Lawyer's Day with Sport, Forum and Free Legal Consultations
 
Yesterday's press conference served for AAM to present activities related to this year's Lawyer Day, which starts this Saturday with a sporting day. Between 2:30 pm and 5:30 pm, in the field of Macao University of Science and Technology (Must), lawyers, interns, employees of the Directorate of Justice Services (DSAJ) and even law students will participate in a series of sports activities.
The second activity, the forum “linking the interior and the outside - Forum on the development of high quality legal services under the initiative‘ a track, a route ’” takes place on May 16th. “In this forum, we will be attended by lawyers from Macao and also from the interior of China, Hong Kong and Southeast Asia,” said Vong Hin Fai, president of the AAM Directorate. This forum takes place at the Studio City Hotel at 2:30 pm.
Also on May 16, at 6:30 pm, the ceremony of opening of the lawyer day is held, followed by a cocktail and dinner, also at Studio City.
Finally, on the weekend of May 17 and 18, between 10am and 8pm, members of the Association will offer free legal consultations at the Tourist Information Center of the Senate Tourism Services Directorate. This time, Vong Hin Fai, lawyers from Hong Kong and China's interior, will also support these free consultations.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:04:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Game operators are vulnerable to retaliation and Chinese slowdown, says Fitch</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/operadoras-de-jogo-estao-vulneraveis-a-retaliacao-e-ao-abrandamento-chines-diz-fitch/</link><description>Financial notation agency Fitch Ratings has considered that the commercial war launched by the United States may undermine Macao gaming operators, which are “subject to retaliation” and vulnerable to Chinese economic slowdown.
 
"US game companies in Macau face increasing geopolitical challenges as trade war continues; commercial tensions between the US and China have raised concerns that US gaming operators may be retaliated, while weaker economic perspectives in China should press the Macao Games' profits," reads an analysis of the trade war on their operation. US companies in Macau.
The Fitch notes that “commercial tensions between the US and China have intensified in recent months, with retaliatory measures between the two countries that raised bilateral rates to more than 100%, and recently, there has been efforts to alleviate the conflict, but there is still no certainty of how the issues will be resolved”, therefore, impacting the evolution of the activity of the three North American companies operating in this sector: Las Vegas Sands, Wynn and MGM Resorts International.
Still, they add, "there are no concrete indications that China has directed measures against playing companies that operate in Macao," where this industry represents 80% of tax revenues, and the three US operators are worth more than half of the revenues of this market.
For Fitch analysts, in addition to the commercial war issue, with increasing tariffs to occupy a prominent place, operators in Macau also face the danger of softening the Chinese economy, which can press the game's revenues in the territory.
“This weaker perspective of economic evolution in China can also press revenues in Macao, but this can be compensated with any government measures to stimulate consumer expense,” reads the report, which recalls that the estimated Chinese growth for 2025 was reviewed down to 3.9%.
Fitch's analysis appears at a time when the game sector has been having the best start of the year since 2019, before the COVID - 19 pandemic began.
Between January and April, Macau casinos registered total revenues of 76.5 billion patacas, more 0.8% than in the same period as 2024.
Macao obtained in 2024 total game revenues of 226.8 billion patacas, 23.9% more than in 2022, but only 73.2% of the recorded in 2019, before the pandemic.
The Macao government predicted, in the budget for 2025, that the year close with total revenues of 240 billion patacas, which would be a 6% increase compared to last year. But on 23 April, the secretary for the economy and finance of Macao admitted that public revenues of 2025 “may not be as optimistic as expected” as the game's revenues are below the monthly target of 20 billion Patacas. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:09:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing Price Index drops 10.6% compared to 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/indice-de-precos-da-habitacao-cai-106-em-relacao-a-2024/</link><description>The global housing price index was 202.4 in the first quarter of 2025, a 10.6% decrease in the same period of 2024 and 2.1% compared to last year's four quarter.
According to the data provided yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the housing price index dropped 0.5% compared to the previous period, with a more significant descent in the price of housing in mud and coloane. 4.2% falls were registered on both islands, while the Macao Peninsula Index accused a slight rise of 0.7%.
Considering the year of building the buildings, it can be seen that the dwelling price index belonging to the echelon from six to ten years descended 3.7%, even though the one or equal to five years has grown 1.1%. Already the housing under construction fell 2.2% in relation to the preceding period.
Looking at the useful area of ​​the autonomous fractions, it is possible to verify that the level of dwelling prices of the 100th square meters of the service area or more and the level of the level from 50 to 74.9 square meters had their descents of 4.2% and 1.4% compared to the proper period. In turn, the 75 to 99.9 square meter level rated 1.1% in the same temporal window. Considering the height of the buildings, there is a decrease of 2% in the rate of echelon buildings greater than seven floors and an increase of 2.8% in the index of those with a level of seven floors or less.
Housing prices have been going down since 2022, after reaching the peak between May and June 2018, when the index was 270.7. The fall was especially abrupt at the end of last year, falling from 231.4 registered in January to 202.3 for the period between December last year and February this year - the lowest brand since 2016.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:09:12</pubDate></item><item><title>More than a thousand complaints about illegal accommodation in the last three years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/mais-de-mil-denuncias-sobre-alojamento-ilegal-nos-ultimos-tres-anos/</link><description>Authorities have received more than 1,000 illegal housing in the last three years, notably about 1,300 suspicious fractions of illegal accommodation for tourists. The Directorate of Tourism Services pointed out that Zape and Taipa are the zones in which the largest number of illegal pensions are verified.
 
From 2022 to March this year 1,062 complaints were registered regarding the illegal rendering of accommodation submitted to the authorities, with 1,377 fractions to be the subject of complaints. The number was advanced by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) and the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), indicating that between 2023 and 2024, 27 cases were communicated by the owners by their own initiative.
The authorities presented the work to combat illegal accommodation on Tuesday at the ordinary meeting of the Islands Community Services Advisory Board, and said they hope to encourage owners to take the initiative in the inspection and submission of complaints.
"Illegal pensions are more in the Zape area, followed by Nape and Taipa, which also have relatively more illegal accommodation units," said the Island Community Services Advisory Board, citing the Executive, in statements to the Chinese channel of TDM Macau.
Under the current law on the prohibition of illegal accommodation of accommodation, in cases where the owners, before being investigated, participate in infringements to STD and have not been involved in the exploitation of illegal accommodation of accommodation, STD may dispense with seal affixing measures at the fraction door and suspension of water supply and electricity, or reduce the application term of these measures.
The Community Services Advisory Body also mentioned that the Government regularly discloses information to the General Assembly of the Condominium and to the “high -risk” private buildings of the illegal accommodation of accommodation, and CPSP is available to travel to buildings to perform awareness seminars on illegal pensions.
According to STD, non-residents authorized to remain for a period not exceeding 90 days when they enter the city can only be in accommodation provided by legally exploited hotel industry, such as hotels, hotels and low-cost accommodation. The activity of accomplishing accommodation by person or entity that does not have a license of the establishment of the hotel industry, to the above individuals, in a building or autonomous fraction not intended for the purposes of hotel activity, including housing, stores, industrial buildings, among others.
STATISTIC STATISTICAL DATA show that, last year, 186 fractions suspected of being used for illegal accommodation of accommodation were sealed, and from the beginning of the year to mid -March, 253 investigation operations were carried out to 124 units, and 35 suspicious apartments were sealed.
There are currently about 47,000 hotel rooms in Macao and the government previously indicated that the number of rooms has reduced since some integrated resorts have renewed their rooms to make them larger, but more rooms will be available on the market as some new hotels are under construction.
Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of STD, expressed the desire to “make the regulations” relating to the provision of accommodation in the hope that licensing could cover, for example, youth inns and small inns, in response to the opinion of the tourism industry about the lack of low -cost hotels.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:03:19</pubDate></item><item><title>India justifies attack with Pakistan delay in responding with concrete actions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/india-justifica-ataque-com-demora-de-paquistao-em-responder-com-accoes-concretas/</link><description>India defended the military operation yesterday in Pakistani territory as a direct response to Islamabade inaction after a terrorist attack two weeks ago in Caxemira Indiana, allegedly carried out by a group based on Pakistan.
 
Indian foreign secretary Vikram Misri transmitted this information during a press conference in which no questions were allowed.
Misri said that although India provided information to Pakistan and expecting measures to be taken against terrorists, there was a significant delay and no concrete measures were taken. "Despite having spent two weeks since the attacks, there is no evidence that Pakistan has taken measures against terrorist infrastructures on its territory or under its control," he said.
Speaking to the media, Misri stressed that the April 22 attack-in the tourist region of Pahalgam, in Caxemira Indiana-, which aimed at civilians and was attributed to the Lashkar-e-Taiba organization, required immediate actions against authors and supporters.
Indian secret services predict, according to Misri, new attacks against India by terrorist cells based on Pakistan, which created a “obligation to determine and prevent”.
In this context, India exercised the right of response, said Misri, stressing that the actions were “proportional and responsible”, centered on the dismantling of terrorist infrastructures and the neutralization of terrorists trying to cross the border.
The Secretary for Foreign Affairs reiterated that India's response should be seen in the light of a recent UN Security Council statement about the Pahalgam attack, which stressed the need to punish those responsible.
At least 26 Pakistani and eight Indians died yesterday, following bombing carried out by Islamabade and Nova Delhi, in a climb of violence between the two nuclear powers that vie for the Caixemira region.
After armed men kill, in the April 22 attack, 26 people in Caxemira Indiana, the tension has increased among neighboring countries, rivals since they became independent of the United Kingdom in 1947.
The two armies exchanged artillery shots along the border disputed in the Caixemira region, a few hours after the Indian air offensive against Pakistani territory, in retaliation for the deadly attack in Pahalgam.
Indian missiles who hit six cities in Caxemira and Punjab Pakistanis and the kixemira shots killed at least 26 civilians, including two 3-year-old girls and a 5-year-old boy, according to the Pakistani army spokesman, General Ahmed Chaudhry, who also reported 46 injured.
India recorded eight dead and 29 injured in the village of Poonch (northwest) in the Indian caixemira, following artillery fire.
The battle, which began at night, continued in the morning around the village, the target of numerous Pakistani projectiles, reported journalists from the France-Presse news agency said. Violent explosions were also heard early in the evening on the outskirts of Srinagar, the main town of the Indian part of Caxemira. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:10:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn Macau profit shrinks more than one third by March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/lucro-da-wynn-macau-encolhe-mais-de-um-terco-ate-marco/</link><description>Game operator Wynn Macau announced operational profits of $ 127.1 million in the first quarter, 38.3% less than in the same period of 2024. The mass market continued to be the main segment for the operator, representing revenues of $ 710.9 million between January and March.
 
According to a statement, the two properties operated by the company registered revenues of $ 865.9 million between January and March, a 13.3% drop compared to the same period of 2024.
Bets on Wynn Macau and Wynn Palace casinos were responsible for most of the company's turnover, raising $ 720 million in revenues, less 12.2% than in the first quarter of last year.
Craig Billings, the mother's executive director, American Wynn Resorts, said in the same statement that the big gamblers were more lucky than normal in the first quarter, something that "negatively affected the results."
In this segment, known as the VIP game, the bets decreased only 1.25% in the two Wynn Macau casinos, but revenues fell much more, 34.4% in homologous terms, to $ 120.2 million.
On average, Macao casinos manage to raise at least 3% of bets on the VIP game, but this amount fell to 1.09% in the first three months of the year, in the case of the Wynn Macao Casino.
The so -called mass market continued to be by far the main segment for the operator, representing revenues of $ 710.9 million between January and March, 6.9% less than in the same period as 2024.
In 2019 the so -called Bachará VIP game represented 46.2% of the total recipes of Macao casinos. But in the first three months of the year this segment was a slice of 25.1%. Big bets were affected by the arrest of the leader of the largest vip betting company in the world in November 2021.
Wynn Resorts, which is building a Casino hotel in the United Arab Emirates, said it continues to "explore opportunities to develop more business or related games in the domestic and international market."
In a teleconference with analysts, after the announcement of the results, Craig Billings, acknowledged that the company could compete for new concessions for casinos in Japan, but only "if the conditions were adequate."
Billings also gave Thailand as an example, a country that is discussing the legalization of casinos and described as "an incredible market, with air transport, infrastructure, tourism, etc. unbelievable." Billings said he did not expect any impact on Wynn Macau from the trade war created by the United States tariffs on imports from China and the two Chinese regions of Hong Kong and Macau.
On Tuesday, the Financial Notation Agency Fitch Ratings considered that the trade war could damage play operators in Macau, which are “subject to retaliation” and vulnerable to Chinese economic slowdown. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:09:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Applications to the Child Support Plan will be made in the “Single Account”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/candidaturas-ao-plano-de-apoio-para-criancas-serao-feitas-na-conta-unica/</link><description>Applications to the new year of childhood assistance subsidy, which are scheduled for this summer, will be made through the “Single Account” application, whose system is about to be launched. The Institute of Social Action indicated that 15,000 children will benefit from the monthly subsidy of 1,500 patacas, and the amount of the average expenses that families spend on baby products, which “is between 900 patacas and 1,300 patacas” per week.
 
The government is preparing the launch of the new childhood support plan, and is elaborating the administrative regulation and finalizing the creation of the respective application system for application for “Single Account” mobile phone, which will be opened “soon” to parents of more than 15,000 children eligible to the program.
Hon Wai, president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), said yesterday that the candidacy will be made through the “Single Account”, where personal data about parents and children are already found and that, after verifying the information and the introduction of bank data in the application, the conditions for the granting of the allowance will be gathered.
At this time, the basic framework of the system has already been conceived. "It is believed that [the system] can be launched soon after the tests are passed. As it is expected to covers more than 10,000 families, who can apply for the program in a short time, we have to test the safety and load of the network," he said.
Hon Wai, who was speaking yesterday at the Macau Forum, the morning program of the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, reiterated that the beneficiaries of the “Childhood Assistance Subsidy” program are holders of the MSAR permanent resident identity ticket, covering those born in 2022.
It is recalled that the plan was announced in this financial year's government lines, being one of the measures that the government intends to use to encourage birth in the territory. The program provides for the assignment of a monthly subsidy of 1,500 patacas, totaling 18,000 patacas per year, to babies and children under 3 years of age. The secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, said that the support plan should be implemented this summer.
Regarding the setting of the amount of subsidy, Hon Wai justified that the decision takes into account the important expenses of families who have children, such as diapers, milk powder and food, based on the average price of baby products in major stores according to consumer board data.
"It is estimated that the weekly amount is between 900 patacas and 1,300 patacas. It is expected that the allowance provides part of financial support to the family and encourages birth," he said. Macau registered last year a fertility rate of 0.58 children, the lowest ever in the territory.
Given the situation of the low desire for residents to have children, IAS added that it will also reevaluate children care services and study access to minors under two years old, as well as reinforce the training of sector professionals and the supervision of day care centers to ensure the quality of services.
"The number of children's care vacancies in Macao is about 7,700 and the offer is greater than 60% of the total population of children under the three years.
 
Senior Census Argates this year
 
In the same radio program, IAS also highlighted the work dedicated to the aging problem of the population of Macau. The government will launch a census and registration of isolated elderly and household aggregates of elderly couples, and the work will begin, on a pilot base this year in the Seac Pai Van and Praia do Manduco areas.
Hon Wai indicated that there are 30,000 isolated elderly and families of elderly couples in Macau, but that the addresses of some may be different from the addresses recorded in IAS. In this sense, the body said that it is working with the cartography and registration database to collect information on the distribution of the elderly in various buildings in various areas, “so that, in case of fire and other situations that require special support, the authorities can immediately obtain relevant information to provide immediate support,” he said.
IAS will also carry out a door to door inquiry after the creation of the database to record the physical conditions of the elderly and provide assistance taking into account the special circumstances of each residential zone in question.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:02:21</pubDate></item><item><title>China justifies participation in the Moscow Parade as an act of respect for history</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/china-justifica-participacao-na-parada-de-moscovo-como-ato-de-respeito-pela-historia/</link><description>Beijing defended yesterday the presence of Chinese troops at the Military Military Parade in Moscow as a demonstration of “respect for history” and not as a gesture of Russia support in the war in Ukraine. "China's participation in the 80th anniversary of the Soviet victory in the Great Patriotic War reflects respect for history and the firm determination to defend the achievements of World War II," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said at a press conference. The spokesman recalled that the victory in war was "the result of the joint struggle of all countries and peoples lovers of peace and justice" and both the Chinese people and the people of the former Soviet Union "have made huge national sacrifices and indelible historical contributions."
The comments came a day after Ukraine criticized the presence of foreign troops in the Parade of the Red Square as a “manifestation of support for the aggressor state”. Beijing avoided responding directly to Kiev's rebuke, but insisted that the position on the war "has been clear and consistent." "Avoiding a new climb of tensions is now the urgent priority. All parties involved must reach consensus and create conditions to achieve this goal," he added. Regarding bilateral cooperation between China and Russia, the spokesman reiterated that "it has always been based on the principles of mutual respect, shared benefit and common success."
The parade in Moscow will also have military units from 12 more countries. Chinese President Xi Jinping will be present on the first visit to Russia since March 2023. A bilateral meeting with Russian President Vladimir Putin is also planned today.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:08:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Varicella cases more than double compared to last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/casos-de-varicela-mais-que-duplicam-em-relacao-ao-ano-passado/</link><description>The number of varicella cases has increased significantly since April, according to data released by health services on compulsory declaration diseases. If, in early April, the weekly average was around 12 cases, last week ascended to 23 cases - more than twice the average weekly cases calculated in the same year's same period.
This abrupt climb was partly due to a case of collective chickenpox infection at Pui Ching Secondary School, which affected a total of 21 people. Students in question began to manifest symptoms such as rashes and small bubbles on the head, limbs, back and chest since early May, having undergone medical treatment without developing serious complications.
Although most patients were vaccinated with a virus dose, health services stress in a statement that this particular case resulted from a “disruptive infection” - that is, when a vaccinated individual gets sick by the same disease that the vaccine should prevent. In these cases, symptoms are usually slight, atypical and shorter. Once they were notified, the health authorities inspected the site and reinforced communication with the establishment concerned to ensure that infection control measures and school suspension rules were being met.
In total, since the beginning of the year and until Tuesday, 195 cases of chickenpox were recorded in Macao-a number higher than last year's same year in 90 cases. About three quarters of the infected are children, mostly aged between eight and 17 years.
As health services recall in a statement, chickenpox is an acute and highly contagious infectious disease, especially when the first rashes appear. The chickenpox occurs predominantly in children aged between five and ten and may manifest throughout the year, being prevalent in winter and spring. In addition to vaccination, maintaining good personal and environmental hygiene is essential to preventing the disease.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:04:19</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ investigation coordinated by architect Nuno Soares shown at the Venice Biennial</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/investigacao-da-usj-coordenada-pelo-arquitecto-nuno-soares-exibida-na-bienal-de-veneza/</link><description>The research project entitled “Mapping Macau's Urban Evolution 1557 - 2022”, from the University of São José Architecture and Design Department (USJ), will be presented at the Venice Biennial at the parallel event “Parallel Worlds, Exhibition from Macao, China”.
This investigation, coordinated by architect Nuno Soares, presents a series of three -dimensional models illustrating the urban development of Macau over 450 years, says USJ in the press note, adding that the project results from a five -year research initiative developed with students of the third year of architectural studies, under the module “Evolution of Urban Landscapes”.
“Parallel Worlds, Exhibition from Macao, China” will be presented as an official parallel event of the 19th International Architecture Exhibition - La Biennale di Venezia, from May 10 to November 23, 2025. Macao's urban landscape, interpreted through architectural language, ”reads in USJ press release, which adds that“ at the heart of the exhibition is a collaboration between the acclaimed Architecture photographer Iwan Baan, winner of Golden Lion at the Venice Biennial, and academic teams at the China Academy of São José, Macau. ” Iwan Baan's photographic works, which “capture the unique urban fabric of Macao”, “will dialogue with architectural models and facilities created by teachers and students from both institutions,” says the institution.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:04:19</pubDate></item><item><title>China asks for sincerity to the US for the meeting this weekend</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/china-pede-sinceridade-aos-eua-para-o-encontro-deste-fim-de-semana/</link><description>China yesterday appealed to the United States to demonstrate “sincere conversations” planned weekend, stressing that it accepted the meeting based on its interests and expectations of the international community.
 
"The United States must demonstrate sincerity in conversations, correct their wrong practices, find a point of balance with China and solve mutual concerns based on equality and respect," the Chinese Ministry of Commerce said in a statement.
The ministry stressed that “all dialogue and negotiation should be based on the principle of mutual respect”, in reference to meetings that the vice-minister He Lifeng-China's main commercial negotiator-will have US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent on Saturday and Sunday in Switzerland.
“In recent times, US guardians have been circulating information on possible adjustments to their tariffs and transmitted this intention to China by different channels, manifesting openness to dialogue,” reads in the statement. "Given global expectations, China's interests and US industry and consumer demands, China has decided to accept talking," he added.
The Ministry has accused the United States of having adopted, since the return to Donald Trump's power, "unilateral, illegal and unreasonable tariff measures," which will "severely affected bilateral economic and commercial relations, disturbed international order and created serious obstacles to global economic recovery."
"To defend its legitimate rights and interests, China has taken firm countereds. Our position is consistent: either in the confrontation, and in dialogue, China's determination to safeguard its development interests will not change, as it will not change its commitment to equity, justice and multilateralism," he said.
The Chinese government has reiterated that it maintains the door open to dialogue, but warned that the United States must recognize "the negative impact of its unilateral tariffs," respect international economic standards and listen to "the rational voices of all sectors." But if the US "says one thing and do another" or use "coercion and blackmail under the disguise of negotiations," this is something China "will never accept," said Beijing. "China will never sacrifice its principles or international justice in exchange for an agreement," he said.
In the same note, the Ministry of Commerce has ensured that China will continue to work with other countries to “reinforce coordination, resist together unilateral protectionism and hegemonic intimidation, defend free trade and multilateralism, and promote inclusive and beneficial economic globalization”.
The Ministry of Foreign Affairs confirmed yesterday that He Lifeng - the confidence figure of Chinese President Xi Jinping - will visit Switzerland from May 9 to 12 for meetings with Bessent, as part of efforts to relieve tension between the two powers.
Bessent had already announced on Tuesday that he will meet with the Chinese delegation this weekend after having a video conferencing with He on February 25, during which they discussed fares and the fight against fentanyl trafficking, a powerful opiate. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:08:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Trips between Hengqin and Macao with multiple entry permission reached 120 thousand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/viagens-entre-hengqin-e-macau-com-autorizacao-de-entradas-multiplas-chegou-aos-120-mil/</link><description>A year after the entry into force of the multi -entry tourist authorization policy between Hengqin and Macau, the number of trips between the two places with multiple entry authorization reached 120,000, growing from a monthly average of around 4,000 to 2024 to over 20,000 in 2025, according to data from Hengqin border post revealed by the People's Diary online.
In May 2024, as part of the efforts to enrich the “Macau+Hengqin” transfronhetic tourist itinerary and meet the diverse tourist needs, the National Immigration Administration decided to implement the Hengqin-Macau group tourism policy, allowing multiple departures and entrances between Hengqin and Macao for the interior of China in at least groups in at least groups in at least groups in at least groups in at least groups Two people for a seven -day period.
The deputy director of the Hengqin Border Post, Zeng Xiang, reported that 86% of travelers using multiple group authorization from Hengqin-Macau entries visited Macau twice or more during the shelf life.
"It's more convenient with Hengqin-Macau group excursions. I can organize my trip comfortably days before without worrying about the number of round trip," a nickname woman, Weng, said, who was traveling with a group of friends.
According to the statistics, more than 50 travel agencies obtained the qualification of hengqin-Macau group excursions and organized a total of 11,000 groups. The number of authorizations issued for group excursions increased from a monthly average of more than 1,000 in 2024 to more than 5,000 in 2025, showing a monthly growth trend.
Su Kun, vice-director of the executive committee of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, said the zone will work with the Macao government to integrate the cultural and tourist resources of Hengqin and Macau with a multi-delayed itinerary tourism model and to make a series of incentive programs in order to promote transionic trips. Hengqin-Macau as one of the popular choices among tourists.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:09:11</pubDate></item><item><title>China announces changes in monetary policy to support economy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/china-anuncia-alteracoes-na-politica-monetaria-para-apoiar-economia/</link><description>China yesterday announced changes in monetary policy to cushion the impact of the US -triggered trade war at a time when Beijing and Washington prepares to resume negotiations in Geneva.
 
The governor of Banco Popular da China, Pan Gongsheng, revealed a cut in the rate of reverse repurchase operations from 1.5% to 1.4%, as well as a 0.25% reduction in commercial bank loan rate, setting it by 1.5%. The mandatory reserve rate was also reduced by 0.5%, releasing about one billion from Yuan (121 billion euros) in additional liquidity.
The Central Bank also reduced interest rate interest rates for five years, as part of a broader effort to stimulate domestic consumption.
The measures arise in a context of economic slowdown, aggravated by the impact of US tariffs, which reach 145% on most Chinese products. The Chinese economy, strongly dependent on exports, already faced a prolonged crisis in the real estate sector.
In response, Beijing applied up to 125% tariffs on US goods and suspended most US agricultural purchases.
On Tuesday, both countries announced conversations between US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, Commerce Representative Jamieson Greer and Chinese vice-minister, he Lifeng. The meeting will take place in Geneva later this week.
Negotiations take place at a time when the two parties continue to publicly reject any concession in tariffs. Analyst Stephen Innes of the asset manager SPI Asset Management warned that the conversations "may be the point of turning to the fragile confidence or rekindles the hell of the trade war."
The tension has shaken the two largest economies in the world.
The US economy contracted 0.3% in the first quarter, while China registered an annual growth of 5.4%, driven by temporary acceleration in industrial production. However, analysts question data reliability and point to a drop in orders for export and business sentiment.
The announcement of the new measures and the diplomatic advance boosted the markets: the bags rose more than 2%in Hong Kong, and 0.5%in Shanghai. The future Americans also recorded gains. But analysts keep caution. "A euphoric reaction is not expected," said Tan Jing Yi of Japanese bank Mizuho Bank. "Any resolution will probably be time consuming. In the short term, there may only be punctual reductions of tariffs on certain products," he said.
China's top scholarships yesterday opened with gains, following the announcement of a new package of measures by Beijing to boost economic recovery, pressured by the tariffs imposed by the United States. During the morning session, the Shanghai rate advanced 0.59% and Shenzhen's rose 0.22%. In Hong Kong, the Hang Seng reference index rose 0.79%.
Also Beijing Scholarship, inaugurated in 2021 and with less expression because it was centered on small and medium enterprises, operated on positive land, with an appreciation of 0.48%.
 
Chinese companies can resist the US trade war
 
The Chinese regulator of securities markets has ensured yesterday that quoted companies in China have resilience and ability to make adjustments to the impact of additional tariffs recently imposed by the United States.
At a press conference, the chairman of China's Value Regulatory Committee, Wu Qing, said the Chinese economy “is a large ocean, not a small lake”, stressing that 90% of the revenues of companies listed in mainland China markets come from the domestic market. "Since the US imposed fares in 2018, at the beginning of the trade war during Donald Trump's first term, Chinese companies have adjusted their production capacity abroad and opened new markets, progressing in building a more diverse export base," he explained.
Recognizing that customs tariffs have created domestic pressures, Wu argued that Chinese bags are undervalued and reiterated their confidence in "stable evolution" and increasing their attractiveness despite "global uncertainties." "The abusive use of tariffs had a serious impact on the world economy and commercial order. Quoted companies were affected, directly or indirectly, with more or less significant effects," he noted.
Wu also indicated that the Chinese authorities have performed “extended preparations” to respond to “external disturbances” and that in recent weeks have supported hundreds of companies affected by US commercial measures.
At the same press conference, the director of the National Administration of Financial Regulation, Li Yunze, announced plans for banking and insurer sectors to expand the support for exporters impaired by the tariff war by reinforcing credit and aid in the transition to the domestic market.
According to analysts of the Goldman Sachs bank, cited by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper, US tariffs-which now reach 145% in certain products-will be able to endanger up to 16 million jobs in China.
The most vulnerable sectors, due to their dependence on the US market, are telecommunications equipment, textiles and chemicals.
Despite the adverse scenario, Wu has reaffirmed confidence in the potential of internal demand and the perspectives of Chinese companies, pointing out areas of growth the sectors of artificial intelligence and semiconductors. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:08:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Al says detained journalists disturbed work. Newspaper considers that accusations are biased</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/al-diz-que-jornalistas-detidas-perturbaram-trabalhos-jornal-considera-que-acusacoes-sao-tendenciosas/</link><description>The arrest of two journalists at the door of the Legislative Assembly (AL) happened almost a month ago, but only now did the agency comment on the situation. In a statement issued on Tuesday night, AL says the two All About Macao journalists “severely” dismissed the plenary meetings, “shouting and pushing” the security guards. All About Macau considers the accusations "biased."
 
On April 17, when the Secretary for Administration and Justice presented the lines of governing action (LAG) of his protection in the Legislative Assembly (AL), two journalists of All About Macau publication were detained after being prevented from entering the plenary room to make the journalistic coverage of the session. This Tuesday night, AL issued a statement about the situation, indicating that the journalists in question did not comply with the rules and disturbed the work.
In recent months, authorities have repeatedly prevented All About Macau professionals and some international agencies from accessing official events to make news coverage. In that session, the journalists concerned will have tried to ask for explanations of the reasons why they were prevented from entering the hemiciclo and agents of the Public Security Police (CPSP) detained them on suspicion of “disturbance of the operation of macao special administrative region”.
In the statement, AL says that “to ensure effective meetings”, he adopted “reasonable measures regarding assistance to meetings by journalists from the media and the public”. “As there was a great influx of journalists from the media and“ since the space for interviews, as well as the places available in the Plenary Room are limited, ”Al restricted journalists' access to the Plenary Room for these journalists, referring them to the auditorium.
“Regrettably,” says All About Macau journalists “did not comply with these measures” at the plenary meetings of April 14, 15 and 17. Al accuses the professionals of screaming and pushing the security guards, "which severely disturbed the order of the operation of plenary meetings." Thus, "to cease the situation and to avoid its aggravation," the people of Al call the police on April 17, "in order to ensure the effective continuation of the plenary."
In conclusion, AL argues that “it has given great importance to the public information of the public about the work done, and it respects the legitimate right of the media and journalists to make interviews and reports”. However, "this right must be exercised within the limits established by law." "As for acts that severely disturb the normal functioning of the Legislative Assembly, it adopts, under the law, the appropriate measures to repress them," says the statement, reiterating that the al "regrets and condemns the above acts of journalists in a publication."
 
“Biased” accusations
 
All About Macau later announced a statement saying that the allegations of the al are "biased." According to the publication, in the presentation of the LAG of the administration and justice folder, the al "ignored" the press law and the regiment of the legislature and "used pretexts to continually obstruct the normal news coverage by All About Macau journalists", which "led to the first time in the history of Macau, a journalist was taken by the police for investigation, or even confronted with a criminal case."
Stressing that the journalists intended only to stay in the hemiciclo to cover the sessions of AL and not disturb the operation of the organ, the All About Macau deeply regrets the situation and says it will no longer make comments, since the case has already entered the court proceedings.
This situation originated several criticisms. The Macao Journalists Association (AJM), for example, questioned the “unjustified exclusion” of “local monthly magazines and online media” - such as All About Macau - the coverage of official events that “frequently involve” members of the authorities. In a statement issued after the arrest of journalists, the association says that these “discriminatory practices have been based by the social communication office with“ justifications that they do not convince ” - such as the limitation of space.
Also the Society of European Journalists and Communication Professionals in Asia (JOCPA) vehemently condemned the detention of the two journalists of All About Macau, stressing that the situation represents "a serious threat to freedom of the press and the right to information in Macao."
 
Macao Lawyers Association in Silence on Detention
 
At the presentation of the lawyer's activities for this year, the Macao Association of Macao Association (AAM) were asked about the arrest of All About Macau journalists and the arrest of a man who was on May 1. However, AAM declined to comment. Oriana Inácio Pun, secretary general of the Association's Board, said only that, as the situation was outside the scope of that press conference, it would not be appropriate to answer.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:05:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian space agency provides for a manned flight by 2027</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/agencia-espacial-indiana-preve-realizar-voo-tripulado-ate-2027/</link><description>The India Space Agency announced yesterday that it plans to launch an unmanned orbital mission later this year, before its first crew flight in early 2027. "This represents the rise of India as a global spatial power," said Jitendra Singh, Minister of India Science and Technology, quoted in a statement.
Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced his intention to send a man to the moon by 2040. "The gaganyaan unmanned orbital mission is scheduled to be launched later this year. Recovery tests have already been performed with the Indian Navy and new sea recovery simulations are planned," said the Ministry of Space, also in a statement.
Along with more testing, this will allow the Indian Space Research Organization to send astronauts to the space. “These milestones will culminate in India's first human space flight in 2027, with the launch of Indian orbit astronauts aboard an Indian Indian rocket from Indian soil,” read the note.
The Isro said the space flight is scheduled for the “first trimester” of 2027.
The most populous country in the world has shown its space ambitions in the last decade, with a spatial program that has grown considerably and has gained impetus.
"Astronaut training is also constantly progressing," said the Indian government. "Four Indian Air Force riders, selected as designated astronauts, have completed their training in Russia and are undergoing more specific mission training in India," he added.
India equaled the achievements of the great powers at a much lower cost.
In August 2023, he became the fourth nation to land an unmanned spacecraft on the moon after Russia, the United States and China.
Indian astronaut Shubhanshu Shukla, 39, has a scheduled launch for the International Space Station in May, becoming the first Indian astronaut to do so and the second in orbit.
The mission, held together by NASA and Isro, will be launched from the Kennedy Space Center in Florida. Shukla, which is expected to pilot the Axiom 4 mission, is among the main candidates for the Isro's space flight program.
Shukla's trip to space will take place 40 years after the iconic flight of Indian Rakesh Sharma aboard a Russian spacecraft in 1984.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:10:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump admits that after all he hasn't spoken to China about tariffs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/trump-admite-que-afinal-ainda-nao-falou-com-a-china-sobre-tarifas/</link><description>The president of the United States admitted yesterday that he has not yet met with China to discuss tariffs, despite having said the opposite in recent weeks, explaining that the meetings will take place "at the appropriate time." "They want to negotiate, they want to have a meeting, and we'll gather with them at the appropriate time. I didn't meet them," said Donald Trump at the beginning of the Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carnery in the White House oval room.
In recent weeks, the US government has announced that it has kept contacts with Beijing about the tariffs that Trump wants to impose globally, and the president himself said he spoke to Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, something Beijing denied and Washington did not clarify later. "Their economy is suffering a lot because they do not sell with the US, and most of the money comes from the US. Don't be fooled. Don't profit from other countries like this," Trump added, referring to China.
The US leader argued that he is addressing tariff negotiations with different countries with a “friendly attitude”, but insisted that the main concern is to protect the interests of the citizens it represents.
"Think of us as a super luxury store, a store that has the products you are going to buy and pay. We will offer a very good price. Let's make big business and, in some cases, make adjustments, but that's how it works," said Trump. "We could sign 25 contracts right now if we wanted to. But they are the ones who have to sign the agreements with us. They want a slice of our market. We don't want a slice of theirs. We don't worry about their market," added the US President.
Trump recalled that Washington "is flexible" and "at some point, in some cases," he will sign some agreements, but stressed that while he wants to help other nations, he will not accept that US commerce is impaired. "In some cases we say that we want to open the country. In other, we want to reduce tariffs. For example, India has one of the highest fares in the world. We will not tolerate it, and they have agreed to reduce it. They have already agreed with it. They would never have done it by anyone but me," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:08:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese analysts highlight strategic value of the relationship with Russia before the visit of XI</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/08/analistas-chineses-destacam-valor-estrategico-da-relacao-com-russia-antes-da-visita-de-xi/</link><description>Chinese analysts have considered that the approach to Russia is strategically beneficial to China, given the growing pressure exerted by Washington over the Asian country, the eve of Chinese President Xi Jinping to visit Moscow.
 
On Friday, Xi will watch the great military parade in Red Square to mark the 80th anniversary of the victory over Germany Nazi. Chinese soldiers will participate in the parade, despite Ukraine's warnings, which considers any foreign participation as “support for the Russian aggressor”.
Russian President Vladimir Putin, and Xi will also make two joint statements, one on bilateral relations and one about “global strategic stability,” Kremlin Diplomatic Counselor Yuri Ushakov said on Tuesday.
In an article published by a Russian newspaper, Xi Jinping greeted “the resilience” of relations between Beijing and Moscow. "Both sides must jointly reject any attempt to disturb or undermine friendship and mutual trust between China and Russia," he noted.
Beijing refused to condemn Russia for the invasion of Ukraine and criticized the imposition of sanctions against Moscow. The Asian country has provided important political, diplomatic and economic support to Russia. Last year, bilateral trade registered a record value of $ 245 billion (215 billion euros).
Zhao Huasheng, professor at the Center for Russian Studies and Central Asia at Fudan University in Shanghai, justified the political option with the “growing strategic pressure” that China is feeling in the Taiwan Strait and the Southern Sea of ​​China. “Good sino-Russian relationships can ensure that China has a stable strategic rear,” wrote Zhao in a rehearsal, noting that the “huge benefits” of the relationship seem to be irrelevant in peacetime, but would be “very important” in the case of conflict with the abroad.
Territorial claims about Taiwan and the Southern Sea of ​​China raised tensions between Beijing and almost every neighboring countries from Japan to the Philippines. China's growing assertiveness in the Indo-Pacific has already led to the formation of regional partnerships led by the United States, including the ASA group or the Aukus security pact.
Maintaining good relationships with Moscow is thus seen by China's foreign policy experts as a way to ensure stability on the earth's border with Russia, over 4,300 kilometers long, and stable energy supply. This allows Beijing to concentrate resources in the coastal areas and surrounding seas, where the United States maintain several military bases in allied countries, analysts agreed.
China wants to assert itself as the main power in East Asia and dilute the American geostrategic domain in the region. The reunification of Taiwan, located between the Southern Sea of ​​China and the Sea of ​​East China, at the center of the so -called “First Chain of Islands”, is a primordial goal in the Chinese project. "If the [Chinese] continent is one day forced to gather [Taiwan] by military means, China would then find an extremely difficult and complex international environment," Zhao wrote.
The trade war triggered by US President Donald Trump, against Beijing, is also likely to bring even more Beijing and Moscow closer.
Chinese analysts highlighted Russia's role in the internationalization of the Chinese currency, Yuan, and looking for a credible alternative to Western transfronistic payment systems. "China and Russia are" half of the sky "for safety and development of each other," said Wang Xiaoquan, expert at the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences.
In a documentary about the 25th anniversary of the climb to power, broadcast on Sunday, Putin also stressed the “strategic character” of the partnership with Beijing. "Our national interests coincide," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 01:08:37</pubDate></item></channel></rss>