<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/cracias-e-outras-ias/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>XI JINPING greets deepening the confidence between China and Russia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/xi-jinping-sauda-aprofundamento-da-confianca-entre-china-e-russia/</link><description>Xi Jinping yesterday greeted the deepening of trust between China and Russia, at the beginning of the Kremlin meeting with Russian homologous, Vladimir Putin in Moscow. XI stressed that "in the face of the international tendency of unilateralism and hegemonic intimidation behavior, China will work with Russia to assume the special responsibilities of the main world powers."
 
Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday greeted the deepening of confidence between China and Russia at the beginning of the Kremlin meeting with Russian homologist Vladimir Putin in Moscow. "Mutual political trust between China and Russia is deepening and pragmatic cooperation ties are becoming stronger," said Chinese President, who is in Moscow for celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the Nazi Germany in World War II.
XI stressed that "in the face of the international tendency of unilateralism and hegemonic intimidation behavior, China will work with Russia to assume the special responsibilities of the main world powers." “I am very happy with this new meeting,” said Vladimir Putin at the beginning of the meeting with XI, broadcast live on Russian television.
The Russian leader expressed gratitude that Xi decided to attend, in Moscow, to the celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the victory over Germany Nazi, as had happened on the 70th birthday.
The Russian head of state recalled that the former Soviet Union (USSR) lost about 27 million people in the war, while in China the number of dead was 37 million, including soldiers and civilians.
Putin said a Chinese guard of honor will march in Red Square on Friday, integrated in the Military Parade, and promised to attend China's victory celebrations about Japan on September 3.
For Putin, the ties between Russia and China are “mutually beneficial” and do not oppose any third country.
The Russian head of state also said that the two countries intend to defend together the "historical truth" about World War II, with Putin to accuse the West of trying to distort. "Along with our Chinese friends, we firmly defend the historical truth, protect the memory of the events of war years and fight against the modern manifestations of neo -Nazism and militarism," Putin said.
According to the Russian presidency, leaders will hold meetings in small and large formats and adopt two joint statements.
The first document will focus on deepening the comprehensive partnership between the two countries and the second in global strategic security. Xi will also participate in a reception and concert offered by Putin to the leaders present in these celebrations.
 
New agreement for promoting and protection of investments
 
Vladimir Putin has announced the signing of a new investment promotion and protection agreement under negotiations with Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping.
At the opening of a Kremlin meeting, Putin estimated the amount of investment projects treated by the intergovernmental commission estimated by more than $ 200 billion.
It also expressed the conviction that this agreement will contribute positively to the creation of a “more favorable” atmosphere and constitute “an important impetus” to the development of economic cooperation, the Russian leader said. In the port of Vladivostoque alone, in the Far East Russian, Chinese companies are involved in 63 joint projects, he said.
 
Putin stressed that the current trade, which rose to almost $ 245 billion (217 billion euros) last year, "is far" from the top limit to both countries.
He also ensured that Kremlin favorably welcomes the travel of the Asian country's car factories to the Russian territory. "Russia has become the first world importer of Chinese cars," he said.
Recognizing that energy is "the locomotive of relationships," Putin said that "last year Russia not only led oil exports to China, but also ranked first in gas supply."
The Russian head of state also announced new energy projects, such as the launch in 2027, of a Russian Far East pipeline that will supply Chinese consumers with 10 billion cubic meters of gas. Putin also stressed that the Russian agricultural sector is ready to increase exports to the Chinese market. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Pairing sessions will provide 61 more job offers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/sessoes-de-emparelhamento-vao-proporcionar-mais-61-ofertas-de-emprego/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), in collaboration with the Federation of the Macao Workers Association (Faom), will hold, on May 15, 16 and 19, three more job pairing sessions, providing 61 more offers. Registration for these sessions open today and take place until May 14th.
On May 15, in the morning and afternoon, the pairing session will be held for SJM Resorts, with 16 job offers for sales manager (conventions and business / banquets / leisure tourism), VIP service supervisor, restoration supervisor, counter employees, concierge, among others. This session will take place at Grand Lisboa Palace.
On the afternoon of May 16, at Hotel Okura, the pairing session will be held for Galaxy, with 25 job offers for western cuisine cuisine, head of team of western cuisine, restaurant operations, restoration services, mixologist, tea art technician, among others.
On the afternoon of May 19 will be held the pairing session for the Information Technology sector, having as participants the “Boardware Limited Information System”, “Kingdee Software Company (Macau), Limited” and “Macau Pass, S.A.”, with a total of 20 employment offers for Human Resources Manager, Deep Customer Customer Manager, Delivery Analyst, Delivery Analyst, expert software, salesperson, among others. This session will be at the headquarters of Dsal.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump refuses reduction before negotiations with Beijing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/trump-recusa-reducao-antes-de-negociacoes-com-pequim/</link><description>US President Donald Trump yesterday denied a reduction in 145% trade tariffs imposed on China as a way to facilitate negotiations for a deal with Beijing before the dialogue of both parties in Switzerland.
Asked if he would be open to reducing the rates on the eve of the meeting, Trump responded with a "no" rotund, during a press ceremony in the oval room of the White House of Oath of the new US ambassador in Beijing, David Perdue. "They need to prevent Fentanil from entering [in the United States]. This would be a very important condition," Trump justified, referring to the demands that Washington will make the weekend in Geneva for a future agreement.
Trump denied Beijing's statement that the beginning of the dialogue in Geneva will be made at the request of the United States. "They said we were the ones who started [the rapprochement]? Well, I think they should retreat and take a look at their files," he said.
The US Treasury Secretary and Chinese vice-minister He Lifeng will meet in Switzerland in the coming days, both parties announced on Tuesday, following the reciprocal imposition of high customs tariffs. "I hope productive discussions aimed at rebalancing the international economic system to better serve the interests of the United States," said US Secretary of State Scott Bessent in a statement before his trip.
Since Donald Trump began his trade war in early April, the United States have imposed 145% tariffs on Chinese products, and the Asian giant has accounted for rates up to 125% on US imports.
China announced last week that it was evaluating a proposal presented by the United States to start negotiations on the fares imposed by both countries on its products.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:31</pubDate></item><item><title>The name of the baby and the Chinese culture</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/o-nome-do-bebe-e-a-cultura-chinesa/</link><description>The choice of name is a very significant practice in Chinese culture since the characters that make up the names have added a symbolic meaning.
Although the new generations are more flexible with regard to local norms, customs and traditions, the choice of a good name is of utmost importance and responsibility, being considered and analyzed several factors because it is believed that this decision will determine the future of the child. The Chinese name should be a harmonious combination of elements and equilibrium of "yin" and "yang". Unlike Western culture, in Chinese culture the nickname precedes the proper name. As a rule Chinese names consist of two unique characters (the nickname and the name), but in aggregates numerous proper names can be composed, and the rule dictates that the maximum of four characters should never be exceeded. It is quite common to see names of brothers with a character in common. According to tradition, the name of the new family member is chosen by grandparents, often determined by phonology or its meaning. However, it is not uncommon to be consulted masters of “Feng Shui” to assist in the process of analysis and choice of name. Thus, the need for compensation for any imbalances that the child may have in his spiritual constitution is guaranteed, especially the harmony between the five elements: water, fire, earth, wood and metal.
Given that the date of birth (day, month and year) define the characters of the five basic elements used in the characterization of a person, it is essential that the name includes the possible missing elements. Therefore, in example, if the characters of the date of birth of the new family member do not contemplate the water element, the balance will appear in the name through a character such as river, lake, sea or rain. If it lacks metal then the chosen character may be gold, silver, iron or steel.
It is not surprising to use the proper name of important historical figures or famous personalities, expecting the child to inherit the characteristics of the person concerned. As with Western culture, sometimes the chosen name aims to honor ancestors, maintaining a connection with the family lineage and showing respect for ancestors.
It is in a ritual of love, designed in a picture of meanings, that the choice of name becomes a bridge between the past and the future, between heaven and the earth, nourishing the baby with the wisdom and legacy of those who came before it. That said, the Chinese names are more than mere words; They are living testimonies of affection, hope, balance and continuity, intertwining the fate of the new member with the stability of the elements, the richness of their lineage and an unshakable faith in humanity.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputy asks for reinforcement of the measures of control of youth obesity</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/deputado-pede-reforco-das-medidas-de-controlo-da-obesidade-juvenil/</link><description>Deputy Zheng Anting asks the government to present reinforced measures for prevention and control of youth obesity, a problem that has assumed increasingly expressive contours in Macao.
 
In a written interpellation sent to the government, the deputy begins by indicating that the rate of overweight and obesity in Macao has already reached 21.7%, a slight increase of 0.5% compared to the data obtained in 2017. Also according to government data, it is found that the rate of obesity of students of the first year of primary education reached 9.1%-ie almost one in ten children in this group.
Prevention and control of obesity is a priority in the region of Macao and throughout China, the deputy says, and several initiatives were boosted to increase a healthy lifestyle. In Macao, specifically, the work of prevention and tracking of diseases within the “Healthy Macau” program have been fruit of the physical condition and the average life expectancy of the population, which increased 0.24% last year.
On the other hand, it notes Zheng Anting, "the overall level of children's physical condition (including age -age) and adolescents decreased." In addition to a greater difficulty in understanding the importance of adopting healthy habits, compared to adults, the deputy points out factors such as lack of exercise, an unbalanced diet, “increasing school load and generalization of electronic products” as the main responsible for this threat to the healthy development of young people.
After this exhibition note, the deputy presents three interpeairs to the government. The first is the need to “implement a weight management action and organize adequate health courses for adolescents in different age groups, so that they know the scientific and correct forms of control and weight loss”. Intervention measures should be especially reinforced with obese students, defends, by providing assistance at various levels, including psychological.
In a second point, Zheng Anting questions the government about the situation of the “Healthy School” plan, which aims to promote healthy diet in Macao schools. “The government will consider increasing the proportion of content on weight control in that plan, with a view to further elevating health awareness and the management capacity of teaching and students?”, He interrogates.
Finally, and in view of the fact that the children are the reflection of the adults surrounding them, the deputy suggests the creation of lectures for education, so that, together with the school, help students “do weight management and create good life habits”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:01:32</pubDate></item><item><title>“Satellite casinos”: game over</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/casinos-satelite-game-over/</link><description>The final thrust on the “satellite casinos” as entities that share casinos' recipes, discharged by the executive head in the presentation of the government lines for the year 2025, was inevitable and no one surprised anyone.
The legislator of the changes of 2022 to the legislation of the game established a period of grace of three years (which ends on December 31, 2025) to allow, in a “smooth” way, the closure of “satellite” or the regaining of their current owners, entities that share revenues of casinos to (meras) casin-managing societies, with only a fixed remuneration for management, or fixed remuneration, or That is, not susceptible to indexing to any metric, namely performance, and, in particular, by express legal determination, to the revenues of the casino. In addition, it conditioned the government's action in the matter by eliminating the “safeguard clauses” that allowed it to follow different path without asking potatoes from the Legislative Assembly, to extend the period of free, to allow the “satellite casinos” to continue to share recipes of casinos.
It was in this context that the Chief Executive reaffirmed the legally established period of grace.
Excluding, probably, the six “game machine rooms” operated by the mocha (which fit the definition of casinos under the law of the game), the eventual closure of the other eleven “satellite casinos”-Landmark, GrandView, Kam Pek Paradise, Royal House, Fortune, Emperor Palace, Pier 16, Le Royal Arc and Legend Palace on the orbit From SJM, Waldo on the orb of Galaxy and Grand Dragon in Melco's trajectory - it is not a social drama as some intend to make believe.
First, because all employees associated with these casinos are (or should be!) Of the game dealers in which they orbit, which ready and easily will absorb them, integrating them into their operations.
Secondly, because associated hotel (and commercial) enterprises will continue to operate (such as those who have continued the seven “satellite casinos” that closed doors in 2022) and developing, benefiting from the limited hotel offer that Macau has been sick for over two decades.
In addition, it is expected that the owners of these enterprises, mostly, if not all, linked to the entities quoted in the stock exchange, fulfill their responsibility to act socially responsibly. For decades they have explored Macao's main economic activity, which has been granted large profits and access to significant funds lifting through the bag.
On the other hand, the closure of the “satellite casinos” or conversion to mere casino-managers' societies brings no harm to the world. On the contrary, since it is the solution that truly be in line with the legislation of the game as a whole, especially with the principle of public tender, according to which only the entities to whom it has been awarded, through public tender, a concession for the exploration of casino -gambling or lucky games and, consequently, making their recipes generated by casinos.
From a strictly economic point of view, and in particular in the current economic cycle, in which it has been realized that the future will not be laughing in the game of gross revenue of the game, it is not uncovered what interest may be the game concessionaires have in casino management contracts. Will there be a game concessionaire willing to pay a remuneration - as low as it may be - to a third entity that you do not need to ensure the management of a casino and will probably not be able to control? Better yet, which concessionaire will want to enter a management contract whereby, in addition to operating expenses, will you still have to bear the remuneration of the management society?
From the point of view of the Casino -managing society, accepting to be the main beneficiary of the casino revenues to merely to provide management services in contrast to a fixed remuneration, without any connection to the casino revenues, it seems at least strange.
In addition, considering the legal limitation of 6,000 gaming tables that can be explored in Macao casinos, what an economic interest can have the legal model of casino management when game dealers can transfer to their casinos (approximately 400) gaming tables attributed to “satellite casinos” and, with their closure, also benefit from a potential increase in players flow in their casinos? And what interest can there be in the business of the "satellite" that is in a decline due largely to the "disappearance" of the game promoters and has no guaranteed viability? Finally, what do you say any questions of suitability of the management society that can be repercussions on the suitability of the game concessionaire and endanger the concession for the exploitation of casino gaming or bad luck?
Establishing a parallel, the interest in the instituted model is equivalent to the interest demonstrated in the past by the figure of game management companies (eliminated in the 2022 changes to game legislation), ie none!
Some "satellite casinos" have already expressed the intention to operate as casino management societies. In this scenario, the Macao government should not be than a watchful viewer, merely approving the casino management contracts presented by the game concessionaires interested in hiring management societies.
Now, if it is acquired that, with some (little) legal engineering, it is possible to “shuffle and give again”, ie, reappoint the “satellite casinos” to the new legal costume keeping everything in the same, you need to be careful. Nothing is more devastating to a jurisdiction of game than boasting a regulatory system according to the best international standards that, in practice, proves artificial and ineffective due to regulatory failure. Only continuous and firm commitment to supervision and control of regulatory compliance ensures that the game industry is maintained in the highest standards to protect players, maintain the operation of tight and honest games, and defend the integrity of the regulatory system.
Contrary to Caesar's wife, it is not enough to seem to seem, you need to be.
 
António Lobo Vilela
Lawyer and author of the book “Macau Gaming Law”
(www.macaugaminglaw.com)
 
This article was originally published in English in the May 2025 issue of Macau Business magazine (with the title “Satellite Casinos:’ Game Over ”).</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Early treatment vacancies for children increase to 500 this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/vagas-de-tratamento-precoce-para-criancas-aumentam-para-500-ainda-este-ano/</link><description>Children with developmental disorders in Macau will have to wait about three weeks to access the first consultation at the Pediatric Joint Evaluation Center. Health services ensure that they have made an effort to reduce waiting time for medical treatment, adding that the number of vacancies in the early intervention service will increase to 500 later this year, with a new equipment with 44 service vacancies.
 
The territory will be reinforced in terms of equipment providing early intervention services later this year, with 44 service vacancies, which will increase the total number of service vacancies to about 500. The authorities recalled that, between 2021 and 2024, they added more than 200 service vacancies for children with development under three years old, through the creation or change of equipment.
Health services, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Che Sai Wang, addressed the work of early childhood intervention, advancing that the waiting time at the CACP joint Evaluation Center (CACP) is about three weeks. After the first consultation at this center, the waiting mechanism for classification to perform occupational therapy and speech therapy for children with needs will be adopted.
In this sense, cases classified as “very urgent” need not wait, and in “urgent” cases and “common” cases, the waiting time for occupational therapy is three to six weeks, for speech therapy is five to six weeks, “which is significantly shorter than the waiting time between 12 and 18 months before CCP creation”, they said.
"Health services have been striving to further reduce waiting time for medical treatment, through the extension of opening hours, and the acquisition of early intervention services to non-profit institutions," said Alvis Lo, Director of Health Services, in response.
Admitting that early childhood intervention is a “prolonged and continuous process” of rehabilitation, the person in charge indicated that it is up to health services to provide the children's evaluation and diagnosis and elaborate a medical treatment program with a total of eight sessions. Upon completion of this treatment, children with later treatment needs will be submitted to treatment and rehabilitation training by the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) or IAS in subsidized early intervention institutions until they have significant improvements.
Deputy Che Sai Wang, in his question, criticized the imbalance of resources for speech therapy services, which is the “most common” disorder among the various forms of children's development difficulties. "If these children, with delays in speech development, are not treated properly in timely time, it is likely that they will then have a problem of dyslexia, affecting their ability in long -term studies and social adaptation," said the legislator.
In this way, the authorities said they also introduced the “cloud platform for the training of artificial intelligence language rehabilitation” as an effective complement to speech therapy services, with which children can receive home training in the company of their parents to increase their linguistic abilities.
According to the government, this system with artificial intelligence technology is already being used in several early intervention institutions for children, having “enough vacancies” to provide services to children. Health services indicate that the system can offer 200 vacancies for professionals and 3,000 vacancies for child rehab treatment and, by the end of last year, provided 44,000 services to 1,878 children.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:02:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Return of the House of Dancing Water: a new era for the city of dreams</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/retorno-do-house-of-dancing-water-uma-nova-era-para-a-cidade-dos-sonhos/</link><description>Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho


After five years of silence and waiting, magic returns to the waters: the show “House of Dancing Water” is reborn more stunning, innovative and vibrant, but keeps its original line. Since its inception in 2009, this world icon has turned water, light and movement into a unique experience, and now, with a new vision and cutting -edge technology, reaffirms its place as the largest aquatic circus show on the planet.
 
Five years of erased lights and empty cisterns come to an end. A long chapter of uncertainty and dryness ends. Emotions emerge again and the astonishment to echo the eight floors of a building built for a single purpose: to create inspiring memories through the art of the water circus. Today officially inaugurates the first show open to the public of the most impressive resident entertainment production of the territory, the "House of Dancing Water".
To the city of dreams, the dream was lacking. The 1,985 dusty seats of a masterful theater that was in a forced hiatus after an unpredictable pandemic that led to the inevitable abandonment of an old team of almost 250 technicians and artists in the infamous year 2020. But to which many were forgotten, the opportunity gave them to flowing ideas from other heads. Recreated for current tastes and a renewed audience, which was already 15 years of history of a multicultural romantic narrative on water, received the hands of experts from around the world, in an interdepartal collaboration that culminated in the introduction of a new company, Our Legacy Creations, or OLC. About a year before this relaunch, the team, headed by François Girard, director-general, and Anna Robb, executive producer, starred in what seemed to be an impossible endeavor. Lawrence Ho left the OLC creative opinion of this recent seem to reinvent what already looked like an intact project.
With new performative elements and improved aesthetics, the visual quality of the show reemed the dimness of a dated and analog technology, to get excited at the top of the lighting, projection and music range (even without live band). The new experience brings to the public refreshed and confident air, with glimpse of an iconic but current past in its renewed content. The "House of Dancing Water" returns with a weight of something that intends to stay, perhaps, for another 15 years.
 
A transmuted legacy for the future
 
In 2009, the original “The House of Dancing Water” came up as an idea of ​​the visionary director Franco-Belga Franco Dragone, one of the founders of Cirque du Soleil, in collaboration with the entertainment giant Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, after the success of “O”, the first modern circus to involve large pools to function as a central stage in Las Vegas. Allied to the infinite tourism current that flooded the New Macao of Entertainment, for 10 consecutive years, one of the most successful artistic and technological productions on the planet, winning millions of viewers from around the world, almost always full of home. Now, this global icon, which has projected this type of project on the map, returns more grand, innovative and exciting, even more after so many memories of its apex.  He reaffirms his statute as the largest aquatic show on the planet and an inexhaustible source of inspiration for theater and art lovers.
The House of Dancing Water (without “The”) was born from a bold vision: transforming water, element of life and movement into the absolute protagonist of the stage. Conceived especially for City of Dreams, which dedicated a major fraction of its complex to the great cement block that would host the theater. With a monstrous pool that can contain up to 10 million liters of water - more than five Olympic pools - it acts as a liquid stage, sometimes invisible. A work of art in itself, an arena where water dances, explodes, and becomes narrative elements that raise public experience to dream levels.
Since its debut in 2009, the show has been a masterful combination of acrobatics, dance, special effects and engaging narrative, which mixes the poetry of the aquatic ballet with acrobat adrenaline, motocross pilots and world -renowned artists, on a established base of the modern circus. Each night, more than 2,000 people-including 80 artists from different countries-come together to create a moment of magic, so pertinent to the city of dreams.
The 2025 debut marks a new chapter in this saga of innovation. Under the artistic direction of Giuliano Peparini, the show was replaced and recreated about the existing skeleton, with renewed scenarios, advanced visual effects, new choreography and a more engaging narrative. The stage of the new House of Dancing Water, now equipped with state -of -the -art technology, allows rapid transformations that lead viewers to underwater worlds, enchanted forests, or futuristic scenarios, all at the rhythm of music and light effects and state -of -the -art projections.
The show maintains its essence of spectacularity, but now with a new dimension of emotional and visual depth through modernity. However, still in the classic such familiar style of the modern circus of entertainment, something that has not changed. The effects of water, created by the Aquatique Show team, continue to surprise. Water jets synchronized with music, columns of water that rise to 20 meters, arches that surround the stage and a romantic rain that creates a dream atmosphere. All this, coupled with the choreography of acrobats that dive, jump and slide to stupid speeds.
 
New elements and spaces
 
The return of the show features new characters, including the charismatic Sailor, who adds humor and lightness to the narrative, balancing the moments of tension with doses of fun, while following the passionate protagonist. The costumes, designed by Valentina Davoli, stand out for the richness of details, modern textures and impactful silhouettes, reflecting an aesthetic that mixes glamor, fantasy and innovation, with a touch of contemporary.
Given a newly instant Prison tank where the main character female character is introduced brings a sensation from the former nineteenth-century scupologist shows, while other new acts also appear in this story, such as the introduction of the magical garden. The former Tanzanian acrobat team has been replaced by something more local. A softened transition to the famous motorcycle act causes everything to be concluded in a cohesive way.
The soundtrack, now reinforced by a completely recorded and digitally added orchestra, provides the emotional and engaging atmosphere of the well -known original version, following every moment of tension, surprise or tenderness.
Other acts forms moved to modify the timeline. With the famous 'high-dives', diving at heights, still completing, but this time for one of the central acts that were moved to the end, the spectacular giant swings. The new production team comes this time to the 300 elements, including artists and technicians, from 30 different countries, many Olympic athletes.
This time, for those who want a closer experience, ticket options range from places in the Golden Circle audience, with access to the free impact and drink zone, to VVIP boxes, which offer a luxury and exclusivity experience, with encounters with personalized artists and services. Prices range from 698 Patacas and impressive 38,000 Patacas for the upper rooms.
The revitalization of the House of Dancing Water stands out as a return to normality for those who already knew this circus dream so well, a conclusion to a night period (in good English theatrical nomenclature, which makes sense to vacation periods or renewals of classic theaters), but especially materializes an opportunity to reinforce the connection between Macau with the rest of the high-level entertainment world. This show symbolizes the potential of an innovative cultural industry that contains in itself the power to promote international artistic exchanges.
Finally, the return of the House of Dancing Water Macao is proof that with vision, talent and innovation, it is possible to make something almost forgotten reborn. This show not only celebrates art and engineering together, but it also represents a pertinent collective artistic intervention on the human ability to dream, to overcome physical limits and to create magic with water, light, sound and movement. The story of love, intrigue and courage that unfolds on stage is a universal metaphor for multiculturality and resilience, values ​​that resonate deeply in any culture, especially in Macao.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macao and France sign an agreement to implement a joint scientific research program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/macau-e-franca-assinam-acordo-para-implementar-programa-conjunto-de-investigacao-cientifica/</link><description>Macao and France signed a deal yesterday about the implementation of a joint scientific research program. The agreement was signed by Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, representing the Government of MSAR, and Christile Drulhe, French consul general in Hong Kong. In the speech given at the time, Tai Kin IP underlined the importance of the agreement, saying that this is "a historical moment."
The Secretary for Economics and Finance has pointed out that the MSar has "adopted an active approach and is fully promoting the development of science and technology." "Efforts will be made to promote and develop Macao's new productive productive forces, focusing on the promotion of scientific and technological innovation, adopting multiple coordinated measures to promote the integration of industry, universities and research," said the ruler.
Tai Kin IP recalled that, two weeks ago, he headed a delegation that moved to Paris to study the concepts of development and the operational models of the scientific and technological parks of that region, as well as the incubation and establishment of starting companies, and to look for future cooperation opportunities. "I was deeply impressed by the development of scientific and technological innovation in France," he said in the speech, adding that this cooperation agreement "is an important opportunity for complementarity and mutual benefit."
The agreement now signed “will not only inject a strong impetus in Macao's scientific and technological innovation, helping Macau play a more prominent role in the scientific and technological corridor between Guangzhou-Shenzhen-Hong Kong-Macau, promoting the development of properly diversified economy, as well as deepening exchanges and cooperation between China and France in the domain and technology and technology and technology and cooperation It will contribute to the advancement of innovative progress, ”concluded Tai Kin IP.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:01:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Legoland will open in July largest theme park in the world in Shanghai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/legoland-vai-abrir-em-julho-maior-parque-tematico-do-mundo-em-xangai/</link><description>The Danish brand LEGO, which specializes in building blocks, will open its largest theme park in the world in East China next July 5, yesterday, local press advanced. The complex, about 52 kilometers southwest of the city center, will feature more than 75 attractions and shows distributed by eight distinct zones, including thousands of figures built with about 85 million lego pieces. Visitors will also be able to watch Lego movies in a 4D movie theater as well as lodge in a 250-room themed hotel, decorated according to five different environments inspired by this universe of recognized toy on the global scale.
Currently, the park is in the final phase of construction: the main entrance is completed and the main 24 attractions are practically ready. About a thousand employees will integrate the team since the opening. The highlight of the park will be the “Miniland” zone, a recreation, built fully with Lego blocks - with a total weight of 45 tons - some of Shanghai's most emblematic areas, as well as other China's cultural and tourist icons. Among the expected shows, we highlight the first show of the world dedicated to the LEGO “Monkie Kid” series, inspired by the Chinese West Day's classic King.
Legoland Shanghai has already started selling season passes and tickets for exclusive visits, including stays at the themed hotel. "We know this market well and we are enthusiastic about its potential. This complex will be a reference and meeting point for all Lego fans in China," said Fiona Eastwood, executive director of Merlin Entertainments, the British group responsible for managing Legoland parks. According to the company, more than 55 million people live two hours - or less - by car the location of the new park. It is recalled that Shanghai inaugurated in 2016 the first Disneyland park in mainland China-after the opening of Hong Kong Park in 2005-and is already planned for 2027 the opening of a new thematic complex dedicated to the Harry Potter film universe.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Installation of video surveillance systems in day care centers from the third quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/instalacao-de-sistemas-de-videovigilancia-nas-creches-a-partir-do-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS) has already prepared the provisions and guidelines on the use and management of the video surveillance system in day care centers, exclusively in resting rooms and areas of activities. The government expects to implement the regime from the third quarter and day care centers must request the authorization to IAS before the installation of the devices.
 
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) expects to implement, from the third quarter, the scheme related to the installation of the day care centers video surveillance system in order to reinforce the protection of children's safety.
The body revealed that it has completed the elaboration of the provisions and guidelines on the use and management of the day care centers, exclusively in resting rooms and areas of activities, taking into account the opinion of the cabinet for personal data protection (GPDP). He stressed that the measure will help day care centers to “reinforce the protection of the security of children who attend these child care institutions”, “more objectively evaluate the services provided in day care” and “clarify, when necessary, the factual circumstances of accidents involving children.
In a press release released on Wednesday, IAS advanced that at the end of last month a clarification session was held with the day care centers sector, presenting the scheme of 49 subsidized and non-subsidized day care centers and 12 management entities, with a total of 86 participants.
According to the IAS explanation, day care centers interested in participating in the video surveillance regime (in rest rooms and areas of activities) should submit a request for authorization from IAS and, after approval of the body, will have to advance the system in the respective spaces according to IAS approved video recording agreements.
Local day care centers may present relevant suggestions to IAS by electronic mail by the 23rd of this month so that it can improve the scheme and formulate subsequent provisions for implementation.
It is recalled that the child care service in day care centers caused concerns in society after a four-month-old baby's death case in October 2023. The smallest had a purple face and had no reaction after a nap at Taipa's Fong Chong day care center, having been sent to the Conde de São Januário hospital center where he was declared dead. The family reported that the daughter was in good health, but lost vital signs before arriving at the hospital, and the judicial police investigated the situation and concluded that no criminal element was linked to the case. The day care center closed doors in late 2023, under the decision of the institution itself.
At that time, the child's parents filed a petition with more than eight thousand signatures to the government, asking for the permission of the installation of cameras in day care centers, and the GPDP gave green light in the same year to the installation of the video surveillance system in these institutions, but only in public areas, in order to find a balance between the security of life and the rights of personal data.
IAS had also stated that it has continually reviewed the situation related to the proportion of day care workers, to safeguard the well-being of children who were delivered to the care of day care centers. It stressed that IAS requires that the day care room should have childhood educator, childhood educator and child caregiver assistant, and regarding day care centers, they are also required to have a health care assistant, but meeting the operability needs may additionally doctors or nurses.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:04:36</pubDate></item><item><title>The new objectives and the governance capacity of Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/os-novos-objectivos-e-a-capacidade-governativa-de-macau/</link><description>The latest events show that the Macao government, under the leadership of the chief executive Sam Hou Fai, has already defined new governing objectives; However, the achievement of all these new objectives will depend on the content of the Public Function reform, in which the definition of objectives, the workplace formation and the performance evaluation will probably be the decisive factors for Macao's government capacity.
On April 27, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, attended a press conference with about 100 journalists from Beijing, Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. The press conference was entitled to “opportunities to meet Macao”, having made some important observations.
First, the Macao Fivenote Plan should take the golden opportunity for the process of deepening central government reforms. As such, Macau must use its uniqueness and geographical strengths to position itself as a platform, base and crucial center to diversify its economy and carry out four main projects.
Secondly, the four projects include an investment of 20 billion patacas for the construction of the university campuses in the deepened cooperation zone with Hengqin, where the University of Macau campus is under construction, and represents the first attempt to build university campuses. The International Education Pole in the in -depth cooperation zone will be built in several phases. In the long run, the International Education Center will help to cultivate more highly qualified talents for the development of the leisure and tourism industry.
The second project consists of promoting Macao as an international tourist and cultural district, fully using the geographical space between the Macau Peninsula and Taipa Island, and building the Macao Museum and Cultural Center, the Macao International Center for Performative Arts and the International Contemporary Arts Center. All of these projects will have as its main elements Chinese culture and history, with the integration of Eastern and Western cultures of Macao. All of these projects will require an investment of 12 billion patacas and the contests will be launched over the next two to three years.
The third project will be the expansion of Macao International Airport, where land recovery will be made, with an investment of 6 billion patacas. International airport equipment will be improved, including launch and landing areas. The main idea is to transform the international airport into a crucial platform and a traffic point to the western part of the Rio das Pearl Delta, linking it to Zhuhai International Airport, so that the two airports complement and supplement mutually in the improvement of their logistics supply chains, the development of transphronic e-commerce and the coordination of an efficient transport network.
The fourth project will be an effort for the research and development companies of the continent and foreign countries to establish their bases and branches in the deepened cooperation zone. The development model and its details will be defined later.
Thirdly, Sam Hou Fai, at his press conference, said that to reinforce the macao government's ability to carry out all these projects and objectives, six coordination committees were created - one aspect that had already mentioned in his recent political discourse. He also pointed out that the Macao government will strengthen its government capacity to improve the investment and business environment, and to promote all infrastructure projects in the deepened cooperation zone. In this way Macao will be more fully integrated into the Great Bay and the continent in his search for economic diversification.
Executive head Sam Hou Fai is undoubtedly an action leader. Between April 27 and 28, he led an employee delegation to visit Zhuhai, Zhongshan and Jiangmen, stressing the way the three cities on the continent can help Macau, while underlining Macau can and will help them more turned abroad through their strong networks with Portuguese-speaking countries. In Zhuhai, Sam visited artificial intelligence companies and placed the tonic in cultural and tourist cooperation. In Zhongshan, its emphasis went on the development of trade, cooperation in the biomedical and pharmaceutical industries and collaboration in cultural tourism and higher education. Sam was interested in exploring with Zhongshan how Chinese medicine will be co-produced by Macau and Zhongshan. In his last stop in Jiangmen, Sam Hou Fai wanted to explore how both cities can develop cultural and tourist industries, reinforce cooperation in the promotion of jiangmen maritime resources and stimulate municipal food industries. One thing was common on Sam Hou Fai to Zhuhai, Zhongshan and Jiangmen: Macao remains a crucial gateway to the three cities of the continent to achieve an advantageous situation for both parties regarding municipal cooperation in the domains of cultural tourism, food industry and commerce.
In analytical terms, the four projects outlined at the Sam Hou Fai press conference to journalists of mainland China, Hong Kong and Macau went beyond their political speech, namely the development of the International Higher Education Center in the deepened cooperation zone. The details related to the development phases are not yet clear and will have to be defined by the Macao government. In addition, the international and cultural tourism zone between the Macao Peninsula and Taipa Island will also have to be prepared, in addition to the need for capital and investment accumulation of the private sector.
While the expansion of Macao International Airport will have a more operational character, the attraction of research and development companies of the continent and other countries to parking their headquarters and install their branches in the in-depth cooperation zone will probably extend beyond the five-year plan of the Macao government. Thus, at least two of the four projects that outlined at the press conference will be a long -term venture.
The chief executive did not explain in detail how the government's ability will be reinforced, except for the reiteration of the six coordination committees. Unlike Hong Kong, where coordination work has been led and led by a group of Under -Secretaries, the Macao government has not yet created the positions of Under Secretaries. Under these circumstances, the six coordination and direction committees created by Sam Hou Fai are directed by himself, the chief secretary and other secretaries. However, taking into account the relatively reduced number of secretaries appointed by the chief executive, this coordination work seems to be quite heavy. If so, the high employees who run the various services must play a crucial role and assist in inter-service coordination, which is and will be necessary for the effective execution of policies. In the long run, if the Macao government intends to reinforce its governance capacity through stronger coordination, the creation of new Under Secretaries may be considered, like Hong Kong's governance model.
Macao's government's ability will also depend on the reforms of the civil service and its detailed content. The reforms of the civil service were implemented in Macao during the Portuguese regime and after December 20, 1999. Although all these reforms started with a project, the results were difficult to evaluate, mainly due to the ambiguity of the progress criteria of progress and the success of these reforms.
Thus, in the content of the upcoming civil service reforms, three questions will likely stand out as the most important criteria for measuring their progress and success.
Firstly, after the Chief Executive has stated all the objectives of governmental achievements, the governmental departments and agencies in question should ideally elaborate a calendar and key performance indicators about how these objectives will be achieved. Secondly, internal discussions will have to be promoted to the upper, middle and lower levels, so that civil servants of the various strata have a clear idea of ​​what they are expected to achieve. Thirdly, training in the workplace will have to be performed and reinforced so that different departments and civil servants at various levels understand how they can and should implement reforms and how objectives will be achieved. Fourthly, performance evaluation will have to be reformulated to correspond to the evaluation criteria to the objectives of the various departments and units. In this way, Macau's government capacity will be reinforced in large way.
In conclusion, the Macao government led by the chief executive Sam Hou Fai has created a freshness image in terms of new political ideas, new political initiatives, new infrastructure projects and new coordination between departments. His political will to implement a whole set of reforms is absolutely clear. The challenges that are placed are the way to reinforce the government's ability and minimize the execution deficit at the middle and lower levels of the civil service. As such, the reforms of the civil service will continue to be fundamental in the three fields of the definition of feasible objectives for the government departments and agencies concerned, the reinforcement of training and the workplace debates and the implementation of effective performance evaluations that associate their performance with objectives that are expected to achieve. Accompanying the content of civil service reforms will be the partnership between the public sector and the private sector, especially since private companies and corporations will be encouraged and encouraged to invest in a wide range of projects, especially those in the in -depth cooperation zone. If so, the public-private partnership will be another important cooperation area that requires stronger government leadership, better government planning, a constant dialogue between public and private domains and effective government control of projects managed by the private sector. Generally speaking, the reforms of the civil service and the public sector will be fundamental to the achievement of the objectives defined comprehensively by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar thanks Macao contribution to the promotion of health cooperation with China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/myanmar-agradece-contributo-de-macau-para-a-promocao-da-cooperacao-na-area-da-saude-com-a-china/</link><description>China's international emergency team (Macao) and high employees of the Myanmar Ministry of Health Department of Health held a exchange meeting on emergency medical techniques on Wednesday. At the time, Myanmar's team handed a letter of thanks to the Macao team, "recognizing their active contribution to promoting health cooperation between China and Myanmar."
During the meeting, China's international emergency team (Macau) presented the transmitted disease prevention and control system and the MSAR emergency response mechanism. The two parts focused on the discussion of the construction of the coordination capacity to respond to health emergencies, the optimization of the disease surveillance network in the community, the vocational training of rapid response teams, and the joint emergency response exercise mechanism.
According to the statement issued by health services, Myanmar's team “highly praised China's experience in building the basic health system and said this exchange provided an important reference for Myanmar to improve the Public Health Emergency Management System, expressed the desire to further deepen bilateral health cooperation”.
In addition, the Macao team and the World Health Organization (WHO) representation office in Myanmar also held a working meeting and WHO professionals “praised pragmatic cooperation between China and Myanmar in the emergency health area, stressing that this type of cooperation serves as an example and is very meaningful to raise the level of regional public health safety”.
This exchange “fully demonstrates the firm determination of China, as a great responsible power, in the continuation of the concept of 'community of future shared for humanity' and in its active participation in global health governance,” reads in the statement of the authorities of MGA, which concludes that “cooperation in health between China and Myanmar deemed the global strategic partnership between the two countries, but also demonstrated through, but also demonstrated through MSAR Single Platform, China's advanced experience in the field of public health and its role at the international level. ”</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:01:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy's profit registered an annual increase of 16% in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/lucro-da-galaxy-registou-subida-anual-de-16-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Between January and March, the Galaxy Entertainment Group registered profits before taxes, interest, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) of $ 3.3 billion from Hong Kong, which represents a 16% jump over the same period last year. Compared to the last quarter of 2024, the climb was 2%.
 
Galaxy Entertanment Group yesterday announced profits before taxes, interest, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) of $ 3.3 billion of Hong Kong in the first quarter of this year, which means a 16% growth compared to the same period of 2024. Comparing the figure with the last quarter of last year, the growth was 2%.
In the first three months of the year, the group generated revenues of $ 11.2 billion, which reflects an increase of 6% in annual terms. Still, revenues in the first quarter of this year fell 1% over the previous quarter.
Galaxy's press release cites Francis Lui, president of the group, which considers that the results of the first quarter were "solid". “During the quarter, we continued to boost all business segments, especially the premium segment, through our unparalleled products and services, the continuous improvement of properties, various shows and entertainment events, as well as the total implementation of intelligent gaming tables, among others,” says Francis Lui.
"We were pleased with the performance of our casinos during the Chinese New Year and, in particular, after the Chinese New Year, who lasted longer than earlier," says Galaxy President in the operator's statement.
Francis Lui also states that "despite the geopolitical turbulence and the continuation of economic slowdown, Macau's global market remained resilient." It is recalled that in the first quarter of this year, gross game revenues totaled 57.3 billion patacas, more 0.6% than in the same period of 2024. Also counting on April, global casinos revenues reached 75.8 billion, ie 0.8% more annually. Despite the growth, this is still short of government expectations, which provided for this year a monthly average of 20 billion patacas.
The group ensures that it will continue to bet on non-game elements, namely in leisure and entertainment facilities and events. Galaxy also pointed out that the 10th hotel in the Galaxy Complex, which is called Capella, opened this month and will be officially inaugurated soon. At the same time, the operator will continue to advance with the development of phase 3 and 4 of her resort. Internationally, the group indicated that it will explore markets like Thai.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Ron Lam asks for measures and transparency on the treatment of stray animals</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/ron-lam-pede-medidas-e-transparencia-sobre-tratamento-de-animais-vadios/</link><description>In a written interpellation sent to the government, Deputy Ron Lam expresses concern about the lack of effective policies to deal with the problem of stray dogs in Macau, increasingly expressive in recent years. In the same intervention, it also draws attention to the lack of transparency of statistical data from the Institute's page for Municipal Affairs (AMI), which after a recent update began to conceal the information prior to 2022.
 
Ron Lam asks the government to implement effective measures to reduce the number of stray animals in Macao and justify the increase in occasions in the Municipal Kennel of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI). In a written interpellation sent in April to the government, the deputy also emphasizes the lack of transparency of AMI statistical data, which from recent update have reassembled only in 2022.
In his intervention, Ron Lam begins to emphasize the growing number of stray dogs in various parts of the territory, including public roads and high road circulation on Taipa Island. According to statistics released by the AMI, and cited by the deputy in the interpetement, in 2024, 1,086 stray animals were captured, more 30% than the previous year and 65% more than in 2022. Under the program “Capture-E-Doptar” (CEA), dogs and cats captured are then made available for adoption if they do not exist potential adopting.
"Many animals were only adopted by animal protection associations, even with no room to welcome them, or adopted by people for fear of animals to be slaughtered," says Ron Lam, considering that the results of the program "were not satisfactory" in the response to the increasing proportion of stray animals. "This measure cannot reduce or control, by source, the increase in the number of stray animals," he criticizes, requiring the government to define "clear objectives and concrete policies."
The alternative would argue, the implementation of the pilot project of “capturing-being-to-go” (CED), which consists of the return of wild animals to its colonies after being sterilized and dewormed. “The government promised to restart the pilot project CED,” presented in 2022 without, however, being sketched plans for its realization. “When will this be done?” He asks.
At a second point of his questioning, the deputy exposes the changes made, recently, to the Electronic Page of AMI. The statistical data related to animal capture have been eliminated and now dating back only by 2022, “which prevents society from knowing and analyzing better” the evolution of the situation. Also the way data is classified has changed: the total number of captured animals now appears separated by the categories “with microchip” or “without microchip”, without indications regarding the species of animals. Finally, the categories of “adopted animals” and “claimed animals” were merged into a single group, making it impossible for “global analysis and objective evolution of the situation”.
"With a view to fulfilling the principle of transparency of information that the Government of MSAR has been emphasizing, AMI should again carry the full records of previous years and publish more statistical data from the past, and more completely, so that the public can know the current situation and the tendency of the evolution of animals in Macao," defends the deputy, thus ending the second topic of his interpellation.
At the last point addressed to the government, Ron Lam mentions the exponential increase of animals slaughtered in recent years, which nearly tripled between 2019 and 2024. The situation of dogs is particularly severe, representing about 72.3% of the 430 deaths induced by AMI last year. Remembering that, according to the Animal Protection Law, the slaughter of dogs and cats should only occur “in the last resort”, the deputy ends the interpellation by questioning the AMI about the fundamentals for the slaughter of the 119 cats and 311 dogs who died last year. Also, how many animals died of natural causes in the facilities of the Coloane Municipal Kennel, a statistic that is not on the body's page.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:03:33</pubDate></item><item><title>China ensures that it “strictly” controls export of double use goods</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/china-assegura-que-controla-rigorosamente-exportacao-de-bens-de-dupla-utilizacao/</link><description>China said yesterday that it “strictly controls” the export of double -use goods, in view of suspicions that Russia is using technological civil use devices for military purposes in Ukraine. "China applies strict controls on the export of double-use goods," said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian when asked reports that exported video games to Russia are being used to operate drones.
Lin Jian also denounced that any "normal technological cooperation" of China "becomes a problem" when there are attempts to "defame the country with unfounded accusations and political manipulation of bad faith." The spokesman has not clarified whether China is considering additional restrictions on technology exports, referring to the competent authorities.
The statements arose after Ukraine expressed concern about the involvement of Chinese companies and citizens in Russian military production, a formal complaint he filed to the Chinese ambassador in Kiev in April, claiming to have evidence.
This week, the European Commission said China "remains a key facilitator" of the Russian war effort and that without this "Moscow support could not continue war with the same strength."
Beijing argued that his position on conflict has been “consistent and clear” and is committed to “promoting ceasefire, disagreement and negotiations”, and guaranteed to have never provided lethal weapons “to neither party” involved in the war.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Man in critical condition after handling shrimp</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/homem-em-estado-critico-apos-manusear-camaroes/</link><description>A 65 -year -old local resident is in critical condition and breathing with the support of a fan after being infected with Vibro Vulnifus, health services said yesterday.
According to the authorities, on the afternoon of April 29, the man, who has antecedents of chronic diseases, was accidentally stung on his little finger his right hand as he handled shrimp at home. In the early hours of the 30th, swelling and pain came, which then spread to the palm of his right hand and right forearm. He resorted to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, having been diagnosed with necrotizing fascitis of the right upper limb with septic shock. After admission, it was treated and transferred to the intensive care unit. Last Wednesday, laboratory tests to their blood samples confirmed that they had vibro vulinifus.
Vibro Vulnifus is a bacteria that naturally live in hot water and infections can happen when one has open wounds exposed to seawater with Vibri Vulinificus or when he eats contaminated seafood. Infections caused by infection through wounds may be slight, but can also cause necrotizing fascitis, with manifestations of extreme pain, redness, swelling and rapid tissue necrosis. People with necrotizing fascitis may have to amputation to save their lives, and in about 20% to 30% of cases, the infection is fatal.
Health services explain that the consumption of shellfish contaminated by vibro vulinificus can cause diarrhea, vomiting and abdominal pain, and there is no generally serious consequences. However, if the infected person has other chronic diseases, namely liver diseases and diabetes, he may develop sepsis, with symptoms such as fever, chills, decreased blood pressure, appearance of bubbles on the skin and, in more severe cases, may result in death.
Thus, the authorities advise to avoid contact of wounds or damaged skin with marine water, clean well and make a proper wound dressing and wear gloves when handling raw seafood, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:01:30</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Philippines exchange accusations for incidents with Atoll in the Southern Sea of ​​China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/china-e-filipinas-trocam-acusacoes-por-incidentes-junto-a-atol-no-mar-do-sul-da-china/</link><description>China and Filipinas accused each other of “illegal entry” and “hazardous maneuvers” in the waters adjacent to the island of Huangyan, claimed by both countries. Manila and Beijing are involved in a territorial dispute over the sovereignty of various islands in this strategic region, with potential oil and gas reserves and where about 30% of world trade passes.
 
Chinese and Philippines authorities were mutually accused of “illegal entry” and “hazardous maneuvers” in the waters adjacent to Huangyan Island, claimed by both countries in the Southern Sea of ​​China.
According to the command of the South Theater of the Popular Liberation Army (Chinese Army), "the Filipina PS35 military frigate reached these waters without the authorization of the Chinese government." The Chinese Armed Forces have organized naval and air means to "follow, monitor, issue warnings and legally expel the ship, thus preventing it from entering Chinese territorial waters." "The operations were professional, justified and legal," said Command spokesman Tian Junli in a statement.
The Philippine Navy said it had detected “aggressive and risky maneuvers” from military ships and China's coastal guard near the atoll played.
A Chinese frigate “followed the unlocked” Filipino PS35 military ship, which was “performing legal and routine maritime patrol operations,” while another “crossed dangerously his bow,” said the Philippine forces in a statement.
The 5403 vessel of the Chinese Coast Guard “tried to obstruct” the PS35 navigation trajectory, read in the same note. "These reckless actions not only represented a direct threat to the safe navigation of the PS35, but also violated international regulations for the prevention of shocks at sea," the statement said. Huangyan is the Chinese name of the Scarborough Atoll, located in the waters of the Southern Sea of ​​China.
Manila and Beijing are involved in a territorial dispute over the sovereignty of various islands in this strategic region, with potential oil and gas reserves and where about 30% of world trade passes.
China, which has the largest sea fleet in the world, claims almost all of these waters for historical reasons, a claim that contradicts the positions of other countries in the region, such as Philippines, Malaysia, Vietnam, Brunei and Taiwan.
Manila and Beijing have a long history of maritime incidents, which have gotten worse in recent years. Chinese coastal guard ships used water cannons against Philippine boats on several occasions in disputed waters, where there were also records of ships, injuring several Philippine soldiers. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Cambodia wants entry later this year of Timor-Leste in Asian organization</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/camboja-quer-entrada-ainda-este-ano-de-timor-leste-em-organizacao-asiatica/</link><description>The president of the Senate of Cambodia defended yesterday that Timor-Leste should enter the Association of Southeast Asian nations (Asean) later this year and that the missing obligations can be fulfilled after full membership.
 
"The royal government of Cambodia and I personally continue to mobilize the support of Asean's other Member States to admit Timor-Leste as a full-right member," said Hun Sen, who began an official visit to Dili in an intervention in the Timorese Parliament.
Hun also considered that Timor-Leste “deserves to become the 11th member of Asean” and that “remaining obligations related to instrument adherence” can be implemented after official membership as a full member.
"We believe that Timor-Leste should not be left out. This was the desire of Asean's founding parents, who wanted to unite all the states of Southeast Asia under the same umbrella of Asean," he said.
The president of the Cambodia Senate, number two of the state hierarchy, also said that he has publicly stated that the full adherence of Timor-Leste should not be postponed and that the "waiting period of more than 10 years was already long enough." "I sincerely hope that this year Timor-Leste officially joins the Asean family," added Hun Sen in the intervention of relations between the two countries and the request for adhesion of Timor-Leste to the organization.
The president of the Timorese Parliament, Fernanda Lay, stressed that Cambodia is an “influential voice of Asean”, which promotes cooperation and stability, and thanked the “invaluable” support for the candidacy for Timor-Leste. "The President has been one of the main defenders of Timorese Integration and this support has been fundamental in our course," he added.
ASEAN's Member States reached an agreement of principle in November 2022 to integrate Timor-Leste in the regional organization, becoming the country to have the status of observer and being able to attend all meetings, including in summons.
The presidency and the Timorese Government decided to point out the year 2025 for the fulfillment of full adhesion, taking into account the fulfillment of a script, which requires the establishment of agrees and diplomatic missions, construction of infrastructure and preparation of human resources, among others.
ASEAN was created in 1967 by Singapore, Indonesia, Thailand, Malaysia and Philippines and aims to promote cooperation between the Member States to ensure peace, stability and economic, social and cultural development of the region. Brunei Darussalam, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar and Vietnam are also part of ASEAN.
The president of the Senate of Cambodia was gathered yesterday with the Timorese President, José Ramos-Horta, and the Prime Minister, Xanana Gusmão.
On Friday, it will be awarded the Timorese Presidency with the Order of Timor-Leste and will give, in the same place, the lecture "The Lessons of Hun Sen: Genocide and Poverty to Freedom and Prosperity." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:53</pubDate></item><item><title>-Cracia and other -ias</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/09/cracias-e-outras-ias/</link><description>It's been a couple of years ago-it is better not to tell how many!-When the author of this text was still cattle, it is perfectly remembered to see Álvaro Cunhal on Portuguese television to classify Gorbachev's reforms 'danger to democracy in Use', as he used to refer to the USSR. This comment came about the attempted coup of state perpetrated by the KGB summit in 1991 and which became known as the August coup. It was by these times that, with the fall of the iron curtain, we were finally able to glimpse the reality of the red paradise, which to be so good, everyone wanted to escape from him.
For Cunhal, who would rather live in Paris than in Moscow, the Soviet Union regime was a democracy; A popular democracy would specify the communists at the time. However, many things have changed in Russia, especially the ownership of the goods that once were from the state, but the idea of ​​democracy, it remains the same, albeit in different inactors.
Although words like democracy, tyranny, and others that such, be part of our daily vocabulary we are not always chords in relation to the semantic burden they have. Less common is to know what its origin is and the historical context in which these terms arose, although this knowledge could bring some light to the meaning of these words.
 
Democracy
Democracy was born in the polis, or city-state of Athens around the 5th century BC. Until then, Athens had been ruled first by kings and then by aristocrats.
At the end of the seventh century BC, popular dissatisfaction in the face of the severe social and economic crisis that was then threatened to lead the city to a civil war. Given the imminent danger of a popular revolt in 594 BC, Solon (638 - 558 BC) was appointed Archon, a kind of high magistrate, with full legislative powers. Solon then implemented a series of reforms whose purpose was first to reduce the power of the aristocracy and allow the greater participation of citizens in the government of the polis. In this context, one of its most significant reforms was to open Eclésia, an advisory body with legislative powers, to all citizens and not only to the members of the aristocracy as until then was the case. In addition, Solon restructured society in classes based on economic power and not on the social, noble or commoner, individuals, and prohibited the reduction to slavery as a way of payment of debt.
Solon was also responsible for the creation of the Heliea or the Popular Court, which allowed all the citizens of the polis access to justice.
Solon tried to balance the interests of the aristocracy and the common people, and although their reforms did not solve all Athens' problems, they were fundamental to the later development of democracy.
Around 508 BC, Clistenes, considered the 'father of democracy', came to power in Athens. This would consolidate many of Solon's reforms and introduce new reforms that would finally lead Athens to become the first democracy in history.
Clistenes converted Eclésia to the central play of the Athenian political regime. Eclésia became the legislative body par excellence in which all citizens could participate, proposing and voting laws. Eclésia thus became a kind of parliament, but with a big difference from modern parliaments. The members of the Legislative Assembly or Eclésia were not elected, since Athenian democracy was a direct democracy, that is, each self -and -male not only had a seat in the Assembly, but was, in fact, to be present, whenever the Eclésia was summoned.
In an attempt similar to Solon's to level the population of the polis leaving behind the traditional social divisions based on blood and wealth, Clístnes reorganized society in ten tribes based on the geographical distribution of the population. Each of these tribes sent fifty representatives to the Boulê, or Council of the 500, which Clístnes reformed. This council was the executive branch of Athens, and its function is to prepare the work of Eclésia and perform its decisions.
Thus Athens already had, at least embryonic, the tripartition of powers, the Executive Power resided in Boulê, the Legislature in Eclésia and the judicial in Helieia.
The word democracy that reads out there means the power of the people in fact refers to dominion or strength, in Greek –kratia, our-Craccia, of the ten districts or demo-demos-that the polis of Athens was divided by clisthens. With the time and because of the word democracy itself and what it came to represent, the word we gave in Greek came to identify with the elements that populated the demo, that is, the people. As for the word –cracia, it is derived from the verb Kratéo, which in Greek means 'being strong' or 'having mastery'.
 
Dictatorship
Others, who not Cunhal, would say that the URSE regime was not a democracy, but a dictatorship, which, although it is a political regime that does not end in -ia, cannot pass without being mentioned.
The Estado Novo regime, which has never been undergoing a democracy, since Salazar has been, since his days of Coimbra, and without hiding it, antidemocrat, is also described by many as a dictatorship.
The Portuguese case of then was similar to that of Russia today, as both regimes were endowed with electoral mechanisms aimed at giving legitimacy to the system. However, these mechanisms, either they were designed to produce the desired results, as in the case of the Estado Novo, or are manipulated, as in the case of Putin Russia. The classic form of dictatorial regimes does not require elections, even though some have been implemented through electoral processes, as was the case with Hitler.
The dictatorship was born in Rome. This does not mean that dictators and dictatorship have not existed before and in other quadrants, but it is Rome that we owe the term dictator and part of the understanding we have from it.
Rome began to be a monarchy. Romulus, one of his founders, became the first king of Rome after killing his brother Remo. According to the mythological tradition, Romulus and Remo were twin brothers, children of Reia Silvia, a Vestal Virgin, and Mars, the God of War.
In all, Rome had seven kings, the last of which, Lucio Tarquínio, nicknamed O Superbo, was deposed in 509 BC, when Rome was then governed by the Senate and two consuls that were elected annually by the people of the patricians of the city. The Senate, who had at first 300 members, also had representatives of the people, they were the plebs tribunes, patricians who were elected to represent the interests of the people, and would eventually have the right to veto on Senate's decisions.
Rome's new constitutional system was designed to prevent power from focusing on the hands of a single man in perpetum. Still, the Roman Constitution provided for the figure of a dictator or dictator who, for a maximum period of six months, could assume power more or less absolutely, in cases of extreme crisis, such as the threat of invasion, revolts, riots, among other exceptional forms of political instability.
In 458 BC, the Aequi, a tribe that inhabited the mountainous region east of the Lazio, threatened to invade Rome. The Senate was then forced to name Cincinato, a former consul of the Republic, dictator with absolute powers for a period of up to six months. He was able to defeat the Aequi in just 16 days, having resigned as a dictator immediately.
During the exercise of the position, the dictator had absolute powers and was legally inviolable, that is, could not be processed or held responsible for his actions while occupying the position. However, once the mandate was renounced or expired, the dictator was again an ordinary citizen and could be tried for abuses of power, corruption, illegal executions or any other crime committed during the exercise of the dictatorship.
Unlike Cincinato, who moved to history as an example of civic virtue, Caesar was accumulating nominations as dictator after each other until what, in the end, led to his murder.
The first time Julius Caesar was appointed dictator was in 49 BC. After his campaign in Gaul, Caesar intended to present himself to the elections for Consul in Absentia, but the supporters of Pompey, who feared the increasing influence Caesar had, did not allow him and consequently threatened to enter Rome with his army. Pompey, who was then consul, along with his supporters, fled from Rome, and when the Senate's mandates expired, there was no one to replace them. Caesar was then appointed by his supporters in the Senate as a dictator to organize new sennarial elections. After eleven days, having been elected consul, Caesar resigned as dictator.
What followed was a civil war among Caesar's supporters, sometimes described as progressives, and the supporters of Pompey, which represented the most conservative wing of the Senate. In the end, as we all know, Caesar was winning, the troops of Pompey being defeated in Egypt and Pompey being killed to betrayal.
Back in Rome, in the year 48 BC, Caesar was appointed Consul and Tribune of the commoner for five years and dictator for a year. Its dictatorship was renewed annually until in February 44 BC, the Roman Senate granted Caesar the title of perpetual dictator, that is, a lifetime dictator. On March 15, 44 BC, the famous March IDUS, just over a month after being appointed Lifetime dictator, Julio César was murdered by many of his supporters in a special Senate session that had been summoned, not only to discuss state matters but also to pay tribute to Caesar, who had recently been appointed perpetual dictator. Upon entering the room, he was surrounded by about 60 conspirators, led by Bruto and Cassio, his longtime friends. It was stabbing 23 times, having covered the face with the toga before he died. According to tradition, he will have recognized his attackers, and seeing among them Brutus, who was like a son to him, have said to him: ET, Brute, Fili Mi? ‘Too you, gross, my son?’.
The reason for the murder perpetrated by many of his own supporters was the perception that Caesar had accumulated too much power and intended to make himself king, which offered the religious and civil conscience of the Romans.
The place where Julius Caesar was murdered, now located in Piazza Di Torre Argentina, was recently reopened to the public.
The Senate session in which Caesar was killed took place in a room attached to the Pompey Theater, as the Curia building, which still exists intact in the forum, was under construction. The original monumental doors of the Curia, made of copper, are today in the São João de Laterão Basilica. Since 1871, when the troops of Victor Emanuel de Saboia, king of Piemonte, have been able to break the wall and invade Rome, these doors have never been opened (not open for official ceremonies; they are opened from time to time for cleaning and maintenance).
The Latin term dictator, which gives our dictator, derives from the verb dictare, in Portuguese, dictate, which, in turn, is etymologically related to our verb to say, the Latin Dicere, and to the Greek Deíknumi 'demonstrate'. The idea is that the dictator dictates and what he dictates, is done without discussion and, much less, vote.
 
Tyranny
Near the dictatorship, but not necessarily the same thing is tyranny. This word, although inherited from the Greek, is not originally Greek. The word Tyrannos, which entered the Greek vocabulary around the 19th century. VII BC and from which we derive our term tyrant will most likely derive from an anatolous anatolia language, possibly the Lydio. It was imported to describe a form of ruler that was more proper to the east near the Hellenic Peninsula, namely rulers who seized power by force.
This word was overcoat used in Magna Graecia, that is, in the Greek colonies of southern Italy, especially in Sicily. The tyrant was someone who worked like a monarch, but whose power was forcibly obtained. In some cases, such as Dionysus II of Syracuse, the tyrant inherited the power of the Father, as if a hereditary monarchy was yet, was still called tyrant.
At first, the word tyrant served only to describe a kind of absolute power without any negative connotation being associated with the term, but as it is not difficult for absolute power to derive in what we now call tyranny, political action, and the behavior of many Greek tyrants have imprinted on the term the connotations it has today.
It was, by the way, to a Tyrannos, more precisely Dionysus I, the tyrant of Syracusa, who Plato tried to sell his theory of the king-philosopher. According to Plato, society will only be truly just when kings are philosophers or philosophers are kings. In the Republic, Plato describes the way a king must be educated in order to reach the status of king-philosopher.
Dionysus I, apparently, was not much turned there and Plato was eventually expelled from the court and, around 387 BC, was sold as a slave. It was thanks to his friend, Cyrene's Simicore, who bought him for about 30 mines (today, about € 300,000) that he could return to Athens. Twenty years later, in 367 BC, Plato again tried his luck, now with his son, Dionysus II, but the thing did not go well and Plato, once again, ended up in prison. Despite the outcome of this story, what she tells us is that for Plato a tyrant was not a type of ruler to avoid and, in principle, was not incompatible with the idea of ​​the righteous ruler that Plato describes in the Republic.
 
Oligarchy
Bernie Sanders, an independent senator for the state of Vermont and ancient competitor for the presidential candidacy of the United States, has been one of the few able to oppose Trump. Since Trump's presidency began to derail - what it didn't take long - Sanders has organized multipurpose demonstrations for all the United States under the aegis of Fighting Oligarchy.
The word oligarchy, this Greek origin, originally does not mean the government of the richest, but the government of the few. The second element of the word oligarchy, which, incidentally, is also part of the word monarchy, derives from the Greek verb arkho which means 'to be the first' or 'stopping power', while the Greek word lies, the first element of the phrase, means 'little'. Thus, etymologically, oligarchy refers to the power of the few, but who are they, the few, who hold power? Obviously, they are the richest; the holders of the great fortunes; In the American case, Musk, Zuckerberg and Bezos, although the latter begins to rebel. It is to these that Bernie Sanders refers when classifying the government of Trump by oligarchy, a government in the service of the few of the richest. As with the word tyranny, it is the use of the word that leads to the specification of its meaning.
Following the fall of the monarchy in Athens in the eighth century BC, power was concentrated in the hands of the most powerful aristocrats and Athens became an oligarchy. The oligarchies often lead to social revolt, revolution, or even civil war. It was exactly to avoid such a fate that Solon was given so much revenue in Athens.
The American case is interesting: How long will the American people tolerate a government that, besides oligarch, undemocratic and with little respect for the rule of law, is it, on top of that, incompetent?</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 03:09:25</pubDate></item></channel></rss>