<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/ipim-realizou-sete-accoes-de-formacao-no-sector-de-convencoes-e-exposicoes-ate-abril/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Earthquake of magnitude 5.5 sacode Myanmar after devastating earthquake that killed 3,600</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/terramoto-de-magnitude-55-sacode-myanmar-apos-sismo-devastador-que-matou-3-600/</link><description>A 5.5 magnitude earthquake yesterday shook the center of Myanmar, recorded the American geological service, at a time when the country suffered the consequences of the earthquake that killed more than 3,600 people in March.
The quake was recorded at 8:54 pm local time at a depth of 7.7 kilometers, according to the United States Geological Service (USGs), which measures seismic activity worldwide.
The epicenter of the earthquake was located about 100 kilometers south of Mandalay, the second city of Myanmar and one of the most affected by the March 28 earthquake.
So far, no new damage or victims have been recorded in the country, where thousands of people continue to sleep on the streets of the areas devastated by the March earthquake and thousands of buildings have been reduced to mountains of rubble.
The strong earthquake killed at least 3,600 people and seriously injured 5,017, according to the last balance of the military junta, which discusses logistics problems and aid shortage.
Following the March catastrophe, both the coup military and the main armed opposition and other ethnic guerrillas declared a temporary ceasefire to facilitate the distribution of humanitarian aid.
Despite the ceasefire declared by the military junta, the groups that oppose the regime denounced more than 60 air and artillery attacks following the earthquake.
International rescuer teams, including from countries such as United States and Japan, are participating in rescue efforts, with a second contingent of 37 experts highlighted yesterday to continue to remove the rubble and look for missing.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:41:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai today presents the lag with a forecast to reinforce patriotic education</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/sam-hou-fai-apresenta-hoje-as-lag-com-previsao-de-reforco-da-educacao-patriotica/</link><description>Academics provide for the defense of national security to remain one of the priorities for the present government. Jiang Chaoyang, a professor at the University of Macao, said that this year's LAG Lines of Government Action (LAG) should be established “more detailed provisions” for the institutional framework of national security. The Chief Executive will present LAG today, not expected to increase benefits from the current economic situation.
 
The Chief Executive will present today's LOC (LAG) lines today for this financial year. Regarding the first report of the lag of Sam Hou Fai in its mandate as the government leader, predictions indicate that social assistance policies may be similar as previous years, but that a reinforcement in the national security defense system and patriotic education should be given.
"The government has been implementing the principle of" Macau ruled by patriots "and it is expected that, based on its previous efforts on safeguarding national security, the executive takes more detailed measures, especially in the aspect of creating mechanism," said Jiang Chaoyang, director of the Center for Constitutional Law and the Basic Law of the University of Macao (one).
Also Cathedral Professor of Law also provides that the Government will “carry out the work of oath to acting and newly re-controlled civil servants, at all levels”, so as to “build a solid sociopolitical base” for the principle of Macao governed by patriots.
According to Jiang Chaoyang, in statements to the Chinese Channel of TDM, preparations for legislative elections will also represent a greater weight in this year's government work, which will “rigorously” the eligibility -verification mechanism for election candidates.
The university teacher considers that it is necessary for the government to improve the legal system related to national security, especially in the domains of political security, social security and economic security. “This year is expected to deepen the construction of educational materials on patriotism and education for national security, and enrich educational resources and activities for young people to love their country and macao, promoting and transmitting the fundamental values ​​of love to the country and Macao,” he said.
Chan Kin Pong, director of Kwong Tai Secondary School and researcher at South China Normal University, foresees more policies dedicated to the “transmission of patriotic values ​​to young people” this year after the launch of complementary teaching materials on national security education that encompasses teaching levels, from childhood garden to higher education.
The chief executive will be today at 3 pm in the Legislative Assembly to present the LAG, followed by the press conference at 5:30 pm at the government's headquarters. Tomorrow, at 3 pm, he goes to the plenary of the Legislative Assembly to answer the questions of the deputies. There will also be the sectoral debates of five secretaries, the lines of governing action in the Legislative Assembly on 17, 23, 25, 28 and 30 of the month.
In turn, a source from the newspaper or world predicts that the first report of the lag of sam Hou Fai will focus on “stability” and benefit measures will remain equal as previous years, as the global economic environment is uncertain. "According to information from the political sector, it is believed that there is a discrepancy between LAG and the highest expectations of the public regarding the population's well-being policies," the newspaper said, without advance the sources of information. He also added that a change in the form of distribution of pecuniary reimbursement is not foreseen by the absence of consensus in society.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:42:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Aipim wants to hold Lusophony journalists in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/aipim-quer-realizar-encontro-de-jornalistas-da-lusofonia-em-macau/</link><description>The Macao Press and English Press Association (AIPIM) held on Saturday the meeting of the General Assembly, where the financial year and the report of activities referring to 2024 was approved and the activities plan for 2025. José Miguel Incarnation, president of the AIPIM direction, said to the end that one of the objectives for this year passes the organization of a meeting of journalists from Portuguese -speaking countries.
"We intend to involve more of our Portuguese and English Communication sector, but especially in Portuguese in Lusophony, so it is being thought of - and has been spoken to the authorities - the holding of an event that can bring to Macau journalists from other Portuguese -speaking countries," said the association's president.
Compared to 2024, incarnation highlighted the growing number of members, which is now in 78. The Association's president also pointed out to the good relations of the local authorities, the Central Government connecting office on the MSAR and the Commissioner of the Foreign Ministry of the Popular Republic of China in the MSAR.
Finally, it is also highlighted to participate in initiatives held in Hong Kong or in the interior of China, such as the intensive course on the Popular Republic of China, which took place at the Fudan University in Shanghai in September last year. This initiative was attended by 12 journalists and other civil society guests.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:36:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.04.14</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/ponto-fatal-2025-04-14/</link><description>The Macao Press and English Press Association (AIPIM) held on Saturday the meeting of the General Assembly, where the financial year and the report of activities referring to 2024 was approved and the activities plan for 2025. José Miguel Incarnation, president of the AIPIM direction, said to the end that one of the objectives for this year passes the organization of a meeting of journalists from Portuguese -speaking countries.
"We intend to involve more of our Portuguese and English Communication sector, but especially in Portuguese in Lusophony, so it is being thought of - and has been spoken to the authorities - the holding of an event that can bring to Macau journalists from other Portuguese -speaking countries," said the association's president.
Compared to 2024, incarnation highlighted the growing number of members, which is now in 78. The Association's president also pointed out to the good relations of the local authorities, the Central Government connecting office on the MSAR and the Commissioner of the Foreign Ministry of the Popular Republic of China in the MSAR.
Finally, it is also highlighted to participate in initiatives held in Hong Kong or in the interior of China, such as the intensive course on the Popular Republic of China, which took place at the Fudan University in Shanghai in September last year. This initiative was attended by 12 journalists and other civil society guests.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:36:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese rate of 125% has entered into force on all US products</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/entrou-em-vigor-taxa-chinesa-de-125-sobre-todos-os-produtos-dos-eua/</link><description>Increasing tariffs on all products imported from the United States to China from 84% to 125% entered into force, with Beijing, with the policy of retaliating the rise in rates on Chinese goods.
 
Beijing's measure was announced on Friday by the Council of State Customs Committee (Chinese Executive), which justified it as a direct response to the latest tariffs approved by Washington, which raise the total rates applied to Chinese exports to 145%.
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce accused the US of following a policy of "coercive unilateralism" and called the recent offensive tariff "game of numbers without economic meaning."
In a turnaround, US President Donald Trump announced on Wednesday night a 90-day suspension of the so-called “reciprocal tariffs” imposed on the rest of the world, but kept and aggravated the rates imposed on China.
The White House clarified on Thursday that the total rate on Chinese products is 145%, as it had to be added the 20% tariff that had previously been imposed on China due to the Fentanil crisis.
A guerra comercial entre as duas maiores economias do mundo intensificou-se rapidamente, numa altura de grande volatilidade dos mercados. A China insiste que não quer uma guerra comercial, mas que “não tem medo de a enfrentar se necessário”.
The Chinese official press has pointed out in recent days that the Asian country has diversified export destinations in the last five years, so it is not as vulnerable to a trade war with the United States as it was during the first presidency of Trump (2017-2021).
CCTV state television recently highlighted the role of the Southeast Asia Nations Association (Asean), now China's largest commercial partner, and emerging countries in general, with which the country already carries out 60% of its trade.
China said Washington should "take all responsibility" for the world economic "turbulence." Following the tariff offensive of US President Donald Trump, who mainly punishes Beijing.
Customs announced by Washington caused “serious shocks and turmoil in the global economy, world markets and multilateral commercial system,” said a spokesman for the Chinese Ministry of Commerce. The United States must “take full responsibility,” he said.
China said the 90 -day break was partly due to Beijing's "pressure". "Under pressure from China and other parts, the United States temporarily suspended the imposition of high reciprocal tariffs on certain business partners," said the Ministry of Commerce spokesman.
 
Taiwan performed first negotiations on tariffs with USA
 
The Taiwan government has announced that it has held the first tariff negotiations with the United States and has new talks to establish “strong and stable” business relationships. Taiwanese government leader William Lai had stated the day before the island, which seeks to protect its exporters from a 32%tariff, was "on the first list of negotiations" by the US government.
Earlier this week, US President Donald Trump postponed for three months the punitive tariffs imposed on various business partners, including Taiwan, after the loss of dollar trillions in global markets. Trump kept the 10% global tariffs over most countries, but suspended higher tax plans on others except China.
In a statement, Taiwan's commercial negotiation office said its representatives made a video conferencing on Friday with “relevant US employees” without identifying them.
Representatives have exchanged points of view on reciprocal customs rights between Taiwan and the United States, non -tariff trade obstacles and a number of other economic and commercial issues, including export controls, ”says the statement.“ Both parties expect to conduct follow -up negotiations… in the near future and jointly build a strong and stable economic and commercial relationship. ”
Taiwan's commercial surplus with the US is the seventh seventh of all countries, having reached $ 73.9 billion by 2024.
About 60% of Taiwan exports to the US are information and communication technology products, including semiconductors. The semiconductors were exempt from the new rates imposed by Donald Trump.
Many Taiwanese were shocked by the range of tariffs, while the Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturer CO (TSMC) chip giant to invest another $ 100 billion in the US had raised hopes that the island could be spared.
 
Trump “remains optimistic” in trade agreement with China
 
US President Donald Trump, “remains optimistic” when the possibility of a trade agreement with China, the White House said. "The president has made it clear that he is very open to the issue of China," said US Presidency spokesman Karoline Leavitt at a press conference without advancing the reasons for Trump's optimism. The two powers are involved in a climb of the commercial duel started by the US president with the tariffs imposed on Chinese products. Earlier, Trump stated in his social network, Truth Social, that customs policy is "really working well." "Our customs rights policy is actually working well. It's exciting for America and the world. It's advanced quickly," he wrote, after China has announced the increase to 125% of customs to US products and after the United States has decided to apply a total of 145% to Chinese products. This statement of Trump arises at a time when the currency, debt, and US actions are under attack in the markets in a context of climbing commercial tension with China. The World Trade Organization said it predicts that this situation could cause a 3% break in world trade.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:41:29</pubDate></item><item><title>António Leong evokes a sensation of “Déjà Vu” with black-and-white photography exhibition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/antonio-leong-evoca-sensacao-de-deja-vu-com-exposicao-de-fotografia-a-preto-e-branco/</link><description>Creative Macau will show a compilation of photos of Macanese photographer António Leong between April 24 and May 12, with the aim of spoilting in the public memories of the “incidents, encounters and personal narratives” that populate the streets of Macau.
 
The Creative Macau Gallery - Center for Creative Industries will open a photographic exhibition entitled “Déjà Vu”, by artist António Leong, between 18:30 and 20:30 on April 24. Black-and-white photographs will continue to be available to the public until May 12, 2025, with free admission.
The exhibition of António Leong, a natural artist of Macau, aims to document the different narratives that coexist and interconnect in the territory. In a press release, the Creative Center reports that the work captures the phenomenon of “Déjà Vu” - a word that describes the feeling of familiarity by glimpsing or experienced something new - by crystallizing, with the click of the House, “ephemeral and stagnation” moments of Macao's essence, which can range from “intricate details of architectural to vibrant to people's daily interactions”.
Each photograph “acts as a portal” describes the organizing association, creating a mosaic of Macao's “past incidents, encounters and narratives” and evoking both feelings of nostalgia, by the familiarity of the portrayed scenarios, as well as “excitement for the discovery of the city”, reinterpreted by the photographer's optics.
“Each photograph of this collection captivated my attention for long periods, inspiring a deep sense of admiration and calm,” explained António Leong, quoted in the same note. "I am pleased to share the consolation they have provided me and sincerely hope that [the public] can also experience their greatness. The lines, shapes and silhouettes used intend to convey the transcendent nature of these themes in the context of our contemporary world."
According to a brief biographical note provided by the organization, António Leong "fell in love with many years ago", having started sharing photographs of his own on the social network Facebook in 2012. His page "Antonius Photoscript" is still used and often updated to this day, revealing particular interest in the dichotomy between Chinese and Western cultures in Macau.
Over the years, the artist has participated in various photographic exhibitions that want to promote tourism in Macao around the world, as well as cooperating with charity organizations and sharing their techniques and experience in this area as an instructor and speaker.  He has collaborated twice with the Macao Cultural Catholic Association, in the “Discoving Everyday Beauty” photographic exhibitions (or “discovering the beauty of daily life”) in 2021, and “Via Pulchritudinis: Macao's Chatolic World Heritage” (or “The Way of Beauty: Macao Catholic Heritage”) in 2024.
He is also a winner of several photography awards, including first place in the “Open Group” category of the Architecture Photography Contest promoted by Curb - Center for Architecture and Urbanism in 2024.
Creative Macau is a project developed by the Institute of Portuguese Studies of Macao, with the aim of supporting creative industries of twelve different areas: architecture, visual arts, show arts, crafts, cinema and video, software and computers development, design, authority, music, advertising and software and computers development.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China may force US operators to sell casinos in Macau, says analyst</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/china-pode-obrigar-operadoras-dos-eua-a-vender-casinos-em-macau-diz-analista/</link><description>An analyst of the game said China could force US operators to sell casinos in Macao in retaliation if Washington Force the sale of Tiktok and ports on the Panama channel.
 
Game consultant Igamix founder Ben Lee expressed fear on the impact of “current friction” between China and the United States due to the Tiktok video platform and the ports operated by the Hong Kong Ck Hutchison group in Panama.
"If China adopts the same retaliation strategy it has been employing," the possibility of US gaming companies being forced to sell operations in Macao to Chinese entrepreneurs "go up some levels," Ben Lee said. "I think after the US threatening to remove Chinese stocks from the bags," everything is on the table, "added the Igamix analyst.
On Wednesday, Scott Bessent, in an interview with Fox Business broadcaster, refused to remove the possibility of forcing Chinese companies to abandon the United States bags: "This decision will be from President Trump."
Creditsights' executive director Nicholas Chen recalled Lusa that new concessions can be terminated “by threat to national or Macao's special administrative security.” Or “reasons of public interest”.
"However, what would constitute such a threat was not explicitly defined by the authorities," said Creditsights expert, who is part of the Fitch Financial Notation Agency group. "We have not seen any nomination, to date, that the governments of Macao or China will be aiming at US -based Macao game operators for national security reasons," Chen added.
On the other hand, he admitted to being worrying in February in Macao as a "foreign opponent" of the United States, imposing restrictions on investment by local companies.
Vitaly Umansky, an analyst at the Seaport Research Partners consultancy company, told Lusa being “very skeptical” about any risks to Macao. "There are much larger targets to hunt in China if China really wanted to score a position," said the expert.
Chinese authorities “have been after a variety of US companies in mainland China, who believe they are sensitive points for the Beijing government, especially technology and health,” he recalled.
Already Ben Lee believes that, instead of changing the terms of the concessions, the Macao government could introduce new laws “that restrict repatriation” or money transfers from local subsidiaries to mother companies in the United States.
Vitaly Umnsky doubts that this could happen, warning that Macau could lose the image as "a suitable environment for investments from abroad entrepreneurs."
On Thursday, an economist at the University of Macao said the trade war could have an impact on companies' investment plans.
In 2023, when the new concessions came into force, the operators were committed to investing more than 100 billion patacas in game-related elements. "I believe investors around the world will be willing to change their investment goals in the context of such high tariffs," said Kwan Fung.
Vitaly Umansky is sure that the operators “will invest everything they have promised,” but admitted that there is doubts about “when it will be invested and what”. "There have been numerous obstacles. The [Macao] government has been slow in project approval and has not made available more land to be developed," he lamented. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:39:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Infringements to the regime of smoking control with annual rise of almost 23%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/infraccoes-ao-regime-de-controlo-do-tabagismo-com-subida-anual-de-quase-23/</link><description>In the first quarter of this year, the authorities registered 1,370 infringements to the smoking prevention and control regime, which reveals an increase of almost 23% compared to the 1,115 offenses detected in the same period last year. Regarding the prevention of alcohol consumption by minors, six offenses were recorded in the first quarter of this year, and in the same period last year there were zero transgressions of this genre.
 
Between January and March this year, the authorities registered a total of 1,370 infringements to the smoking prevention and control regime. Data released by health services show an increase by close to 23% compared to the same period of 2024, when 1,115 gender transgressions occurred.
Noting that over the first three months of 2025, 62,410 inspections were made, authorities detail that there were a total of 1,262 cases of illegal smoke, 71 cases of electronic cigarette transport for macao entry and exit, 31 suspected cases of violation of other laws in question, such as non -posting the prohibition of smoking in the places provided for in the law and not to state notice prohibition of sale of tobacco products to children under 18 in the places of sale.
Regarding the type of establishment with the largest number of cases of people to smoke in prohibited places, casinos were those that recorded, in total, 194 cases (15.4%), followed by restoration establishments, with 186 cases (14.7%) and stops of passenger transport vehicles, with 139 cases (11%). The Directorate of Inspection and Coordination of Games, in collaboration with health services, made 212 inspections to Macao Casinos, having detected 194 cases of people to smoke in forbidden places.
Regarding the regime of prevention and control of alcohol consumption by minors, six suspicious cases were recorded in the first quarter, three of which involved the sale or availability of alcohol to minors. The other three cases were related to various sales establishments or making alcoholic beverages available that did not afford the prohibition of sales or availability of alcoholic beverages to minors. In the first quarter of 2024, no violations of this regime had been registered.
It is recalled that the sale of tobacco products and alcohol to children under 18 is prohibited and, if in doubt as to the age of buyers, commercial establishments must request them to present an identification document. In case of refusal, it is assumed that the subject is smaller, and the sale of the product in question should be refused, and the offender is subject to a fine of 20,000 patacas.  On the other hand, the supply of alcoholic beverages for minors for non -commercial purposes is also a legal offense and may result in a fine of 1,500 to 20,000 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:36:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Association of journalists “seriously concerned” with restrictions imposed by the government</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/associacao-dos-jornalistas-seriamente-preocupada-com-restricoes-impostas-pelo-governo/</link><description>The Macao Journalists Association is “seriously concerned” with the government's opacity led by Sam Hou Fai. The association regrets the “significant reduction” of opportunities to interview or ask for clarification from the rulers. Macao's PORTUGUESE AND ENGLISH Press Association, for its part, prefers to wait to see the government's behavior.
 
Since the government of Sam Hou Fai has taken office, the Macao Journalists Association (AJM) has noticed a “growing number of official events held at the closed door”, resulting in a “significant reduction in opportunities for journalists to interview directly the chief executive, secretaries and other high employees”. In a statement sent yesterday to the newsrooms, AJM says it is “seriously concerned” about the situation.
"Once again, we exhort the Government of the Mishem to honor its promise of respect for freedom of the press," says the association, demanding dialogue with the public and the media, "for the community to have a better understanding of their politics and vision."
Several journalists have warned of this “abnormal standard” with regard to press provisions since the new administration has taken office. The AJM recalls that, "although the restrictions imposed by the Covid-19 pandemic have been raised for a long time and the normality has already been resumed in the lives of many people," several of the events in which the chief executive participated were not open to the press, as before. On other occasions, only social communication agencies were invited near the government, denounces the association. "This situation has no precedents in more than two decades of existence of MSAR," lament journalists.
In addition, "the government continues to refuse, irrationally, that local monthly magazines and online media will cover some kind of official events." For example, the All About Macau publication, which has a monthly frequency and an online version, is prevented from being present at events. The same has happened with international publications and agencies.
The Social Communication Office (GCS) has justified these decisions that there has been greater demand on the part of abroad media for news coverage of official events and, according to the authorities, the space in press conference rooms is not sufficient.
"These answers raise serious doubts about the integrity of employees and their understanding of the role of journalism, and reflect a lack of knowledge of international norms for an open government, eventually undermining the credibility and public image of the Mashely," AJM says.
The association speaks of a “systematic deterioration of press agreements organized by the authorities”, since these situations are not “isolated incidents or limited to certain media”.
The AJM also recalls that the chief executive indicated in January that the Macao Basic Law protects freedom of the press and that the government was willing to cooperate with the media sector. “AJM sincerely expects this shared aspiration to be realized,” reads the association's statement.
The Association reiterates that "journalists do not need speeches and press release, but appropriate provisions to hold reports on site, where journalists can hear the voices of all stakeholders, interact directly with the decision makers and clearly understand the logic and guidance of current public policies."
"AJM expects the government to maintain its commitment to the rule of law and to repose, as soon as possible, the agreements with the news coverage of the media, so as to prevent the right of the public from being informed to be continually imposed," the association concludes.
 
Wahoo does not have this perception
 
For its part, José Miguel Incarnation, president of the Macao Press in Portuguese and English Press Association, says that the association did not receive reports that allow to confirm this greater opacity of this government. “We neither have the opposite view nor we have the view that things are like this, we have not yet been made this idea. From what we have spoken, we do not have this perception,” he says in statements to the end.
Incarnation also pointed out that the wahoo expects that, after the presentation of the Governing Lines (LAG) - which happens today - the activity of journalists "be more cared for by the government".</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:40:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Association anticipates little GDP growth in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/associacao-anteve-pouco-crescimento-do-pib-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>The Macao Economic Association said that macroeconomic performance in the first quarter “could be slightly weaker than expected”, so gross domestic product (GDP) could be unchanged or register only one rise up to 0.6% over the same period last year.
According to economic forecasts released yesterday, the association said the calculation model projects a value of GDP until March 98.5 billion patacas and 104.5 billion patacas, which corresponds to a homologous actual growth rate of -2% to 3%. "Due to uncertainty and instability, the forecast of GDP for this whole year may only be similar to last year," he said.
The monthly analysis highlighted the “unbalanced and uncoordinated” situation in local economic indicators in recent months, and capital flow has marked a record, while prices of concessionaire actions and consumer and restoration confidence rates remain at a “weak” level.
The investigation team also lowered the forecast of Macao's prosperity rate to the second quarter, from a classification of 6.4 to 6 points, from a scale from 0 to ten. Despite a low review, economic perspectives remain at a “stable” level.
The association's pessimism came mainly from the tariff policies recently imposed by the United States and China, which add factors of world economic instability.
"The 'trade war' will aggravate the uncertainty of Macau's economy. Although global economic perspectives in the first quarter of this year have been stable and favorable, the new unexpected situation is quite special and can exert some pressure on the stable functioning of China's economy," he noted.
The association led by economist and former deputy Joey Lao warns that Macau is not "immune" to risks, and carefully study the future situation and make preparations to deal with various challenges. "
On the other hand, the group took the opportunity to criticize the “irresponsible policy” of US tariffs, indicating that the decision not only “seriously violated” the rules of international trade and has generated turbulence in the financial market, but it can also have a long range impact on the growth of the world economy, “leading to economic recession,” said the association.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Alice's magic arrived in Macau with a new show resident at the Grand Lisboa Palace</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/a-magia-de-alice-chegou-a-macau-com-novo-espectaculo-residente-no-grand-lisboa-palace/</link><description>A maze between magic and the dream. “The Adventures of Alice” is the title of the new dance production that debuted at Grand Lisbon Palace Resort on April 12th. A reinterpreted Lewis Carroll classic, the show brings with it a choreographic panoply and an immersive 360 ​​-degree scenario, where the imaginary unfolds in reality. The first phase of shows takes place for several days until May 4th.
 
On Saturday, Grand Lisbon Palace Resort was the scene of the release of “The Adventures of Alice”, a dance show that marks the beginning of a series of residential resort productions, coordinated in collaboration with the renowned artistic director of Hong Kong Ballet (HKB), Septime Webre. The debut, held in the resort's South Atrium area, turned Lewis Carroll's classic narrative into a captivating theatrical experience, filled with creativity and charm, brought from Alice's universe in Wonderland.
With choreography specially created by Webre, the show is accompanied by a new score by composer NG Cheuk-Yin and features costumes specially designed by Liz Vandal, known for his work at Cirque Du Soleil. These elements, combined with ingenious scenic effects and close interaction with the audience, transport viewers to Alice's magic landscape. In the two opening shows, held on the weekend, members of the Macao artistic community, dance professionals and enthusiasts were able to enjoy the performance, a new addition to the city's cultural and entertainment panorama.
Inspired by the acclaimed Ballet “Alice (In Wonderland)”, presented by Webre in 2018 and which won audiences in various places, including Beijing and Singapore, the new format was adapted especially to Macau. Production uses a 360 -degree immersive stage, providing a state -of -the -art audiovisual experience that invites viewers of all ages to embark on a imaginative trip around the world of Alice, the colors, fantasies and visual effects, typical of high -caliber entertainment production.
Grand Lisboa Palace features a program that includes two representations in each of the eight days chosen, all accessible to the public at no cost. After each performance, guests will be able to join Alice and her friends for group photographs.
As part of the spectacle launch, open auditions were held to recruit young dance talents in the Greater Bay region. This initiative aims to provide professional training and stage experience to rising artists, as well as strengthen the local ballet scene, in line with some of the government's guidelines for encouragement in the show and performance.
Daisy Ho, SJM's director general, said: “SJM is committed to cultivating Macau's artistic and cultural ecosystem. This new residence space offers a valuable stage for local interpreters, while fostering exchanges with international renowned production teams, raising the caliber of local talents and reinforcing the position of Macao as 'city of performative arts'.
Ho also referred to the accessible content of the new project: “The show is in a surrounding and community-oriented form, bringing art closer to people and offering a new dimension to family entertainment in the city”
The first phase of “The Adventures of Alice” will take place on several dates, these 12, 13, 18, 19 and 20 April, as well as May 2, 3 and 4. The resort also invites visitors to explore “Alice’s Dream Wonderland” at level 1 and to get lost in the secret garden at level 3.
Until June 30, guests can take the opportunity to try Alice -inspired culinary delights on the Lounge Lobby Lobby, as outstanding characters such as Alice and the Queen of Cup will make special appearances, interacting and having fun with the little ones with festive parades. In addition, guests will have the opportunity to create memories in “GLP Art”, part of the Grand Lisboa Palace Casino complex.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Exhibition of Macau Visual Arts 2025 will receive applications between 9 and 11 May</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/exposicao-das-artes-visuais-de-macau-2025-vai-receber-candidaturas-entre-9-e-11-de-maio/</link><description>Applications for the “Annual Exhibition of Macao Visual Arts of 2025 - Chinese Painting and Calligraphy category” will be open from May 9-11. The collection of works will be done in person, between 10:00 and 19:00 hours, in Art Space, located at the Cultural Center of Macau.
Local artists are invited to present, individually and only once, a work or artistic set in the areas of traditional Chinese painting, handwriting, recording of sinetes and experimental paint. If they choose to deliver a set, the regulation determines that it is limited to four pieces that constitute a single original work, completed between 2023 and 2025. At the time of the candidacies, competitors - of 18 years or more - must present the resident identity ticket (BIR) and the duly completed registration form.
The results of the selection process will be announced until August, on the Electronic Page of the Cultural Institute (IC). All works selected by the jury will be exhibited at the exhibition, taking place between November this year and January 2026, including ten awards for “exceptional works” with a remuneration of 30,000 patacas for each. In a statement, the IC said that the winning works will also be presented next year in collective exhibitions in Hong Kong or in the interior of China, "in order to encourage [artists] to expand their artistic creations, widen exchange and cooperation and obtain more development opportunities."
In the same statement, the organization clarifies that the show was, this year, renamed “Collective Exhibition of Macao Artists” for “Annual Exhibition of the 2025 Macao Visual Arts - Chinese Painting and Caligraphy category”, in order to “highlight the professionalism” of the event. In addition to the change of designation, the regulation of the collection of the works, the composition of the jury and the awards attributed to the winners was also “adjusted and improved”, also reinforcing cooperation with cultural and museological institutions outside the territory. This year, the jury will consist of five artistic professionals in the interior of China, who will governed by criteria such as originality, creativity, content and expressiveness of works.
The exhibition regulation and the registration form can be consulted and discharged on the IC electronic page or in person at the IC Visual Arts Development Division in Tap Siac Square.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Expo Osaka 2025 opens the doors to the public</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/expo-osaka-2025-abre-as-portas-ao-publico/</link><description>The Osaka 2025 Expo in Japan opened the doors to the public yesterday, with the participation of 158 countries, including Portugal, and the forecast of attracting about 28 million people over the next six months.
 
Despite the rain that fell in the morning, an hour before the doors opened, already a crowd row to enter the room, located in Yumeshima, artificial island erected in Osaka Bay, the Spanish news agency EFE.
Equipped with umbrellas and rails, the audience began to enter 9:00 after the opening ceremony.
Expo, which runs until October 13, has the theme of “drawing the societies of the future to our lives” and is expected to attract about 28 million visitors, of which 3.5 million are foreigners, according to the organization.
Studies estimate that the economic impact of world exposure reaches between two and 2.9 billion of yen (about 12.27 to 17.6 billion euros). This is an important injection of money for the fourth largest economy in the world, which is discussed with the reduction of domestic consumption due to the acceleration of inflation, as well as the impact of the tariff trade war began by the President of the United States, Donald Trump.
The event, according to EFE, has so far generated a modest interest among the Japanese population, after a series of negative news, such as the high costs or delays in the construction of some national pavilions.
Portuguese participation in the exhibition has as its theme “Ocean: Blue Dialogue” and has the involvement of more than 150 companies, associations, municipalities and national artists.
The Portugal Pavilion was designed by Japanese architect Kengo Kuma, winner of the International Contest for this purpose, which raised some controversy, namely with criticism from the Order of Architects, for not being a Portuguese.
Portugal's official mascot in the exhibition will be called UMI-which means Japanese ocean-a seahorse who, according to the prime minister, Luís Montenegro, is “a beautiful choice to mark the element that turned on Portugal and Japan about 500 years ago”.
The president of the Portugal Agency for Investment and Foreign Trade (AICEP) said last week that “there is a sea of ​​opportunities” that Portugal and Japan can develop together, under the Osaka Expo. “Portugal, of course, makes a major investment in the Osaka exhibition and, in addition to publicizing the Portuguese culture and tradition, the goal is also to reap the economic results that this exhibition can produce to Portugal,” said Ricardo Arroja, who spoke to journalists at the end of the Portugal's participation in Expo 2025 Osaka, which took place at the entity's headquarters.
The Portugal General Commissioner at Expo2025 Osaka stated in January that the global investment of operation “is 21 million euros” and is expected to reach or exceed the 1.4 million visitors of the Portuguese Pavilion. "There are goals for what we intend to have in Japan. For example, we expect to have or exceed 1.4 million visitors in our pavilion," said Joana Gomes Cardoso. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:41:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin cooperation zone is “the first priority” of Guangdong-Macau cooperation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/zona-de-cooperacao-em-hengqin-e-a-primeira-prioridade-da-cooperacao-guangdong-macau/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai met yesterday with Liu Cigui, member of the Permanent Committee and Director of the Hong Kong Connection Committee, Macau, Taiwan and Overseas Chinese of the Chinese People's Political Conference, which leads a delegation from the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay study group Kong-Macau of the Hong Kong, Macau, Taiwan and Chinese Overseas Committee. of the Political Advisory Conference of the Chinese people. At the time, the head of the Executive of the MSAR reiterated the commitment of MGA in relation to Hengqin.
Sam Hou Fai has begun to ensure that the government of the MSAR “is profoundly implementing the spirit consecrated in President XI Jinping's important speeches and instructions”, as well as “grasping the opportunities provided by national development, firmly accelerating the development of the proper diversification of Macau's economy, participating in an active and proactive way, in the construction of high quality Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macae Bay, Strengthening the integration of high quality resources from Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, deepening synergistic development, intensifying the articulation of legal rules and creating an innovative management mechanism. ”
At the meeting, the Chief Executive stressed that "the construction of the cooperation zone in Hengqin is the first priority of in -depth cooperation between Guangdong and Macao." This year, it is recalled, begins the second phase of the construction of the Cooperation Zone and the Government of the MSAR “is solidly boosting the goals and tasks set, to make all efforts so that the construction of the cooperation zone achieves even greater results, supporting the development of the great bay and creating an area with a high quality of life capable of providing good conditions to live, work and travel”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:36:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Xanana Gusmão appeals to dialogue and reconciliation in G7+ countries for peace</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/xanana-gusmao-apela-para-dialogo-e-reconciliacao-nos-paises-do-g7-para-paz/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Timor-Leste, Xanana Gusmão, called for G7+ member countries to promote national dialogue and reconciliation as the way to resolve conflict after the global system has failed.
 
"It's time to accept a painful truth: the global system led by powerful nations has repeatedly failed us. But as leaders we must also recognize our responsibility and act in accordance," said Xanana Gusmão.
The Timorese leader spoke at the sixth G7+ministerial meeting, as part of an intervention on how to “safeguard peace in turbulent times: the great vision of G7+”.
Under this intervention, Xanana Gusmão made four proposals to G7+countries, starting with an appeal to national dialogue and national reconciliation.
According to Xanana Gusmão, G7+ members have moral authority and experience to defend reconciliation not as an agenda imposed by third parties, but as an "essential process led by those who have lived war and understand its consequences." "We have the power to do this because our actions are moved by solidarity, not by their own political or economic interests. We are not here to dictate solutions, but to be next to each other as partners in peace," he said, asking UN Secretary-General António Guterres, the appointment of a special envoy for G7+.
The second proposal made by the Timorese leader involves the creation of a “peer learning framework”, which could be a model for policies, strengthening of institutions and to guide G7+ defense work on the global stage. "Although we are labeled as fragile, our countries have immense wisdom and experience that can inspire significant reforms in state construction. Our struggles have made us experts to overcome adversities, and the lessons we have learned are invaluable," he said.
The third proposal, addressed to the international community, requires G7+ countries to be seen as “equal partners”. "They should go beyond seeing fragile states as perpetual beneficiaries of help and, instead, investing in our resilience. A more stable G7+ means fewer crises, less wars and ultimately a small need for international aid," said Xanana Gusmão.
The Timorese Prime Minister also stated that fragile states are knowledgeable and can contribute to global peacebuilding efforts.
In the last proposal, addressed to the Member States of the Organization, Xanana Gusmão requested mobilization of political capital and investing in the strengthening of G7+. "We have the potential to safeguard peace in our countries, resist external interference, and prevent our nations from becoming again hegemonic rivalry fields," said the ruler. But, according to the Timorese Prime Minister, it is necessary to strengthen the "unity to restructure the global conversation about the construction of peace."
For Xanana Gusmão, the G7+ can remain a passive observer or join to protect its Member States from the "scars of war and poverty."
 
Branches for conflict mediation
 
The G7+ proposed the name of the president of Timor-Leste, José Ramos-Horta, as a special envoy for the mediation of conflict situations in the Member States of that block, announced the organization's secretary general, Helder Costa. "The ministers, given the situation of fragility and crisis that face several G7+countries, decided to propose the name of José Ramos-Horta, President of the Republic of Timor-Leste, as special envoy to make mediation in conflict situations," said G7+Secretary General Hélder Costa.
Others of the meeting's conclusions, according to the G7+Secretary-General, was the election of a new leadership, which was attributed to the Solomon Islands from January 2026. “Sierra Leone will continue the presidency until December 2025, which from January 2026 will be assumed by the Minister of Foreign Affairs Solomon,” said Hélder Costa.
The G7+ was established on April 10, 2010, in Dili, and arose with the concern that traditional development cooperation did not improve the situation of fragile nations. Afghanistan, Burundi, Central African Republic, Chad, asres, Ivory Coast, Democratic Republic of Congo, Guinea-Concrite, Guinea-Bissau, Haiti, Liberia, Papua-Nova Guinea, Sao Tome and Prince, Sierra Leone, Somalia, South Sudan, Timo-Leste, Togo and Yamen G7+Member States. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:41:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Air quality at “very unhealthy or dangerous” level due to dust storm</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/qualidade-do-ar-no-nivel-muito-insalubre-a-perigoso-devido-a-tempestade-de-poeira/</link><description>Macau is being affected by a dust storm and today's air quality level can reach the “very unhealthy to dangerous” level. The concentration of atmospheric pollutants has a significant increase since Sunday dawn, according to weather and geophysical services, due to a northeast monsoon that brings soil dust in the north regions. The body appeals to the general population to minimize the strenuous activities and the time of outdoor permanence.
 
Catarina Chan
*Proteced Email*
 
The air quality index in Macau can reach the “very unhealthy to dangerous” level during the day due to a dust storm that significantly increased the concentration of atmospheric pollutants in the territory.
According to the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), the dust storm was mainly caused by the strong winds by the ground in the north of China, which swept the dust and spread to the south, and, along with the Northeast Monção, reached south of China and the Pearl River estuary.
The information available on the SMG Portal indicates that the concentrations of pollutants in the territory rose sharply between 10 pm on Saturday and the dawn on Sunday, remaining high yesterday. According to the authorities air quality monitoring data, the timely inhales of inhalable particles in PM10 suspension in several monitoring stations at 10am yesterday was over 350 μg/m3. Already at the station on the roadside of Ká-Hó was recorded a record of the time concentration of 428 μg/m3, verified at 5am yesterday, said the body.
The SMG have analyzed the current conditions of dust transmission and meteorological circulation and predict that the dust storm continues to affect the southern region of China to this day. However, they stated that with the passage of this storm, it is believed that the concentration of pollutants in Macau gradually decreases from today.
In this case, the authorities remind the public to take protection measures to the warning about air quality, as well as pay attention to the last weather forecasts.
The body appeals to the general population to reduce activities, namely the strenuous, outdoor, and the time that is spent abroad. If people need to leave, they should wear a protective mask and drink more water, SMG recommend.
For people with heart or respiratory diseases, pregnant, children and the elderly, who are more sensitive to dust, should pay more attention and avoid outdoor activities, remain closed as much as possible, keep the air fresh and pay attention to physical condition, according to SMG. If they do not feel well, they should immediately seek medical attention, adds the body
It is recalled that the China National Meteorological Center has issued warnings for strong wind and dust storm, and advanced that 18 provinces in the country were affected by the dust. The Chinese meteorological observatory predicts that the dusty time prevails to this day in southern Xinjiang, the central and western inner Mongolia and in the north and southwest of Guangdong.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:41:20</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM performed seven training actions in the Convention and Exhibition sector until April</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/14/ipim-realizou-sete-accoes-de-formacao-no-sector-de-convencoes-e-exposicoes-ate-abril/</link><description>The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) carried out seven training and exhibition training actions in the first four months of the year, attracting more than 300 graduates and enabling more than 80 certificates of professional courses with international accreditation.
The figures, released in a statement by IPIM, refer to data collected until April 10. The seven training actions in question, organized in articulation with the business sector and various higher education institutions, intend to align with the strategy of diversification of the economy provided by the Government of Masters through the continuous dynamization of training works on various aspects of the sector. Explored topics include planning, bidding, assembly safety, marketing and crisis management.
IPIM emphasizes that these initiatives “attracted a wide participation” of industry professionals, such as “representatives of integrated tourism and leisure companies, convention and exhibition centers, event professional organizing entities, representatives of sectoral destination management companies”, as well as operators of this sector from the interior of China.
Last Thursday-April 10, the last day considered in the IPIM statement-a workshop was also held on “strategies for the ICCA conventions [International Congress and Convention Association]” whose speaker was the Asia Pacific Director, Waikin Wong. The ICCA official, with more than 20 years of experience in organizing international conferences, spoke before 70 representatives of the sector in Macao and explained, among other topics, “the key strategies of bidding”.
In the same event, there was also an exchange activity entitled “Meet@Macao”, in which “more than ten academic leaders and experts” in areas such as Big Health and Tip Technologies dialogued with convention and exhibition operators on the holding of professional conferences in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 02:41:29</pubDate></item></channel></rss>