<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/tribunal-rejeita-ordem-de-detencao-contra-ex-presidente-yoon/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Steel bamboo</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/bambu-por-aco/</link><description>While structures have pondered the strength of the elements in their natural resilience, and humanity confronts its own evolution. Traditional forms and centenary methods are replaced by the evident improvement of technique and tools, such as mammired consciousness is replaced by electromagnetic connections. Meat by plastic. Bambus by steel.
 
It is indisputable, in the matter of security you do not play. When lives are put to the test, decisions are made based on what is now proposed as more efficient against failures. It is by these lines that the neighboring government of Hong Kong and its “Development Bureau”, with the representation of Terence Lam, gradually decided to extinguish the use of structures and scaffolding composed by Bambus in construction. Since 2018, due to what they call “intrinsic weaknesses”, the department has accounted for 23 deaths directly related to building buildings with this type of natural scaffolding. A tradition seen on the Chinese continent in twelfth -century paintings and in writings of Master Carpenter Lu Ban, 2500 years ago.
The interior of the country completely abandoned bamboo, this species of grass of stalks that permeates the vast bean territory, from Hainan to Jiangsu, and to Sichuan valleys. Steel came to replace the organic weaknesses of these massive nodular canas.
But regardless of the contemporary discussion of which work practices are made safely or not, of a craft that has climbed the passage of time, they are the “intrinsic weaknesses” that an artisan takes and plays. In the hollow lightness of the bamboo is a flexibility superior to the steel. An easy -to -cut material that gives Aso to rapid changes. Erecting any kind of imaginable way from nylon yarn tangent tangents is not only infinitely cheaper, but it offers masters of this work options that are limited only to what is physically possible.
Its function as the main structure of unique buildings, which stand by themselves to host musicians, actors and set designers in traditional operas, among other functions, is a work of art itself. Within a few weeks, a “dream warehouse”, worthy of large -scale shows, which in Hong Kong come to join thousands under their curved bamboo ceiling in tension, combined with spruce wood, famous for their peculiar resonance appreciated by the masters of the lutery.
A group of men with black plastic tails join with the tutelage of a master to guide the straight lines of the work composed of two types of Bambus, the “Mao Jue” and the “Kao Jue”, aged at least at least at the third year of age. The first, thicker, dense and strong, grounds in the ground, often dug through the streets of the streets, constituting robust points of support. The second, thinner and slightest type is widely used for the rest of the structure, such as platforms, divisions or support for the roof of the buildings.
Bambus structures are reusable, easy to store and transport. Canas usually remain unchanged to their third application in works and may be stored in the open. It is for these and other reasons that the practice is not abandoned so easily, both for the practical reasons for its application and for the creative flexibility it unfolds. Not only does it keep an active a pantheon of co-artisans who pour their knowledge for generations, as contemporary architects inspires new views on the habitable space. Local teams, such as Impromptu Projects, have been studying ways to introduce these millennial traditions into the modern design. A form of preservation, but mainly of appreciation for the beauty of the natural incorporated in the artificial.
While in the neighborhood the practical functions of Bambus are abandoned-curiously transit through Macao from the Zhaoqing zone in Canton and Guangxi in southern China, before they reach the high verticality of the Hong Kong skyscrapers-art immortalizes tradition. The smell of cement and silicone may replace the perfume of sawn wood; The sharp sound of the iron bursting with the bamboo cracks that opens, to keep everything more “strong and safe”. But what these installations project in history is not inheritance or traditionalist resistance, it is rather an option for the beautiful, creativity and cultivation of the intangible artistic human spirit, in collaboration with the nature and space that surrounds it. Bamboo cathedrals erected by men and women for the sake of art keep this theater of emotions alive that is life. Because it is not always necessary to exchange bamboo for steel.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Cultural constructions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/construcoes-culturais/</link><description>As traditional construction methods are replaced by more modern approaches throughout the southern region of China, the theaters of Macau temples maintain the inheritance of bamboo building techniques.
 
The eighth day of the fourth lunar month is the traditional celebration of Tam Kong's birthday, a Taoist deity of the sea. And by the coast, in the coloane village, the usually quiet area in front of the Tam Kong temple comes alive with the construction of an impressive Cantonesa opera theater, built entirely in bamboo. After its conclusion, the structure welcomes a series of shows over several nights, in celebration of divinity.
The imposing three -story structure is the largest of its gender in Macao, composed of hundreds of bamboo sticks and sprugging wooden beams of various lengths, all united without a single nail, screw or any other piece of metal. The main structure of the theater covers more than a thousand square meters. It is functionally divided into stage and areas of sitting places, with triangular arc structures forming the roof.
O mestre Leong Wo, um experiente construtor de teatros de bambu, chega à aldeia na sua motocicleta, trazendo consigo todas as ferramentas do seu ofício, pronto para começar a trabalhar. Enquanto trabalha, ele explica: “Usamos principalmente dois materiais: madeira maciça de abeto como pilares de suporte e bambu oco como suportes suplementares”.
When the annual commemorative presentations come to an end, the entire structure is dismantled and most of the building materials are stored and reused the following year. “Every year we carefully store the materials. Black wood can last more than a decade and bamboo needs to be replaced every two years.”
From the beginning of the construction process until the theater is completely dismantled again, it takes about 50 days in total.
In Macau, bamboo is easily available due to its accessible and versatile nature, and bamboo scaffolding is found throughout the city, commonly used in construction projects. In fact, the handicraft of these traditional bamboo opera theaters was listed as an intangible cultural heritage.
However, neighboring Hong Kong began replacing traditional bamboo scaffolding with more reusable metal rods for public works projects starting this year. Thus, although this craft orally transmitted from building flexible and temporary bamboo structures have resisted centuries of storms and historical changes, its future now seems uncertain.
While Master Leong guides us by the theater under construction, he points to the slightly curved bamboo sticks, eight to nine meters long, high. “The arched roof can withstand heavier loads, while creating more room to hang decorative plates, making the show more pleasant to our audience!”, He explains.
Following the master Leong, the ingenious structure of the whole bamboo theater becomes clearly visible, with its complex set of wonderful bamboo sticks and intertwined spruce wood.
According to Master Leong, the Tam Kong Temple Theater can accommodate more than 1,000 people and have a total of three entrances, with the main building linked to a covered corridor that controls the flow of people, while offering space for tents and meals, linking the temple to the sea.
Similar bamboo theaters are also installed in the A-MA temple, Fok Tak Chi Temple, Lin Kai Temple, and Taipa Pak Tai Temple, but the Tam Kong Temple Theater is particularly spectacular.
The Tam Kong Temple was built in the first year of the reign of Tongzhi (1862), founded by fishermen who loved Tam Kong as a deity of the sea. Tam Kong is widely venerated in all coastal areas of Guangdong.
Historically, the tradition of the Macau Temple Operae dates back to over 280 years, keeping alive the original form of local beliefs and culture. Compared to neighboring regions, where these presentations disappeared in most of Hong Kong's urban temples and withdrew to Lingnan's rural areas, Macau's preservation is notably complete.
Master Leong recalls a visit to Hong Kong's largest bamboo theater and his surprise with his ability to accommodate five to six thousand guests. “It was so big! Even the macau bamboo theaters can't match their size, but our handicrafts are more refined,” he comments.
Today, this architectural style survives only sporadically in parts of the Delta of the Pearl River, Chaoshan, Fujian and other coastal areas of the Southeast. All developed distinct characteristics due to local customs, practical needs and construction techniques, which vary from region to region, but also share some common characteristics.
As Master Leong says, regardless of the type of structure, the fundamental principle is to adapt to the real circumstances: "I will find out as I advance-this is how I solve the problems."
 
Crafts with hands, eyes and heart
 
Master Leong explains that the construction of each year begins with a fixed procedure: identify the key points of the pillars on earth and water, respectively, followed by the construction of perimeter walls and temporary supports, placement of green plastic leaves, stage assembly, entrance hall installation and, finally, theater decoration with floral plates and tracks.
During construction, artisans move agilly throughout the structure, using only visual estimates, mental calculations, body measurements and balance to determine the spacing between bamboo sticks and cargo support points, maintaining the symmetrical aesthetics of theater-a craft that requires not only strength and agility, but perfect synchronization between hands, eyes and soul.
Master Leong recalls that when he started working on temple bamboo theaters, he had no official projects, only two photos that didn't even show the whole structure: one showing the left side and one the right side - which he had to join to understand the internal structure. At that time, scaffolding artisans could build without projects or machines, and master Leong had to learn the craft by carrying bamboo and wood sticks to the place every day with his teacher.
After two years of learning, Master Leong obtained his instructor license in 1980. "Basic knowledge takes only two years to be dominated, but everything beyond that requires its own creativity," he says. Since entering the business, she has been working in temples in Macau for over 40 years.
The construction of the Tam Kong Theater requires about 70 to 80 artisans. Prior to the start of construction, the team says in the temple for safety and good time: in June, Macau enters its storm station, so the birthdays of the main deities, such as Tou Tei and A-MA, all occur before the Festival of the dragon boat, on the fifth day of the Chinese calendar.
Master Leong remembers a celebration of A-MA's birthday for over a decade, when a signal 8 has hit the region. Fortunately, the bamboo theater remained standing. This miracle resilience was the result of the skillful hands of the artisans, who built resistant structures capable of enduring the forces of nature.
"The flexibility and resistance of bamboo are really amazing, and it demonstrates a surprising resistance even against strong winds," says master Leong proudly. “We started work on the first day of the third lunar month every year, rain or sunbathe. The whole project takes about a month, so we can end well before Tam Kong's birthday,” says master Leong with a smile, demonstrating a strong sense of pride for his work.
At the end of the month, we returned to the place when the festivities end and, at sunset, the last bamboo rod is removed, returning Tam Kong's temple square to their usual peace and tranquility. Although this iconic bamboo theater has come to an end for another year, it will continue to create vivid folk memories for the people of Macau in the coming generations.
As the sea breeze sweeps the rocky coast now empty, it is easy to imagine this simple fishing village for half a century, with the echoes of the Cantonese opera melodies and the public applause of the public to raise the night.
True inheritance is not just about perpetual existence, but to the annual rebirth, such as the tides of the river in front of the Tam Kong temple, which flow and reflore, and those carefully stored bamboo who support each other for one more celebration season.
 
Macau Closer</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Kim Jong-un's wife reappears after a year and a half at the opening of a tourist complex</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/mulher-de-kim-jong-un-reaparece-apos-ano-e-meio-em-inauguracao-de-complexo-turistico/</link><description>The wife of the North Korean leader reappeared in public after a year and a half, at the inauguration of a tourist mega-compulsion in the Kalma region on the east coast, according to photos published yesterday by the official news agency.
 
Pictures of the event, released by KCNA, show Ri Sol-ma standing or sitting a few steps from her husband, leader Kim Jong-un, and her daughter, who is believed to be called Ju-AE at the event held on Wednesday.
Rii clothes - white shirt, wide black pants and what appears to be a Gucci bag - contrasts with the most formal white set worn by the daughter, who is speculated to be the heiress of the regime, according to the EFE news agency.
The export of luxury goods to North Korea is banned by Resolution 1718 of the United Nations Security Council, which imposes sanctions on the Asian country by nuclear programs and ballistic missile programs.
However, according to EFE, the country is known for using diplomatic bags, customs -free and inspection to bring such articles as gifts to the leader's family.
This is the first public appearance of RI since the New Year of 2024, when the state media showed it to attend a show.
Unlike women from the two previous North Korean leaders (Kim Jong-un's father and grandfather), who remained behind the scenes, Ri has frequently appeared in the media since Kim took power in 2011.
The event chosen for the return of RI was the ceremony of completion of a large 'resort' in the eastern coastal region of Kalma, which Kim greeted as one of the largest achievements in the country this year, according to KCNA.
The official press said the resort has a capacity of 20,000 guests, with facilities to swim, do sport and recreational activities, as well as stores and restoration spaces. "Wonsan Kalma's coastal area should play a key role in the development of North Korea's tourist culture," Kim said during a speech at the event, according to KCNA.
The agency also wrote that Kim ordered operators to provide maximum comfort and leisure facilities for tourists.
Kim described the Kalma resort as the first step in developing cultural tourism in the country and said that the upcoming workers' party congress, yet for announcing, will confirm a large plan to develop new large -scale tourist zones in other regions.
The Russian Ambassador in North Korea and members of the embassy were invited to the ceremony, which indicates that Russians are expected to be among foreign tourists who will spend vacation there.
The inauguration takes place on July 1 and will lead the country to announce greater flexibility of borders after years of restrictions due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau competition creates a prize for Palop and Timor-Leste startups</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/competicao-em-macau-cria-premio-para-startups-de-palop-e-timor-leste/</link><description>The fifth edition of the 929 Challenge competition in Macao will include an award for the best startup of African countries of Portuguese Language (Palop) and Timor-Leste, the organization announced yesterday.
Marco Duarte Rizzo, co -founder of the 929 Challenge, told Lusa that the 'Future Builders' award was created to encourage participants in the least developed Lusophone countries. "We have a common language, but the level of economic development of each of the countries is completely different," explained Rizzolio, on the sidelines of a press conference.
The latest edition of the Chinese startups competition and Portuguese -speaking countries recorded a new maximum, with over 1,600 participants in over 320 teams. However, in 2024, 929 Challenge did not receive any projects from Timor-Leste or Sao Tome and Principe.
With the new prize, RizzoLio said he hoped that this year's edition there will be 'startups' of all nine Lusophone countries. "The goal is this, encourage, but it is also helping ... If they can win that award, it is already motivating for them, so that they can develop the project," he explained.
The Portuguese startup IPlexmed, which develops fast genetic diagnostic devices, won last year's edition, while also the Portuguese NS2, which provides intelligent solutions to monitor water quality for sustainable aquaculture, was third.
The only time a Palop and Timor-Leste team arrived at the finalists was early in the first edition, released in 2021, in the middle of Covid-19 pandemic, then only directed to college students. A project from the Guinea-Bissau Lusophone University to install solar panels in the Gabu region of the east of the country, was in second place. “In the end, those who win are often teams that already have mature products, mature services,” explained Rizzolio.
Registration is open until September 30, for both companies and university students.
Rizzolio, also a professor at the City of Macau, recalled that the competition has new partners, including Startupporto, Cape Verde Digital and Eduardo Mondlane University in Mozambique. The best 16 plans - eight companies and eight university students - will have 10 minutes to convince the jury of the 929 Challenge and potential investors in the final in November. The other co -founder of the competition, José Alves, stressed that the competition “is not yet a success” because so far he has not been able to attract projects to open doors in Macau. "We need to identify the best startups, invest in them and bring them to the mainland China market, or take them from China to Lusophone countries," the professor explained.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestine I - The Biblical “fallacy”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/palestina-i-a-falacia-biblica/</link><description>When everyone was starting from Anatevkana's small imaginary village in Ukraine in the 1905 winter, Yente, the matchmaker, Golde's wife, Tevye's wife, the leading protagonist of the roof violin, starting with the younger daughters to America, which she went to Palestine, saying ‘What do we say all the pascoas? For the year, in Jerusalem! '
The response of the matchmaker, in the final scenes of this Broadway musical, debuted in 1964 and converted into a film in 1971, verbalizes the desire that many Jews had, especially from the nineteenth century, to return to the Holy Land. To the feeling expressed by this fictional character of this musical about the life of the Jews in the tsarist Russia, when converted into political ideology, it is called Zionism, and it is this political movement responsible for the creation of the modern state of Israel.
The word Zionism derives from Zion, a term that originally referred to the hill where the primitive city of Jerusalem was situated and, over time, became just another name for Jerusalem.
Zionism as a political movement appears in the late nineteenth century. With the emancipation of Jews in Europe and the growth of so-called anti-Semitism, the idea began to develop among the Jews that they could return to Palestine and establish a Jewish state.
In 1896, Theodor Herzl, an Austro-Hungarian Jew, published the 'der Judenstaat' pamphlet, that is, 'the Jewish state' in which he defended the creation of a Jewish state in Palestine. The following year, 1897, Herzl organized in Basel, Switzerland, the first Zionist Congress where 208 delegations from 17 countries participated. There was a world Zionist organization, which adopted the Basel program where the main objectives of Zionism as a political movement, namely, the creation of a Jewish state in Palestine, the adhesion of all Jews in the world to Zionist ideology, the exaltation of Jewish nationalism and the creation of Jewish colonies in Palestine.
 
The biblical base of Zionist ideology
Until a few years ago, most people knew at least the main stories of the Bible because they were part of our religious cultural identity and part of the general culture of the West. Many of these stories have come to the big screen, such as Cecil B. Demille's famous 'Ten Commandments' with Charlton Heston, among many others. Who did not know the story of Daniel in the grave of lions, Samson and Delilah, from the passage of the red sea on foot, the burning bush, among many others? Nowadays, unfortunately this general cultural knowledge is almost completely lost and the great biblical tales have been circumscribed to religious knowledge.
Although cultural knowledge of the text, or parts of the biblical text has been lost, continues to persist the erroneous idea that the modern state of Israel is in a way the heir of an ancient Jewish state that existed during the period covered by the biblical narrative in the Palestine region. This belief is grounded in history - if this can be called the Hebrew people as the Bible narrates it.
According to the biblical narrative, the Hebrews who had been enslaved in Egypt, escaped slavery by Moses' hand, after the famous ten pests, and had crossed the Red Sea on foot, then wandered through the Sinai Desert, for forty years, before entering the promised land, ie the geographical zone known as Palestine and that encompasses the modern state of Israel and Space occupied by the Palestinians under Israeli occupation, namely the Gaza Strip and the West Bank.
Once in Palestine, the tribes of Israel were distributed throughout the territory and finally founded the kingdom of Israel whose first king was Saul. Then came David who established Jerusalem as the capital of a single kingdom composed of all twelve tribes. His son Solomon, according to the biblical text, would have formed a great empire in conquering the kingdoms around him.
Solomon, biblical tradition also attributes the construction of a magnificent temple in Jerusalem. But with his death in 930 BC, ten of the twelve tribes were separated and formed an independent kingdom. Thus, and according to the biblical narrative, the United Kingdom of Israel was divided into two, Israel, whose capital was Samaria, north, headquarters of the ten rebel tribes, and Judah, to the south, composed of two tribes, whose capital was Jerusalem.
In 722 a. C. The Northern Kingdom was conquered by the Assyrians while Judah was allowed to continue to exist with a certain autonomy in the face of payment of tax. Judah thus became what is called the client kingdom of the Assyrian Empire.
In 586 BC the Babylonians, who, however, had subdued the Assyrians, conquered Judah, destroying Jerusalem and bringing captives to Babylon their ruling classes.
However, in 539 BC the Persians conquered the Babylonian Empire, and Ciro, the Great, allowed, in 538 BC, that the leaders of Judah returned and Jerusalem be rebuilt; Judah continued, however, as a province of the Persian Empire and not an independent kingdom.
In 332 BC, Alexandre Magno conquered the Palestinian region, where the Persian province of Judah was. When Alexandre Magno died in 323 BC, his empire, which was basically composed by Greece and the Persian empire he had conquered, was divided by his generals. The geographical situation of Palestine caused Judah to become territory disputed by the Syria's selands and the Ptolemeus of Egypt.
In 167 BC, the famous Maccabean revolt against Antiochus IV Seleucid that will culminate in 141 BC with the establishment of the Hasmonean dynasty when Simon Tassi is made high priest. In 139 BC, the seleucids recognize Simon as the leader of the Jews and Judah becomes an independent state of fact.
Judah will remain independent until 63 BC. When Pompey conquers Palestine, and Judea, as Judah was called, was incorporated into the Roman Empire and the rest is history.
From what was outlined above the following "truths" on which Zionism was based, namely, that the Jews, with their twelve tribes, occupied the entire region of Palestine, at least since the beginning of the first millennium BC; that the kingdoms of Israel and Judah began to be a unique kingdom and, having divided into two, were yet both Jewish kingdoms; which Solomon conquered all the kingdoms around him creating an empire, and finally, that Jews have always been the same uniform people practicing religious monotheism that is often called Judaism. All these base ideas of Jewish nationalism fostered by Zionism find their foundation in the biblical narrative.
 
Archeology, history and religious myth
Since the eighties of the last century that many of these biblical “truths” have begun to be concerned, but it is mainly from the nineties, and thanks above all to Israelite archaeologist Israel Finkelstein, that this monument of religious myths disguised as history has begun to collapse. The first two problems for Finkelstein draws attention are that biblical archeology was a subsidiary of religious and not independent studies as it should, and that when archeology actually actually acted, archaeological findings did not confirm what the biblical text says.
Modern archaeologists are said that in the past their counterparts in Palestine worked with the shovel in one hand and the Bible in the other. This image serves to say that archeology served, not to discover new facts, but to confirm the biblical text. This subsidiary archeology of the Bible still exists, and now that it has been challenged, it has two goals, namely confirming the biblical text and challenging or even trying to deny the conclusions of independent archeology.
Although with the fierce opposition of archaeologists and biblist historians, modern archeology proved that the Unified Kingdom of Israel never existed, that the North Kingdom, called in the Bible of the Kingdom of Israel, was not a Jewish kingdom, that the southern kingdom or Judah was a fragmented small state in which the leader would be more the king of Jerusalem than Jerusalem in the days of days David and Solomon would have been a small cluster of a few hundred people of people and not the magnificent city that the Bible portrays, that of the two kingdoms, by far, the most prosperous, most populous and technically more advanced was the Northern Kingdom, that the empire of Solomon never really existed - with some archaeologists even in question the existence of the Solomon himself! acquired is due to migratory movements of some meaning from the north, after their conquest, and they brought with them some of their civilizational superiority to Judah.
In addition to these new historical truths, modern archeology and research vehemently deny the monotheistic character of the religious practices of populations of varied ethnic origin that then inhabited Palestine and that the texts that make up what we call Old Testament are a much more recent creation than traditionally created.
 
The historicity of biblical stories
One of the problems that the biblical text faces is that it has a religious or even sacred character and, as such, has a theological information. Since theology is supposedly interested in the ultimate truth, the way theologians position themselves before the biblical text is conditioned by the theoretical assumptions and the objectives of their discipline, which determine what is understood by truth.
Although today, both archeology and history, and the philological and critical studies of the biblical text coincide that the biblical narrative in general cannot be taken as historical truth, many continue to try to prove that the biblical text is a valid historical source. This happens above all between American evangelical Protestants and some ultra-orthodox Jews, for the most part, also Americans. European and Israelite biblical academics, as well as Catholic theologians, European Protestants, and moderate American Protestants tend to accept the findings' conclusions without great difficulty and, whenever appropriate, incorporate them into their religious studies.
To give only one example of an ancient biblical tale whose factuality can be disputed based on historical and archaeological investigation, let's look at the case of Egypt's escape, an episode that narrates how the Hebrews escaped slavery in Moses -guided Egypt; Nowadays the communic opinion among academics is that this episode does not describe real facts.
Of the various reasons pointed out, let's see only two. First, according to the biblical text, the Hebrews would represent between a quarter and a third of the population of Egypt. If suddenly a country lost a third or a quarter of its population, it would necessarily have serious, especially economic consequences. However, the Egyptians who recorded everything do not mention any part of the loss of such a significant part of their work force or any crisis that would necessarily have derived from such a demographic change.
On the other hand, the Hebrews would have left the land of their clavagies towards the Promised Land where, presupposed, they would be free and responsible for their own destiny. However, it happens that by the time these facts would have happened, the Palestine region was part of the Egyptian Empire. Thus the Hebrews would have fled from Egypt to Egypt!
Obviously conclusions like these conflict with the concept of Bible as The Unerring Word of God that most of the Protestants, especially Americans, still defend.
From a less bacoca perspective of the biblical text, theological truth and historical truth are two distinct things. They can coincide, as sometimes happens, for example, Jesus, as a man, came from Palestine. However, theological truth does not depend on the historical truth, that is, the theological value, or religious - that is not exactly the same - what is described in the Bible does not depend on its factuality.
For example, the objectivity of worship of the wise men, an episode still known to most people and which is narrated at the beginning of the second chapter of the Gospel of St. Matthew is problematic, even because of the vague character of the text itself. Still, the theological message that the text wants to pass is clear and it does not depend on who the wizards were, of what Magoi, a word of Persian origin, that is, how many wizards-different traditions point to three, six or even twelve-what were these wizards-what our tradition, for example, is to call them kings-even where the text says, etc.
The factual details or even the historicity of the event does not remove its high theological content from the message. The worship of these wizards can be interpreted as representing the universal recognition of Christ, for wizards are the first Gentiles or pagans who worship Jesus and their gifts, namely incense, gold and myrrh are also symbols of theological semiotics. Gold represents the recognition of Jesus as king, incense, which only offers God in altars, indicates the recognition of his divine nature, and myrrh, that of his human nature, since myrrh was the perfume that was then used in the preparation of bodies for the funeral.
Another important element is the fact that it is nature - a star - that guides them to God, suggesting that revelation is also done through the world, idea, in fact, defended in Vatican I, in 1870. There are more symbolic elements in this episode, but they come to illustrate the principle that the importance of the message does not depend on the factuality of what is told; The factuality of the text is secondary to its symbology. The evangelist who tells us this episode was not present in the scene and is not reported to have intervened the interveners to know what has passed there accurately, if, in fact, something has passed.
This leads us to another point. The wizards, according to the biblical text, will have found themselves with Herod, who tried to obtain the precise location of their birth already with the idea of ​​having Jesus killing. The text also says that, warned in a dream, after visiting the boy, they returned directly to their lands without meeting with Herod again. Herod has realized that he had been deceived, he has all the boys kill until he was two years old. This, being true, would necessarily have caused sufficient furor to have passed into the annals of history. However, no other source, besides St. Matthew-not even the other gospels-mention this event, which also escaped the radar of the famous Jewish-Helenistic historian Flávio Josephus (37–100), which, in his Jewish antiquities corroborates, outside any religious context, the existence and questions that led to the crucifixion of Jesus in addition to comments on the early Christians in the early Christians Palestine. Josephus is, moreover, one of the independent historical sources that attest to the real existence of Jesus and certain facts narrated in the Gospels.
How did the evangelist access to the data of the private conversation between Herod and the wizards when they, as the text says, returned to their lands? All of this has led to the factuality of this episode had been called into question and today many believe that this episode is “fictitious”, that is, not factual but only a literary-religious vehicle to pass a certain theological message. The intention of the biblical author is not to write history, but to tell stories that support the message for the message that it intends to pass.
Although not from the Old Testament, this episode shares the same problems as the Hebrew texts, that is, their religious character associated with their lack of factual credibility. For many, accepting that the texts may be “wrong” presents itself as a real challenge, insofar as such an admission could lead to other truths to be concerned too, that is, if this is not true, what guarantees do we have that the rest is? This could lead to the collapse of the religious building, especially on the Protestant side, where the Bible is the only form of revelation accepted by the community. If what the Bible says is not true, then how is it?
 
The factual value of the Old Testament
The Old Testament text, being primarily of a religious text, is similar to that of the new, as its first intention is not to write history. Both are organized in several layers that intertwine with each other. Contrary to an onion where the various layers that compose it are separated and can be independently, the various strata of the biblical text are not differentiated, which leads to the historical stratum, which exists, does not distinguish, to the naked eye, from the religious-theological stratum, ethnological stratum, or even the literary stratum. This is just thickening the problem of reading and textual interpretation and can lead, as it does in some quadrants, which one opts for a literal reading in response to the fear of losing something along the way.
Another layer that crosses the biblical text of Les to Les is the political stratum that, in turn, can be classified in intern, who is actually embedded in the text-we will speak to the next, God willing-and in external, that is, the use of biblical text for political purposes.
Zionism uses the biblical text to justify the assertion that the modern state of Israel is heir to the ancient Jewish kingdom of Israel as this is described in the Old Testament. However, archeology and history have already proved that this ancient Unified Kingdom of Israel is a biblical myth, which already then at the time of its composition was to justify the existence of an independent Jewish state in the face of external forces that wanted to subdue Palestine. History also shows that the primitive kingdom of Judah was a rudimentary sociopolitical structure and that the Northern Kingdom, which the Bible calls the kingdom of Israel, was not a Jewish state of all. In fact, history says that, as an independent state, a Jewish state only existed from 139 BC to 63 BC, thus in question the millennial pretensions of Zionist Judaism.
The biblical text continues, despite its lack of historical value, to serve as a crutch to Israelite territorial claims. In 2011, the now declared war criminal, Benjamin Netanyahu, said in a joint session of the American Senate that 'in Judea and Samaria [understand themselves in the West Bank] the Jewish people are not a foreign occupying force'. These words were followed by a great ovation of applause that can only find justification that both the House of Representatives and the American Senate are full, especially on the republican side, but not only, people who believe that everything that comes in the Bible is true as, some believing even in the creation of the world in seven days!</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotel occupancy rate between January and May rose to 89.2%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/taxa-de-ocupacao-hoteleira-entre-janeiro-e-maio-subiu-para-892/</link><description>Between January and May, the average occupancy rate of Macau hotels reached 89.2% - five more percentage points compared to the same period last year. Still, hotel establishments received fewer guests this year.
 
In the first five months of this year, the average occupancy rate of the hotel establishments of Macao was 89.2%, plus five percentage points, compared to the same period last year. However, the number of visitors hosted fell 2.1% to just over six million. The data were revealed yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). Statistics also show that the average permanence period of guests remained at 1.7 nights.
At the end of May this year, there were 147 hotel establishments, another four in annual terms, providing a total of 45,000 guest rooms, less 3.7%.
In May, the average hotel occupancy rate set at 87.8%, plus 4.5 percentage points in annual terms. DSEC points out that the occupancy rate of 5 -star hotels (91.4%), 4 -star hotels (80.7%) and 3 -star hotels (84.2%) increased by 6.5; 1 and 3.4 percentage points, respectively.
Last month, hotel establishments hosted 1,228,000 individuals, plus 2.7%in annual terms. The number of guests in the interior of China (902,000) ascended 3.7%compared to May 2024 and international guests (100,000) increased 12.9%.
DSEC also made the bills to the excursions and indicated that the number of tour was 855,000 in the first five months of the year, plus 0.7% compared to the same period last year. The number of international visitors entries in excursions (99,000) ascended 12.4%, in relation to the same period of 2024, noting that the visitors of South Korea excursions (46,000) rose 24.2%. However, the number of visitors in excursions from the interior of China (732,000) registered a homologous drop of 2.2%.
For its part, the number of Macao residents exits who purchased service agencies to travel abroad was fixed at 219,000, rising 7.6%, compared to the identical period of 2024. It should be noted that 58,000 were outputs of travels, plus 4.8%.
Looking only at the month of May, the number of visitors from visitors who arrived on excursions to Macao was only 128,000, down 21%, in annual terms, mainly due to the number of visitors in the interior of China (101,000) excursions (101,000) decreased 27.9%. However, the number of international visitors in excursions (22,000) grew 22.8%, compared to May 2024, noting that visitors in South Korea excursions (8,000) ascended 20.5%.
The number of Macao residents exits who purchased service agencies for traveling abroad corresponded to 48,000 in the month under analysis, plus 5.2%, in annual terms, of which 34,000 were from residents who traveled individually (plus 18.4%) and 14,000 were from residents who traveled on excursions (less 17.7%). The DSEC also says that 12,000 were exits of residents who traveled in excursions inside China.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Government uses the end of World War II to promote patriotism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/governo-usa-fim-da-segunda-guerra-mundial-para-promover-o-patriotismo/</link><description>World War II - or "the victory of the Chinese people in the war against Japan and world victory against fascism," for Chinese authorities - ended 80 years ago. The Macao government is associated with the celebrations and LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, said the date should be used to "stimulate patriotism and national pride."
 
The Macao government wants to use the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II - and the consequent end of China's Japanese occupation - to stimulate the patriotism of the population. Yesterday, local authorities presented a list of activities to celebrate the "80th anniversary of the Chinese people's victory in the war against Japan and the world victory against fascism."
These activities intend to “recall history, honor ancestors and promote the great patriotic spirit and the great spirit of resistance”, as well as “reinforce historical knowledge and cultivate patriotic feeling” of the population of Macao, yesterday stated Lam. The secretary for social affairs and culture said that this series of activities will allow residents, “especially young people”, to know “the history of“ war " anti-japanese ”while“ vigorously the concept of peace ”is promoted.
"It is necessary to guide the population of Macao to support with concrete actions to the country's peacekeeping policies and actively spread the culture of peace of China to the outside world," the secretary said in the speech given yesterday, acknowledging that the history of China should be told in the construction of a community of common destination for humanity in the New Age. "
Thus, on September 3, the central government authorities will hold a ceremony at Tiananmen Square in Beijing, including a military arrest, and the Government of MSAR will organize a group of young people to watch the broadcast and hear the speech of Xi Jinping so that they can “feel the impact of the greatness of the nation and military power and share the honor of being Chinese”.
Between the end of August and September, an exhibition related to the theme in the complex of the commercial cooperation platform between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries will also be held. In schools, didactic materials will be shown on the subject and local associations will be encouraged to commemorate the occasion through shows, fairs and exhibitions, for example.
Kong Chi Meng, director of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), also promised to “deepen, in many ways, the knowledge of young students about the history of the War of Resistance” and “cultivate patriotic sentiment”.
The official also said that a package of complementary teaching materials will be launched for elementary and secondary students, in order to deepen and expand the teaching of history ”, while schools will be encouraged to perform educational activities. DSEDJ also wants to deepen the exchange mechanisms to allow young people from Macau to visit the historical facilities and places of war inside China.
Authorities want to "use history as a mirror": "Remember ancestors, not forget the difficulties, value peace and convey the spirit of resistance of the Chinese people."</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities avoided 192 cases of scam in the first three months of the year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/autoridades-evitaram-192-casos-de-burla-nos-primeiros-tres-meses-do-ano/</link><description>In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Song Pek Kei, the Secretary for Security's Office says that between January and March, the authorities were able to prevent 192 cases of slopping involving about 30 million patacas. The Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM), Unit Police Services (SPU) and the Judiciary Police (PJ) ensure that they are collaborating with the financial sector and electronic payment applications in reinforcing anti-bullshit mechanisms, while seeking to expand the range of awareness campaigns.
 
In the first quarter of 2025, the Judiciary Police (PJ) prevented 192 cases of scams that, in total, involved an amount of about 30 million patacas. The data are contained in a document signed by Chang Cheong, the Secretary's Chief of Staff for Security, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Song Pek Kei.
The deputy's questioning, issued in May, warned of the growth of cyber burla crimes in Macao and increasingly large damage to victims of these “traps”, common on electronic payment platforms such as Alipay or Wechat. “Computer Burla criminal groups are increasingly organized and hidden,” said Song Pek Kei, noting that the “convenience of the Macao financial system” makes the region particularly attractive to the convergence of criminal organizations.
In the first point of the question, the deputy questioned the government regarding the point of situation of the Burla Control mechanism imposed on the financial sector by the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM), in the most recent update of “Directive on Electronic Banking Risk Management”. In the response of Chang Cheong-issued after the hell of the Unit Police Services (SPU), the Judicial Police (PJ) and AMCM-it is currently “required” to financial institutions that implement procedures for monitoring circumstances and providing appropriate training for employees, so that they can be informed of “evolution” and “trends” of the schemes of the schemes and trends of the schemes. fraudulent.
The cooperation of AMCM and PJ with the financial institutions of Macao and the electronic payment platforms resulted in the implementation of “various tracking and recovery measures”, says the chief of staff, citing recent data. If, in 2024, the authorities avoided 597 cases of slopping, referring to about 110 million patacas, in the first trimester of Macao alone 192 burlas, involving about 30 million patacas, have already been made.
According to Chang Cheong, "several local banks have created models for identifying and monitoring" suspected cases based on PJ information provided by PJ, which has resulted in "a climb on the number of suspended and impeached transactions for suspicion of involvement in circumvents." In order to reinforce this measure, PJ and various electronic payment platforms also contributed to the creation of a “direct and fast notification mechanism”, which allows suspicious accounts to be freeze immediately or that reveal irregular activity.
 
90% of the 2024 financial inquiries were associated with slogans
 
Deputy Song Pek Kei's second point was related to the need to expand the coverage of awareness campaigns, extending them to sectors such as tourism and leisure and hospitality. On this topic, the Secretary for Security's Office emphasizes that “PJ is committed to reinforcing cooperation with various sectors to promote the prevention of slops”, taking into account the specific characteristics of each. So far, authorities have created 21 communication groups with different sectors, such as game, restoration and public transport, where they disseminate "the latest anti-beast information to the professionals involved."
In the third and final point of his questioning, Song Pek Kei was urged the reinforcement “of the prevention and investigation” capacity of computer science and money laundering crimes in Macao, while appealing to safeguarding the “security of public goods”. Regarding this point, AMCM said that, in addition to seminars about combating capital laundering, it maintains a line of communication with the financial sector in which it issues advice and guidance on response measures to be adopted. Also the SPU's financial information office said it often conducts training actions for different sectors, in collaboration with "the regulatory authorities of industries and non -financial professions."
The PJ, in turn, has ensured that it has increased the capacity to combat this type of crime - namely, through “parallel financial investigations” and cooperation with the China, Hong Kong and other countries. Police intercooperation has already allowed, for example, "to resolve several cases in which they used (…) telecommunications, jewelery and cryptocurrency stores to whiten the money obtained through burlas." The reinforcement of the PJ's investigation capacity had an impact on last year's numbers: by 2024, police launched 93 inquiries within the parallel financial investigation, double those recorded in 2023. More than 90% of these cases were associated with burla crimes.
Chang Cheong also recalls that the recently up -to -date PJ Bond Coordination Center has already allowed the dismantling of "two hiders of criminals located in homes, where the fraudulent so -called". It is recalled that, last May, PJ inaugurated a modernized version of this Coordination Center, which is already fully operational after an experimental period. The center's latest structure, originally conceived in the second half of 2022 and updated in April 2023, includes more advanced facilities and technologies designed to sensitize the public regarding the potentialities of artificial intelligence.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:55:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping Felicita Mozambique for the 50 years of Independence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/xi-jinping-felicita-mocambique-pelos-50-anos-da-independencia/</link><description>The president of China sent a congratulations to his Mozambican counterpart, Daniel Chapo, for the 50 years of national independence. Xi Jinping praised, among others, the historical ties of friendship, confidence and mutual support between the two countries.
 
China President Xi Jinping yesterday sent a congratulation message to his Mozambican counterpart, Daniel Chapo, for the 50 years of national independence, according to a statement from the presidency of Mozambique.
In the message, the head of state conveyed, on behalf of the government and the Chinese people, “the sincere congratulations and the best compliments” to the government and people of the African country, read in the statement.
The President of the Popular Republic of China praised, among others, the historical ties of friendship, confidence and mutual support between the two countries. "Since the establishment of diplomatic relations for 50 years, despite changes in the international situation, China and Mozambique have always maintained confidence and mutual support, and have enjoyed a solid friendship like a rock," he says in the document, which quotes the message.
Explaining that the date also symbolizes the 50 years of China-Mozambique cooperation, Xi Jinping highlighted the importance of cooperation relations between countries, expressing their “commitment” and availability to work to strengthen these ties.
For the Chinese leader, “the anniversary” of diplomatic relations between the two nations symbolizes a new starting point “to reinforce traditional friendship, deepen mutual benefit cooperation in initiatives such as high quality belt and route cooperation and the China-Africa Cooperation Forum (FOCAC)”, building in partnership a new chapter of the global strategic cooperation partnership.
Mozambique celebrates the 50 years of independence, with the main ceremony in Maputo, directed by the President of the Republic, Daniel Chapo, and with the presence of several heads of state, including the Portuguese, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, Samia Suhulu, as guest of honor, Guinea-Bissau, Umro Sissoco Embaló, Emmerson Mnangagwa.
The central ceremonies, which took place at noon yesterday, took place in the historic stadium of Machava, which changed designation to the National Independence Stadium, where the first president of the country, Samora Machel, proclaimed independence at the early hours of June 25, 1975, after a fight against the Portuguese colonial regime that began on September 25, 1964.
In addition to the official speech of the President of the Republic, the ceremony included military parades, cultural moments, a message from the representatives of the 50 -year -old citizens. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:16</pubDate></item><item><title>United States and China exchange accusations about influence in Latin America</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/estados-unidos-e-china-trocam-acusacoes-sobre-influencia-na-america-latina/</link><description>The United States and China held a harsh exchange of arguments on the influence of external actors in Latin America during the General Assembly of the Organization of American States (OAS), held in Antigua and Barbuda.
The inflamed moment occurred during the dialogue between the OAS Member States, including the United States, and the organization's permanent observers, such as China, the EFE agency reported.
US representative, Michael Kozak, emphasized, not to directly mention Beijing, that all observers who contribute to OAS funds must “respect the principles” of the Inter -American Democratic Charter. "We will oppose all the efforts of any member or observer who seeks to use financial contributions to undermine reforms or weaken democracy in the Americas," he said.
The American also warned of “the persistent threat represented by evil external actors who manipulate governance, migration and information”, with the aim of distorting the historical priorities of the OAS. “We are clear about who is responsible for this chaos,” said Washington's delegate in a clear allusion to China.
Minutes earlier, Chinese representative Xie Feng had advocated the cooperation model promoted by his country and highlighted the five programs announced by President XI Jinping in May after the ministerial meeting between China and the Latin American and Caribbean states (Celac).
Xie Feng reiterated that China seeks to build a community with Latin America and the Caribbean with “a promising future” without hidden agendas, and rejected any external attempt to prevent this objective. "We have no geopolitical calculations. We do not attack third parties, so our cooperation must be exempt from external interference," he said, also not directly mentioning the United States.
The Panama Channel has been one of the focuses of disputes between the two superpowers, as one of the first actions of Donald Trump's new administration was to press Panama to limit the presence of Chinese companies in port management and to detach themselves from Beijing's track and route initiative.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:16</pubDate></item><item><title>China receives ministers from the defense of Iran and Russia for multilateral meeting</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/china-recebe-ministros-da-defesa-do-irao-e-da-russia-para-reuniao-multilateral/</link><description>China yesterday received the Ministers of Defense of Iran and Russia, at a meeting of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization (OCS), which occurs after the NATO summit, which dictated the increase of European military spending. This meeting in Qingdao, a coastal city in eastern China, happens after the entry into force on Tuesday of a ceasefire between Israel and Iran-an OCS member country.
The event also occurs a day after a summit of the leaders of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) in The Hague, where members agreed to increase their defense spending, according to the demands of US President Donald Trump.
Chinese Defense Minister Dong Jun presented yesterday the meeting in Qingdao, which houses an important Chinese naval base, as a counterweight in a world that suffers from growing "chaos and instability." "The most crucial changes in one century are accelerating, unilateralism and protectionism are increasing," said Dong Jun on Wednesday, in the presence of Russian defense ministers, Iran, Pakistan, Belarus and other countries, according to the Xinhua official news agency. "The hegemonic, dominators and intimidating acts severely impair the international order," he said, appealing to his counterparts to "act more vigorously to collectively safeguard the environment conducive to peaceful development."
Beijing has long been looking for OCS, which has ten members, such as a counterweight to the United States Allied Blocks, encouraging, namely, political, security, commercial and scientific collaboration.
Indian Defense Minister Rajnath Singh, also present in Qingdao, said OCS members should "collectively aspire to fulfill the desires and expectations" of peoples and "face the current challenges." "The world we live in is undergoing a drastic transformation. Globalization, which has once approached us, is losing its momentum," he said through his office on the social network.
On the sidelines of a meeting with his Chinese counterpart, Russian Defense Minister Andreï BeloousSov greeted relations with China, who reached an “unprecedented level”. "Friendly relationships between our countries maintain a dynamic of upward development in all directions," he said.
China officially presents itself as a neutral in the face of Ukraine's Russian invasion, but several allied Kiev governments consider that Beijing provides Moscow to crucial economic and diplomatic support.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese Culture in Macau II - Toponymy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/cultura-portuguesa-em-macau-ii-toponimia/</link><description>More than a sign, a symbol of culture and art. Such is the toponymy of Macau, which materializes in a panel consisting of glazed tiles, with a total of thirty centimeters in height and sixty long, true to the genuine shades of blue and white present in Portuguese tiles.
In it cohabit the name of the street in Chinese and Portuguese. However, the Chinese characters do not always correspond to what is read in Portuguese. In Rua do Padre António, for example, the translation of the Chinese characters means Rua dos Antigos buildings, and the famous Almeida Ribeiro Avenue, known in Chinese by San Ma Lou, translated into Portuguese would be Nova dos Cavalos Street.
According to the latest data issued by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) there are 21 streets in Macao with the name of Chinese personalities, 47 with names of Santos and 222 honoring foreign personalities, including Portuguese.
With a tone of curiosity, my heart warms me to know that the largest street in Macau is the Avenida de Friendship, which gains immeasurable proportions in the well-being and everyday immigrants and that, at a personal level and in mode of outburst, I estimate that it lasts mutually in the West/East relationship.
My routine of tasks and weekly needs leads me to circulate through the late street of Coimbra, where it is coincidentally allowed to enjoy a toast in Portuguese bread accompanied by a sock of milk, who know the house. Sporadically, as a norm between serpentous shortcuts in order to fick the chaotic traffic, the discreet Rua da Figueira is responsible for my nostalgic smile when I can visually project the image of the extensive sand and the good trip silhouette on the blind facades of the old and humble dwellings that characterize the street.
More than a simple sign, the toponymy of Macao perpetuates the memory of culture, Portuguese ancestors and our origins.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Foreign trade records deficit of 9 billion in May, despite the 2.3% increase in exports</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/comercio-externo-regista-defice-de-9-mil-milhoes-em-maio-apesar-do-aumento-de-23-nas-exportacoes/</link><description>The most recent data released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services reveal a distinct evolution in the territory foreign trade during May, with export growth and decrease in imports.
In the month in question, the value of exported goods reached 1.06 billion patacas, representing an increase of 2.3% compared to the same month of the previous year. On the other hand, imports registered a 4.5%break, totaling 10.05 billion patacas. Consequently, the May trade deficit settled at 9 billion patacas.
In the first five months of the year, foreign trade totaled 56.36 billion patacas, a 4.7%reduction compared to the same period of 2024. Of these, 5.67 billion patacas corresponded to exports, with an increase of 2.3%, while imports totaled 50.69 billion patacas, having decreased 5.5%. The deficit accumulated during this period was 45.02 billion patacas, a reduction of 3.05 billion compared to the same interval of 2024.
Re -exports reached 945 million patacas, growing 4.6% over the same month of the previous year. The significant increase of 239.4% in re-exports of casino articles is highlighted. However, articles such as footwear and beauty products recorded breaks of 33.6% and 25.8%, respectively. Domestic export, in turn, fell 13.6%, reaching 112 million patacas, with descents in copper sectors and pharmaceutical products.
In the analysis by destinations, exports to the Hong Kong region and the United States grew 12.2%and 7.4%, respectively, in the first five months of 2025. Already markets in China, countries of 'one track, one route' and European Union recorded 5.3%, 69.7%and 25.5%. As for the products, we highlight the textiles and clothing, which grew 5.9%, and non-textile products, with an increase of 1.9%.
Regarding imports, the values ​​from the European Union, the interior of China and a track, a route ’decreased 7.6%, 2.5%and 3.9%, respectively. On the other hand, imports from Japan grew 4.5%, reaching 3.77 billion. At the level of consumer goods, there was a 5.2%reduction, especially the decrease in imports of clothing, shoes and gold jewelery.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Joey Lao Ahead of Jiangmen list in the legislatures, Zheng Anting and Lo Choi in are left out</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/joey-lao-a-frente-da-lista-de-jiangmen-nas-legislativas-zheng-anting-e-lo-choi-in-ficam-de-fora/</link><description>Joey Lao, former deputy appointed at the time of Chui Sai On, will join the electoral race for the direct suffrage of this year's legislatures. With the departure of Zheng Anting and Lo Choi In-Two current deputies who are part of the Jiangmen community in Hemiciclo, Joey Lao takes the lead of the “Union of Macau-Guangdong” list.
 
Former deputy Joey Lao can see his return to the Legislative Assembly as a head of the Macau-Guangdong Union list, linked to the Jiangmen community. In this context, the current deputies Zheng Anting and Lo Choi in will be out of Hemiciclo in the next legislature, as they do not re -run the next elections scheduled for September.
Yesterday was the last day for the lists to present the candidacies to the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) and the political program. The Macau-Guangdong Union list is among the eight lists with a directly admitted candidacy commission, being the last one that formalized the candidacy. The list consists of 14 elements, including group leader Joey Lao, number two Lee Koi Ian, as well as NG NGA Fan and Law Iam Leong.
Joey Lao was a deputy between 2017 and 2021 under the appointment of the then Chief Chui Sai on. Among other positions, he is president of the Board of the Macao Economic Association and a member of the Harbin Political Advisory Conference.
Already the number two on the list, Lee Koi Ian, is a member of the Provincial Guangdong Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) and is head of the SEG FUNG JOBAL CHAIN.
Lee Koi Ian also directs the Macao Youth Entrepreneurs Association, an organization linked to the Macao Youth Federation, which was founded by several public figures such as Chui Sai Cheong, Tina Ho, Kou Hoi In and Chan Meng Kam, whose current president is Alvis Lo, director of health services.
 
Team with guys
 
During the presentation of the list and political program, the agent of the list Chan Sio Cheng, president of the Macao Kong Mun (Jiangmen) countryman Association, said he hopes to create a “new atmosphere” in the team with a new members of members.
Joey Lao, in statements to the newspaper or Mun, stressed that the team's candidacy aims to fight for "greater happiness" to Macau and will request and help the government to make Macau's economy "more dynamic." In concrete, the economist considers that the executive should study the increase in pension to the elderly through a mechanism of binding the pension to the value of social risk. "At the same time, to encourage the governments of Guangdong and Macao to allow the elderly to receive medical treatment, pension and subsidy for the elderly while living in the cities of China in the Great Bay," he said.
Joey Lao added that the team's work will focus on economic development, population welfare, cooperation between Macau and Guangdong, governance and youth development.
Lee Koi Ian, in turn, stressed that the government must be even more attentive to the community economy and the financial difficulties of citizens. "Being a businessman and entrepreneur, I understand the difficulties and weaknesses of the business environment of Macau and I hope that the government can introduce more measures to revitalize the economy and help small and medium enterprises," he said. He also asked the government's effort to improve the environment and landscape of old neighborhoods to bring more tourists to consume in these neighborhoods.
The number three on the list, NG NGA Fan, also deputy secretary of Macao's Sustadement Alliance and Economics, said he will be dedicated to the scope of youth development in terms of the study, employment and entrepreneurship of young people.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:53:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Candidates will be analyzed by the State Security Defense Commission by July 15</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/candidatos-vao-ser-analisados-pela-comissao-de-defesa-da-seguranca-do-estado-ate-15-de-julho/</link><description>After the deadline for the presentation of the candidacies and the political program to the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), the lists will now be scrutinized by the State Security Defense Commission by July 15.
It is up to this Commission to “determine whether candidates defend the Basic Law and are faithful to the Special Administrative Region of Macao of the Popular Republic of China, as well as issuing a binding opinion to Caeal on the verification of uncomfortable,” explains the authorities.
These legislative elections, which result on September 14, will be the first after the revision of the Electoral Law to the Legislative Assembly (AL), which provides for the removal of candidates considered by the authorities as being insufficiently “patriotic”, without appeal. The new law also provides for the criminalization of incitement to abstention.
A total of eight lists presented their 14 -seat candidacy in the hemiciclo intended for deputies elected by the Direct, which constitutes a significant decrease compared to previous suffrage. In the 2021 elections, for example, 19 lists were initially formalized, and five of them did not go to votes after Caeal disqualified dozens of pro-democracy wing candidates.
In the context of the indirect elections, Caeal received six candidacies, more than in the 2021 elections.
It is recalled that, in addition to the 14 seats in the hemiciclo for deputies elected by direct suffrage, that is, by all certified residents, there are also 12 places in AL to deputies elected by indirect route, that is, by a restricted number of associative leaders linked to certain sectors. In addition to these, there is still place for seven deputies appointed by the chief executive.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:13</pubDate></item><item><title>First case of “space oil” trafficking after revision of the drug law</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/detectado-primeiro-caso-de-trafico-de-petroleo-espacial-apos-revisao-da-lei-de-droga/</link><description>The Judicial Police detected the first case of “spatial oil”, Ethomidate, a substance that was included in the control list after the recent change in the drug law. A man of Vietnamese nationality was arrested, who would have sold the ethomidate to the countrymen for the last three weeks. In a home search of the suspect, police found 635 grams of ethomidate, valued at 37,000 patacas in the market.
 
The first case of drug trafficking linked to ethomidate was detected, a substance commonly known as “spatial oil”, after the entry into force on Tuesday of the amendment of the prohibition of production, trafficking and illicit consumption of narcotic and psychotropic substances.
The Judicial Police (PJ) announced yesterday the detention of a 25 -year -old man of Vietnamese nationality on suspicion of drug trafficking. During the police operation, police seized a total of 635.6 grams of “space oil”, including the weight of the containers, in an estimated market value of 37,000 patacas.
At a press conference yesterday, the authorities released the case and said they identified the man involved “based on information and investigations”, and carried out the operation at 11 pm on Wednesday, having detained the suspect in his home in the central zone.
During the home search, the PJ found several bottles of different sizes, which will have been used as ethomidate containers, which were stored in the room, on the building's stairs, as well as in the mailbox on the building's floor. Electronic cigarettes and their cartridges were also seized, and a large number of packaging instruments. "It was confirmed that the equipment contained Ethomidate after we do quick tests," he said.
The PJ indicated that the man began working in Macau, as a non-resident worker in the area of ​​warehouse management, four years ago. The individual refused to cooperate in the investigation, but the PJ said he determined that the detainee was devoted to the sale of “space oil” three weeks ago, and customers mainly countrymen. According to police, the man also sold the drug in the central zone, charging 1,000 patacas for each small bottle.
Authorities will still investigate whether the man is also a drug consumer, especially ethomidate, as well as the number of customers who have already made the purchase, and their source of importation of narcotics. The detainee was yesterday sent to the prosecutor.
 
Test in three minutes
 
Yesterday the International Day against Drug Abuse and Trafficking was signaled. At the opening ceremony of the drug fight week campaign, Sit Chong Meng, director of the PJ, said the body has already acquired new drug test equipment earlier this year, introducing new rapid tests of ethomidate. The official explained that the test can be completed in three minutes and that in order to respect human rights, the work of the testing would be done as much as possible in the police squads.
Sit Chong Meng reiterated that police have been concerned about the situation of ethomidate trafficking in schools and the community. It is recalled that the substance was eventually subject to control under the drug law whose change was passed later this month.
The PJ spokesman recalled that from 2023 to last Tuesday, five cases were recorded in which substances containing ethomidate were detected, four of them were processed due to simultaneous detection of other controlled substances, and one case in which traces of ethomidate in electronic cigarettes were found. The official added that the smoking control law was reviewed in 2022, and that it was “effective” to control the circulation of electronic cigarettes in Macao.
In his speech given at the event, Sit Chong Meng indicated that the number of drug -related cases has kept low in the last decade, and that PJ will continue to work in the fight against the drug, especially among younger groups. According to Sit Chong Meng, between 2014 and 2024, the number of drugs and toxicodependencies has shown a decreasing trend, with 94 cases of drug trafficking and 111 cases of drug use in 2014, and 49 cases of trafficking and 15 cases of drug use last year were recorded. The data represent a significant decrease of 52% in cases of drug trafficking, as well as a 87% reduction in cases of narcotic consumption within 10 years.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:54:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice of Hong Kong evaluates appeal from first journalist convicted of sedition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/justica-de-hong-kong-avalia-recurso-de-primeiro-jornalista-condenado-por-sedicao/</link><description>Hong Kong's court will look at a appeal in September of the first journalist sentenced to the prison sentence under the law of sedition. The hearing was requested by Patrick Lam Shiu-Tung, former Stand News's interim wording chief.
 
Hong Kong's court will look at an appeal by the first journalist sentenced to the prison sentence under a law of sedition, the press of the former British colony yesterday advanced.
According to the Hong Kong Free Press news portal, the Court of Appeal marked the hearing requested by Patrick Lam Shiu-Tung, former Stand News' interim writing head.
The Stand News News Portal closed doors in December 2021 after a police operation involving 200 police, the company's freezing and the detention of the board, including Patrick Lam.
Last October, Lam filed an appeal of the conviction, a month earlier, to 14 months in prison, the first sentence against a journalist under an established sedition law when Hong Kong was an ancient British colony. The return to Chinese rule took place in 1997.
Although the first instance considered Lam guilty, the chief of writing came out of freedom due to health issues and for already fulfilling 10 months in custody.
Defense lawyer, Audrey Eu Yuet-Mee, presented in court medical reports that indicated that Lam had a rare disease that left him less than 30% of the renal function.
Also in September, the same court sentenced the former Stand News editorial chief, Chung Pui-Kuen, to 21 months in prison by sedition.
Judge Kwok Wai-Kin considered Chung and conspiracy to publish and reproduce seditious materials, along with Best Pencil (Hong Kong) Ltd, the company that owned Stand News.
While reading the sentence, the magistrate stated that the defendants were not true journalists.
The trial, which began in October 2022, lasted about 50 days, and the verdict was postponed several times for reasons that included waiting for the result of an appeal in another historical case of sedition.
The end of the stand News occurred months after the disappearance of the pro-democracy newspaper Apple Daily, whose founder, Jimmy Lai Chee-Ying, is detained on charges of collusion under the harsh national security law imposed by Beijing in 2020.
Hong Kong is ranked 140th among 180 territories in the world's press release index of reporters without borders for 2025, while occupying 80th position in 2021 and 18th in 2002.
In March 2024, the city government enacted another new security law that raised concerns about a greater restriction on press freedom. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Contemporary War: new characteristics and implications</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/guerra-contemporanea-novas-caracteristicas-e-implicacoes/</link><description>Since the terrorist sequestration of aircraft in the World Trade Center attack on September 11, 2001, the contemporary war in the world has taken on some new forms that seem to shape how wars will be conducted in the coming decades.
Firstly, a hybrid type of war, as mentioned by some analysts, emerged as the most prominent feature of contemporary wars. Specifically, the hybrid war combines the ingredients of guerrilla tactics, terrorism, spying, infiltration, information collection, precise planning and execution, high technology use, mobilization of a large number of drones, cyber attacks, and ballistic missile launch. Hamas' action by attacking Israel, for example, presented a number of characteristics, including the use of parachutes to attack the civilian population, the infiltration of terrorists into enemy territory and the kidnapping and murder of civilians. In response, Israel's armed forces have adopted hard -line and cleaning tactics, penetrating militarily in Gaza, using missiles and other conventional weapons, accompanied by the total elimination of all underground and arsenal bunkers hidden in Gaza.
In the war between Russia and Ukraine, the Russian Armed Forces attacked Ukraine performing first cybercings against enemy targets and using ballistic missiles, traditional tanks and army. In response, Ukraine has adopted ballistic missiles to defend its territory and attack enemy targets, using surprise attacks in the Kursk region and mobilizing drones in a recent SpiderWeb operation to destroy Russian military aircraft after a successful infiltration of these deadly weapons in Russian territories.
The most recent and ongoing war between Israel and Iran has been characterized by Israel's precise goal of eliminating important military leaders and essential scientists and the use of ballistic missiles to destroy all enemies accurately. In response, Iran has used transnational ballistic missiles and transf by retaliation of Israelite attacks. The most prominent feature of the war ongoing between Israel and Iran is that Israel has adopted a preventive attack on military leaders and top scientists in Iran, due to its assessment that Iran has enriched uranium to a point where it is very close to producing nuclear bombs. As Israel realized Iran as a "real" military threat to the survival of its state, the preventive attack was considered "necessary".
These conflicts illustrate the growing complexity and ambiguity of modern battlefields, where boundaries between combatants and non -combatants, state and non -state actors and physical and digital fronts are diffuse. Arsenal available for both sides in contemporary war is no longer limited to conventional weapons or traditional military hierarchy; On the contrary, it covers a network of strategies and technologies aimed at disturbing, demoralizing and destabilizing opponents at various levels. The effectiveness of such approaches is demonstrated by the unpredictability of results, the speed of climbing and the deep psychological impacts on both military personnel and civil populations.
In addition, technology has democratized and radicalized war tools, allowing smaller groups or even individuals to bring asymmetrical campaigns against much larger opponents. The proliferation of cheap drones, encrypted communications, and cyber abilities has made it possible for non -state actors to influence the course of unprecedented conflicts. This scenario requires that states and the Armed Forces adapt quickly, learning not only how to defend themselves against these multifaceted threats, but also how to anticipate the next evolution in hybrid tactics.
At the same time, the information space became a vital conflict theater. Disinformation, advertising, spying and psychological operations are used as precision as ballistic missiles, aiming at the perceptions, morals and cohesion of societies far from the front line. Social networking platforms, news cycles and digital communications are used as weapons to shape narratives, justify actions and obscure atrocities, making truth itself a contested and volatile.
Secondly, proxy wars can be seen as another new feature of contemporary war. The best example is Ukraine, which was seen by Russia as a US proxy under the Biden administration and the US -led Western allies, including NATO members. The change in US foreign policy regarding Russia and Ukraine shortly after Donald Trump's second presidential victory in early 2025 offered, curiously, an opportunity for a peaceful resolution of the Russian-Ukrainian war, which, however, is deeply affected not only by the maximum demands made by the Russian side, but also by the anxieties of European states, notably France, United Kingdom and Germany, that excessive concessions made to Russia by the Trump administration will be a zero -sum or a detrimental agreement to the interests of Ukraine and NATO members. The Challenge of the Russian-Ucranian War is whether both sides are willing to make concessions so that a proxy war does not turn into a large-scale war, dragging more NATO members to an extensive war that spreads throughout Europe.
Thirdly, a hidden ideological division is behind the contemporary war. The war between Russia and Ukraine is strongly shaped behind the scenes by a serious ideological division between Western capitalist democracies and non -western authoritarianism. NATO, led by the West, still sees Russia as a state parallel to the former Soviet Union, with the real territorial ambition to restore the territories of the Soviet Empire, while Russia is supported by non -western authoritarian states, namely North Korea and also China. North Korea even sent 12,000 military soldiers and officers to help Russia repel the Ukrainian offensive in Kursk, while China has been seen by the US and its allies as a supplier of 'double -use' goods, beneficial not only for civil use, but also for military logistics supplies in Russia. Although China has denied civil and military goods to Russia, Moscow seems to deal very well with the economic sanctions of Western states thanks to their harmonious economic relations with Beijing. Moscow's close economic and military partnership with North Korea also alarmed the US and its allies in Europe.
On the other hand, the ideological struggles between China and the Allies led by the US, namely the Philippines, can be seen in the disputes on some reefs and islands in the southern China Sea. The Philippines resorted to international legal arbitration, whose result, however, was rejected by China. Although so far China and the Philippines have managed their territorial disputes relatively peacefully and skillful, using their maritime ships, the policy of superpowers is behind the scenes with ideological inclinations. Specifically, the Philippines are ideological and militarily supported by the US and Japan, which have perceived the military rise and the modernization of China as a "real" threat to American and Japanese national interests. Fortunately, so far, territorial disputes and maritime conflicts between China and the Philippines over the southern China Sea reefs have not yet degenerated at war.
The Asia Pacific region has been relatively peaceful so far, but the recent three-day war between India and Pakistan, which suddenly discussed and fought conflicts about Caxemira, surprised many observers. Although India and China have reached a peaceful consensus, removing their military forces from the regions disputed after a series of high -level military negotiations between the two parts of their border disputes, the sudden outbreak of war, though very short, between Pakistan and India showed the fragility of peace between the two regional powers of southern Asia.
Fourthly, the contemporary war is taking on other new forms, including commercial and tariff wars, technological war (control of semiconductor production technology export), resource war (rare land export control) and war control war (the Panama channel, where the US have sought to restrict the capacity of any China -related companies, such as C. K. Hutchinson, to manage ports).
This extensive and unconventional contemporary war in the world has been mainly observed due to the difficult transition from a US -led unipolar world to a perhaps multipolar world, in which both hard power and US power are declining in the face of the rapid growth of countries like China, Iran, North Korea and Pakistan, which have developed capacity or almost ability to produce nuclear weapons. Israel, as an ally near the US, realized, as mentioned earlier, the almost capacity of Iran to produce nuclear weapons as a "real" threat, especially since Israel is a small state compared to Iran. The US, under the administration of Donald Trump, see China as the main enemy, whose economic ascension should be contained, whose US students should be selected and whose expansion of infrastructures and expansion and Economic aid to other parts of the world have been seen as a geopolitical threat to national interests and the global rule of Washington.
Fortunately, contemporary war in the world is now confined to some regions, such as Ukraine, Israel and Iran, without spreading to more countries in Europe and the Middle East, not to mention Asia, where Asian states have managed their conflicts very well and relatively tolerantly. Still, a third world war should be avoided and, unfortunately, is approaching whether contemporary war is not managed with skill and diplomacy.
A key factor that contributes to temporary world peace in the midst of the regional war is the use of diplomacy. China's recent economic and military rise has been accompanied by the widespread use of diplomacy to deal with territorial and economic disputes with other countries. Diplomacy is still an important factor that helps the world to maintain relative peace, such as the efforts of the United Kingdom, France and Germany to act as intermediaries between Iran and Israel and to act as brakes and counterweights against US oscillations, which can change to protect Russian interests more than Ukrainian interests in the war between Russia and Ukraine. China has also advocated the importance of multilateralism, in which international organizations, such as the UN and others, still play a crucial role by appealing to the parties to conflict to end war and continue dialogue and negotiations. At a time when the US has shown signs of distrust in international organizations in resolving disputes between state, China has been curiously adopted a much more liberal approach to dealing with international relations. As such, world peace is still maintained, perhaps because emerging powers, such as China and Iran, are still open to the use of diplomacy to deal with international conflicts and disputes.
In conclusion, the contemporary war in the 21st century is now characterized by the hybrid nature of the war, combining guerrilla tactics, terrorism, spying, infiltration, intensive collection of information, high -tech use, drone mobilization, cybers and ballistic missile launch. The contemporary war is also punctuated by proxy wars with a high degree of ideological struggles and behind -the -scenes disputes. She has also taken on new ways, notably business and tariff war, high -tech war, energy war and resources, and the war control war in the world. Fortunately, the emphasis on diplomacy and trust in multilateralism, in which different nations and states try to solve their differences through dialogue and negotiations, and through meetings and discussions in international organizations, remain the two pillars that prevent contemporary war from deteriorating even more, becoming a large-scale war around the world. In this sense, the new global security paradigm must recognize that deterrent is no longer only military, but also economic, informative and diplomatic. Peace, therefore, becomes an active process that requires patience, ingenuity and multilateral cooperation sustained between regions and domains. We hope that international diplomacy and organizations, within the ideology of multilateralism, will bring and bring continuous world peace, which is now quite fragile due to the difficult and precarious transition from the previously led unipolar world after the collapse of the former Soviet Union to a more uncertain multipolar world, in which many new emerging powers are challenging US hegemony and their national interests and national interests Allies, not only economically, but also military and politically.
Looking to the future, the evolutionary scenario of global conflicts requires a reformulation of traditional security structures and the cultivation of resilient but ironically more fluid alliances that value diplomacy over wars and conflicts. The growing interdependence of economies and technological infrastructures means that the chain effects of any regional war can be felt far beyond the immediate theater of operations, affecting everything from supply chains to energy markets and even food safety. This interconnectivity amplifies the risks of local disputes, making careful balance between hard power and mild power essential to prevent contemporary war from becoming another world war.
Moreover, as emerging technologies - such as artificial intelligence, autonomous weapons systems, and quantum communications - they reach the battlefield, there is an urgent need for new standards and agreements to regulate their use. The absence of clear international standards increases the risk of unwanted calculation errors and consequences, especially as states and non -state actors run to explore these advances for strategic gains. The rapid pace of innovation challenges diplomatic institutions to follow, creating an urgent need for dialogue between technologists, political decision makers and military leaders. The so -called rules -based order has been contested, especially since these rules are seen as determined by hegemonic states and their followers in the past. Perhaps a great challenge for the states of the world is, on the one hand, respect and follow the rules that have been agreed and, on the other, update, revise and refine the rules that present gaps and controversial areas.
Ultimately, the future of conflict management will depend on the will of all states of the world to accept differences and complexities, promote adaptability and persist in dialogue and negotiations. Thus, diplomacy remains not only a crisis management tool, but a proactive force for stability and hope in a world increasingly defined by constant uncertainties and conflicts.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese exports to Lusophone countries reach a new record until May</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/exportacoes-chinesas-para-os-paises-lusofonos-atingem-novo-recorde-ate-maio/</link><description>Chinese exports to Portuguese -speaking countries had the best performance ever for the period under analysis, increasing 1.6% in the first five months, compared to an equal period of 2024, according to official data released yesterday. According to information from China's customs services, goods sold to Lusophone markets until May reached $ 34.6 billion. This is the highest value for the first five months of one year since the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (Macao Forum) began presenting this data in 2013.
The data released reveal that the main reason for the new record was Angola, whose imports from China rose 72.6%to $ 2.32 billion. Still, and despite a 1.9%homologous decrease, Brazil remains by far the largest buyer in the Lusophone bloc, with Chinese China goods to be close to $ 28 billion. Second on the list, ahead of Angola, comes Portugal, which bought products in the amount of $ 2.71 billion, 6.2% more than in the first five months of 2024. In the opposite direction, exports from Portuguese -speaking countries to China fell 18.5% between January and May 2025, compared to the same period last year.
The Lusófono block sold goods worth $ 47.6 billion to the Chinese market, the lowest value for the first five months of one year since 2020 at the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic. The descent was mainly due to the largest Lusophone supplier in the Chinese market, Brazil, whose sales fell more than one fifth (21.3%) to $ 38.4 billion and the second largest Chinese commercial partner in the Lusophone bloc, Angola, saw exports decrease $ 3.5% to $ 6.91 billion. Similarly, Portugal's sales sales to China decreased by 7.1%to $ 1.15 billion. On the contrary, Mozambique exports rose 12.2%to $ 720 million. Equatorial Guinea exports to the Chinese market dropped more than a quarter (26.7%) to $ 379.3 million. Almost all Portuguese-speaking countries saw China's goods to shrink in the first five months of 2025, including Timor-Leste (less 3.1%) and Cape Verde (less 82.5%). In addition to Mozambique, São Tomé and Principe was exception, with exports to the Chinese market that more than quadrupled, but without exceeding $ 15,000. Guinea-Bissau did not sell any products to China.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Court rejects detention order against former President Yoon</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/27/tribunal-rejeita-ordem-de-detencao-contra-ex-presidente-yoon/</link><description>A court of Seoul yesterday rejected a prosecutor's request to stop former South Korean President Yoon Suk-Youol for alleged obstruction to the court, under the investigation of the martial law he declared in December last year.
The South Korea Public Prosecution Service explained that the court rejected the request because Yoon had expressed willingness to appear before the authorities, which is why he was summoned next Saturday. "If he does not attend, we will consider requesting a formal arrest warrant," the prosecutors said.
Special Prosecutor Cho Eun-Suk, appointed by South Korean President Lee Jae-Myung, took over the case a week after Parliament approved an independent investigation into events in early December 2024, when Yoon declared a short-term martial law.
The request for the detention warrant is motivated that Yoon has not responded to three calls made this month to witness, in the context of the investigation on various accusations of insurrection.
Yoon is accused of obstructing a warrant of detention issued in early January against him after decreing the martial law and having ordered the presidential security service to erase the telephone records of three commanders after the failure of their political maneuver.
The martial decree lasted only six hours, but managed to dive South Korea into the worst political crisis in decades.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 05:52:19</pubDate></item></channel></rss>