<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/oms-aponta-riscos-para-a-saude-publica-apos-cheias-na-ilha-de-sao-vicente/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Macao artists expose works in celebration of the 80th anniversary of victory against fascism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/artistas-de-macau-expoem-obras-em-celebracao-ao-80-o-aniversario-da-vitoria-contra-o-fascismo/</link><description>When traditional Chinese art meets collective memory, a visual narrative that transcends time is born. This is the proposal of the exhibition “Songs of Glory to Ink and Brush”, which will be inaugurated today, September 30, at 6.30 pm at the Rui Cunha Foundation, the result of a collaboration with the Association of Caligrophies, Pintors and Sculptors of Macao Seals. Through the calligraphy, painting and engraving of seals, the collection of works celebrates the 80th anniversary of the victory of the Chinese people in the war against Japan and the world victory against fascism. Patent until October 11, the exhibition expects art to serve as a “bridge to unite the force that safeguard the prosperity of the homeland and the stability of Macao, writing a new chapter for peace and world development,” according to the organizers.
Under curated by Hong San San Rodrigues, the show brings together about 50 works that act as emotional documents from a decisive period in world history. Through the three pillars of classical Chinese art, more than 30 local female artists interpret historical scenes, patriotic poetry and peace themes, creating a dialogue between cultural heritage and historical conscience. “In this exhibition, members instill their deep knowledge of history and sincere praise for peace in their creations of traditional Chinese culture, using brush and ink as a container and notch knives as material. Each work carries with it the memory of martyrs and a deep affection for the homeland,” said Hong San San, president of the organizing association.
Exposure is distinguished by technical mastery in the three disciplines represented. Calligraphy reveals the expressive force of the Chinese characters, where the thickness and direction of each trait communicate specific emotions, according to the curator. Already the paintings, following both the Gongbi (thorough brushstroke) style and Xieyi (free style), explore the relationship between figuration and abstraction. Already the recorded seals, traditionally used as an artistic signature, become symbols of cultural identity and resistance.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timorese opposition requires serious investigation to enter Asian mafias in the country</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/oposicao-timorense-exige-investigacao-seria-a-entrada-de-mafias-asiaticas-no-pais/</link><description>The political opposition of Timor-Leste yesterday requested a serious and transparent investigation to Asian mafias in the country and the condemnation of Timorese who will allegedly have facilitated their entry into the territory.

"The prime minister has to authorize the judicial authorities to conduct a serious and transparent investigation into how Asian mafias have managed to enter Timor-Leste," said the deputy of the Revolutionary Independent Revolutionary Bench (Fretilin) ​​Florentino Ximenes "Sinarai" during the plenary session.
"Fretilin wants to know who allowed these mafias to enter. They were some central government rulers or some Raeoa [Special Administrative Region of Oecussi-Ambeno] authorities who paved the way for their entry into our country," the deputy asked.
Florentino Ximenes “Sinarai” said authorities have to identify and condemn the authors who are behind the mafias, even if they have consolidated financial and political power in the country. "Fretilin raises this issue because, two years ago, we have faced problems related to money that arose in Maubisse, with a transfer of $ 42 million that entered the country, as well as investigations into millions of dollars whose whereabouts the official information continues to hide from the public," said the deputy.
Florentino Ximenes “Sinarai” also lamented information on the alleged entry of private cash airplanes in the country, without any control.
Agio Pereira, Minister of State of the IX Government, recently released an anonymous manifesto, which denounces that the mafias have already bought state institutions with their unlawful money.
The manifesto denounces that the mafias infiltrated the state's organisms, managing to obtain fraudulent licenses to operate with their criminal companies in Timor-Leste.
Fretilin also asked the government to publicly explain the biometric project recently started by the IX Government for electoral cards. This is because, according to a UN report, Tech Company President A - a company with intention to fund the biometric authentication project in Oecusse - has been convicted in Singapore for involvement in a conspiracy to steal personal data from a cybercriminals union of China. "We hope that the biometric project for the Electoral Card, conducted by the STAE and the Ministry of State Administration, is not captured by Tech Company's mobster interests," said Florentine Ximenes "Sinarai".
Fretilin has appealed to the judicial authorities, including the police and the courts, to act with seriousness, honesty and integrity in the investigation and combat of the domination of Asian mafias in Timor-Leste.
In addition, Fretilin has also appealed to the attention of the Timorese people, especially students, academics, activists and non-governmental organizations, so that they are vigilant against those who have in recent times use the power of the state only to serve criminal interests and illicit businesses, to the detriment of the interests of the Maubere people.
The United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) warned this month for the proliferation of criminal networks at the Oedusi Enclave in Timor-Leste, noting that recent investigations show contamination of the region. “Oedusi's special administrative region seems to have been the target of criminal networks,” reads a report on Timor-Leste, which shows that there are all signs of digital criminal activity in this area, including the performance of people who have already been convicted of similar crimes in other Asian countries.
In the report, the UN states that "criminals are exploring investment citizenship programs for various passports, using them to facilitate their operations and escape the authorities" and adds that "this activity is further facilitated by obtaining fraudulent passports."
Recently an investigation by the Timorese authorities led to the detention of 10 people on suspicion of involvement in the activity of exploitation of illicit games and crossbly crossing in that enclave.
In the report, the UN adds that companies targeted for police investigations in Oecusse are directly linked to the 14K (Fourteen K) Network, led by Wan Kuok-Koi, a criminal and head of the Macao mafia, whose companies have been on the Black List and sanctioned by the United States Treasury Department since December 2020.
The 14K (Fourteen K) mafia network is known as a criminal union whose operation extends to Macao, China, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar and Malaysia. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 23:56:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Museum of the Grand Prix conjugates high speed and pastry in collaborative artwork</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/museu-do-grande-premio-conjuga-alta-velocidade-e-pastelaria-em-obra-de-arte-colaborativa/</link><description>The Macau Grand Prix Museum hosts a unique work in the world until November 16: a 2.9 -meter chocolate sports supercar, the result of the collaboration between the Swiss artist Saiff Vasarhelyi and the pastry chef Bob Tay. The exhibition, which opened the doors yesterday, represents another bet on the “Tourism + Sport” strategy of the territory, as Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes said, who was present at the event.
Macau is surprising again for the fusion between the automotive universe and the art of condoms with the inauguration of the exhibition “Chocolate Supercar” at the Grand Prix Museum. The central work, a 2.9 -meter -long chocolate futuristic supercar and 100 kilograms of heavyweight, was developed over 300 hours of meticulous work by the duo of international artists, marking the second edition of the project, which previously saw a Formula 1 car born.
The current project is born from the collaboration between Swiss artist Saiff Vasarhelyi, known for his F1 team interventions, and Bob Tay, Wynn pastry chef, holding multiple international food art premiums. Together they turned the vehicle's bodywork into an artistic expression screen using three distinct chocolate concentrations to create winding lines and explosive colors that capture the aesthetics of speed.
Saiff Vasarhelyi brings with it an unusual trajectory. He worked as a software engineer for some time before devoting himself to his passion for urban art, where he made a distinct style flourishing graffiti with luxury design. His aircraft and street art techniques have already adorned F1 team equipment and premium fashion pieces, making him a prominent voice in the intersection between urban culture and the world of motorsport. Recently, the British F1 pilot George Russel has paraded one of Vasarhelyi's works inside the Mercedes boxes, in the shape of a hat specially created for the construction company.
On the other side is Bob Tay, whose curriculum in the art of pastry shop brought him from Hong Kong to Macau. Author of the last work done in the first edition, is triple winner of the “Annual The Best Artist Trophies” and holder of 27 prizes in international pastry competitions, Wynn's chef also features the experience of working on artistic projects for Disney. His mastery in the transformation of chocolate into sculptures finds in this supercar the maximum expression of his talent.
Macau's director of Macao Tourism Services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, highlighted during the inauguration the evolution in the face of the previous year's project: “This time we took a step forward, also collaborating with an internationally acclaimed artist. It's a piece of art you can see and even feel for the aroma of chocolate”.
The exhibition is part of a wider strategy of the museum, which also includes a Pirelli show and luminous projections planned for the “Light Up Macau” festival in December. These elements reinforce the positioning of the space as a tourist attraction pole besides the automotive competitions, aligned with Macau's view as UNESCO's creative city, as the director pointed out.
The timing of the opening, a few days of the Golden Week of National Day of China, is no coincidence. Tourist authorities project a daily average of 150,000 visitors during the eight days of holidays, supported by the new visa policies that make it easier to visit Zhuhai and Hengqin residents.
The Grand Prix Museum will maintain extended hours during the festive period, with free admission on October 1st and exceptional opening on Tuesday, the 7th. The Exhibition of Chocolate Supercar will remain patent until November 16. The museum's opening hours are from 10h00 to 18h00, ending on Tuesdays.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing alerts for the dissemination of military secrets in live broadcasts on the internet</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/pequim-alerta-para-divulgacao-de-segredos-militares-em-transmissoes-ao-vivo-na-internet/</link><description>The Chinese government warned of the risk of disseminating military secrets during live broadcasts on social networks, after a netizen had released images of activities in a air base near his home.

In an article published on his Wechat social network account and quoted by the EFE news agency, the China State Ministry of Security released the case of a netizen called Chen who, surprised by the novons flying at low altitude, started a live broadcast, “publicly sharing images taken from his window in military aircraft movements”.
According to the ministry, the netizen was warned by some people in the hearing through the comments, who informed him that he should not be transmitting this content, but the transmission continued, with the citizen “tempted to increase visualizations” on his channel, even after receiving a call from the Air Base, which he responded with insults.
The broadcast lasted almost an hour, added 20,000 views and led to continuous dissemination of “dynamic information on military operations, types of aircraft and breakage times and landing, which represents a serious threat to China's military security,” said the official publication.
The ministry has opened an investigation into the incident, which may result in a prison sentence up to ten years for the netizen, although the official statement does not specify whether Chen has already been tried or being detained. "Chen is suspected of intentionally disclosing state secrets and his reckless decision to challenge the law through relay inevitably will have serious legal consequences," the Chinese government said.
Authorities also asked the population that you will not let the search for fame on the internet become a reason that brings to the crime and remembered that seemingly harmless activities, such as broadcasting live or sharing locations or photographs, can potentially lead to the "escape of state secrets and endangering national security." "Cyberspace is not a lawless land and any act that exceeds the limits of legality will face severe punishment," warned the security of the state of the Asian country.
The ministry periodically reports on its official Wechat account of spying cases and has repeatedly asked Chinese citizens who suspect employment offers or suspicious information requests, especially from foreign sources, and avoid sharing confidential data on the internet.
In 2023, the ministry requested the mobilization of the whole society to “prevent and combat espionage” and announced a series of measures to “reinforce national defense” against “foreign intelligence activities”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 23:58:28</pubDate></item><item><title>China sends 2,000 workers to build battery factory in Spain</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/china-envia-2-000-trabalhadores-para-construir-fabrica-de-baterias-em-espanha/</link><description>Chinese giant Catl will send about 2,000 workers to Spain to build a car battery factory valued at 4 billion euros, in a joint project with Stellantis automotive construction company, the Financial Times said.

The unit will be erected in Figueruelas near Saragoça, next to a Stellantis factory, which produces Opel, Peugeot and Lancia vehicles. CATL has pledged to recruit and form about 3,000 Spanish workers to operate the factory after completion, scheduled for the end of 2026, but analysts and unions warn of the company's reluctance to share technology and knowledge.
Headquartered in Ningde, Southeast China, CATL is the world's largest manufacturer and supplier of electric vehicle battery solutions.
The massive shipping of labor recalls the Chinese strategy in Africa, where companies in the country built dams, roads and ports with contingents of Chinese workers. The scale of the project in Spain, however, is unprecedented in large European economies, reflecting Beijing's bet to consolidate external dependencies of its state -of -the -art industry. “I don't think the Chinese want to share knowledge with us,” said José Juan Arceiz, a UGT union leader and a member of the European Council of Workers of Stellantis, quoted by the British newspaper.
Experts heard by the FT stress that Beijing seeks to transform China into an “self -sufficient fortress”, while reinforcing dependence on the rest of the world of their productive chains in a context of geopolitical competition with the United States.
In total, the country concentrates 80% of the worldwide manufacture of batteries and is the headquarters of electric vehicle brands that are threatening the status quo of a sector led for decades by European, American and Japanese manufacturers.
The project has 298 million euros of European funds and supported by the socialist government of Pedro Sánchez and the opposing popular party. Aragon's regional vice president, Mar Vaquero (PP), said that "it is necessary to normalize the fact that China, as a highly innovative and technological country, to settle in other countries." Already the party of far right Vox considered the investment a "huge risk".
The Spanish bet in Chinese technology comes after the collapse in March this year from Swedish Northvolt, which was pointed out as the best European hope to compete in a sector dominated by Chinese manufacturers.
In addition to CATL, other China companies are expanding presence in Europe: Aesc Envision prepares a unit in Spain and Gotion, in partnership with Volkswagen, is advancing with factories in Germany and Valencia.
China China Aviation Lithium Battery (Calb) also announced an investment of two billion euros to build a battery factory in Sines, Portugal, which is expected to be operational in 2028. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 23:59:33</pubDate></item><item><title>China and North Korea wake up reinforcing ties and opposing hegemonism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/china-e-coreia-do-norte-acordam-reforcar-lacos-e-opor-se-ao-hegemonismo/</link><description>North Korean and China Foreign Ministers pledged on Sunday to deepen bilateral ties and resist hegemonism and unilateralism, in an implicit reference to tensions with the United States.
The meeting, held in Beijing, took place about three weeks after North Korean leader Kim Jong Un, and Chinese President Xi Jinping celebrated their first summit in more than six years, in which they promised mutual support and reinforced cooperation. Both participated in the military parade that marked, in Beijing, the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II in the Pacific, along with Russian President Vladimir Putin.
The joint presence of Kim, Xi and Putin, the first of the genre, was seen as a sign of a tripartite front potential against Washington, although it remains uncertain to which outer Beijing will be willing to align in a block against the US.
During the meeting with Chinese counterparts, Wang Yi, North Korean Foreign Affairs, Choe Son Hui, quoted Kim by stating that reinforcing the relationship with Beijing is an “unshakable position” of North Korea. Choe expressed intention to deepen the friendship bonds “in line with the spirit of Kim-Xi summit,” according to the official North Korean agency KCNA.
Wang defended the need to reinforce strategic communications and bilateral exchanges. Chinese news agency Xinhua also cited the minister, who underlined China's opposition to “all forms of hegemonism” and the readiness to cooperate with Pyongyang in regional and international affairs.
Choe stated that North Korea is willing to cooperate closely with China in multilateral forums to “resist unilateralism and power policy” and promote an “more just and equitative” international order.
Analysts interpret these statements as an allusion to parallel disputes in both countries with Washington - China in its strategic rivalry with the US and North Korea by the nuclear program.
The KCNA indicated that the two ministers exchanged points of view on international and regional issues and "reached total consensus" without giving further details.
Kim's participation in the Beijing Military Parade marked his first presence at a large multilateral event in 14 years of leadership.
In recent years, Pyongyang has deepened cooperation with Moscow, providing troops and ammunition for war in Ukraine, but experts consider that Kim now seeks to rebalance the relationship with China, the largest commercial partner and the main source of foreign aid. For Beijing, maintaining influence on North Korea is essential after alleged periods of cooling in bilateral ties.
The attention now turns to the delegation that China is expected to send Pyongyang in October, when North Korea marks the 80th anniversary of the founding of the Workers Party, an event expected with a new military parade and weaponry display. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 23:57:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Pr Timorense promulgates law that revokes lifetime pension by deputies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/pr-timorense-promulga-lei-que-revoga-pensao-vitalicia-dos-deputados/</link><description>The president of Timor-Leste, José Ramos-Horta, promulgated yesterday the law that revokes the lifetime pension of deputies and former detainees of the sovereignty bodies, but asked the government a rational, fair and worthy transition. "In promulgating this law, I do it after deep consideration. I know that it will affect the lives of leaders and militants of the long struggle for independence. This law does not remove their rights as veterans and rights enshrined in a dignified and just reform," said José Ramos-Horta, in a press statement after promulgating the law.
In the statement, the Timorese President recommended to the government that in the execution of the law "consider a rational and fair transition, ensuring decent solutions." "The path of democracy is made of difficult choices. The greatness of a nation is not only for the courage to reform, but also for the humanity with which its citizens treat, including those who serve the state," said the Timorese President.
The Timorese Parliament approved on Thursday, in general, a bill to revoke the lifetime monthly pension for deputies and former detainees of sovereignty organs. The bill was approved by 61 of the 65 deputies that make up the National Parliament. The revocation of the lifetime pension law was made as part of an agreement established with university students, after three days of intense protests, which also led to the cancellation of the purchase of vehicles for deputies.
In the context of the agreement, the deputies also pledged to review the law on freedom of meeting and manifestation and to ensure proper financing for the productive sectors in the debate of the next state budget, which will begin in October.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 23:55:27</pubDate></item><item><title>WHO points out risks to public health after floods on the island of São Vicente</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/29/oms-aponta-riscos-para-a-saude-publica-apos-cheias-na-ilha-de-sao-vicente/</link><description>An assessment by the World Health Organization (WHO) indicated diseases transmitted by contaminated water or mosquitoes, as well as mental disturbances, such as public health risks, in the current post-right period on São Vicente Island, Cape Verde.
The torrential rains of the August 11 storm caused nine deaths, two missing and destruction of infrastructure on the Cape Verdean island. "There is an increase in diarrhea and respiratory infections, however, the situation remains within the warning threshold. Due to poor water and sanitation conditions, teams were mobilized to reinforce active surveillance of diseases with greater risk of occurrence," reads in the document, dated Friday and consulted yesterday by Lusa.
According to WHO, “alerts were issued due to cases of diarrhea, fever and headaches” among people who were housed in schools (nine cases, including two children) and in another center installed at Mindelo Stadium (six cases in adults).
Limited access to water, sanitation and hygiene “is a key risk factor for acute diarrhea” and floods, after prolonged drought, “can increase exposure to diarrheal pathogenic agents: drought conditions concentrate and are then released with flood water, increasing the risk of disease transmission,” the document described.
The risk of gastroenteritis outbreaks in São Vicente “increased significantly”, associated with “low risk perception of food safety, precarious hygiene and sanitation conditions and frequent reports of outbreaks of food origin between residents and tourists”.
In the case of the risk of diseases transmitted by vectors, such as the mosquito, in which dengue, malaria and other arboviroses fall, the risk “increased significantly” due to the waters that accumulated after floods. "The Ministry of Health and an WHO entomologist were sent to St. Vincent to assess the impact of flooding on the risk of mosquitoes transmitted by mosquitoes," says WHO, noting that the Government of Cape Verde had already declared, on August 1, "a national contingency situation, based on the need to prevent and mitigate the potential risk of dengue propagation and malaria reintroduction."
On the other hand, the floods in St. Vincent “significantly affected mental health conditions in affected communities” because of “destruction of houses, families' travel, loss of subsistence means and interruption of essential services,” he adds. All are factors that contributed "to increasing levels of psychological suffering, anxiety and trauma."
Although water production has been restored, "the distribution system is not yet fully functional and vulnerabilities in the drainage system persist."
In addition, “limitations on solid waste management and hospital waste were observed, along with the persistence of animal carcasses in some communities, representing additional risks to public health”, the document also indicates.
The WHO also warns of the risk of increased food insecurity, such as the United Nations Agriculture and Food Organization (FAO) had already foreseen last week.
The storm has reached the subsistence means, “gravity”, especially between “small farmers and families of fishermen, who also suffered crops, irrigation systems, boats and goods. Important agricultural zones, such as Calhau stream, Tchon d'A Holanda and Vineyard Ribeira suffered extensive damage, with small farmers losing cultures and cattle,” he described.
The WHO is providing technical and financial support for human resources, transportation and medical material, epidemiological surveillance, sending psychologists and to support the opening hours of health centers and the installation of a hospital waste incinerator. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 23:55:54</pubDate></item></channel></rss>