<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/o-lam-espera-que-iniciativas-de-desenvolvimento-de-talentos-alcancem-novos-patamares/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Authorities bet on intelligent top-cartographic technologies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/autoridades-apostam-nas-tecnologias-topo-cartograficas-inteligentes/</link><description>The Cartography and Cadastre Services Department intends to introduce new intelligent and advanced technologies that can promote the top-cartographic system and improve urban planning in Macau. The organization points, in this case, to the application of technologies such as drones, radars and 3D laser scanning.

Accelerated urban development was one of the reasons that led authorities to plan to introduce new technologies for topo-cartography. The 13th Exchange on Topo-Cartographic Technology and Geographic Information between Beijing, Hong Kong and Macau took place yesterday in Macau, through which the Directorate of Cartography and Cadastre Services (DSCC) hopes to deepen knowledge of intelligent topo-cartographic technologies and promote the development of geographic information technologies.
DSCC admitted to being attentive to the application of technologies such as drones, radars and 3D laser scanning, as well as the development of GIS (geographic information system) and GPS (global positioning system) technologies in neighboring regions. “Macau is considering the introduction of these advanced technologies, in order to further refine its technical structure of topo-cartography, thus improving urban planning”, revealed Wong Kin Him, head of the DSCC Data Collection Division, speaking to Jornal Ou Mun, on the sidelines of the event.
The representative added that four satellite reference stations have been established in Macau, which serve to provide the latest GPS positioning information to the engineering and construction sectors, as well as support cartography work.
“The urban landscape is continually transforming, as Macau’s rapid urban development in recent years has seen numerous construction projects completed, along with new land reclamation works,” he highlighted.
Wong Kin Him pointed out that, to monitor geographic changes in real time, authorities regularly use drones to update aerial images. The respective data is disseminated to the public and the engineering sector through GIS systems, facilitating daily mobility and project execution.
In this way, the person responsible assumed that, in the future, the authorities will deepen the application and innovation of top-cartographic technologies, in addition to strengthening cooperation with neighboring regions, raising the standards of geographic information service and supporting the sustainable development of Macau.
In turn, Vicente Luís Gracias, director of DSCC, also assured that the organization will continue to optimize geographic information services and promote the respective sharing of information, as well as providing geospatial technological support to improve urban administration capacity.
The director, in his opening speech at the event, stressed that the exchange session allows the topo-cartographic sector in Beijing, Hong Kong and Macau to learn about and exchange the latest top-cartography technologies and raise the professional level.
According to a statement released by DSCC, the current edition of the event was organized by DSCC and co-organized by the Beijing Society of Surveying and Mapping, The Hong Kong Institute of Surveyors, The Hong Kong Institution of Engineering Surveyors and Department of Land Surveying and Geo-Informatics of The Hong Kong Polytechnic University.
This exchange, since its first edition held in Beijing in 1999, has been organized, rotating and biennially, by Beijing, Hong Kong and Macau. In the last 25 years, twelve editions have been held. Macau hosted the exchange this year, becoming the host again after the 2017 edition.
DSCC detailed that this year's exchange includes a special reporting session, where experts and academics addressed technical research issues in various areas, including smart cities, geospatial infrastructure development, 3D realistic scene construction, artificial intelligence, remote sensing monitoring and geospatial information mega-data.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:16:58</pubDate></item><item><title>The development policy of the northern metropolis in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/a-politica-de-desenvolvimento-da-metropole-do-norte-em-hong-kong/</link><description>The rapid development of the Northern Metropolis plan is not only a political process that responds to the aspirations of the central authorities, but also a significant step leading to the deeper integration of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region (HKSAR) into Shenzhen from now until 2047.
The recent political speech delivered by Chief Executive John Lee became a turning point in the development of the Northern Metropolis. He expressed concern about its progress over the past three years, suggesting that following visits by Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong Macao Affairs Office (HKMAO), to Hong Kong in June 2025, the HKSAR leadership felt the need to accelerate the development of the Northern Metropolis. In June, Xia called on Hong Kong's ruling elites to remove "barriers" that slowed down the development process of the Northern Metropolis. His remarks put some pressure on HKSAR ruling elites to speed up the construction of the megacity in the northern part of Hong Kong. More significantly, John Lee promised Xia that he would accelerate the development of the Northern Metropolis and the Hetao region (TVB News, June 22, 2025).
John Lee's political speech mentioned several important initiatives related to the rapid development of the Northern Metropolis. Firstly, he himself chairs a committee to lead the development process. Secondly, a working group on developing and operating model drafting will be chaired by the Finance Committee to deal with the development of industrial parks, the establishment of public-private partnerships such as the Build-Operate-Transfer Model, and the introduction of new financing schemes such as equity, bonds and the provision of land as “a kind of equity participation”. An industrial park company responsible for 23 hectares of land in Hung Shui Kiu will be created. Thirdly, a working group on the planning and construction of the University City will be chaired by the Chief Secretary of Administration and will study the development of this city, seeking opinions from presidents and representatives of local, continental and international universities. Fourth, a working group on planning and development will be chaired by the Deputy Secretary of Finance, which will deal with coordination, execution and coordination work in the areas of engineering, land, transport, environmental protection, job creation and increased productivity.
In response to Xia Baolong's call for the HKSAR to remove barriers, John Lee mentioned a series of initiatives to accelerate the development of the Northern Metropolis. Firstly, an accelerated processing system will be created, allowing the adoption of construction methods, technologies, materials and equipment from the mainland and abroad, with the aim of reducing construction costs. Secondly, a phased development approach will be adopted, using the continent's pilot project for the development of retail, entertainment, convention and exhibition facilities, to attract companies before any long-term development. Thirdly, land exchange and alienation will be adopted to promote market participation and accelerate development, while land concessions will be granted to companies in a more flexible manner. Fourthly, land granted as lease instead of land lease may have a term of more than seven years to attract business investment. Fifth, landowners can hand over government-planned land to offset the amount payable for in situ land exchange or large-scale land alienation. Fifthly, the government can allow property developers to pay land premiums in phases. Sixth, the government contracts Mass Transit Railway Corporation Limited (MTRCL) to review private housing development around MTR station areas.
John Lee also announced that specific legislation will be introduced to accelerate the development of the Northern Metropolis. Such legislation will allow the government to draw up statutory procedures for the creation of industrial park companies, manage the cross-border flow of people, goods and capital, attract research institutes to establish themselves in Hong Kong, speed up the approval of construction plans, make use flexible in contour zoning plans (OZPs) and expedite the payment of compensation for land repossession.
Such competitions are naturally attracting some companies to present their proposals for developing the site. At the end of March 2025, it was reported that 22 companies from Mainland China and Hong Kong had already expressed interest in a pilot project to develop large plots of land in the Northern Metropolis. Interest was sparked by Xia Baolong's visit to Hong Kong and the appeal of former Liaison Office director Zheng Yanxiong, who, in February 2025, asked Mainland Chinese companies in Hong Kong to expand their investments in the construction of the Northern Metropolis.
In addition, the Hetao Shenzhen-Hong Kong Scientific and Technological Innovation Cooperation Zone (Cooperation Zone), currently located on both banks of the Shenzhen River (comprising Shenzhen Park and Hong Kong Park), will promote collaboration between the two parks in the development of information and technology. Construction of the first three buildings of Phase One of the Hong Kong Park of the Cooperation Zone (Hong Kong Park) has been completed. Tenants from the fields of life and health technology, microelectronics, new energy and artificial intelligence are gradually moving into these buildings. Construction of the other five buildings will be completed in the coming years.
In fact, Xia Baolong visited the Hong Kong Park of the Hetao Shenzhen-Hong Kong Science and Technology Innovation Cooperation Zone on February 9, 2025. He was accompanied by Acting Executive Director Eric Chan and Financial Secretary Paul Chan to listen to presentations by Development Secretary Bernadette Linn and Secretary for Innovation, Technology and Industry, Sun Dong, on the latest developments in the Park (Hong Kong Government Information News, February 10, 2025).
Finally, the San Tin Technological Hub, which occupies around 210 hectares of land, will serve as a strategic base for the development of information and technology. The transport infrastructure network will be developed and accelerated with the planned completion of Kwu Tung Station and Hung Shui Kiu Station in 2027 and 2030, respectively. An agreement between the government and MTRC aims to complete a major rail link in the Northern Metropolis at least two years before 2034. According to the Department of Roads, mainland China's construction standards will be integrated into the construction of the Northern Metropolis, which will reduce costs by about 20% to 30% (Hong Kong Free Press, July 11, 2025). At the same time, Chinese national standards for railway lines meet the safety requirements of Hong Kong fire, electricity and building regulations. The Northern Link will be an important project, as the Northern Metropolis is expected to provide more than 900,000 homes for around 2.5 million people who will live close to the border with Shenzhen. More importantly, the Hong Kong-Shenzhen Western Railway Link (Hung Shui Kiu-Qianhai) will also be developed, connecting Hong Kong and Shenzhen in a more convenient and profound way.
The plan, as described in the policy document, was quickly implemented from the end of September. The working group on planning and construction of the University City began its work at the end of September, when the Secretary of Education, Christine Choi, revealed that participating universities must work with industrial sectors and recruit international students from 100 countries, who will be distributed across 200 programs at the eight publicly funded universities. These international students are expected to come from ASEAN countries and the Belt and Road initiative.
University City will occupy ninety hectares of land, including fifty-two hectares within the Ngau Tam Mei New Development Area. The Urban Planning Council discussed changes to the Nau Tam Mei Zoning Plan on October 17, as its fifty-two hectares of land will serve as the basis for the campus of a third medical college. Ten hectares of land will be set aside for a comprehensive hospital that will provide medical services to the Northern Metropolis. This hospital is expected to integrate teaching, training and research, supporting the San Tin Technological Hub.
At the same time, Development Secretary Bernadette Linn informed lawmakers on October 3 that the government would propose a legal framework by the beginning of 2026 to accelerate the development of the Northern Metropolis. This legislation is expected to be deliberated and approved by the new Legislative Council, after its election in December 2025, in the year 2026.
On October 10, the government opened public tenders for the sale of the Sandy Ridge Data Complex land in the Northern Metropolis, adopting for the first time the “two envelope” approach, meaning that proposals will be evaluated based on price and non-price criteria. Seventy percent of the weighting will be given to the technical, qualitative merits and good planning of the non-premium bid, while the remaining 30% will be allocated to the land premium bid (Hong Kong Standard, October 10, 2025). The Sandy Ridge Data Complex is expected to provide advanced computing resources to drive the development of Artificial Intelligence industries.
The development of the Northern Metropolis in the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region (HKSAR) is technologically, socially, economically and politically significant.
Technically speaking, the Northern Metropolis will allow the HKSAR to capitalize on the strengths of Shenzhen's rapid development in Artificial Intelligence and Information Technology (IT), so that the city's competitiveness is strengthened, in addition to Hong Kong's traditionally strong status as a financial, monetary and aeronautical hub. Different plots of land will be developed more flexibly through the double envelope system, which will allow companies and property developers to present more innovative proposals, rather than relying solely on paying the land premium. The IT hub that will be built in the Northern Metropolis, together with the new and spacious residential areas, will attract more talent from mainland China and locals to work in the region. Currently, some talents from mainland China have chosen to reside in Shenzhen instead of Hong Kong, where rental costs for some of them are much higher than on the mainland. The complete and faster construction of the Northern Metropolis will enable the HKSAR to develop IT, attract more talents from the mainland, and integrate Hetao's IT development with Shenzhen more dynamically.
Socially, the construction of the Northern Metropolis in the HKSAR will represent a new wave of new cities, parallel to the construction of many satellite cities (such as Shatin and Tuen Mun) in Hong Kong under British rule during the 1970s and early 1980s. What makes these new cities in the Northern Metropolis unique is that they will be remarkably close to Shenzhen, making closer integration a reality. deep Hong Kong with Shenzhen. The migration of around 2.5 million people from Hong Kong to reside in the Northern Metropolis will become an important sign of the faster speed and wider scope of urbanization in the rest of the New Territories. In other words, as 2047 approaches, the New Territories will become increasingly urban, requiring the development of many more public services, the establishment of new districts under the geographical constituencies of the District Councils and the Legislative Council, the construction of new private and public housing units, and the completion of the Northern Link, which will play a crucial role in the Northern Metropolis' transport network.
From an economic point of view, the development of the Northern Metropolis meant that Lantau's Vision of Tomorrow was outdated. Considering the financial deficits faced by the HKSAR government, the development of the Northern Metropolis, which can mobilize and maximize private sector investment, is a more economically viable and pragmatic option. When asked by lawmakers about the future of Lantau Vision in early June, Finance Secretary Paul Chan stated that the government's focus would be on the Northern Metropolis, although research into the Lantau Vision of Tomorrow recovery initiative continued (Hong Kong Standard, June 2, 2025).
Politically speaking, the development of the Northern Metropolis will position the HKSAR well in the process of deeper integration with Shenzhen. If the Guangdong-Macao In-depth Cooperation Zone in Hengqin is part of an important movement involving the idea of ​​“first implementation, first experimentation”, then it can be anticipated that, by the year 2047, the idea of ​​drawing the Shenzhen first line, and the second line, which will follow the model of the Hengqin first and second lines, will be a possibility. It remains to be seen whether Shenzhen's “first line” will form another zone of in-depth cooperation with the HKSAR. As the borders between Hong Kong and Shenzhen become increasingly blurred, it is likely that the Macau-Hengqin cooperation model will also be adopted in the Hong Kong-Shenzhen cooperation zone.
Another political implication of the Northern Metropolis is that, since the central authorities have emphasized the importance of raising the HKSAR's governance standards, the rapid development and construction of the Northern Metropolis will become one of the crucial indicators of Hong Kong's effective governance. Thus, John Lee's government is expected to lay the foundations for the development of the Northern Metropolis.
Related to the issue of governance is the repossession and compensation of land for some rural populations in the New Territories – an important issue that will need to be managed with care, communication and political skills. The government adopts the principle of developing different areas of land, which may imply that some farmland and rural villages are left untouched, with villages and high-rise buildings coexisting in the future. Still, any need for land repossession and compensation will need to be addressed with governance skills, relying on rural leaders and elites as effective intermediaries between the government and rural residents of the Northern Metropolis.
In conclusion, the development of the Northern Metropolis will become a crucial indicator of the effective governance of the HKSAR, whose administration is expected to accelerate the construction of the Northern Metropolis, ranging from infrastructure projects to transportation networks, and from residential to commercial facilities. Public-private partnerships will be necessary to complete the completion of the Northern Metropolis. The Northern Metropolis is expected to provide for the effective provision of public services, the provision of clinics and schools, the establishment of a new IT center, the establishment of new campuses of different universities and the existence of a comprehensive hospital and the third medical college. Migration from other parts of Hong Kong and Kowloon to the Northern Metropolis will be observed gradually, triggering a new process of “urbanization” of the rest of the New Territories. When the Northern Metropolis is completed, Hong Kong will be positioned and ready to integrate more closely with parts of Shenzhen, following the example of Macau-Hengqin, making Hong Kong and Macau key drivers in the socio-economic development of the Greater Bay Area.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:07:32</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAL announces winners of workplace safety game</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/dsal-anuncia-vencedores-de-jogo-sobre-seguranca-no-trabalho/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) announced the list of winners of the third phase of the “Knowledge about healthy living in the workplace” competition, entitled “Occupational safety and health in the office”. The names of the winners, as well as the correct answers, are available for consultation on the DSAL website.
The 30 winners were randomly selected from a total of 4,944 participants, of which 4,636 got all the answers right. The group of winners has until November 21st to collect the reward – a supermarket coupon worth 100 patacas – at the information desk of the DSAL Occupational Health and Safety Department. The organization warns that any attempt to withdraw after the established deadline will not be accepted.
The fourth phase of the game takes place between now and November 23rd, under the theme “Prevention of musculoskeletal injuries of the lower limbs”. Interested parties can obtain more information about the game by visiting the DSAL website or contacting 2871 7781.
According to DSAL in a statement, the game aims to deepen the population's knowledge in terms of occupational health and safety. If they manage to correctly answer all the questions in three of the four phases of the game, participants are automatically included in the grand final draw of 15 winners, of which five will win 1,000 patacas and ten will win 500 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:13:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Once again, failed opportunities in Ukraine</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/mais-uma-vez-oportunidades-falhadas-na-ucrania/</link><description>On August 15, Presidents Putin and Trump met at a military base outside Anchorage, Alaska, for a day-long summit to discuss the ongoing Russo-Ukrainian War. Trump sought to convince Putin to agree to a ceasefire and then direct Russian-Ukrainian negotiations to end the war, which has now entered its 1340th day (44th month). Trump left the meeting empty-handed, with no agreement. Putin gained legitimacy as it was the first time he was invited to a Western country since he ordered the total invasion of Ukraine in February 2022.
Since then, instead of a ceasefire, the war has only intensified and expanded. Each side carried out drone and missile attacks against each other. Zelensky claims that Russia attacked last week alone using around 3,270 drones, 1,370 guided aerial bombs and almost 50 missiles. Their aim was to paralyze Ukraine's civil infrastructure, leaving tens of thousands of people without heat and light daily as a cold, dark winter approaches. Russian troops made some gains along the Donetsk and Zaporizhzhia regions in eastern and southern Ukraine, capturing some villages. However, critically, its summer offensive failed, with few tangible gains, failing to capture Pokrovsk or other critical cities strategically located in the Donbass region. Russian tactics indicate that they want to make life so miserable for the Ukrainian people that they will force their government to agree to a ceasefire on Russia's terms.
Since the failure of the Alaska summit, Ukraine has received critical information from US intelligence services, allowing them to carry out precision strikes against Russian oil refineries using Ukrainian-made drones and US-supplied ATACMS missiles. These attacks caused gas and oil shortages in Russia, as well as a sharp increase in gasoline prices. For example, last weekend, Ukrainian drones struck a huge gas processing plant in Orenburg, in the Southern Ural Mountains region, causing fires. They forced the suspension of natural gas supplies from Kazakhstan, a close ally of Russia in Central Asia. Another drone attack hit another oil refinery in the Samara region. Today, Ukraine hit a key pumping station on the Druzhba pipeline, which transports fuel from Russia to Hungary and Slovakia, disrupting supplies to these countries.
In recent weeks, Ukraine has been lobbying for the delivery of Tomahawk missiles. It is a long-range, all-weather, jet-propelled American cruise missile currently used by the navies of the US, Australia, the Netherlands and the United Kingdom to launch land-based attacks on ships and submarines. They have a range of up to 2,400 km, bringing much of Russia to their targets. Tomahawks can cause real damage and havoc in Moscow or St. Petersburg, or hit air and missile bases, training sites and weapons factories in Siberia, far from Ukraine. Therefore, they could be a turning point in the war. However, the US does not have a large arsenal of Tomahawk missiles and has therefore been reluctant to part with them; and Ukraine does not have suitable launchers, as these missiles are launched from the sea. But even the threat of Ukraine receiving Tomahawk missiles forced Putin to resume peace talks.
President Zelensky had a meeting scheduled at the White House with President Trump last Friday, October 17th. He hoped to seal an agreement that provided for the supply of Tomahawk missiles to the United States. Previously, Trump praised Zelensky and Ukraine's “courageous” war effort, even declaring that it was possible for Ukraine to retake all territory lost to Russia, including the provinces of Donetsk and Luhansk in the east, along with the regions of Zaporizhzhia and Kherson in the south. Trump criticized Putin, declaring that Putin is not interested in peace, even acknowledging that he was manipulating Trump to gain time and more Ukrainian territory.
However, on Thursday, October 16, Putin and Trump had a long telephone conversation. At Putin's request, they agreed to meet in Budapest, Hungary, for a summit that would be organized by the Hungarian leader, Victor Orban. Then, presumably, they would discuss a ceasefire, but one favorable to Russia. Putin apparently offered Trump a land swap in which Ukraine would give up the rest of the Donetsk and Luhansk provinces, giving Russia the entire crucial Donbass region, an industrial and agricultural bastion with rich minerals, including rare earth minerals that the U.S. so desperately wants to compensate for the loss of Chinese supplies, as well as large stocks of coal and steel. In return, Russia would return parts of the Zaporizhzhia region it had captured to Ukraine.
When Zelensky arrived at his scheduled meeting at the White House, he was greeted with a transformed situation. Trump informed him that the promised Tomahawk missiles, so feared by the Russians, were off the table. Instead, Trump pressured Zelensky to agree to this highly unfavorable land swap, which would leave Ukraine defenseless against any future Russian resumption of war. Once again, Trump told Zelensky that Ukraine would likely lose the war since Russia is the larger and more powerful country. According to multiple sources, the meeting devolved into swearing and shouting, reminding observers of the February meeting at the White House. Zelensky was then essentially ambushed by Vice President J.D. Vance and Trump, and was even escorted out of the White House. Last weekend, Zelensky left Washington empty-handed, once again humiliated after an argument between Trump and Putin.
Zelensky's unattended visit to Washington, as well as the subsequent White House announcement that Putin and Trump would meet in Budapest, left European leaders once again horrified. The unstable American leader changed his mind 180 degrees again. They feared that any Budapest Meeting could result in a Munich-style agreement, forcing Ukraine to cede up to a third of its territory. This would include territory that Ukraine spent 18 months defending at great cost in human resources and extensive lines of defense, which would be given to the Russians in this “land swap”. At the Munich Conference in 1938, Czechoslovakia was forced to cede the Sudetenland, with its lines of defense, to the Germans, leaving Czechoslovakia open to total absorption by the Germans the following spring. European countries discussed the possibility of donating 140 billion euros of the Russian Central Bank's frozen assets to Ukraine “so that Ukraine has the necessary resources” to maintain its defense efforts. Trump then told European leaders that he was in fact in favor of a ceasefire in effect, along the current battlefields, with no further territorial concessions from Kiev. European and Ukrainian leaders said they could live with a ceasefire in place as long as Ukraine received adequate security guarantees.
Those plans are now on hold. The White House stated that there are “no plans” for the US president to meet with Putin. In a phone call on Monday, Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov told Marco Rubio that his country's negotiating position remained unchanged, demanding all of Donetsk. Putin made his wish come true: Ukraine will not receive the feared Tomahawk missiles, which could cause real damage to Russia itself; and the war—its deaths, destruction, and suffering—continues as autumn gives way to winter. However, in another twist, today Trump imposed sanctions on two major Russian oil companies, Rosneft and Lukoil, the first sanctions imposed by the US since Trump returned to the presidency. The sanctions aim to cut off revenue from the sale of oil that finances Russia's war efforts. However, this US action was neutralized, as the Trump regime refused to impose secondary sanctions on India and China, the two largest buyers of Russian oil. Thus, Trump's retaliatory policies only confused everyone involved—Ukrainians, Russians, and Europeans. What the future holds for Ukraine largely depends on the whims of Mr. Trump.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:08:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 700 people flee Myanmar online fraud center to Thailand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/quase-700-pessoas-fogem-de-centro-de-fraude-online-de-myanmar-para-a-tailandia/</link><description>Almost 700 people fled one of Myanmar's biggest online fraud centers and crossed the border into Thailand. The group was made up of “foreign nationals,” both men and women, and authorities expect others to cross the Thai border.
 
Almost 700 people fled one of Myanmar's biggest online fraud centers yesterday and crossed the border into Thailand, a Thai provincial official said, following a military operation at the complex.
A total of “677 people fled the fraud center” of KK Park, crossing the Moei River to reach Thailand yesterday morning, Sawanit Suriyakul Na Ayutthaya, deputy governor of Tak province, close to the border with Myanmar, told the news agency France-Presse (AFP). “The immigration police and a military operational force collaborated to provide assistance within the scope of humanitarian procedures (…) and these people will be subject to control”, he added.
The Tak provincial administration office announced in a statement that the group was made up of “foreign citizens”, men and women, and that authorities expect other people to cross the Thai border.
In Myanmar, complexes where online scammers target foreigners with sentimental and commercial schemes thrived along the little-guarded border with Thailand during the civil war, triggered by a coup d'état, in February 2021. Most locations are under the control of Chinese criminal groups, in collusion with Burmese militias, writes AFP.
According to experts, the military junta turns a blind eye to fraud networks, in the hands of militia allies, who, in return, control the border regions. But the Burmese power is also under pressure from China, the junta's biggest military ally, to put an end to these schemes, as Beijing is unhappy with the number of Chinese citizens who participate in and are targets of these scams.
China, Thailand and Myanmar undertook a joint effort, much publicized in the media, to eradicate the scourge. In February, around seven thousand workers were removed from the system. But these “cyber fraud factories” are thriving more than ever in the Southeast Asian country, according to an AFP investigation published in mid-October. For example, Starlink satellite dishes have mushroomed on rooftops to compensate for Internet shutdowns by Thai authorities.
In AFP images, almost 80 antennas are visible on a single roof of the KK Park complex. SpaceX announced on Wednesday that it has disabled more than 2,500 Starlink Internet receivers used in these cyber fraud centers. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:11:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Young Timorese hope that Timor-Leste's membership in ASEAN is not just symbolic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/jovens-timorenses-esperam-que-adesao-de-timor-leste-a-asean-nao-seja-apenas-simbolica/</link><description>Young Timorese hope that Timor-Leste's accession to the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) is not just symbolic, but that the country will diversify in several areas to become more competitive in the region. "Timor-Leste's accession to ASEAN is a very important achievement, through which our country can obtain several opportunities in the region. I think this is something very positive", Felipe Freitas Cabral, a student at Instituto Superior Dom Bosco (ISDB), told Lusa. But, considered Felipe Freitas Cabral, Timor-Leste has not yet committed enough to raise its standards to meet the organization's demands, which could mean that this membership ends up being just symbolic. "We participate in ASEAN only as a symbol, but within the organization we have no influence and only appear as members. And without influence, we cannot compete within this region", highlighted the young Timorese.
Felipe Freitas Cabral stated that Timor-Leste needs "first to diversify its economy, because currently 90% depends on oil and gas. This reveals a big gap or a problem that the country needs to resolve quickly." “To fully join ASEAN, I think that we must first strengthen our economy, so that we can compete with other countries in the region”, added Freitas Cabral.
Regarding the contribution of youth to the country, the young man highlighted that everyone has a role to play, and it is essential that students commit themselves and acquire good skills to contribute to national development.
For Aprilia Martins, a student at the National University of Timor Lorosa’e (UNTL), Timor-Leste’s accession to ASEAN is a “great opportunity” for the development of several sectors. According to the young woman, ASEAN could also allow for the strengthening of political relations and bilateral cooperation with member countries, and in the field of education, young Timorese will be able to benefit from scholarships at recognized universities in the region.
In the agricultural sector, the young Timorese expressed hope that technological development could be promoted among farmers. Asked about the contribution of Timorese youth, Aprilia Sonita Martins stated that it is important to start preparing now to compete with young people from other countries in the region. “We need to study hard, because in the future we will be the force that will drive the development of our country”, concluded the UNTL student.
Timor-Leste will become the 11th member state of ASEAN on Sunday, during the summit of heads of state and government of this Southeast Asian organization, which will take place in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 14 years after submitting its application for admission.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:10:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong records first death due to chikungunya fever</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/hong-kong-regista-primeira-morte-devido-a-febre-chikungunya/</link><description>Hong Kong authorities yesterday announced the first death caused by the chikungunya virus, following an outbreak in neighboring Guangdong province. The Hong Kong Center for Health Protection (CHP) announced the death, on Thursday, of a 77-year-old man who suffered from a chronic illness, according to a statement. The victim visited Guangzhou, capital of Guangdong province, between September 30 and October 13, and began to feel fever and joint pain after returning to Hong Kong, the CHP said. With his health condition worsening, the man was admitted to intensive care at Ruttonjee Hospital, where he died due to the virus, aggravated by multiple organ failure.
This year, Hong Kong recorded 42 cases of disease caused by the chikungunya virus, but authorities stressed that all were classified as infections coming from outside the territory. Transmitted by mosquitoes, the chikungunya virus causes fever and joint pain, with symptoms similar to dengue, affecting children, the elderly and people with pre-existing illnesses more seriously. The CHP stressed that this infection is rarely associated with serious symptoms, with a mortality rate of less than 0.1%, but warned that high-risk individuals should immediately seek medical attention if they experience symptoms. Hong Kong health authorities have reinforced prevention measures in affected districts and spread pesticides to try to eliminate mosquitoes in risk areas. Schools implemented measures to control stagnant water, where mosquitoes breed, and the Chinese region reinforced border surveillance.
Worldwide, between January and September, almost 445,300 suspected or confirmed cases of chikungunya and 155 deaths were reported in 40 countries, according to data from the World Health Organization. In mainland China, almost 16,500 cases of chikungunya were registered until the end of September, in an outbreak concentrated in the cities of Foshan and Jiangmen, close to Hong Kong and Macau, which recorded 29 cases imported and eight local cases. Foshan authorities have imposed strict preventative measures, including the use of mosquito nets, drones and disinfectant, with threats of fines and electricity cuts for those who do not eliminate standing water. At the end of August, the European Center for Disease Prevention and Control highlighted that 27 chikungunya outbreaks were recorded this year, a new record on the European continent.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:12:57</pubDate></item><item><title>David Kong: from football to dog daycare</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/david-kong-do-futebol-a-creche-canina/</link><description>In Macau, they know him for being a footballer, but in Portugal, in addition to being a player at Anadia Futebol Clube, Macanese David Kong is the owner of Just4buddies, a dog daycare and hotel, in São Domingos de Rana.

Honey! Lord! Bullet! You hear the names, almost overlapping, while trying to take some photographs. The objective is to try to calm the mood, while some dogs jump from one side to the other, run around the ball or curiously investigate the camera. For the employees of Just4buddies, a daycare and hotel for dogs, in São Domingos de Rana, this is a normal working day, as the footballer and owner of this business, Macanese David Kong, tells PONTO FINAL.
It all started in the summer of 2021, when, in conversation with a friend, who owned a dog daycare in Loures, called Vila do Cão, she decided to invest in the business. “He asked me: we’re going to close, do you want to keep it?”, reveals David. He always had dogs in the family, but he never thought he would work with them professionally. Still, he took a risk.
The deal went well, but the distance and time lost in traffic was a lot. Therefore, when he discovered that Just4buddies, located in São Domingos de Rana, five minutes from his house, was for sale, he decided to take the risk, in January 2024. “The previous owner owns the space and I own the business”, he explains. For some time he tried to maintain both daycare centers, but at a certain point he had to choose. “I was left with this one”, he says.

Daycare and training

At Just4buddies they offer daycare, hotel and, in specific cases, animal training services. They never close. “This is like a house, the dogs are really free, there are no boxes and, at night, we always have someone working — one, two, three, four people, depending on the number of dogs”, he says. They all sleep together. “We have beds for humans and beds for dogs — if they want to sleep in the bed with the human, they can do that; if they want to sleep on the floor, they can do that,” he says, adding: “The idea is to be loose and free.”
On the other hand, there are rules. "The dogs must undergo an assessment first. They must be extremely sociable and, as soon as they show any type of aggression or anxiety, if we feel that they are not comfortable inside, we refuse", he explains. “Not everyone loves being in the middle of 50 (at most) — maybe they like being with one or two”, he continues. Furthermore, from one year onwards, all animals must be spayed or neutered.

There are 13 workers for a maximum number of 50 dogs, many with Veterinary Medicine courses or training in Veterinary Assistants. The team also includes a canine trainer.
“We don’t teach — if they want to educate the dogs, they do a training session,” he says, clarifying that they also offer this service, although not inside the facilities. “The tutor also has to be polite many times; training has to be at home, because almost everything starts at home”, he declares.

Who are the customers

Not all customers are necessarily from that area. “We have a little bit of everything: for those who stay there overnight, it usually happens when people go on vacation”, he reveals. They can be customers from Loures, the Algarve or other places. “We have foreigners and Portuguese”, he says.
As for the daycare service, there are usually more people from the Cascais area or surrounding areas, who, as a rule, leave home to work in Lisbon and do not want to leave their dogs alone at home for too long. “We only have one or two who really come from far away and make a point of coming here to leave the dog, because it has gone well, they like it and they feel confident”, he explains. In fact, one of the services they offer and what distinguishes them from other companies of their kind is the possibility for owners to view their animals, from their cell phone or computer. “We have cameras and the images are transmitted live to the tutors, who can monitor them”, he declares.
There are those who leave their canines every day, because they have to work in person away from home. But there are those who only leave them on the days when they are not teleworking. Entry starts at 7:30 am. After that, around 9:30 am, the dogs are in the Just4buddies garden to socialize and play. “We are monitors, we are not friends to play with; we have activities, like ball races, we make cookies, we pull the rope, but the truth is that they also play with each other”, says David, describing a normal day. “They rest when they want and play when they want”, he adds. After eating, the normal thing is to sleep a little. “We have nap time and, as with children, if they don't do it, the end of the day is more complicated”, he says. “We also have our own meal times, which will be between 11:30 am and 12:30 pm, and dinner will be around 8 pm, but it also depends on the guardians’ wishes [if they have any specific requirements]”, he reveals.

In the Just4buddies villa there is a garden, where the animals spend most of their time, and a house. “The interior is more for when it’s raining or for separating a tired dog, or for lunch,” he says.
Around 5 or 6 pm, owners start to appear to collect their animals. Then, until 7pm, all daycare dogs leave, leaving only those who will stay there overnight. “At about this time we give everyone dinner and there comes a time when they go to sleep; we spread the beds around the space, so that everyone can decide where they are going to sleep”, he says.
They rarely take their dogs outside. “We only do it for long stays, so the dog can relax a little – this is fun, but very intense”, he says.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:26:43</pubDate></item><item><title>“If I had stayed in Macau, it would be difficult to have reached Bordeaux”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/se-continuasse-em-macau-era-dificil-ter-chegado-ao-bordeaux/</link><description>FC Girondins de Bordeaux was where he made the most money, but it was at Sporting Clube de Braga that David Kong enjoyed playing most. Nowadays, he is at Anadia FC.
He began his football career in the territory, with Benfica de Macau, when he was a child. One day, Luís Filipe Vieira, former president of SL Benfica, went to Macao and ended up recruiting him to do training in Lisbon. “In 2010, I came and stayed here, I pursued my career in Portugal”, reveals David Kong. His career includes several clubs such as Feirense, CD Mafra, GS Loures, CD Cova da Piedade, SC Braga, Boavista, Oriental Dragon FC, Moncaparachense, Fabril Barreiro, but the highlight of his career was probably his three-year stint at FC Girondins de Bordeaux, where well-known names in football played at the time. “I played with them on FIFA, on Playstation, and I ended up meeting them there, it was fun”, he reveals.
The Bordeaux experience
When starting his football career in Macau, David Kong knew it would be difficult to make the leap in his career. “Normally, whoever is in Macau, if they want to make a living out of this, has to leave the territory”, he says. “You don’t need to come to Portugal, you can go to China or Japan”, he declares, giving other examples of places to grow in the sport.
In the territory, the biggest problem is the “lack of competitiveness”, which can then affect potential talents. “These are the formative years and, in Portugal, kids start very early”, he declares. “I remember only starting to play seriously when I was 11, while there are children playing from the age of seven in Portugal”, he says.
Now playing for Anadia FC, he doesn't worry too much about what the future holds for him. “I never had a manager: it was always me and my father [Rui Cardoso]”, he states. After all, opportunities are also the result of the contacts that arise.
And, even admitting that football, especially in the lower divisions, is an “unstable” environment with some unknowns in the future, David Kong highlights: “It’s what I like to do, football always comes first”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:19:39</pubDate></item><item><title>China installs new floating barrier on reef disputed with the Philippines</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/china-instala-nova-barreira-flutuante-em-recife-disputado-com-as-filipinas/</link><description>China has installed a new floating barrier on Scarborough Reef, disputed with the Philippines, according to satellite images released yesterday, worsening tensions in the South China Sea.

The structure blocks entry into the reef lagoon – known as Huangyan in China and Bajo de Masinloc or Panatag Shoal in the Philippines – according to an image captured by geospatial company Satellogic and distributed by US firm SkyFi.
Neither the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs nor the Philippine Coast Guard have so far responded to requests for comment, according to the Hong Kong newspaper South China Morning Post. “New material collected by satellite shows an illegal floating barrier installed by the People's Republic of China at the entrance to Scarborough Reef,” SkyFi executive director Luke Fischer wrote on the social network X (formerly Twitter).
Ray Powell, a maritime security expert and director of the SeaLight project, who analyzed the high-resolution images, confirmed that the photograph was taken on October 8. “This is not the first time that China has installed a barrier on the reef; the intention appears to be to restrict access to the lagoon,” he said.
Located about 220 kilometers west of the Philippine island of Luzon, the reef has been under Beijing's control since a naval confrontation with Manila in 2012 and has been a frequent scene of incidents between the two countries.
Last week, China said it had “expelled” two Philippine reconnaissance planes from the area, a day after Manila reported “aggressive interference” by a Chinese helicopter and fighter jet during a routine flight.
In September, Beijing also announced its intention to declare Scarborough Reef as a natural reserve, a measure rejected by the Philippines because it considers the enclave to be in its exclusive economic zone.
The Chinese think tank South China Sea Strategic Situation Probing Initiative argued on social media that the new installation would be “a response to the provocative behavior of the Philippines” and that “China has the right to act within its sovereignty”.
Beijing and Manila maintain territorial disputes in the South China Sea, a route through which around 30% of global maritime trade flows. Although a ruling by the Permanent Court of Arbitration in The Hague in 2016 found the Philippines in favor of several of its claims, China continues to claim almost the entire sea.
Since Ferdinand Marcos Jr. assumed the presidency in 2022, the Philippines has adopted a firmer stance in defending its sovereignty, denouncing clashes between vessels from the two countries more frequently. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:12:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands profit rose to $272 million in third quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/lucro-da-sands-aumentou-para-272-milhoes-de-dolares-no-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>Sands China's profit in the third quarter of this year reached 272 million US dollars, that is, 1.5% more compared to the results of the same period last year. Revenues increased by 7.5% compared to the same period in 2024.

Sands China's total gross revenues increased 7.5% to US$1.9 billion in the third quarter of this year, compared to the third quarter of 2024. The gaming operator's profit was US$272 million between July and September, up 1.5% compared to US$268 million in the third quarter of 2024.
The third quarter results were released yesterday by the gaming concessionaire in Macau. The document, sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, also says that the result of Sands China's properties before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) was US$601 million in the third quarter, an increase of 2.7% compared to the same period last year.
Quoted in the statement, Robert G. Goldstein, President and CEO of Las Vegas Sands, parent company of Sands China, said: “We remain excited about our growth opportunities in both Macau and Singapore as we realize the benefits of our recently completed capital investment programs.”
“In Macau, our decades-long commitment to making investments that increase the attractiveness of business and leisure tourism in Macau and support its development as a global center for business and leisure tourism positions us well for future growth”, highlighted Goldstein, adding that the group's financial liquidity allows it to support these investment programs in Macau.
A large part of the group's revenue comes from casinos. The Venetian casino alone achieved revenue of 543 million US dollars in the third quarter, which, even so, means a drop compared to the 554 million in the same period last year. Sands China's second highest-earning casino property is the Londoner, which achieved gaming revenue of $525 million between July and September, a significant increase compared to $338 million in the third quarter of last year.
In the month of September, the total revenue of the gaming industry in Macau was 18.3 billion patacas, 17.5% less compared to the previous month of August, when casinos earned 22.15 billion patacas and broke the post-pandemic record. In terms of accumulated revenue, between January and September this year the casinos raised around 181.34 billion patacas, that is, 7.1% more compared to what they had raised in the same period last year.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:16:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese agrifood company signs agreement to have a “strong presence” online in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/agroalimentar-portugues-assina-acordo-para-ter-forte-presenca-online-na-china/</link><description>PortugalFoods signed an agreement with Tmall to have “a strong Portuguese presence” on one of the largest e-commerce platforms in China. The signed cooperation protocol is “very interesting”, said the executive director of PortugalFoods.
 
PortugalFoods signed an agreement with Tmall to have “a strong Portuguese presence” on one of the largest e-commerce platforms in China, the leader of the agri-food sector association revealed yesterday.
The executive director of PortugalFoods considers the cooperation protocol signed during the 2nd China–Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition (C-PLPEX), in Macau, to be “very interesting”. “Our objective is to really start working on establishing – I’m not saying a store – a strong Portuguese presence on this platform”, explained Deolinda Silva. “It’s not easy, but they are there ready to help us, and we are also increasingly acquiring more knowledge about the challenge that awaits us”, admitted the director.
The cooperation began yesterday with a presentation of products from PortugalFoods member companies alongside Chinese companies “from the most varied categories”, revealed Silva.
The association brought products from 12 companies to C-PLPEX, but has more than 200 members including companies, entities in the scientific system and the agri-food sector and other related activities.
The presentation is part of a Tmall strategy to promote Portuguese agri-food products “in an aggregated way, to gain some dimension”, explained the executive director of PortugalFoods. “The work that needs to be done with these Chinese partners is immense, because there is practically no presence of Portuguese products”, lamented Silva.
The first contact with Tmall took place during the 2024 edition of the FHC Shanghai Global Food Trade Show, a food fair in Shanghai, the financial capital of China.
PortugalFoods will participate in this fair again, between November 12th and 14th, to “better understand the potential that exists to create partnerships” to find future buyers, said the executive director.
China “is a market with brutal potential but which must be worked on in phases and by regions”, said Silva, who pointed to southern China as a priority.
According to figures provided by PortugalFoods, Portuguese agri-food exports reached 10 billion euros in 2024, a growth of 8.5% compared to the previous year.
The numbers for 2025 are not yet finalized, but the association anticipates growth, albeit more modest than that seen last year. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:15:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Fafe company will produce one million puddings per year with an eye on China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/empresa-de-fafe-vai-produzir-um-milhao-de-pudins-por-ano-com-olho-na-china/</link><description>A company in Fafe said yesterday that it is investing in robots to be able to produce, per year, one million puddings inspired by the abade de priscos pudding and start exporting to China.
The creator of Pudim da TV, Paulo Fernandes, announced that, by the end of the year, the company's factory in the district of Braga will have four robots operating, thus reaching the capacity to produce one million puddings per year.
The manufacturing unit, created two and a half years ago, already supplies desserts to more than 400 restaurants in Portugal and exports to nine countries in Europe and South America, said Fernandes.
The businessman was speaking to journalists during the second day of the 2nd China–Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition (C-PLPEX), which is taking place simultaneously with the 30th Macau International Fair.
Fernandes brought Pudding from TV to the territory “above all to try to understand what the Chinese palate is like here, if the pudding is well accepted or if we have to make some adjustments to the flavor”.
The company, whose turnover reaches “a few hundred thousand euros”, also intends to “find partners” to distribute the pudding and repeat “the exponential growth” of pastel de nata abroad.
On October 13, Macau inscribed the local custard tarts, invented by a British resident in the city, Andrew Stow (1955-2006), and inspired by the Portuguese pastry, on the Intangible Cultural Heritage List.
Paulo Fernandes said he is analyzing the possibility of joining a Macau Government program, which will come into force in November, to help foreign companies internationalize from the Chinese region.
The chef revealed that he has meetings scheduled with potential partners. Depending on interest, Macau could be the TV Pudding “gateway” to markets such as neighboring Hong Kong and mainland China.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:13:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Pop Mart, maker of Labubu, falls 10.8% in Hong Kong amid doubts about growth</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/pop-mart-fabricante-de-labubu-cai-108-em-hong-kong-entre-duvidas-sobre-crescimento/</link><description>Shares in Pop Mart, the Chinese company responsible for the global phenomenon of Labubu figures, sank 10.8% yesterday, the biggest drop since April, in a new episode of volatility that contrasts with the good sales results released the day before.

The devaluation reflects investors' growing caution regarding the possibility of a slowdown in the company's growth, after several quarters driven by the popularity of its collectible products.
On Wednesday, Pop Mart shares rose 4.23% on the Hong Kong stock exchange, despite the negative tone of the market, following the announcement that revenue in the third quarter increased between 245% and 250%, driven by Labubu's virality on social media and the company's international expansion.
According to data provided by the company, domestic sales grew 190%, while international sales soared 370%, highlighted by increases of 175% in the Asia-Pacific region, more than 740% in Europe and almost 1,270% in the United States.
The strong drop recorded yesterday is largely attributed to profit taking, after appreciation of more than 186% since the beginning of the year, and uncertainty about the sustainability of the current growth rate.
The stock fell 8.1% on Tuesday, its worst performance since April, weighed down by fears of a slowdown in sales after months of euphoria. The preliminary release of results helped to temporarily dispel these concerns, but the absence of an official date for the presentation of the accounts maintains uncertainty regarding the company's future evolution.
Executive chairman and founder Wang Ning expressed confidence in the long-term resilience of the Labubu character, arguing that cultural icons continue to generate revenue even after peak popularity.
According to the Bloomberg agency, the explosion in demand forced the company itself to revise its internal goals upwards. If at the beginning of 2024 Pop Mart predicted a turnover of 2,800 million dollars, in August Wang raised this target to 4,200 million dollars, pointing to the brand's global momentum as a key factor.
Founded in Beijing in 2010, Pop Mart has established itself as one of the main Asian references in the toy and collectible figures sector, combining exclusive design, limited editions and collaborations with international brands, artists and franchises. Its business model is based on so-called “surprise boxes”, which encourage repeat purchases and have created a community of fans willing to pay high premiums for rare pieces.
Among its main lines is Labubu, a monster with pointy ears and a mischievous smile inspired by Norse mythology, created by Hong Kong artist Lung Ka-sing in 2015 and integrated into the company's portfolio in 2019. Lusa</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Brothers André and Bruno Santos perform in Macau on November 8</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/irmaos-andre-e-bruno-santos-actuam-em-macau-a-8-de-novembro/</link><description>André Santos and Bruno Santos, duo “Mano a Mano”, come to present the show “Trilogia das Sombras” in Macau. The duo, who come to Macau at the invitation of “Somos! – Associação de Comunicação m Língua Portuguesa”, will perform at Casa Garden on November 8th, at 8pm. Entry is free.
“Trilogia das Sombras” is the name of the most recent album by “Mano a Mano”, which includes music, poetry, performance and visual arts, inspired by the work and life of the artist Lourdes Castro. This fifth album by the Madeiran guitarists has the format of a book-disc, designed by Carla Cabral with inspiration from the artist's books by Lourdes Castro, and using sewing, painting, drawing and transfer on fabric and paper. There is also a text by José Tolentino Mendonça and a recitation of the poem Lourdes Castro, Rua da Olaria. In this concert, in addition to the brothers' usual paraphernalia of guitars and chordophones, the show features a performance by Tiago Martins who, behind a screen and inspired by Lourdes Castro's Shadow Theater, interacts with the music; and with the scenography by the architecture studio Pontoatelier.
“Somos” also reveals that the show will have a special guest, instrumentalist Fang Teng, concertmaster of the Macau Chinese Orchestra, who will perform emblematic works of Portuguese musical culture, “in this way strengthening ties that have united our peoples for centuries and creating a moment of perfect musical and cultural bond”. Fang will transpose the notes of Portuguese music onto the erhu, a traditional Chinese instrument with two strings and played with a bow. “A note that promises to delight and move the audience”, highlights the organization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Deputies distributed across AL committees</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/deputados-distribuidos-pelas-comissoes-da-al/</link><description>The Legislative Assembly (AL) committees have already been established for this legislature and the Board has already proposed the deputies who will join them. The proposal came from the AL Board and will be voted on at the plenary meeting that will take place next Tuesday.
The Bureau's proposal determines that ten deputies will be part of the 1st Standing Committee: Wong Kit Cheng, Nick Lei, Chui Sai Peng, Lam Fat Iam, Lei Wun Kong, Che Sai Wang, Wong Chon Kit, Kevin Ho, Ella Lei and Joey Lao.
The following parliamentarians will be part of the 2nd AL Standing Committee: Ip Sio Kai, Lam Lon Wai, Vong Hou Piu, Kou Ngon Seng, Lee Koi Ian, Chao Ka Chon, Chan Hao Weng, Wong Ka Lon, Song Pek Kei and Ngan Iek Hang.
The 3rd AL Permanent Commission will be composed of 11 deputies: Leong Sun Iok, Leong Hong Sai, Si Ka Lon, Angela Leong, Pereira Coutinho, Leong Pou U, Iau Teng Pio, Chan Lai Kei, Loi I Weng, Ma Chi Seng and Kou Kam Fai.
Members of the Monitoring Committees were also chosen from among the 33 AL deputies. The Monitoring Committee for Public Land and Concession Affairs will feature Ella Lei, Joey Lao, Chui Sai Peng, Lam Fat Iam, Lei Wun Kong, Che Sai Wang, Wong Chon Kit, Kevin Ho, Wong Kit Cheng and Nick Lei.
The Monitoring Committee for Public Finance Affairs will have Song Pek Kei, Ngan Iek Hang, Vong Hou Piu, Kou Ngon Seng, Lee Koi Ian, Chao Ka Chon, Chan Hao Weng, Wong Ka Lon, Ip Sio Kai and Lam Lon Wai as members.
Finally, the Monitoring Committee for Public Administration Affairs will have the following deputies: Ma Chi Seng, Kou Kam Fai, Si Ka Lon, Angela Leong, Pereira Coutinho, Leong Pou U, Iau Teng Pio, Chan Lai Kei, Loi I Weng, Leong Sun Iok and Leong Hong Sai.
The Board also defined the seven deputies who will be part of the Rules and Mandates Committee: Chui Sai Peng, Iau Teng Pio, Lei Wun Kong, Angela Leong, Ip Sio Kai, Wong Kit Cheng and Song Pek Kei.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:14:32</pubDate></item><item><title>FC Porto with a demanding test against Moreirense, Sporting and Benfica more relaxed</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/fc-porto-com-teste-exigente-ante-o-moreirense-sporting-e-benfica-mais-desafogados/</link><description>On Monday, FC Porto faces a very demanding test of leadership in the Portuguese Football League, visiting Moreirense at the end of the ninth round, in which rivals Sporting and Benfica will face more accessible opponents.

The two-time national champion, who occupies second place, three points away from the 'dragons', plays on Sunday at the Tondela stadium, second to last, while Benfica, third placed, four points from the leadership, receives Arouca, 11th in the table, on Saturday, on a very busy day, with elections for the governing bodies for the four-year period 2025-2029.
FC Porto's task – which in the previous round let the first points slip away, drawing 0-0 against Benfica – appears more arduous, as the championship returns to the country's stadiums, after the long three-week break for the qualifying matches for the 2026 World Cup and the third round of the Portuguese Cup.
The blue and whites travel to the home of fifth place, a hitherto impregnable stronghold of Moreirense, where they won all four matches played in front of their fans and laid the foundations for their good classification in the competition, since, as visitors, they lost three of the four matches played.
On the other side will be the undefeated leader of the I League, under the command of Italian coach Francesco Farioli, who, in contrast to the 'canons', won the four games played away from the Estádio do Dragão and even has an encouraging record at Monday's opponent's ground, where they lost only one of the 14 meetings.
Sporting will try to take advantage of the fact that they entered the field the day before to put pressure on their rival from Porto, which they failed to approach in the last round, letting the victory over Sporting de Braga slip away in the 90+7 minutes, following a penalty committed by captain Morten Hjulmand, which allowed the Minho team to draw 1-1 at the José Alvalade Stadium.
The team coached by Rui Borges, which on Wednesday beat Marseille, 2-1, in the Champions League, can provisionally match FC Porto and the Tondela stadium, home of the 17th and penultimate placed team, seems to be the right place to do so, as the hosts have not yet celebrated any triumph there.
Sporting, on the other hand, could find itself in an identical situation when the kick-off takes place in Tondela, as it may have been provisionally overtaken by Benfica, which hosts the quiet Arouca, on election day, with six candidates for president: Rui Costa, current president, Cristóvão Carvalho, João Diogo Manteigas, João Noronha Lopes, Luís Filipe Vieira and Martim Mayer.
Coach José Mourinho suffered a double setback on Tuesday, with the 3-0 defeat in Newcastle, for the Champions League, and the injury of defender Amar Dedic, who will hardly be able to face Arouca, who lost six of the eight games played at the Estádio da Luz for the competition, but one of the two that drew happened, precisely, last season (2-2).
The ninth round opens this Friday, with Alverca, ninth placed, hosting Gil Vicente, notable fourth placed and which, in case of victory, will equal Sporting in second place, while Minho rivals Vitória de Guimarães (seventh) and Sporting de Braga (eighth) try to reach places more in line with their objectives, facing Famalicão (sixth) and Casa Pia (14th), respectively. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:08:44</pubDate></item><item><title>China criticizes sanctions on Russian oil companies for having “no basis in international law”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/china-critica-sancoes-a-petroliferas-russas-por-nao-terem-base-no-direito-internacional/</link><description>China yesterday criticized the new sanctions announced by the United States Treasury Department against Russian oil companies Rosneft and Lukoil, for “lacking a basis in international law”. “Beijing systematically opposes unilateral sanctions that have no basis in international law and are not authorized by the United Nations Security Council,” said Chinese diplomatic spokesman Guo Jiakun, at a press conference.
According to Guo, dialogue and negotiation remain “the only viable way” to resolve the “crisis” in Ukraine, warning that “coercion and pressure will not solve the problem”.
On Wednesday, Washington announced sanctions against the two main Russian oil companies, accusing them of financing the “Kremlin war machine” and justifying the measure with Russia's alleged “lack of serious commitment” to a peace process to end the war in Ukraine. “Given Russian President Vladimir Putin's refusal to end this senseless war, the Treasury is sanctioning Russia's two largest oil companies,” Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said in a statement.
State-owned Rosneft is responsible for almost 6% of world oil production and about half of Russian production. Together with Lukoil, it exports 3.1 million barrels of crude daily.
The two companies were already under US sanctions, but the new measures now extend to subsidiaries and entities in which they hold more than a 50% stake, directly or indirectly.
The sanctions include freezing assets in the United States, banning transactions with U.S. companies or citizens, and exclusion from the U.S. financial system.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:12:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Health Services call for regular breast cancer screening</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/servicos-de-saude-apelam-ao-rastreio-regular-do-cancro-da-mama/</link><description>Breast cancer has always been the leading cause of new cancers among women in Macau. There were 291 cases of breast cancer and 55 cases of deaths from this disease in 2023. The Health Services emphasize that breast cancer is preventable and controllable, calling for the adoption of measures to maintain breast health, including regular screening exams.

The Health Services urge the public to pay attention to breast health, highlighting that breast cancer has become the most common type of cancer among women in Macau. The organization indicates that residents aged 18 or over must undergo regular screenings for the prevention and control of breast cancer.
According to data from the Health Services, breast cancer has always occupied first place among new cancers among women at least in the last few decades since it has been registered by the authorities.
Macau's most recent cancer report also shows that, in 2023, 291 new cases of breast cancer were registered, with the crude incidence rate per 100,000 women being 80.4. The number of fatal cases from breast cancer was 55 cases, with a crude mortality rate of 15.2 per 100,000 women, with this mortality rate being 10.9 per 100,000 women in 2020.
On the occasion of “International Breast Cancer Awareness Month”, which takes place every year in October, the Health Services hope to raise public awareness about breast cancer and the importance of its prevention and treatment. In a statement, the organization emphasizes that breast cancer is a preventable and controllable disease, therefore, it calls on residents to take proactive preventive measures.
According to authorities, eligible residents can now access the “Cancer Screening Scheduling Platform” in the “My Health” section of the “Single Account” to participate in the breast cancer screening program. "Performing regular breast self-examinations and medical imaging tests is crucial for early detection. High-risk people should consult their doctor to develop a personalized screening plan," they emphasize.
The Health Services say that the public should also be alert to identify the symptoms of breast cancer early, for example, masses in the breasts or armpits, abnormal bleeding from the nipple, abnormalities in the skin of the breast or nipple, and persistent pain in the breast or armpit, among others.
In fact, they warn the public to practice a healthy lifestyle. According to the Health Services, lack of exercise, obesity, smoking and not breastfeeding can increase the risk of breast cancer, so a balanced diet, regular exercise, adequate rest, and encouraging mothers to breastfeed should be maintained.
Those diagnosed with cancer must also actively receive the respective therapy, emphasize the Health Services, and standardized therapy must be started as quickly as possible. The therapy program must be designed according to the different stages of cancer and medical advice, including surgery, chemotherapy, radiotherapy, targeted therapy and hormone therapy.

PATIENT SUPPORT CENTER
 
In the statement, Health Services adds that the Cancer Patient Resource Center is providing comprehensive support to patients and their families facing the challenges of breast cancer.
More than 6,900 users were served at the center last year, including 1,900 users of outpatient nursing consultation services, which were mainly home-based counseling and emotional support after radiotherapy and chemotherapy, and more than 2,600 users of outpatient rehabilitation consultation services.
The organization indicates that the establishment also offers rehabilitation exercise classes after breast surgery, gymnastics for the elderly, healing yoga, among others. Thematic lectures on medical health, health education and various leisure activities are held periodically.
It is worth remembering that Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário recently organized a thematic lecture “Stay Healthy, Share the Love” in response to Breast Cancer Prevention Month. The lecture, which was attended by 30 people, discussed breast cancer therapy, aiming to promote knowledge among patients and the population about the prevention and therapy of this disease.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:18:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Lam expects talent development initiatives to reach “new heights”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/23/o-lam-espera-que-iniciativas-de-desenvolvimento-de-talentos-alcancem-novos-patamares/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture assured that the Government will take advantage of Hengqin's advantages to create an “important platform for the training and gathering of qualified local staff”. On the other hand, O Lam said he hopes that initiatives to develop qualified personnel in the Greater Bay Area will reach “new heights”.

The 3rd Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area Development Conference for High-Quality Skilled Personnel began on Wednesday, taking place in Macau and whose opening ceremony was presided over by O Lam, Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture of the Macao SAR. On the occasion, the governor expressed confidence in Greater Bay Area's talent development initiatives.
In his speech, O Lam recalled that the Macao SAR Government is moving forward with the construction of the Macau and Hengqin International Education (University) City and the State's regional university-industrial technology transfer center. Furthermore, Macau takes advantage of the four national reference laboratories existing in the territory, he noted. These projects aim to “create an important platform for the training and gathering of qualified local professionals”.
At the same time, taking advantage of the Service Platform for Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, “Macau will develop its role as a two-way platform to attract resources from abroad and promote expansion abroad,” said O Lam. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture also said that she “firmly” believes that, “by leveraging the strengths of the three regions of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, the initiatives to develop qualified personnel in the Greater Bay Area will, without a doubt, reach new heights”.
Li Yun, vice-governor of the People's Government of Guangdong Province, also spoke at the opening ceremony of the conference. Quoted in the Macao SAR Government's statement, the official stated that the three regions have deepened cooperation in mutual integration and connectivity, and implemented services that allow for “well-integrated qualified staff”, “easy employment” and “facilitated social security” in the Greater Bay Area.
Zhang Wenmiao, director of the Human Resources Mobility Management Department of the Ministry of Human Resources and Social Security of the People's Republic of China, promised that authorities in mainland China will “firmly support the development of the Greater Bay Area” to “provide better services and a more convenient environment for the development of qualified personnel”.
Warner Cheuk Wing-hing, Deputy Secretary for Administration of Hong Kong, highlighted that qualified personnel “are the main driving force for promoting social progress and economic development and constitute a crucial factor in building a high-quality bay”.
In this edition, the conference includes the Thematic Exhibition Pavilion for Qualified Personnel, where government bodies and companies from the three regions of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau present to the public information on industrial development, commercial investment, qualified personnel policies and development opportunities in the Greater Bay Area, among others. The governments of the cities of the Greater Bay Area and 50 companies participating in the conference will present their qualified personnel policies and the prospects for the development of qualified personnel in companies, with the industries involved including the integrated tourism and leisure industry, finance, technology and big health, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:18:03</pubDate></item></channel></rss>