<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/tui-eleva-pena-de-procurador-adjunto-para-21-anos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Noise in housing buildings motivated more than three thousand complaints last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/ruido-em-edificios-habitacionais-motivou-mais-de-tres-mil-queixas-no-ano-passado/</link><description>Environmental protection services and public security police received more than three thousand complaints about noise in housing buildings last year. However, only 68 of the cases were processed and fined. Authorities stress that the effectiveness of enforcement of the noise law depends on the cooperation of complaints in the process of collection of evidence.
 
Noise in housing buildings generated by social life caused about 3,100 complaints to the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) and the Public Security Police (CPSP) last year, but only 68 cases were accused and fined. The number reveals that the overwhelming majority of cases were archived as they are considered as not detected noise after follow -up.
The statistical data were advanced by the authorities and, among the complaints, most were presented to CPSP and about 300 were received by DSPA. Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, DSPA stressed that, in general, the work of executing the law "has been quiet".
“The application of the noise law has been quiet in general and will continue to be optimized in the future. However, the effectiveness of law enforcement depends, among other factors, the cooperation of the complainants in the process of collection of evidence, so if the complainants can cooperate with the agents responsible for the application of the law, it will be easier to solve the noise problem. ” , he pointed out.
According to DSPA, the noise law regulates mainly the seven sources of noise pollution, while CPSP oversees compliance with daily life and pets in housing buildings and activities in public spaces, while the inspection of other types of Noise is up to DSPA.
Data from the body for last year show that the total number of noise complaints reached 10,538, of which 9,989 were filed and 102 were prosecuted. The “noise generated by social life” was the dominant type between cases and resulted in 7,075 complaints, while “industry, commerce or services” motivated 1,306 complaints and “works of modification, conservation and repair in housing buildings” provoked 632.
A total of 456 complaints arose from “equipment used in construction works and works” and 443 belonged to the noise pollution of “air conditioning and air ventilation equipment”. The “similar shows, fun and activities” led to the presentation of 15 complaints and 164 were “other types of noise”.
In terms of accusations, DSPA had admitted that the prosecution rate was “low,” as it turns out in neighboring regions. Highlighting that there is difficulties in verifying the accusation, the body explained that noise in social life “has a sudden, random and not continuous nature”, so police agents, in most cases, cannot collect evidence, since when they arrive At the site the noise has ceased to exist or due to the lack of cooperation by the complainant. But emphasized that a descent of the number of complaints related to noise in social life was registered.
The DSPA also dismissed the intention to change the noise law, justifying in a previous response to the interpellation that has already revised the noise law and the standard on acoustics in 2019 and 2020.
Cited by the newspaper or Mun, the authorities reported that the current periods of noise control “have balanced” the needs of residents in terms of work, rest and activities, and were established after a broad consultation. In this sense, legislative review is subject to a consensus of society.
DSPA, moreover, revealed to have reinforced the sensitization of the noise law in the places of concentration of people in Macau and, at the same time, has promoted the law through the dissemination of information to the work agencies or the resource management companies Human, providing advertising material in various languages, hoping to improve the sensitization of law by non-resident workers.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:33:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea says DeepSeek sends data from users to Tiktok owner</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/coreia-do-sul-diz-que-deepseek-envia-dados-dos-utilizadores-para-dona-do-tiktok/</link><description>South Korean authorities said yesterday that the Chinese Application of Artificial Intelligence (AI) DeepSeek sent data from South Korean users to Bytedance, owner of the popular Tiktok social network, also of Chinese origin.
 
This is the first time a national regulatory entity confirms the potential data escape from DeepSeek users to third parties, according to the South Korean press, and happens after South Korea joined other countries the day before, In the prohibition of using the Chinese AI application, due to its risks to safety.
The South Korea Personal Information Protection Commission (PIPC) has confirmed the warnings of some cybersecurity experts that DeepSeek could transfer personal data to other entities without the consent of users. "We have confirmed that DeepSeek communicated with Bytedance," said a PIPC spokesman, quoted by local Yonhap news agency, saying that the regulator still has to check what type of data was transferred to the owner of Tiktok and on which scale was .
The South Korean law requires operators to have the explicit consent of users to transfer their data to third parties.
South Korea announced on Monday the withdrawal of Deepseek from local application stores, while investigating the way the Chinese company manages users data.
The PIPC has also issued an official warning about the Chinese AI model, advocating its use, and local ministries and government agencies blocked it. PIPC advised against the use of the Chinese AI model. The local ministries and agencies blocked him.
Previously, local companies such as South Korean automobile manufacturer Hyundai Motor had already restricted their employees' access to Deepseek, also due to possible escapes from their data.
The Ministries of Finance and South Korean environment announced two weeks ago that they were blocking DeepSeek, at least temporarily, thus joining the Ministries of Foreign Affairs, National Defense and Economy, Commerce and Industry, which prevented access to that model from its terminals.
The Ministry of Interior had already recommended to the ministries and the 17 regional governments of the country to be careful against possible data escapes through the use of Deepseek, taking into account what it considers to be a process of storing uncommon by the Chinese company .
DeepSek revolutionized AI's global panorama after the revelation last month of its latest linguistic model, which impressed experts for its most efficient and economic performance compared to United States competition. However, its data management led other countries, such as Italy to Australia, to analyze the service and to impose restrictions on access to public institutions, invoking risks to national security.
 
 
BOX
 
China guarantees that it protects privacy after Seoul accusations of DeepSeek
 
China said yesterday that it attributes great importance to the protection of privacy, after Seoul said that the Chinese application of artificial intelligence (IA) Deepseek sent data on South Korean users to Bytedance, owner of the social network Tiktok. "The Chinese government attributes great importance to data privacy and security and protects them according to the law," said Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakoun. This is the first time that a national regulator confirms the potential escape from DeepSeek users to third parties and has been happening after South Korea joined other countries the day before, in the ban on the use of Chinese AI application, due to their safety risks. The spokesman said China expects "relevant countries to avoid adopting an approach based on generalizations or politicizing economic, commercial and technological issues."</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:41+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Disclosed the results of the contest for conception of itineraries “visit and learn”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/divulgados-os-resultados-do-concurso-para-concepcao-de-itinerarios-visitar-e-aprender/</link><description>The list of works awarded by the Contest for Conception of “Visit and Learning” itineraries was published yesterday, February 18, on the Electronic Page of the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD).
In all, 186 proposals were received, 69 of students of students and another 117 of general groups. Within each group, 10 works with gold, silver and bronze awards and seven with honorable mentions were selected and distinguished, according to criteria that valued, among other factors, the nature of the theme, creativity and viability.
The contest regulation included three topics for the creation of scripts: “Education on the national conjuncture”, “between ancient and modern times” and “cultural and museological exploitation”.
The winners will now be notified by the organizing entity, separately, on the awards survey, whose values ​​oscillate between 3,000 and 10,000 patacas in the student group category and 6,000 and 20,000 patacas in the general group category. The awards ceremony will take place in April, at the 13th International Tourism Expo (Macao Industry).
The contest began on April 28 last year and was later extended until September 27, so as to enable interested parties to improve their candidates. According to STD description, the initiative - intended for both students and the general public - aimed to boost the development of “tourism + education” through the creation of itineraries that would use and explore the potentialities of “Macao Tour Resources” , in a format of “teaching and learning with tour”.
In a press release, STD also emphasizes the efforts it has been developing to promote and encourage other projects under the same motto, “Tourism + Education”. Last year, for example, initiatives such as “Museum Journey: Macao and China Cultural Exchange Meeting”, the “Seminar for the Tourism Promotion Industry for Study Travel in Macao” or Student Tour Activities of Students from Hong Kong Macao.
The Contest for Conception of “Visit and Learning” itineraries, an organization of STD, tells how co-organizers entities the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services, the Cultural Institute, the Polytechnic University of Macao, the University of Tourism of Macao, the Macao Technology Productivity and Transfer Center, the Association of Macao Travel Agencies, the Macao Tourism Agencies Association and the Tourist Industry Association Macao.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Residence for the elderly received 483 candidacies in the second launch phase</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/residencia-para-idosos-recebeu-483-candidaturas-na-segunda-fase-de-lancamento/</link><description>The second round of residence applications for the elderly ended last week and the Social Action Institute received 483 applications, involving about 600 people. Authorities are analyzing the submitted documents and verifying the candidates' self -care capacity, believing that the procedures will be completed “soon”. In addition, no more complaints from tenants were received about the problem of bad smells near the residence for the elderly.
 
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) received a total of 483 applications for the second round of applications to the residence for the elderly, involving more than 600 people. The deadline for presentation of applications ended last Friday and the authorities are now advancing with the assessment work and self-care capacity of the candidates, whose process should be concluded “soon,” said Hon Wai, president of the body .
“Based on the work organization of the last phase, it is believed that we can complete the short-term analysis. Some jobs may take longer, but with the last time experience, we will make them as soon as possible so that interested elderly people can choose their apartments and change faster, ”the official promised, on the sidelines of a Spring lunch that took place yesterday to the workers of social institutions.
Hon Wai also presented the situation of the project's first phase candidacies, which attracted about 900 applications. Everyone has already chosen their fractions, and about 600 families have moved to the residence for the elderly last year, while the remaining 300 candidacies chose to move this year.
Authorities are now dealing with the relevant procedures that should be completed next month, which include the signing of contracts and communication with the tenants. In this case, a total of 900 fractions will be occupied by March.
The president of IAS stressed that a review of the work of the entry of tenants in the residence for the elderly since October last year and “some measures” of improvement, particularly in the care of the elderly and safety, have been taken. “We conducted a fire simulacrum and, last month, we worked with the property management company and our residents to simulate, in order to improve safety work,” he said.
Regarding the issue of bad smells with the residence for the elderly, Hon Wai indicated that IAS no longer received complaints from tenants about the problem. It is recalled that the situation of bad odors on the northern avenue of the Hippodrome avenue motivated ten complaints filed by residents to IAS; Three tenants requested the departure of the apartment and seven intended to change to other units.
Hon Wai was no use the final resolution for these cases, but reiterated that if tenants asked for the exchange of apartments due to concerns or other reasons such as family factors, "authorities will follow the situation and cooperate as far as possible." However, he pointed out that the number of cases of fraction exchange is currently “small”.
 
Less requests for subsidy
 
Regarding the Inclusion and Harmony Program in the community, Hon Wai revealed that each concession attracted the presentation of requests from more than 5,000 families, benefiting over 11,000 people. IAS eventually launched the first concession of the special allowance of this program, whose presentation of requests ended yesterday. The program aims to alleviate the economic pressure of the three types of vulnerable families, such as single -padded families, families with disabled members and families with chronic patients.
The official added that the number of allowances for subsidy has been decreasing in recent years, “which indicates that many families who have applied for subsidy have come out of poverty due to support in various aspects, such as education and work”, he said.
 
ABSENCE OF THE SECRETARY
 
IAS yesterday held a spring lunch from the social services sector, which was attended by about 600 representatives and workers from social institutions, but with the absence of Lam. The secretary for social affairs and culture has been presenting presence and talk about this event in recent years, talking to the media.
In his speech, the president of IAS stressed that this year is the year that marks the beginning of the sixth government and the priorities of the body's work will be the establishment of an improved structure of care for the elderly, reinforcement of cases of detection of cases hidden from isolated elderly and creation of an environment favorable to birth and family.
The body also aims to advance with the set -off plans for the development of the support services to the elderly and rehabilitation between 2026 and 2035, as well as to increase the number of vacancies of support services for the elderly, early intervention and rehabilitation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM provides for growth of 15% of international visitors at MICE events</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/ipim-preve-crescimento-de-15-de-visitantes-internacionais-em-eventos-mice/</link><description>The IPIM president announced the forecast of optimistic numbers for the conventions and exhibition sector, as well as the intention to promote professional formations with international recognition for MICE industry workers. Vincent u devalues ​​the decrease of visitors and revenues obtained in 2024 compared to 2023, and speaks of a “encouraging” and “relatively rapid” recovery compared to the pre-pound numbers.
 
The president of the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), Vincent U, announced that a 15% increase in international visitors is expected at convention events and exhibitions in the year 2025.
Vincent U also stated that, in order to promote the MICE industry - meetings, incentive, conferences and exhibitions - in Macau, workers in this industry will be encouraged to participate in more professional formations, especially those with internationally recognized certificates.
The announcements were made in response to the newly deprived MICE sector statistics, for the year 2024, which point to a decrease in the number of participants and event visitors (less 17.1%) compared to 2023, as well as the generated revenues by this type of activity (less 8.2%). On the other hand, the number of events of this genre increased by 31.4% over the last year.
Speaking to Chinese TDM, Vincent U-who also holds the position of Secretary General of the Commission for the Development of Government of the Government of MSAR-justified the fall of visitors with changes in the international sector, which now enables the Online participation, and the very characteristics of professional MICE events, restricted to a smaller audience.
He also acknowledged the decrease in the expense of visitors compared to the previous year (and, by extension, the revenues obtained), but considered it a consequence of the survey of pandemic restrictions: 2023 being the first year of recovery after Covid-19 , visitors to MICE events were more “aggressive” in their consumer standards.
In the same intervention, it complimented the recovery of the activities of the convention and exhibition sector as “relatively rapid” and equipped it at the foregoing level of 2019. These “encouraging” results are due, it adds, “preparations made during the SARS Outbreak ”and the recovery work done in the last two years.
According to data released Monday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), in 2024 1,524 convention and exhibition events were held, 364 (31,%) than in the previous year of 2023, having The most significant increase focusing on those who focused on the themes “Trade and Management” and “Tourism” (140 and 78 events, respectively).
In turn, the number of participants and visitors did not exceed 1,332,000, a 17.1% reduction in homologous terms, and revenues were 5.48 billion patacas, representing a decrease of 8.2 % compared to 2023.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China defends Europe's participation in peace negotiations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/china-defende-participacao-da-europa-nas-negociacoes-de-paz/</link><description>China's permanent representative at UN, Fu Cong, said yesterday that Beijing greets the agreement between the United States and Russia to start peace talks about Ukraine, but considered it imperative that Europe participate.
"We hope that all parties involved in the crisis in Ukraine will strive in the process of peace dialogue and reach a fair, lasting and binding agreement accepted by all," Fu said during a session dedicated to the matter, on the UN Security Council , whose rotary presidency is occupied by China in February.
Fu's statements, released yesterday by the state press, are the first of a Chinese representative about the agreement between US and Russia.
US Secretary of State Marco Rubio and Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov met in Riade at a meeting that could lead to a summit between Presidents Donald Trump and Vladimir Putin.
The Chinese diplomat expects the parties to "address the profound causes of this crisis through negotiation and find a balanced, effective and sustainable security framework to achieve lasting stability in the region."
However, Fu considered the participation of Europe to be imperative in negotiations, as the conflict "occurs on European soil." "China has consistently defended the peaceful resolution of disputes and global conflicts through dialogue and consultation", something that "applies to the problem of Ukraine", in which Beijing "has been actively involved through diplomatic mediation", maintaining contacts with All parties, he said.
It also defended the proposal presented by China two years ago, an initiative of 12 points that defended respect for sovereignty and territorial integrity of all nations, but also took into account the “legitimate concerns of security” of countries.
This proposal was received with skepticism by the West due to the ambiguity demonstrated by the Asian country during the conflict and its approach to Moscow. "The evolution of the situation has shown that China's proposal is objective, fair, rational and pragmatic, reflecting the broad consensus of the international community," said the Chinese diplomat.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada Consul visited Tis and Must</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/consul-do-canada-visitou-a-tis-e-a-must/</link><description>Charles Edwin Reeves, Canada Consul General in Hong Kong and Macau, visited the Macao International School (TIS) and the Macao University Science and Technology Campus (Must). At TIS, the consul was “warmly received with a musical action of secondary students, giving a cheerful tone to the occasion”, reads in the statement released yesterday by the institution, which adds that, after the musical moment, Charles Reeves wanted to know “Innovative educational approaches and TIS community initiatives”.
According to the press release, one of the highlights of the visit was the presentation of gifts from the school offered by the eldest students of the kindergarten: "This gesture stressed the spirit of collaboration of TIS and the importance of international friendships."
In addition, Consul Reeves conducted a session for secondary students, where he talked about studying abroad, particularly in Canada. This presentation aimed to inform students about the various educational opportunities available and reinforced the consulate's commitment to promote educational relationships that benefit students from Macau and Canada.
Quoted in the press release, the consul considered that this visit was "an excellent opportunity to interact with the strong Canadian community in TIS and continue to build strong relationships to benefit this and future generations of students from Canada and MSAR." Lorne Schmidt, responsible for the school, said that "this visit reinforces the dedication to international education and cultural exchange."
TIS currently has about 1,300 students from 40 different countries.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:31+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau registered 90 cases of suicide last year - the largest number in over a decade</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/macau-registou-90-casos-de-suicidio-o-ano-passado-o-maior-numero-em-mais-de-uma-decada/</link><description>25 people took their lives in the last quarter of 2024. At least 11 years ago, the number of suicides was not so high, aggravating the one that has been a growing and particularly expressive trend after the pandemic restrictions are raised.
 
25 cases of death by suicide were recorded in the fourth quarter of 2024, raising to 90 the total number of cases last year. This is the highest number of suicide deaths recorded in Macao since at least 2013.
The four quarter of 2024 was the one that pointed out the most deadly victims for suicide compared to the remaining three: the first two accounted for 22 cases individually, and the third 21.
The data provided by health services point to a number of male victims far higher than female (17 and 8, respectively) in this last quarter, confirming a majority male incidence in suicide deaths in Macao. The victims belonged to different age groups, aged 13 to 75, and most (20 people, ie 80%) was resident of Macao.
The latest statistics outline a pessimistic portrait of the last decade and show a growing trend in the number of suicides committed in the MSAR: if the year 2023 had already been highlighted by reaching the highest number of the last decade, 88, the total victims of 2024 surpasses it and reaches 90. Nevertheless, it is important to highlight that the data provided by health services and the direction of statistics and census services They only go back to 2013 and do not allow a broader analysis of how this phenomenon has evolved throughout the early 21st century.
In a statement, health services reveal that the data collected allow you to conclude that "the possible causes of suicide are mainly resulting from mental illness and emotional, financial, or game -related diseases." They warn, however, that the causes of suicide are “complex” and that they may be due to a combination of multiple factors such as “mental illnesses, psychological, socioeconomic, family, human relations and biological genetic factors”.
The health authority points out that “effective suicide prevention requires everyone's attention”, and empathy and connection with others are indispensable. “To reduce the incidence of suicide, residents should contact, communicate and worry more about people around them, their daily lives and encourage those who are in emotional problems to actively seek professional help,” he reads If in the press release.
Health services also refer that, given this problem, they have attributed more resources, increasing the accessibility of mental health services and supported non -profit associations in the creation of community psychological counseling institutions. The Government of MSAR has, moreover, and as the press release, “given great importance to the mental health of residents”, namely through the widening of social support networks and the mobilization of the whole society.
Simultaneously, the number of requests for help has also increased. Last December alone, Caritas received a total of 1,406 calls for the “Life Hope” support line, 56 of which were related to people who planned to end life. These numbers show an exponential increase compared to December 2023, when the organization's support line received only 788 phone calls.
Speaking to the end, at the end of last year, Paul Pun, the secretary general of Caritas, indicated that it was the young people who resorted most to the support line, especially due to family and personal problems. Another cause for the increase in requests for help-and that may help contextualize the numbers of the last quarter of 2024-relates to the December festivities: "Festivities also affect interpersonal relationships between family, for example."
Caritas's open line can be contacted by number 28525222 and offers 24 hours support in Chinese, English and even Portuguese. For more information on mental health, health services advise consultation with the “Electronic Mental Health Information Page”, available on the institution's website.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:34:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau will be the scene of the FIA ​​Annual Conference for the first time</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/macau-sera-palco-da-conferencia-anual-da-fia-pela-primeira-vez/</link><description>Macao will host the 2025 FIA annual conference, an unprecedented event in the territory, scheduled to take place between June 10 and 13 at the Galaxy International Convention Center (GICC). The event will bring together more than 500 delegates from 147 countries, seeking to discuss the future of motorized sport and mobility in general. The choice of Macao as a hostess highlights the importance of the region in the field of international motorsport, taking advantage of the Macao Grand Prix as a backdrop and the growing importance of territory in Greater China.
The Fédération Internationale de L'Amaro (FIA) announced that its “Extraordinary General Assemblies and Conference 2025”, or “Extraordinary General Assemblies and 2025 Conference”, official title of the event, will be held in Macao, from 10 to 13 June of the current year. The decision marks the first time that the prestigious event is hosted in the territory, reinforcing Macau's position as a center for motor racing and global mobility.
The conference, which will take place at the Galaxy International Convention Center (GICC), will bring together more than 500 Senior Delegates of the FIA, representing 147 countries. The initiative is the result of a partnership between the FIA, the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC) and the Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG). The event aims to discuss and delineate the future of motorized sport and global mobility at a crucial time for industry, taking into account the new environmental guidelines and sustainability -related issues.
Macao's choice as a 2025 conference hostess is particularly significant, according to the federation itself. Highlighted by the legendary Macao Grand Prix, one of the most emblematic moments of the worldwide motorsport calendar, Macau offers an ideal scenario for the event of great strategic importance.
The challenging stroke of the guide circuit has been the scene of top -pilots' skill demonstrations, including future Formula 1 stars. Macao's tradition in motorsport was recently evidenced in the “celebration of the 75th anniversary of the People's Republic of China and 25th anniversary of Rae de Macao - 71st Macao Grand Prix ”, which included running from the FIA ​​World Cup, attracting international competitors from renown, while opening the new regional formula category simultaneously.
Mohammed Ben Suulayem, president of the FIA, expressed satisfaction with Macau's choice: “Macau is a multicultural and exciting region, the perfect scenario to unite our members from around the world. I thank AAMC and Galaxy Entertainment Group for welcoming us, and I hope for an extraordinary conference and general meeting of success, ”he expressed on the FIA ​​official page.
The strategic importance of this year's conference in Macao is expanded by the growing role of the region in the economic level of Greater China in the adoption of electric vehicles. China remains the largest car market in the world, whether from combustion or electric vehicles. The event in Macau will underline the central role of the region in defining the future of mobility, both in the area of ​​the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay and on the global stage.
“We believe the Galaxy International Convention Center will be the perfect place for the FIA ​​conference. Macau's unique geographical location in the heart of Asia, global accessibility, international cultural heritage and profound appreciation for motorized sport, guaranteed by the 71 years of the Macao Grand Prix, combined with our world -class hotels, will ensure warm And memorable reception to delegates around the world, ”said Francis Lui, president of GEG, in the FIA ​​advanced statement.
Chong Coc Veng, president of AAMC, also left his impression of the importance of the event in Macao: “We are pleased that the 2025 FIA conference will be held in Macao. Macao is a unique destination that preserves a multicultural heritage, coupled with gastronomic, cultural and sports events, including the prestigious Macao Grand Prix, with the Fia World Cups. June is the perfect time to visit Macao and enjoy its distinct flavors and rich culture, with the fusion of Chinese and Portuguese influences. ”
The Galaxy International Convention Center, located at Galaxy Macau Integrated Resort, regularly hosts sports events and world -class conferences, as well as international exhibitions. Gicc's state -of -the -art infrastructure and investments in the development of sport in Macao reflect the government's vision to make Macau in a “sports city”. The FIA ​​conference in 2025 represents another opportunity to boost the integration of tourism and sports in the territory, reinforcing the intention to make Macau in an attractive destination for “Meetings, Encouvents, Conventions and Exhibitions - Mice Tourism” (Meeting Tourism, Incentives , Conventions and exhibitions, in Portuguese).</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:31:37+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Andrea Bocelli acts in Macau on March 29</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/andrea-bocelli-actua-em-macau-a-29-de-marco/</link><description>The Italian tenor Andrea Bocelli will act in the Galaxy Arena on March 29th. According to Galaxy, Bocelli will present a “unique setlist, offering fans of Macao, Hong Kong and all Asia Pacific a rare opportunity to see this artist exceptional live ”. The date of starting the tickets has not yet been revealed.
Throughout his remarkable 30 years of career, Andrea Bocelli has achieved international success through his duet with Sarah Brightman in "Time to Say Goodbye", which was at the top of the German singles table for 14 weeks. Also noteworthy is for collaborations with Celine Dion in “The Prayer” and “Vivo per Lei”.
Andrea Bocelli attracted worldwide attention in 2020 with her record music event, which became one of the biggest musical performances of all time. He also participated in the One World: Together at Home by Lady Gaga concert, joining stars like Lady Gaga, Celine Dion, Lang Lang and John Legend to spread messages of love and hope in difficult times.
Throughout his career, Andrea Bocelli has over 90 million albums sold and over 16 billion streams. BOCELLI has also played for four US presidents, three popes, the British royal family and several prime ministers. “March 29 promises to be an unforgettable night, with Andrea Bocelli giving her first concert in Macao, Galaxy Macau,” reads the organization's press release.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Vietname will dismiss 100,000 civil servants in the largest cut in recent decades</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/vietname-vai-despedir-100-mil-funcionarios-publicos-em-maior-corte-das-ultimas-decadas/</link><description>Vietnam approved a plan to reduce public expense, as part of the objective of achieving an annual growth of 8%, which will imply the dismissal of about 100,000 civil servants. The Vietnamese National Assembly approved the law of government organization with 463 votes in favor of a total of 465 seats in the hemiciclo.
 
The Vietname Parliament yesterday approved a plan to reduce public expense, as part of the purpose of achieving an annual growth of 8%, which will imply the dismissal of about 100,000 civil servants.
The Vietnamese National Assembly approved the law of government organization with 463 votes in favor of a total of 465 seats in the hemiciclo, reported the official newspaper Nhan Dan.
According to the reform, about 100,000 Vietnamese civil servants will lose their employment and the dimension of ministries will be reduced by about 20%, in which it is the highest restructuring since the country's pro-market changes in the 1980s.
The Secretary-General of the Communist Party and Vietnam's top leader, to Lam, defended the reforms, stating, in December, that, “to be healthy, sometimes it is necessary to take a bitter medicine”, indicating that the priority is to rationalize the priority Country management and increase transparency and decentralization.
The Vietnamese government is carrying out an anti -corruption campaign, which critics denounce as aiming at opposite factions of the single party system.
Authorities announced in December that they plan to restructure or merge 14 ministries or ministerial agencies, and only eight will be maintained as they are.
The plan is also part of the Government objectives of 8% growth for this year, compared to 7.09% in 2024, which, according to the authorities, will open the way for the country to reach two -digit growth from 2026.
Government strategies to achieve the goal include, in addition to institutional reforms, the acceleration of public and private investment and the reinforcement of the sectors of the transforming industry and high technology.
Vietnam has established itself as a leading regional production center in semiconductor production, an alternative production destination for China, Hanoi's largest commercial partner. However, the country may be affected by customs rates that US President Donald Trump is considering imposing nations with high tariffs.
On Friday, Vietnamese Industry Minister Nguyen Hong Dien said the country is willing to "open its market by increasing imports from US agricultural products," in order to avoid possible rates.
Hanoi expects imports and exports to grow 12% this year, although rice export prices, one of the main products, have fallen last week to the lowest level of the last nine years. The impact that Trump fares will have on Vietname is still unknown. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:39+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Local film production companies can apply for Filmart 2025 until tomorrow</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/empresas-locais-de-producao-cinematografica-podem-candidatar-se-ao-filmart-2025-ate-amanha/</link><description>Local film and television companies can apply to participate in the Macau Pavilion in the Hong Kong International Film &amp; TV Market (Filmart) 2025, until tomorrow.
The Cultural Institute (IC) will install the Macao Pavilion in the Hong Kong Filmart venue, with the intention of “promoting Macao's film and television production industry and making external projects interested in collecting images in Macao”. In this sense, IC aims to mobilize the participation of Macau's film producing entities and television programs and create a viewing platform for the local sector, “to widen opportunities for exchange and cooperation with the abroad and to stimulate synergy between cultural and creative industries and tourism2.
Applications are intended for Macao companies with experience and historical filming assistance in Macao of a minimum of six non-local cinematic and television projects, from 2014 to 2024. IC will then select up to eight companies to participate in the event, based on criteria such as their experience in supporting the production held in Macao of Cinematographic and Television Projects outside the interior of China, Macao, Hong Kong and Taiwan, the size of non -local cinematic and television projects to which support was provided during their production in Macau and the functions performed during the process. Companies that have already registered do not need to resubmit the registration again.
Regulations and application form can be consulted and discharged on the Macao Cultural and Creative Industries Page at www.macaucci.gov.mo.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government of Timor-Leste and New Zealand discuss work program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/governo-de-timor-leste-e-nova-zelandia-discutem-programa-de-mobilidade-laboral/</link><description>The Timor-Leste government and the New Zealand Embassy began discussions about the Labor Mobility Program yesterday between the two countries. “The objective of this meeting was to start discussions with the State Secretariat of Vocational Training and Employment (Sefope) about the Labor Mobility System. New Zealand's scheme applies to the sectors of horticulture and fruiting, ”the New Zealand ambassador in Timor-Leste, Helen Tunnah told reporters.
The ambassador explained that there is still no date for the start of the program or a defined number of workers, but expects, after discussions with the Timorese authorities, to have a “well -structured program”.
Regarding the criteria for Timorese workers to apply for jobs in New Zealand, the diplomat stressed that technical teams on both sides will discuss the best possible benefits for workers.
The Secretary of State for Vocational Training and Employment, Rogério Araújo Mendonça, explained that the meeting yesterday held was extremely important, especially to advance to the phase of a possible signing of a memorandum of understanding later this year. “There is not yet an agreement between the two governments. We are only in the discussion phase. The government of New Zealand and the Timor-Leste embassy in New Zealand will continue to work together, ”he said.
The Secretary of State has also appealed to young people who are preparing for the program that verify the existing training centers in the municipalities and at national level, to enroll in formations in the areas already identified by New Zealand, namely horticulture and fruit growing.
Timor-Leste currently has work programs, with Australia, South Korea and Japan.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan will include Taiwan as a place of origin in family records</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/japao-vai-incluir-taiwan-como-local-de-origem-nos-registos-familiares/</link><description>Japan will allow citizens of Taiwan to subscribe to the island as a place of origin in the country's family record instead of China, a Japanese Ministry of Justice official said yesterday. When a Japanese citizen marries a person of foreign origin, the nationality and name of the spouse are registered in the registration system maintained by the authorities.
Currently, the people of Taiwan are described as from China. However, "from May, following a revision of the Ministry's rules, the name of the territory can be registered in the" nationality "field of family registration," said a Ministry of Justice official, quoted by France-Presse .
The Japanese residence record and certificates of foreign and long -term foreign residents already allow Taiwan's registration as a territory of origin. "Practical difficulties also arose due to discrepancies in the names of countries or territories: Taiwan in the permission of residence and China in the family record," the official said to justify this administrative harmonization.
Tokyo cut official relations with Taiwan in 1972, indicating at the time, in a joint statement with Beijing, which he understood and respected the fact that "Taiwan was an inalienable part of the territory of the Popular Republic of China."
However, Japan has maintained narrow economic ties with Taiwan and TSMC's Taiwanese giant TSMC opened a new factory in Japan last year.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:38+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International activity of the bank sector recorded an increase in the end of last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/actividade-internacional-do-sector-bancario-registou-aumento-no-fim-do-ano-passado/</link><description>The proportion of the international activity of the Macao Bank Sector recorded an increase in the fourth quarter of last year, said the monetary authority of Macao (AMCM), which adds that Macao's international banking activity was mainly distributed through Asia.
 
The proportion of the international activity of the Macao bank sector increased in the fourth quarter of last year. The information was released yesterday by the monetary authority of Macau (AMCM).
On the other hand, AMCM says the quota of financial investments in international markets in the total active of the banking system grew 0.1 percentage points to 83.4% recorded in December last year. International responsibilities in the total liability of the banking system increased from 80.5%, recorded at the end of September 2024, to 80.9%.
AMCM also reported that Pataca is not the main currency in international bank transactions. At the end of last year, the Macao coin occupied a quota of 0.8% and 0.6%, respectively, in the total asset and total of international financial liabilities. Hong Kong's dollar accounted for 31.9%, the US dollar 39.3%and Renminbi 20.3%, for example. The Hong Kong dollar, the US dollar, Renminbi and other foreign currencies accounted for 31.9%, 39.3%, 20.3%and 7.6%, respectively, the total of the international active and 38.4%respectively and 38.4% , 38.5%, 19.0%and 3.5%, respectively, of total international liability.
The AMCM details that, at the end of December 2024, the total of the Macao Bank Sector International Assets grew 0.4% of the previous quarter, having reached 2,010.4 billion. It is to mark a growth of 3.5%, corresponding to 1,499.2 billion patacas of availability over the outside and a decrease of 7.6%, corresponding to 511.2 billion patacas of local active in foreign currencies. Loans of banking on the outside that constituted most international assets grew by 18.8%, having reached 536.9 billion patacas.
The total international responsibilities of the Macao bank sector reached 1,952.1 billion patacas, having registered a rise of 0.8% compared to the fee registered three months ago. Responsibilities to abroad reached 1,013.1 billion patacas, when compared to those of the previous quarter, corresponding to a quarterly growth of 3.9%, while internal responsibilities in foreign currencies recorded a decrease of 2.2% to 939 billion Patacas. Deposits in foreign residents and MSAR government in local banks represent the largest component in the total of international responsibilities. These deposits grew by 3%, having reached 722.6 billion patacas at the end of December 2024.
According to AMCM, Macao International Bank Activity was distributed mainly through Asia. Until the end of December 2024, the Macao Banking System cash wands within China and Hong Kong were 39.5% and 24.2%, respectively, in the total of outside active. The quotas of availability in Portuguese -speaking countries and in the countries integrated in the initiative “a track, a route” occupied 0.6% and 12.1%, respectively.
As for liabilities over the outside, they registered a 40.3% quotas for Hong Kong and 38.9% to the interior of China. Regarding Portuguese -speaking countries and the countries integrated in the initiative “One Range, a Route” registered quotas of 0.3% and 8.8%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:32:36+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Strain has been “basilar stone” of cooperation between Macau and the interior of China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/cepa-tem-sido-pedra-basilar-da-cooperacao-entre-macau-e-o-interior-da-china/</link><description>Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, participated yesterday in a session of dissemination and clarification regarding the changes made to the Student and Commercial Relations of Narning Relations between China and Macao (Cepa). At the time, the ruler assured that the MSar will maintain a “close communication and cooperation” with the interior of China.
 
Yesterday morning, a dissemination and clarification session was held on the changes made to the Economic and Commercial Relations of Narrowing Agreement between the interior of China and Macao (CEPA). The session was attended by Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, which highlighted the importance of cooperation between Macao and the Chinese continent.
This strain II, which comes into force on March 1, provides, for example, the reduction of access requirements for Macau service providers and the elimination of the exercise requirement, at least three years, of substantial commercial activity in Macau so that the startups can benefit as soon as possible from the preferential treatment provided for in the strain. In addition, new liberalization measures are added to the sectors of state, financial, audiovisual and cultural technology services, among others.
In the speech given at the time, Tai Kin IP described the strain as “the important basic stone of economic and commercial cooperation between the interior of China and Macao”, noting that the agreement has provided “an important institutional guarantee for the deepening of economic cooperation and commercial between the two territories ”. This “has not only promoted deep integration and synergistic development of both parties into the economic and commercial area, but has also given solid support and wide development opportunities to Macao companies in the exploration of the interior market of China”, defended the Secretary for Economics and Finance of MSAR.
These changes to the strain demonstrate “the continuous widening of the degree of liberalization from the interior of China to the MSAR, constituting a concrete practice of the country in promoting high level exterior in the new era, also representing a significant measured measured to support the integration of Since at the conjuncture of national development, ”said Tai Kin IP.
The secretary also pointed out that the new measures “not only will provide new opportunities and spaces for the development of the proper diversification of the economy of Macau, but will also offer greater facilities for professionals in the areas of construction, accounting, medical treatment, education, etc. ., to develop their professional careers in the interior of China and extend the development margins of their professional services, thus providing more favorable conditions for the integration of the various sectors of the community of Macau at the great conjuncture of national development ”.
In conclusion, Tai Kin IP reiterated that "the Government of MSar will continue to maintain close communication and cooperation with the respective state ministries and commissions."</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:37+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese technological actions rise with demonstration of support from Xi Jinping</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/accoes-das-tecnologicas-chinesas-sobem-com-demonstracao-de-apoio-de-xi-jinping/</link><description>The actions of China's technology companies rose yesterday during the morning session on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, after Chinese President Xi Jinping, having met with sector executives on Monday.
The Hang Seng Tech index, which brings together the actions of the country's large technology, rose 3.04%, until the session break, and has already accumulated a valuation of about 30% this year, also due to optimism in relation to the Chinese sector Artificial Intelligence (IA), after the launch of DeepSek's great language model.
The best performances of the session were from the Xiaomi (+5.87%) electronics and electric vehicle manufacturer and the short video sharing platform (+9.7%).
Tencent and Alibaba digital giants, the two largest companies in the market capitalization index, rose 3.42% and 4.34%, respectively.
On the Chinese continent, the climbs were more modest, with the Shenzhen scholarship - centered precisely in the technology sector companies - to rise 0.13% and the 0.29% Shanghai Scholarship.
During the meeting with businessmen, on Monday, Xi called for “to make the most of their abilities”, in what he classified as a “privileged moment” to “reaffirm trust” in the private sector.
The meeting was attended by Xiaomi, Byd and Huawei, although the most prominent figure was the founder of Alibaba and once the richest man in the country, Jack Ma, in his apparent official reconciliation with the Chinese leader, after More than four years practically missing from public life after criticizing financial regulators during a speech in Shanghai.
The meeting was seen as a demonstration of support from Xi to a sector that in recent years has suffered a regulatory campaign of the authorities, which resulted in multimilior fines to companies such as Alibaba, Tencent and “Uber Chinese” Didi.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tui Elevates Penalty of Assistant Prosecutor for 21</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/19/tui-eleva-pena-de-procurador-adjunto-para-21-anos/</link><description>Macao's deputy prosecutor Kong Chi was sentenced to 21 years in prison. The prosecutor had appealed from the 17 -year -old sentence in a process where he was accused of helping people escape to court.
 
Kong Chi was yesterday sentenced to 21 years in prison, after the prosecutor appeals to the 17 -year sentence in a process where he was accused of helping people escape to court. “The final decision on the case of passive corruption and the prevarication of the prosecutor's magistrate (which is suspended from duties), which was convicted in 21 years in prison, was rendered by the TUI [Last Instance Court, which ] Consider it guilty of the crime of association or secret society ”, reads in a statement released late in the afternoon by the office of the president of Tui.
In January last year, Macao's Second Instance (TSI) considered Kong Chi guilty of dozens of passive corruption crimes for unlawful act, abuse of power, prevarication and violation of secrecy of justice.
The sentence also decided the loss, in favor of the Macao authorities, of assets arrested by the assistant prosecutor worth 14 million, considering “of unknown origin”.
The five judges of the Collective Court considered that this money will have come from bribes, disguised as “fees or consulting fees”, paid to the couple of entrepreneurs in the Choi SAO money exchange business.
In return, according to the TSI sentence, between 2008 and 2015, the assistant prosecutor ignored evidence, advised people under investigation to change testimonials, shared confidential information or under secret justice, even in cases attributed to other prosecutors.
The assistant prosecutor, who had been on a long-term unpaid fork since February 2022, who returned to Macao in September 2023, and was immediately placed in pre-trial detention, had denied all accusations.
The macao justice applied at the time still penalties of 14 and six years in prison, respectively, Choi Sao Ieng and Ng Wai Chu. Now Tui has also reviewed the feathers of Choi and NG, condemning them to 16 and ten years, respectively.
In this case was also involved the lawyer of Portuguese nationality Kuan Hoi Lon, which the TSI acquitted because it considered that there was never any contact with Kong Chi.
In 2017, former Ho Chio Meng Attorney, who led the Macau MP from the transition from Portugal to China in 1999 until 2014, was sentenced to 21 years in prison for various crimes, including bleach, whitening of capitals and criminal association. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-19T03:36:32+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>