<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/bnu-organiza-seminario-sobre-o-espirito-das-duas-sessoes/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Beijing highlights “Macao progress in patriotic education”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/pequim-destaca-progressos-de-macau-na-educacao-patriotica/</link><description>LAM, Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, was in Beijing between March 29 and April 1, where he met with China Communist Party Department (CCP), who applauded Macao's efforts in the scope of patriotic education.
The secretary met with Hu Hipan, head-to-law responsible for the daily work of the Communication Department of the CCP Central Committee, which highlighted “Macao's remarkable progress in patriotic education”, reaffirming the “continuous support” of her department to the “Macao Cultural Industry Development”.
Human also expressed the “hope of additional strengthening of mutual cooperation between the CCP Central Committee Department and the Government of MSAR in social and cultural affairs, promoting the Macao compatriots to continue the beautiful traditions of love for the homeland and Macau”.
Beijing's guardian expects greater promotion of exchange between civilizations and greater proactivity in promoting Macao's sociocultural integration in the global conjuncture of the country's development.
The LAM and the MSAR delegation also visited the Ministry of Education, where they met with Wu Yan, Deputy Minister of Education, to talk about “the construction of a strong nation in the field of education and the continuity of the implementation of the development of the Macao Higher Education System”. Wu Yan expressed his support for the development of Macao education and expressed his hope that Macau can contribute to the integration of education, science and technology and qualified staff in the country, says the government's government statement.
Wu Yan also suggested that Macau's higher education institutions adopt a "high quality development" as well as to operate with "high precision" and "integrate into the general conjuncture of the country's development."
The delegation of the MSA also visited the China Communist Party Museum and the National Performance Arts Center, “where the magnificent history of the Communist Party of China in its 100 years of struggle, as well as the country's important cultural facilities, reads in the government's statement, which underlines that the masters intends to“ continue to explore cooperation with the Communist Party Museum and the National Center for Performative Arts. of the country's educational, cultural and historical resources and support Macau to continue to enrich the content of 'a base'. ”</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:06:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Promoted “Instagramble” tour with guidance from photographer David Lopo</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/promovido-passeio-instagramavel-com-orientacao-do-fotografo-david-lopo/</link><description>On April 12, the city will be the scene of a group photographic adventure entitled “Instagramble Macau”, promoted by the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) in partnership with Casa de Portugal in Macau. This photographic tour, according to the organizers, aims to provide an enriching and relaxed afternoon, intended for young people and adults with interest in photography and creative interaction on social networks.
The event will start at 15h00, with the meeting point in the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery. Participants will be able to use any type of camera, including mobile phones, as well as collecting the necessary equipment, including audio guides, before starting a visual excursion that will last for three emblematic locations near Grand Lisboa. The iconic building, known for its powerful presence, will be the ideal scenario to capture images that reflect not only the architectural heritage of the city, but also the moved social environment around it.
David Lopo, the mentor of the event, brings with it a rich formation and experience in the field of photography. A native of Porto, Portugal, David had his first contact with photography during the university years, where he completed a degree in sound and image at the Catholic University of Porto. In 2019, David moved to Macao with the aim of expanding his horizons and focusing on the areas of photography and digital illustration. Currently, in addition to acting as a freelancer, he works at Casa de Portugal, teaching multimedia courses, including photoshop and photography, as well as conducting didactic activities to younger generations, such as the current photography project.
Registration for the tour is free, but limited to 20 participants, which ensures a more personalized and rich experience. To ensure the logistics organization of the event, interested parties must register in advance, sending an email to * Protected email * or contacting number 28923288, informing your name and phone number, until 6 pm on April 11.
This tour is not only intended to promote the aesthetic appreciation of Macau, but also to celebrate the 13th anniversary of the FRC. The event takes place in Portuguese and English.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Caritas alerts to the lack of services for the elderly before aging</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/caritas-alerta-para-carencia-de-servicos-para-idosos-perante-o-envelhecimento/</link><description>Paul Pun, Secretary General of Caritas, considers that government policies for the elderly population “will not be able to accompany Macau's rhythm of aging” in the future. For Pun, the executive should solve the problem of the long line waiting for the elderly homes, as well as the lack of vacancies for home care services.
 
Caritas defends the review and improvement of policies for the elderly, namely social assistance measures, as well as the quality and number of vacancies of senior care services.
Paul Pun, Secretary General of Caritas, stressed that Macau is facing a problem of continuous aging and decreased birth, warning of the future social structure that will gradually evolve into an aged society.
"Although the government has already invested funds to improve the work of care for the elderly and increasing the number of places for various services in response to elderly services in the community, it will not be able to track the long -term aging pace," Pun said in statements to the newspaper or Mun.
Emphasizing the predictable insufficiency of services to the elderly population, Paul Pun said it is necessary for the government to consider supporting measures to seniors in a long -term perspective.
It is recalled that the present government is about to present its first report of the government lines, which is scheduled for next Monday. The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, has mentioned several times that the governing team attributes great importance to issues related to children and the elderly, and will develop measures dedicated to these two groups of the population. Government statistics show that the aged population in Macau continues to increase and, at the end of last year, there were 100,200 elderly people 65 or older, representing more than 14% of the total population.
Paul Pun, in this context, pointed out that social assistance, health care and transport policies should be optimized. "According to the experience of social services, the long waiting time for the elderly homes and the lack of places for home care are common problems in Macao," he said.
He explained, based on the current waiting list of 1,000 people to the public homes, about two thirds of people, ie 600 people, need integrated home care services. "Care providers can only find workers to help or take care for themselves. Thus, the government is expected to increase resources for home care services in the future, so as to relieve pressure on care providers," he suggested.
In addition, Paul Pun proposes to introduce incentives to encourage the elderly to have a healthy life, so that the public can prepare to their own aging and aging of society, thus reducing the investment of public resources and society.
It also requested more sports facilities for the elderly. Paul Pun hopes that there are incentives for the elderly population to do more exercise in order to slow down the decline of their physical functions and maintain their physical and mental health.
 
Deputy calls for an increase in the value of the pension for the elderly
 
Deputy Nick Law renewed the request to the government to review the pension adjustment mechanism for the elderly, linking it directly in the future to the value of social risk, with the aim of reinforcing the protection of the reform of the elderly. The deputy highlighted the growing challenges in the future about the work related to the care of the elderly and considered that the government must ensure the “basic protection” of the life of the elderly population to inflation. "The performance of many elderly comes from the government and some of them have no other income or savings, so the government's social protection plays an indispensable role in the lives of the elderly," said Nick Law, also suggesting the creation of a "security network" for the most basic needs of the elderly.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:08:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan says negotiations with USA on rates include exchange rates</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/japao-diz-que-negociacoes-com-eua-sobre-taxas-incluem-taxas-de-cambio/</link><description>Japanese finance minister Katsunobu Kato yesterday indicated that the exchange rate between the dollar and the yen will be on the table in negotiations with the United States about tariffs.
 
Kato confirmed what analysts have been suggesting, based on the United States' priority objective of reducing trade balance with countries with which they have deficit and to which tariffs -which he calls reciprocal -such as Japan. “There were several communications with the American side, including exchange rates, and then movements in the gearboxes, although the details have not yet had the details. It has been determined, ”Kato said in a speech in the Japanese parliament.
The leader also explained that discussions about the exchange rate will be held among the finance ministers of both countries.
The Japanese government announced on Tuesday that the minister responsible for economic revitalization and new capitalism, Ryosi Akazawa, will be Tokyo's main representative in tariff negotiations. Washington, in turn, appointed the duo graduated by Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent and commercial representative Jamieson Greer to lead the team.
Observers pointed out the possibility that Washington demands that Tokyo take measures to strengthen yen over the dollar, a measure that would help reduce the cost of Japanese imports to the United States and reduce the country's current commercial deficit with Japan.
This could be the counterpart that the United States demands from Japan for reducing the imposed tariffs and would also be in line with Banco do Japan (Boj) plans to continue to increase interest rates, which are currently 0.5%, while the economic situation allows.
Although Iene has valued about 7% over the dollar so far this year, it has dropped 25% over the dollar since 2020.
Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba and US President Donald Trump talked by telephone on Monday and agreed to start discussions about the rates that went into effect yesterday.
Bessent signaled on Tuesday through the US social network to maintain “productive conversations” with Japan, “one of the closest allies” in the country, and indicated that they will include “rates of tariffs, non-tariff barriers, exchange issues and state subsidies”.
White House spokeswoman Karoline Leavitt also said the negotiations will be "adapted to the case of each country" and include more than just tariffs, including "foreign aid or US military presence and how it is paid" for this mobilization.
Greer, in turn, declared in a speech in the US Senate that Japan faces "structural impediments" to US industrial exports. He noted, moreover, that the US "could have greater and better access to the Japan agricultural market."
The "reciprocal tariffs" that the United States-the largest market for Japanese exports-began to apply yesterday to 24% in the case of Japan and are added to another 25% vehicle, steel and aluminum imports battery.
 
Aid of 1.8 billion euros for South Korean automotive industry
 
South Korea yesterday announced a help of 1.8 billion euros to support car manufacturers after the imposition of additional 25% tariffs on the US imported vehicles. "Given that cars and car parts are the main exports of South Korea to the United States, we hope that the decision to impose customs rights of 25% on these articles will be a significant blow to our automotive sector," the government said in a statement.
United States President Donald Trump announced last week punitive tariffs on imports to the US from most globe countries. South Korean products are subject to an additional 25% tax from yesterday.
The US leader, who returned to the White House in January for a second term, also decided to aim at the cars produced abroad and sold in the US with a 25%surcharge, as well as certain spare parts manufactured outside the United States.
The South Korean government said that, having consulted the national automotive industry, it decided to introduce "a set of measures to protect the sector, focusing on the most urgent demands."
South Korean car exports to the US totaled $ 42.9 billion (38.9 billion euros) by 2024, according to authorities. As part of the announced help plan, Seoul will increase by two billion of Won (1.2 billion euros) a financing program for the automotive industry.
The main South Korean builder, Hyundai Motor, will also create a support plan for a Won billion (610 million euros) for the sector's South Korean companies, in partnership with the main financial institutions.
Companies affected by the US commercial offensive can also benefit from tax postponements up to nine months, according to Seoul. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:09:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Weng Cheong and Rusty Fox open wings to the new exhibition space with print and conceptual photography</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/wong-weng-cheong-e-rusty-fox-abrem-alas-a-novo-espaco-expositivo-com-gravura-e-fotografia-conceptual/</link><description>Macau has a new home for creativity. The Lotus Art Space (LAS), in the fishermen's dock, debuts its space with the exhibition “Whispers of the Unseen”. The show presents the works of Wong Weng Cheong and Rusty Fox, which investigate the intersection of technology and urban disconnection. While Wong creates surrealist compositions that challenge perception, Fox captures moments that reveal alienation in everyday life.
 
The Lotus Art Space, a new reference point on Macau's art scene, first opened its doors on March 26 with the exhibition “Whispers of the Unseen”, a duo shows that it brings together the work of two emerging artists: Wong Weng Cheong and Rusty Fox.
The curatorship, in charge of Chang and Lam Sio Man, explored the diversity of the creative practices of these two local artists who, while using different means, share an enriching metaphorical approach to contemporary reality. Wong Weng Cheong, through high precision engraving techniques, presents scenes that combine hyperrealism with surrealism, reflecting internal desires and conflicts that inhabit the human psyche. In turn, Rusty Fox uses photography to capture aspects of urban life that often go unnoticed, transforming everyday life into a visual poetics that questions normality, while metamorphosis nature into almost human forms.
The “Whispers of the Unseen” exhibition is not just limited to showing works, but it also intends to be an opportunity for the public to engage in deep dialogues about human experience and the complexity of modern life. Through his two -dimensional works, Wong and Fox invite viewers to an introspection of the "whispers" that permeate their reality and dreams.
Wong Weng Cheong, born in Macao and graduated in Fine Arts from Goldsmiths College at the University of London, uses modern technologies such as artificial intelligence and 3D graphics to create immersive compositions. His work covers from dead compositions to digital installations and images, characterized by a realistic representation of surreally quiet scenes. According to Wong's description, the artist seeks, through his works, to challenge the perception of space by viewers, encouraging a reflection on underlying social relations. His last exhibition “Above Zobeide” represented Macao at the 2024 Venice Biennial.
Rusty Fox, in turn, is a photographer who grew up shaped by the dynamics of urban life. His art explores the contrast between living organisms and inanimate objects, questioning the nature of the people who inhabit the city as described on its official page. With a solid formation in photography, including a master's degree in documentary photography at the University of South Wales, Fox has already exposed internationally, standing out at photography festivals in Europe and Asia. His work causes deep reflections on human condition and emotional disconnection in the midst of the city's accelerated life, refers to his latest “night” publication.
In addition to being a showcase for these talented local artists, the show marks the launch of the “International Macao Art Exhibition Program 2025”, promoted by Lotus International Art Exchange Association. This program aims to bring the creations of Wong Weng Cheong and Rusty Fox to international platforms, such as the cities of New York and London, positioning Macao in the panorama of global contemporary art and reinforcing cultural exchange.
With an area of ​​110 square meters inside the Legend Palace Hotel, LAS has the mission of presenting a diverse variety of high quality art exhibitions, public programs and events that foster connections between local and international artistic communities. A project guided by Lam Sio Man, also curator of this new exhibition.
The construction collection will be available for visits until April 30th. Visitors will be able to enjoy the exhibition from Tuesday to Sunday, from 12h00 to 19h00, except on Mondays. The Lotus Art Space is located in store H, on the Legend Palace Hotel, in the fishermen's dock, to the right of the entrance of the hotel shopping center.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>D'As Ascens presents photographic exhibition about the beauty of Macau's daily life</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/das-entranhas-apresenta-exposicao-fotografica-sobre-a-beleza-do-quotidiano-de-macau/</link><description>The Portuguese Bookstore Art Gallery will receive the photographic exhibition “Remains of the City”, a project by Pedro Paz and organized by D´Ama Enda Macau - Cultural Association. With an inauguration scheduled for next Tuesday, April 15, the collection of 33 photographs proposes the recovery of the “banal and ephemeral” landscape of the streets of Macao, so often ignored by the inhabitants, in a letter of love of the “beauty of the little things of everyday life”.
 
D'As As Endas Macau - Cultural Association will present the photographic exhibition “Remains of the City”, by Pedro Paz, between April 15 and May 6, at the Portuguese Bookstore Art Gallery. The inauguration takes place next Tuesday, at 18:30, with free admission.
The show brings together a selection of 33 color photographs captured between 2018 and 2020 in mobile chamber, “by choice and as a form of artistic expression”. Divided into three series ("You've Got Mail", "Framing the Invisible" and "Where Chaos Meets Color"), compilation comes to present a vision of Macao centered on scenic details full of color, history and meaning that help to trace the contemporary portrait of Macanese identity, the result of a miscellaneous cultures and realities.
According to a press release from the Association of As Guts, the “pictorial, without the human presence” approach to the houses, objects and architecture of the territory serve as an invitation to the public to observe “the urban daily life of Macao in another way, where the details that often pass us out of poetic composition of aesthetic impact”.
The intention of the 33 works gathered in this show, continues the association, is to allow photography to take over as a static portrait, but an immersive experience of reflection and exploitation of the territory. “The author's work goes beyond the moment: immortalizing fragments of reality, giving them depth, highlighting details of the daily life that escape the hasty look from the inhabitants of the city,” reads, in the note sent to the press. "His work reveals the invisible in the visible and proposes a reflection on the deep layers of reality, where the banal and the ephemers are eternalized. Observing and reflecting on these photographs offers an experience that goes beyond the look. Each image invites us to rediscover the meaning and beauty of the small things of everyday life."
Pedro Paz was born in Lisbon in 1979, having spent his childhood in Macao until he was 18, in 1997. Degree in History, with a strand in art and heritage, the photographer eventually returned to the “historical streets and alleys that marked his childhood” in 2012, “rediscovering elements of a distant past” and “urban landscapes, textures, non -inhabited places in this exhibition.
The D'As As Guts Macau - Cultural Association is a structure of artistic creation and diffusion based in Macau that promotes the diffusion of contemporary art in different areas. In addition to the organizer, the event is also sponsored by the Fund for the Development of Culture of the Government of MSA and has the support of the Portuguese Bookstore.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Asian bank wants Timor-Leste to invest more to develop human capital</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/banco-asiatico-quer-timor-leste-a-investir-mais-para-desenvolver-capital-humano/</link><description>The Asian Development Bank (BAD) defended yesterday in the report on the perspectives of economic growth for Asia that Timor-Leste should increase investment in human capital development.
 
"High rates of poverty and malnutrition persists, alarming levels of delay in child growth and gaps in the domains of health, education and competences," can be read in the report, which considers investment in human capital a "significant political challenge."
Highlighting the creation of the interministerial task force for government social affairs, as a “promising step” for the development of “early childhood, nutrition and food security and the empowerment of young people”, BAD argues, however, that investment can still be “more reinforced”.
For this, BAD proposes the optimization of budgetary expense with the increase of public investment in education, the development of skills, social protection and health.
According to the bank, that increase should be a "priority" because it remains below the target of 8% of gross domestic product, defined in the Timor-Leste strategic development plan for 2011-2030. "National health and education investment spending can more than double, through the relocation of current expenses, ensuring the proper functioning and greater efficiency of public services," argues that financial institution in the report.
BAD also proposes that investments in human capital development are “well targeted” and that more work is needed to improve access to health services, support early childhood development with education, health and nutrition programs.
For young people, BAD argues that more continuous learning opportunities, scholarships and technical and professional training be provided and, on the other hand, that social protection systems are reinforced with the attribution of more support. "The reinforcement of investments in the development of human capital is essential to promote long -term economic growth and achieve sustainable development objectives," the report points out. Finally, the report proposes that resources must be mobilized more effectively through policies and regulations that favor public-private partnerships.
Timor-Leste is one of the youngest countries in the world with 1.3 million inhabitants, 64.6% of which are under 30 years old. But according to UN data, 47% of children under the age of five suffers from chronic bad nutrition, 8.6% acute malnutrition, 32% have a weight below and deficiencies of vitamin A, iron and iodine. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:09:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Collective exposure in the SCM Hostel reflects on the relationship between technology and nature</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/exposicao-colectiva-no-albergue-scm-reflecte-sobre-a-relacao-entre-tecnologia-e-natureza/</link><description>The exhibition “Verses of Rain in Late Spring”, organized by CAC - Circle of Macao Culture Friends, will present more than a dozen multimedia work signed by five artists. The inauguration ceremony will take place on April 16, at 6:30 pm, at the Holy House of Mercy Holy Artistic Center (SCM), where the show will remain on display until May 28.
Participating artists in the exhibition - Cindy NG Sio Ieng, Kit Ka Ieng Kit, Wang Tou Kun, Chon Iap Lam and Xiaoqian LI - will resort to modern technological methods such as digital photography, interactive digital sound installations, computer -made paintings and invisible paint to create works that have both visual and auditory impact.
The virtual lighting techniques used by the collective simulate natural light and shadow effects that refer to spring days, while the sound data collected in real time allows the audience to “experience the rhythm of coexistence between all living beings” according to the description made by CAC in a statement. The result is an “interdisciplinary creation” that challenges the canons of traditional artistic narratives, reinterpreting the “ecological wisdom incorporated into the 24 solar terms” established in ancient China and exploring “issues of technology and sustainable development”.
“The goal is to provide the public a cyclic philosophical experience of‘ Rain nourishes All Grains ’, encouraging contemplation of the relationship between technology and nature while appreciating art,” summarizes the CAC. Grain Rain station happens around late spring when temperatures increase and rain becomes more frequent. This concept, known as Guyu in Chinese language, was the sixth of the 24 solar terms created by ancient Chinese agricultural societies and the last regarding spring.
The CAC originated in 1985 in Macao, with the purpose of promoting various types of cultural activities in the region, as well as the dissemination of indigenous talents.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Central Banks of India and New Zealand lower interest rates</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/bancos-centrais-da-india-e-nova-zelandia-baixam-taxas-de-juro/</link><description>The central banks of India and New Zealand yesterday cut interest rates at 0.25 percentage points, respectively, to 6% and 3.5%, due to the increase in tariffs announced by the United States and the global commercial uncertainty.
"Recent tariff increases and uncertainty about global trade policy have weakened the prospects for world economic activity," the New Zealand reserve bank said in a statement, one of the first to react to economic turbulence that affects the world markets.
"Following a detailed assessment of the evolution of macroeconomic and financial conditions and perspectives, the Committee of Monetary Policy of the Bank of the India Reserve (RBI)] unanimously voted to reduce the reference rate by 25% base to 6% with immediate effect," said RBI governor Sanjay Malhotra, in a video statement.
"Recent measures related to customs rights on trade exacerbated uncertainties regarding economic perspectives in the regions, which represents new winds against global growth and inflation," said Malhotra.
With similar arguments, the two countries thus reacted to the tariffs announced by the United States last week, at a minimum customs rate of 10% over all exports to the United States and additional tariffs imposed on about 60 countries, in force since last Saturday and yesterday, respectively. In response, China has announced rates about the US, while other countries chose to negotiate with Washington.
The New Zealand Central Bank stresses that "the tariff increases announced by the United States, the retaliation actions of various business partners and the growing geoeconomic uncertainty will have a significant negative impact on global growth." "The search for our exports should decrease, reflecting a weaker activity in the economies of our business partners, especially in Asia," anticipates the Central Bank, which also points to a possible decrease in imports.
In addition to a similar perspective on exchanging exchanges, RIB also announced a reduction in Indian Gross Domestic Product (GDP) estimates to 6.5% for the 2025-2026 (April-Março) fiscal year of 6.7% previously projected.
This is the second consecutive occasion in less than three months that RIB decides to lower interest rates -in February it also cut 25 base points -after keeping them unchanged for five years.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:09:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Humid weather forecast, with fog, rain and thunderstorm</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/previsao-de-tempo-humido-com-nevoeiro-chuva-e-trovoada/</link><description>A moist maritime air stream will cause time in the coming days to be humid, with fog or fog, rain and thunderstorm, predict meteorological and geophysical services (SMG).
Authorities explain that with the removal of high atmospheric pressure, a sea air stream will bring humid and fog time to the Guangdong coast later this week. During this period, waterproofers are foreseen. At the same time, the temperature will gradually rise and the maximum can reach 27 degrees Celsius. This may cause poor visibility conditions due to fog and loss of grip due to wet or slippery floor. Therefore, SMG appeal to drivers who pay attention to the road situation and adopt preventive safety behaviors.
In addition to Macao, most of the Guangdong province regions will be affected by adverse atmospheric conditions. Based on the current forecasts, the front will reach the area of ​​the Pérola river estuary on the weekend, bringing strong winds, water and thunderstorms, reiterate the SMG.
After the departure from this front, the time in Macao will become very dry and the temperature will go down slightly. The situation is expected to improve early next week, with fresh time in the morning and evening.
Given the large atmospheric changes of the spring station, SMG guarantee that they will follow the weather situation, in permanently disclosing updated meteorological information, as well as necessary alerts or warnings. Authorities appeal to the population to pay attention to weather information and take response measures in due time.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:06:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Tui confirms a sentence of three years and three months in prison to a man who beat ex-girlfriend</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/tui-confirma-pena-de-tres-anos-e-tres-meses-de-prisao-a-homem-que-espancou-ex-namorada/</link><description>The last court (TUI) has decided to maintain the penalty of three years and three months in prison and compensation of 1.8 million patacas to a man who, in September 2020, violently assaulted his ex-girlfriend. The woman got several physical and psychological sequelae.
 
The last court (TUI) dismissed the appeal presented by a man sentenced to three years and three months in prison and the payment of more than 1.8 million compensation patacas for assaulting his ex-girlfriend, causing several physical and psychological damage.
The case dates back to the night of September 13, 2020. The individual led to the area where his ex-girlfriend lived to wait for her. According to the court, when the victim arrived at his car, he saw his ex-boyfriend, stopped the vehicle in the opposite track and, since he had already been the victim of aggression from his part, called a friend to ask for help.
At this point, the defendant made a marching and collided with the victim's vehicle, causing him to block the right front door, which could not be opened. Then he left his vehicle and, with the key in his hand, crashed violently into the glass window next to the woman's vehicle driver. As he could not break the glass, he retreated his vehicle and collided again against the ex-girlfriend's vehicle.
He then managed to enter the vehicle through the already departed window, pressed the victim with his body, attacked the victim's eyes and face with the key, and punched it on his head and body. During the attack, he suddenly bit the left forearm and fingers of the victim's left hand. Then he went to the rear seat, where he pulled his hair to prevent his escape, causing his hair loss. Finally, with the help of passersby, the woman managed to get out of the vehicle, and the man was dominated.
The victim was immediately transported to the hospital, where she underwent examinations and treatment. After the expert examination, it was found that the woman had suffered bruises and abrasions on the scalp, various bruises and abrasions on the face, brain concussion, right eye bruise, traumatic cataracts in the right eye, hemorrhage in the lower right eyelid, right eye retinal concussion, severe hearing impairment in the right ear. According to the outcome of the expertise, the incident caused a reduction in vision, asymmetry between the right and the left eye, which affected its appearance and, at the same time, caused it to suffer from posttraumatic stress syndrome, requiring long-term treatment.
The alcohol test made to the perpetrator revealed a blood alcohol rate of 1.33 grams per liter, which exceeded the legal limit. The court also points out that the conduct of the man caused serious damage to the woman's vehicle and damaged the Road Stone Floor.
The Base Judicial Court (TJB) condemned the man for a crime of simple offense to physical integrity, qualified damage and driving in a state of drunkenness to a single penalty of three years and three months in actual arrest, driving inhibition for a period of one year and six months and the payment of civil compensation to ex-girlfriend of more than 1.8 million Patacas.
The defendant appealed the decision to the second instance court, which dismissed the appeal, and later appealed to Tui. The TUI collective proved that the woman suffered a loss of vision of 7%to 10%, as well as post-convulsive syndrome because of the attack, with a degree of disability of 10%. Thus, Tui decided to maintain the effective imprisonment of three years and three months, as well as compensation of 1.8 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:06:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Open competition for the operation of 20 newsstands in the mud market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/aberto-concurso-para-a-operacao-de-20-bancas-no-mercado-da-taipa/</link><description>The announcement regarding the opening of the public tender was published yesterday for the operation of the vacant stalls of the mud market. The contest, which ends on May 23, is related to 20 light food stalls or cultural articles and a cafeteria.
 
The public tender is open for the operation of the unoccupied stalls of the Taipa market. The information contains an announcement published yesterday by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) in an official bulletin. There are, in total, 20 newsstands in the contest, which ends the 45th day from the publication of the announcement, ie May 23. The term of the contract is three years.
In mid -March, when the market revitalization plan was presented, AMI said I hope to take advantage of that space to “properly combine it with the Taipa Village trade, regarding the life of the population, community functions and cultural and tourist elements, taking advantage of public spaces and community resources for complementary development”.
This Taipa market revitalization plan proposes that elements of 'gastronomy + cultural creativity' are added, 'providing an exploration platform for citizens interested in dedicating themselves to cultural and creative industries or gastronomy with their own characteristics, jointly promoting the transformation of traditional markets. ” The newsstands in question are light food or cultural articles and there is also a cafes to contest.
Those interested in the exploration of the newsstands should unload the necessary documents on the IAM portal, fill them and deliver them to the various AMI service centers.
The provisional security to pay for the candidacy for light food stalls or cultural and creative articles goes from the 3,000 patacas to 5,000 patacas. For the candidacy for cafeteria, the value of the provisional security is 8,000 patacas. Income to pay for each lightweight food board or cultural and creative articles range from 486 to 1,854 patacas, depending on their area. These stalls have a minimum area of ​​8.1 square meters and a maximum area of ​​30.9 square meters. The cafeteria will pay an income of 2,040 monthly patacas.
In the evaluation of the competition, the criterion to which AMI attributes the most weight is that of the competitor's operation strategies, with 60%. Then comes the diversity of the typology of goods (20%), the time of bank exploration (10%), the experience and qualifications of the competitor (5%) and the convenience of payment instruments (5%).
AMI is currently doing optimization works in the mud market, which should be completed on the 4th quarter of this year, when the newsstands in question will begin to be explored.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:07:57</pubDate></item><item><title>China retalia with another 50% in US import rates</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/china-retalia-com-mais-50-em-taxas-sobre-importacoes-dos-eua/</link><description>China has announced an additional 50% retaliation rate on US imports to 84%. The rates come in today.
 
Beijing announced yesterday an additional 50% retaliation rate on imports from the United States to 84%, intensifying the trade war between the two largest economies in the world. The Chinese Ministry of Finance has stated that the new rates apply beyond the 34% previously announced on imports from the United States. The rates come into force this Thursday.
Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday appealed to the “reinforcement of strategic ties with neighboring countries” in his first public appearance since Donald Trump increased to 104% customs about China.
XI, who did not mention the US President, urged his employees during a working meeting to improve relationships with neighboring countries “through proper management of differences”, with a view to “reinforcing ties in supply chains,” said the official news agency Xinhua.
China's relationships with neighboring countries are “at their best level in modern history” and at the same time Beijing is “in a crucial phase deeply interconnected with changes in regional dynamics and global developments,” he noted.
The Chinese leader argued that China's diplomacy with his neighbors will be based on the construction of a "shared community", one of the most repeated buzzwords by the Chinese Communist Party leaders (CCP) in which it is argued that prosperity is only sustainable if nations work together.
At the meeting it was also stressed that China should reinforce its sense of responsibility and maintain a “diplomacy of a neighborhood, sincerity, mutual benefit and inclusiveness”.
It has also been underlined that China should "support countries in the region to maintain their own developmental pathways and correctly manage conflicts and differences." "We must build a high -level interconnection network and reinforce cooperation in industrial and supply chains," added the Chinese leader, stressing the importance of "maintaining regional stability and cooperating in matters and law enforcement." The Chinese leader has not made any reference to the United States and Beijing has been underlining so far that he will not give in to Trump's rates.
Trump ordered on Tuesday the application of an additional 50% rate on Chinese products, raising total customs rates to 104%. Trump said Beijing wants a deal "desperately" but said China doesn't know how to "start" negotiating and stressed that the White House is waiting for a Xi Jinping call.
In the possible future negotiations between Beijing and Washington is also the future of Tiktok's application operations in the US, which Trump's government has demanded that it disconnect from its mother company, Chinese Bytedance, to be able to operate in US territory.
 
Answer to Trump
 
The Chinese government has assured yesterday that it has "firm will" and "abundant resources" to respond with determination if the United States insists on "further intensifying its restrictive economic and commercial measures." "With firm will and abundant resources, China will resolutely take contracted and fight until the end," said the Chinese Ministry of Commerce, in a widespread statement yesterday. The ministry reiterated that "there are no winners in a trade war" and that "China does not want one," but "will not be crossed if the legitimate rights of its people are violated."
The Chinese government published a white book on Tuesday defending China's position in its economic and commercial relations with the United States. In the document, China states that "both countries are an opportunity and not a threat to each other" and appeals to Washington to "immediately" the "unilateral imposition of tariffs."
The document also urges the US to “reinforce dialogue, manage differences and promote cooperation” and stresses that Beijing is “willing to communicate” with the US “on major bilateral economic and commercial issues and addressing their concerns through dialogue and on an equal footing”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:07:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Meteorological services perform emergency electricity simulacrum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/servicos-meteorologicos-realizam-simulacro-de-electricidade-de-emergencia/</link><description>The Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (DSMG) and the Macao Electricity Company (CEM) held, last Tuesday, a simulacrum of electricity supply for emergency situations, regarding the approach of the typhoons.
According to a statement issued by DSMG, both parties simulated damage to electricity operating facilities and then activated the emergency electricity supply mechanism or reserve generator, according to the malfunction level.
Once the exercise has been completed, the two organisms listened to workers' opinions and took stock of the experience, so as to optimize the collaboration capacity between the parties involved.
In a statement, DSMG adds that the simulacrum aimed to raise “ability to respond unforeseen incidents” and the improvement of the “emergency mechanism” in order to ensure that the territory is prepared to deal with extreme weather and geophysical situations.
According to information advanced by the weather services in late March, Macau could be affected by about five to eight tropical storms throughout this year, especially during the typhoons that will begin around June and end in October.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:06:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing praises Spain's role in the approach of China to the European Union</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/pequim-elogia-papel-de-espanha-na-aproximacao-da-china-a-uniao-europeia/</link><description>China yesterday highlighted the positive role Spain is playing in improving Beijing and the European Union, in a context of growing commercial tensions between China and the United States. "The ties between China and Spain maintain strategic stability and are based on opening, cooperation and mutual benefit," said Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian yesterday at a press conference in Beijing, where Spanish government, Pedro Sánchez, has been expected to start an official visit on Friday.
The spokesman for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs has described Spain as "an important European economy and a fundamental cooperation partner within the European Union."
Sánchez's visit, the third in three years, will coincide with the 20th anniversary of the China-Spain Global Strategic Partnership, which both countries consider a priority framework for their bilateral relations.
The trip takes place in a period of climbing the trade war between China and the United States and after the Chinese Prime Minister, Li Qiang, spoke to the president of the European Commission, Ursula von der Leyen.
The two leaders committed to defending free trade and reinforcing the role of the World Trade Organization (WTO).
Beijing thus expects European partners, such as Spain, can help cushion international uncertainty, keep worldwide supply chains and reinforce economic and commercial cooperation with Asia.
Sánchez will be received in Beijing by Chinese President Xi Jinping and will have meetings with the Prime Minister, Li Qiang, to diversify export markets, reinforce economic ties with Asia and face global challenges such as climate change and war in Ukraine.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:07:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Central Bank Secure Yuan after strong offshore devaluation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/banco-central-chines-segura-yuan-apos-forte-desvalorizacao-offshore/</link><description>Beijing lowered yesterday only Yuan's daily reference rate, although the Chinese currency 'offshore' has recorded a strong devaluation in recent hours, marking China's determination to stabilize the currency.
 
A few hours before US President Donald Trump, increasing customs rates at all products from China to 104%, the Popular Bank of China (Central Bank) allowed Yuan to weaken over the US dollar, setting its average point at 7.2066 Yuan for every US dollar.
On Tuesday, the Central Bank set the rate at 7,2038, marking the first time that Yuan has fallen below the psychologically significant threshold of 7.2 since September 2023. "The Central Bank has allowed Yuan to weaken as expected, but this is no evidence of structural change in currency management," Dan Wang, director for China (‘Think Tank’), argued. Group, quoted by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post. "Given the current tariff pressures, the Central Bank has extended the Yuan negotiating band to fully recognize the voltage in the currency market, simultaneously sending a clear sign of its determination to defend the stability of the currency - this political orientation leaves no room for speculation against Yuan," he said.
The intention of the Central Bank was to reassure markets and maintain control, rather than helping exporters to continue selling their products to the US, he added. "The Central Bank will seek to stabilize, not devalue, the currency during the trade war," said Wang.
Yuan 'offshore' fell 1.1% to 7,4290 for every dollar in New York negotiations at the end of Tuesday-the weaker level since 2010. Compared to Yuan 'Onshore', which is strongly regulated by the Central Bank and can only oscillate at a maximum of 2%, the Yuan 'offshore' is free of capital controls and is more sensitive to the feeling of global risk.
An investment bank report Goldman Sachs said on Tuesday that China's Popular Bank could tolerate a smooth, ordered depreciation from Yuan.
Although the flexibility of fiscal policy remains the main tool for dealing with the impact of US tariffs, and exchange rate depreciation will be a less effective and less effective stimulus tool, the Central Bank is expected to allow for greater bidirectional flexibility in yuan fixing, according to the report. “Exchange stability remains a priority for Chinese policies formulators, with the focus more on the management of the depreciation rhythm than in the target of a specific USD / CNY level,” reads the same note.
 
Shanghai and Shenzhen bags
 
The reference rates of Shanghai and Shenzhen bags advanced yesterday 1.31% and 1.22%, respectively, despite the entry into force in the United States of additional 50% rates on Chinese products.
The Shanghai Stock Exchange Reference Index rose 41.26 points to 3,186.81, while Shenzhen registered a rise of 115.21 points to 9,539.89. These markets thus reversed the losses with which they opened the session of 1.13% and 1.63%, respectively.
Shanghai and Shenzhen scholarships fell 7.34 and 9.66%, respectively, on Monday, following the contracted package announced last Friday by Chinese authorities, which included additional 34% rates on US products.
On Tuesday, these scholarships were able to recover 1.58% and 0.64%, thanks to support to the market announced by state-owned Chinese investment institutions and stock repurchase plans by large Chinese companies.
The Central Chinese state fund Huijin Investment said on Tuesday that it has sufficient capacity to ensure the stability of the scholarship market and stressed the "strength" of its assets and its "abundant liquidity" to "assume a strategic role in ensuring the stability of Chinese markets", while the Popular Bank of China (Central Bank) promised "liquidity support" to the background, if necessary.
Asset state operator China Chengtong has announced that it will mobilize 100 billion yuan (12.325 billion euros) to support action repurchase plans.
More than 175 Chinese companies quoted in the stock market, such as Sinopec, Haier and CATL, announced in the last 24 hours of action repurchase as a stabilization measure, said the Chinese newspaper Caixin.
The Shanghai Stock Exchange met on Tuesday with representatives of 10 scholarship market institutions, such as Changjiang Securities, Eastern Securities and Dongwu Securities, which underlined the importance of “maintaining market stability” and “preventing risks”.
The White House confirmed on Tuesday the imposition of additional 50% rates on goods from China. Under the whole, customs rates on imports from the Asian country are from yesterday 104%. The China Ministry of Commerce warned the day before the Asian country "will fight until the end."
Last Friday, China launched a battery of counterfeit to the rates announced last week by Trump. These include 34% rates on imports from the United States, sanctions against some of their companies, restrictions on the export of certain rare lands, the suspension of chicken and sorghum imports from certain US companies, as well as the opening of anti-monopoly and anti-dumping investigations against US companies and products. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:07:04</pubDate></item><item><title>AI processed 300 cases of illegal deposit of restoration sector waste</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/iam-processou-300-casos-de-deposito-ilegal-de-residuos-do-sector-da-restauracao/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) made, by March, sanitary inspections to more than 2,500 food sector establishments, in order to reinforce the control of pests and rodents. The body caught the public's attention on environmental hygiene, advancing that more than 300 cases of illegal deposit of waste committed by restaurants were fined.
 
Local authorities reiterated their commitment to work on the city's environmental hygiene and public health. The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) revealed that it has fined more than 300 cases of illegal waste deposit by restaurants over the past year, stating that the night shift investigation team particularly oversees the removal of waste in restaurants to avoid waste spread on the public road and attract rodents.
The AMI added that it intensified the health inspection to food sector establishments, having inspected more than 2,500 restaurants and Take-Away stores in the first three months of this year.
At the Macau Forum, the morning program of the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, it was revealed that the number of inspections has increased from year to year and intensified the control of pests and rodents. Once any irregular situation is found, the establishment will be required to adopt cleaning and disinfection measures and, according to the body, will be submitted to reinspects.
"With the efforts of AMI and industry, the number of rats complaints has a decrease in the last two or three weeks," said Cheong Kuai Tat, head of the AMI Food Security Department.
Cheong Kuai Tat also pointed out that rodent prevention and control is a “long -term task” and that industry has the responsibility of formulating effective plans for matter and creating a “rodent free environment” to “protect the golden card from Macau as a city of gastronomy”.
It is recalled that the government last week launched the “city cleaning campaign” that foresees interdepartmental work to perform cleaning and dissemination activities, “in order to reinforce the awareness of residents and various sectors about rodent prevention and mosquito extermination”.
The campaign runs between April and May, and during this period several services will reinforce inspections to food establishments, food transformation establishments and construction workers shipyards, to encourage establishments responsible for implementing effective food and solid waste treatment measures.
In turn, in the radio program, Ieong Chon Kit, a doctor at the Health Service Disease Prevention and Control Center, said the body proceeds to notice notice in private establishments that would not eliminate garbage and other various objects, informing the competent departments to meet health risks.
He stated that health services have been monitoring the situation of mosquitoes in various zones through ovitrap rates and to take action to combat these insects. According to Ieong Chon Kit, in the first quarter of this year, about 4,000 sources of mosquito proliferation were performed. The frequency of chemical elimination of mosquitoes has been adjusted twice a month since March, and 400 mosquito elimination works were performed from January to March.
"At the time when mosquitoes are more active, we will increase the frequency of chemical control against mosquitoes. Today, the frequency of chemical control has been duplicated where we consider sanitary black points, ie sources of proliferation that we cannot eliminate and where mosquitoes are most likely to reproduce," he explained.
Ieong Chon Kit also stressed that April will be the most active reproduction time of Aedes albopictus mosquitoes, so the public eliminates mosquito proliferation sources in their homes and workplaces and take adequate anti-fulfillment measures.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:09:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Pairing sessions will offer 79 job vacancies on the 16th and 17th</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/sessoes-de-emparelhamento-vao-oferecer-79-vagas-de-emprego-nos-dias-16-e-17/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs (DSAT) and the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) will collaborate in the organization of three employment pairing sessions for sectors of hotel, transportation and retail. Registration for the events, scheduled for the third week of April, are already open from 9:00 am today and until 12:00 pm on April 15th.
The first session will take place on April 16, in the morning and afternoon, in collaboration with SJM Resorts. On this day, 21 job openings will be available for restoration supervisor, sales manager at conventions and exhibitions or leisure tourism, VIP service supervisor, counter and restoration employees, among other functions.
The second session, to be held on the morning of April 17, focuses on the Tourism and Public Bus Transportation sector, having as participating companies Limited Tourism, Transmac (Macao Urban Transportation) and TCM (Macao Collective Transport Society). In this session, 28 job offers are included for driver and station heads.
The third and last pairing session will take place on the afternoon of the same day, Thursday, with 30 job offers for the position of seller at CDFG Macau, a limited unipessoal society.
In total, the three pairing sessions will provide 79 job offers. The first session will take place in the Shang Zhou meeting room, on the second floor of Grand Lisbon Palace Macau, while the rest will be held on the 2nd floor of the Faom Building, located at Ribeira do Patane Street, 2-6.
Registered candidates who have signaled interest in these sectors will be contacted by SMS to register, which is also open to any Macao resident through the Macao Single Account. The number of vacancies is limited, so interested parties are advised to mark as soon as possible.
DSAL often organizes pairing sessions in conjunction with other institutions, with the aim of helping Macao residents who are looking for employment to integrate into the job market.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:07:08</pubDate></item><item><title>BNU organizes seminar on the spirit of the “two sessions”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/10/bnu-organiza-seminario-sobre-o-espirito-das-duas-sessoes/</link><description>The National Bank Overseas (BNU) organized, on Tuesday, a seminar on the guidelines set forth in the “two sessions”, that is, the meetings of the National Popular Assembly (APN) and the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), which took place in Beijing last March. The meeting, conducted in English, intended to provide employees-especially foreigners-a deeper understanding of national policies.
The seminar promoted by the Portuguese Bank had as its main speaker Choy Ming Wai, Macao member of the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference. In a statement released yesterday by BNU, it is read that the hearing-which included executive directors, department directors and staff-obtained “perspectives on the latest regional development trends, with the aim of taking advantage of development opportunities such as the Great Bay area”.
BNU explains that initiatives such as this fall into the “continuous mission” of encouraging “effective learning” and “professional development” of its employees. "Through this initiative, the seminar aims to deepen the understanding of BNU employees about the priorities of national and business development, in constant evolution, and emphasize the dedication to empower their employees with knowledge, skills and essential prospects to navigate in a dynamic environment, boosting the bank's sustained growth and sustainable success," concludes the entity.
The "two sessions" usually occur in parallel in early March, every year, and have as their main objectives the definition of goals and priorities for China's economic and social developments. Regarding this year's sessions, the Government of MSar people has already assured that it will comply with the central authorities' guidelines, with all the secretaries of the local executive to manifest, through official communications, agreement with regard to these meetings.</description><pubDate>2025-04-10 05:07:09</pubDate></item></channel></rss>