<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/internautas-revelam-pouco-auto-controlo-no-uso-da-internet/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Turbulence in a multipolar world: ultra-nationalism, the perception of the “Chinese threat”, the ideal of great Russia and the Trump doctrine</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/turbulencia-num-mundo-multipolar-ultra-nacionalismo-a-percepcao-da-ameaca-chinesa-o-ideal-da-grande-russia-e-a-doutrina-trump/</link><description>Since Donald Trump's victory as a new US president in January 2025, the turbulence in world politics has become much more prominent than before. In fact, even before Trump's electoral victory, the turbulence in world politics could be seen in the emergence of ultranationalism in many countries and the perception of the so -called "threat of China." Underlying these nationalist and anti-china currents was the transformation of a Unipolar world led by the US into a multipolar world where more countries have nuclear weapons and challenge American military hegemony.
At the end of World War II, he was attended by a bipolar world in which the former Soviet Union struggled with the US for the world's political and economic rule. However, the former Soviet Union collapsed under the combined influence of the US containment policy and Glasnost policy and Mikhail Gorbachev's political reforms. The collapse of the former Soviet Union in late 1991 led to the emergence of a unipolar world in which the US became the only most powerful, economic and militarily superpower.
However, China's rapid rise since the early 2000s has undergone US supremacy in the world. Many US allies gradually developed a feeling of the so -called “threat of China”, seeing the Chinese regime not only as an economic threat but also as a military threat. Chinese military actions were seen as “ambitious” and territorially assertive in the Southern Sea of ​​China. China was also seen as a “threat to national security” by countries that did not get used to seeing a rapidly developing Chinese nation state. Confucius institutes were seen by hostile countries to China as a “negative” cultural arm that carried out “united” work rather than purely educational organizations that could and can improve the deeper understanding of Chinese language and culture.
The perception of the "Chinese threat" has never been seriously postponed, partly due to a prejudice perhaps deeply rooted against so -called yellow danger and, in part, because China has changed, since late 2012, its foreign policy, no longer adopting a discreet approach during the era of deng -pill to adopt a more assertive and great visibility foreign policy.
When Donald Trump was first elected US president in 2016, US foreign policy showed signs of self-protection at the expense of his soft power, where democracy and human rights were traditionally the Universally exported US values. The US withdrawal from the transpacific partnership in 2017 represented a warning signal to the world that American leadership has become much more self-protective and less international than ever.
The Russian invasion of Ukraine in early 2022 raised serious questions about geopolitical development and peace in Europe. If Russian President Vladimir Putin was committed to restoring the territorial borders of the former Soviet Union, then the intention of Ukraine, under the command of President Zelensky, to adhere to the NATO, in fact, a threat to Russia's national security. However, the military support of the EU and the NATO, as well as the US, Ukraine has become a dangerous spark that could trigger a larger regional war and, with the subsequent participation of North Korean military from the Russian side, perhaps a global war.
The sudden attack of Hamas to Israel in 2023 and the consequent Israeli retaliation against Hamas in the Gaza Strip illustrated the dangers of ultranationalism, which could not only put ethnic groups against each other, but also dip the Middle East in a new political-military turbulence crisis.
Donald Trump's second presidential presidential victory since early 2025 has plunged world politics into a new era of persistent turbulence and political-military uncertainties. The Trump doctrine of raising the US national interest to an unprecedented level of primordial importance has made many countries uncomfortable, from Denmark, whose Granelândia is now under the coveting look of the US, Canada, whose government will retaliate against the Trump administration's reciprocal tariff policy. Trump has also welcomed his Russian homologist Putin, trying to change the traditional US containment policy regarding the Russians to a more friendly policy if not necessarily appeasing to Russia. To prevent the US from being dragged to a power war with Russia, Trump and its national security team are interested in negotiating directly with the Putin government, but the challenges are knowing if Putin and its strategies are adopting a postponement tactic and even if there is a ceasefire agreement, will Russia cease to constitute a military threat to Poland, the Bal and other states. EU?
Trump's second administration is undoubtedly creating more turbulence and uncertainties than ever in world politics. Seeing China as a military, economic and technological threat, Trump administration continues its trade war, tariff and technological with China. The current controversy about how the Chinese state apparatus has seen C. K. Hutchison about Blackrock commercial transactions on ports along the Panama channel, which was considered by Trump as the American political influence, demonstrates that China expects Hutchison, based on Hong Kong, to place the company's national interest in the company's economic interest. It remains to be seen how the port saga will unfold on the Panama Canal, but one thing is certain: Hong Kong -based Chinese companies will have to consider the evaluation of political risks, especially when dealing with US transactions in the context of economic and technological struggles between the US and China.
The turbulence in world politics is now revealing several potential points of inflammation that could cause larger regional wars, if not even a global war. The first point of inflammation remains the Middle East, where any israelite and Palestinian ultranationalism will continue to have branches. The latest US military attack against Houstis in Yemen illustrated the danger of widening Israelo-Palestinian conflicts to other places in the Middle East. Of course, the attacks of the homestei rebels to Israeli ships were equally problematic and highly dangerous.
Another point of inflammation is Eastern Asia, where the increasingly anti-continental, anti-opposition, and pro-EU regime has caused strong verbal warnings by the mainland China authorities. Aggravating the tensions between the two sides of the Strait are North Korea's warnings of Japanese missiles installed in Hokkaido, Japanese perception of North Korea's threat to national security, and South Korean instability. The dispute between China and the Philippines over the southern China sea reefs is also another potentially conflicting area that deserves our attention.
Even more important, while war in Ukraine is not resolved, the potential for expansion for a larger European war persists. The United Kingdom, France and Germany considered the change in US foreign policy uncomfortable in relation to Russia and Ukraine. However, when they set up Ukraine against the Russian invasion, these Central EU states are antagonizing the ideal of establishing a great Russia. It remains to be seen how the Russian-Ucranian war will unfold in the coming months.
Ultimately, from a macro perspective of world politics, the transformation of world politics of a US military, economic and technologically dominated unipolarity to a multipolar world characterized by new emerging powers has made Trump administration debate with the decline of US hegemony and the weakening of its soft power. It remains to be seen whether the struggle for the dominance of world politics will be more tolerant from the national point of view, more peaceful from the regional point of view, less violent from the military and more harmonious point of view from an ethical point of view than current evolution.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:11:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorenses deputies devalue impact of non -extradition of Philippine in adherence to Asean</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/deputados-timorenses-desvalorizam-impacto-de-nao-extradicao-de-filipino-na-adesao-a-asean/</link><description>Several Timorenses deputies yesterday defended the decision of the Court of Appeal not to extradite Arnolf Teves, at the request of the Philippines, and devalued any impacts on the process of adhesion to the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean).
The Timor-Leste Appeal Court has ruled last week not to extradition of Deputy Filipino Arnolf Tevees JR for the Philippines, an Asean member state, which applies to life imprisonment and has a bill to reintroduce the death penalty.
In Article 35 of the Constitution of Timor-Leste refers to its point 3 that "extradition is not permitted for crimes to which the law of the state requesting death or life imprisonment is not allowed, or whenever the extradite is admitted to being subject to inhuman, degrading or cruel torture or treatment."
Filipino Arnolfo Teves was arrested in March 2024 in Dili, following an Interpol capture warrant, issued at the request of the Philippines, who accuse the deputy of being responsible for the death of 10 people.
The Philippine Authorities claimed to be “disillusioned” by Timor-Leste “not showing confidence in the administration of justice in the Philippines” and recalled that they were one of the first Member States to express support for the country's adhesion to ASEAN.
For the deputy of the Bench of the National Congress of Timorese Reconstruction (CNRT), Patrocínio Fernandes, the impact of this case is minimal, because, he considered, the Philippines cannot make decisions based on a single person.
Lídia Norberta, deputy of the Fretilin bench, explained that Timor-Leste, as a country that committed to the international community, should collaborate with democratic principles and respect human rights. "The case of Arnolf Teves is an internal issue of one country. In the context of Asean, one country cannot interfere with the internal problems of another. This is one of the principles of Asean," explained Fetilin deputy.
For the deputy Verdial de Sousa, from the Khunto bench, the process was conducted based on the Timorese legislation and the defense of human rights. "Regarding the adhesion of Timor-Leste to Asean, I note that this situation will not affect our adhesion process. Therefore, I believe that the decision of the Timorese Court will have no impact on this direction," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:19:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal warns that game dealers have to maintain impartiality in the elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/caeal-avisa-que-concessionarias-de-jogo-tem-de-manter-imparcialidade-nas-eleicoes/</link><description>At a meeting with representatives of the six Macao game concessionaires, the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Committee (Caeal) warned that companies have to fulfill the duty of neutrality and impartiality in the elections in September.
At the meeting, which also had elements of the Games Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) and the Macao Games and Entertainment Association, Caeal stressed that dealers “cannot do acts that somehow favor or harm an application at the detriment or advantage of others”.
On the other hand, workers in these companies, in the exercise of their duties, “have to observe rigorous neutrality, being prohibited the display of symbols, stickers or other elements of electoral propaganda at the workplace”. In addition, "they cannot take advantage of the time and space of work for advertising acts or vote appeal." "It is important to be aware that the workplace includes the canteens and rest rooms, and is also considered to exercise workers during rest time and meals within working hours," said Caeal.
The body led by Seng Ioi Man stressed that operators should “do work well in this level of management, clearly transmitting to all staff the explicit message to rigorously maintain neutrality and impartiality, as well as continuously warn the workers to perform their duty to avoid violation of the law”.
If an offense occurs from a worker, it will be considered an act of its own and its responsibility. Thus, if the entity verifies an infringement situation, it should communicate as soon as possible, to Caeal or DICJ, so that they can follow and immediately deal with the case.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:11:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Association calls for more support for autistic children</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/associacao-pede-mais-apoio-para-criancas-autistas/</link><description>Yesterday the day of World Consciousness on Autism was signaled. The date has served for the General Association of Macao Women of Macau to warn of the challenges that autistic children still have to face. Jennifer Chau, leader of the association and also Fuhong's director, has called for more support from the government and the community so that the suffering of the disease can be better integrated in society.
 
Yesterday was signal to the World Day of Conscientization of Autism. At the time, Jennifer Chau, vice president of the General Association of Macao Women and Director of the Fuhong Rehabilitation Association, warned of the difficulties that children with autism have to overcome.
The official stated that children with special needs, namely those who suffer from autism, "continue to face different challenges after receiving treatment," such as community integration when they become adults. Jennifer Chau said he hoped the community to support these groups and their caregivers, also suggesting that the government reinforces cooperation with social companies to improve the support and vocational training system, "in order to facilitate the integration of these groups into the community and to increase their self -esteem."
Quoted by the newspaper or Mun, Jennifer Chau noticed an "active investment" by the government in relevant services and obtained "some results in reducing waiting time for initial diagnosis and treatment."  However, he said that most parents want the frequency of treatment to increase, "in order to better take advantage of the gold period of treatment."
The official also suggested that, in addition to continually increasing the provision of services to shorten the waiting time for treatment, the government also exploits the possibility of supporting parents to choose more treatment services through subsidies or extending the goal and amount of subsidies for existing care providers, "in order to relieve the financial charges of families in question."
Jennifer Chau stressed that "support for the integration of people with disabilities in the community can help reduce pressure on care family members and create an inclusive social environment, which is of great importance for the sustainable development of society." The leader of the Women's Association pointed out that "many people of the high functionality autism have demonstrated extraordinary potential in specific areas and, through continuous formation and support, can make full use of their strengths in their professional domains." However, after completing their studies, "they continue to need more comprehensive pre-professional training and a longer period of adaptation and psychological counseling."
Finally, the official suggested that the government “reinforces collaboration with social companies to expand diversified vocational training programs and support the operation of these companies by reinforcing the existing financing mechanism, the reserve of stores in public housing neighborhoods and the concession of affordable incomes, and the increase of public contracts”, for example. This would allow better integration of people with disabilities in the community, he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:17:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho says that masters and doctorates from Macau “have no relevance” in the job market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/coutinho-diz-que-mestrados-e-doutoramentos-de-macau-nao-tem-relevancia-no-mercado-de-trabalho/</link><description>José Pereira Coutinho addressed yesterday a written interpellation to the government in which most young people in Macao do not proceed with higher studies, such as masters or doctorates, because they consider that “such qualifications have no relevance in the local [work] market”. In fact, “these high qualifications eventually become a barrier in search of their first job,” says the deputy.
Coutinho says that "most employers privilege candidates with prior experience in specific areas, which are often incompatible with the degrees obtained, such as Public Administration courses or Portuguese Language Degrees." In addition, "young people licensed at foreign universities also face great difficulties in part of the local market, due to the incompatibility with low added jobs." The deputy says this situation "is particularly evident in the scarcity of jobs related to digital technology, automation and the use of artificial intelligence."
The leader of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) says that "it is fundamental" that the government understands the trends of the labor market, suggesting the creation of jobs in areas such as scientific data analysis and interpretation, cybersecurity specialists, biomedical engineering, robotic medical care, nanotechnology and industrial automation and system analysts, among others.
"These professions require a combination of technical training, such as programming and statistics, combined with interpersonal skills, such as communication and critical thinking," says Coutinho, adding that "as AI continues to evolve, new opportunities and specializations will certainly emerge" and, therefore, "the quality of education must also evolve, creating jobs that match the needs of the economic development of the field."
Pereira Coutinho considers that it is “imperative” that the government “implements, urgently, proactive policies in the educational scope”. “The adoption of concrete quality teaching and learning strategies is essential to achieving a standard of 'excellence' that allows not only creation, but also the attraction of world leadership technological companies,” he says, adding that the executive should adopt “urgent” concrete strategies for “teaching and quality learning”. These policies should focus on the formation of highly qualified young people and the collaboration between higher education institutions and technology companies.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:10:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal accident raises doubts about Xiaomi autonomous driving technology</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/acidente-fatal-suscita-duvidas-sobre-tecnologia-de-conducao-autonoma-da-xiaomi/</link><description>Chinese car manufacturer Xiaomi said yesterday that he will cooperate with police in investigating a fatal car accident that involved one of his models equipped with autonomous driving technology.
Three female students died on Saturday night after the Xiaomi Su7 electric vehicle in which they were following a concrete barrier in a section of the highway tenhou-shangrao in Anhui province in east China.
The vehicle was in the navigation mode of autopilot (no) immediately before the accident, traveling at a speed of 116 kilometers per hour, according to a company report. But the car detected an obstacle in a select section and issued a warning before returning direction to the driver, Xiaomi told. A few seconds later, the vehicle clashed at a barrier at a speed of 97 kilometers per hour.
Videos published on social networks show the car burning on the motorway, followed by a charred carcass. Law Jun, the founder of Xiaomi, said in a "online" message that has a "heavy heart", adding that your company will continue to cooperate with police investigation.
The accident aroused doubts among netizens about the reliability of Xiaomi's autonomous driving system. Others were asked why the car burned down or if the doors would open in an emergency.
On the Weibo social network, a woman who identified herself as the mother of the driver of the vehicle stated that Xiaomi had not contacted her, accusing the company of "not taking the lives of these three children seriously." "As family members of the victims, we have a lot of questions. Why did the vehicle fire after hitting the barrier? We just want an explanation," wrote the woman.
The Chinese Giant of the consumer electronics, from mobile phones to vacuum cleaners, entered the electric automobile market in March 2024 with the launch of its Su7 model.
One year 200,000 units were sold at a price of about 210,000 yuan to the standard model. Xiaomi's stock price fell 5% following the accident.
Battery manufacturer Catl said yesterday that the model was not equipped with his batteries. Chinese manufacturers dominate the world market of autonomous vehicles.
Xiaomi stated that its model is able to overcome and change track on the highway, but stresses that the system is not intended to replace the driver. The company said it had created an internal team to investigate the accident and has already contacted the victims' families through local authorities.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:18:59</pubDate></item><item><title>China urges companies to respect local laws after falling tower in bangedoque</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/china-insta-empresas-a-respeitarem-leis-locais-apos-queda-de-torre-em-banguecoque/</link><description>The China Embassy in Thailand has called for Chinese companies in the country to “respect local laws”, after a investigation into the collapse of a Bang of Bang of Bang of Apartments, which killed about 10 people.
Beijing “constantly urges Chinese companies abroad to respect local laws and contribute positively to society,” said the chancel yesterday on his Facebook page.
The construction of the tower, located near the popular Chatuchak market in northern Bangcoque, involved a branch of Chinese state company Railway Group (CREC) and its local partner Italian-Thai Development (ITD).
The tremors reduced the structure to a pile of rubble in a matter of seconds, causing the death of about ten people, with ever smaller hopes for more than 70 people who are still cornered in the rubble. Most victims were workers of Burmese, Laoconiana, Cambodian and Thai nationality. The 30 -story building aimed to host government offices. "We have to determine where the error occurred," said Thai Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra, who on Monday ordered an investigation into the materials and safety standards on site by a group of experts that should present a report this week.
Beijing sent a team to Bangkok, including rescue teams, and promised to "continue supporting Thailand if necessary."
China is the largest source of direct foreign investment in Thailand, with $ 2 billion (1.8 billion euros) injected into the kingdom by 2024, according to the Open Development Thailand data supplier.
Paetongtarn Shinawatra announced on Tuesday that the investigation will not be "specific to a country." "We don't want any particular country to think we're just looking at them," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:18:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Captured more than 500 dogs stray last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/capturados-mais-de-500-caes-vadios-no-ano-passado/</link><description>The number of boundary dog ​​captures registered an increase of almost 50% last year. The Institute for Municipal Affairs has revealed that 568 dogs have been captured and is reinforcing inspections in the places highly frequented by stray dogs, namely Colaane. It ensured even more cooperation with animal protection associations to reduce the number of stray animals.
 
Last year 568 dogs were captured, which represents an increase of almost 50% compared to 2023, the Institute revealed for municipal affairs (AMI). The body's statistics show that the previous year there were 380 boundary dog ​​captures and in 2022 were 253.
AMI reiterated that “always attributes importance” to the management of stray animals and is reinforcing the inspection work in places frequented by stray dogs. AMI's statement arose in a press release published on Tuesday, following a case of aggression in which a resident was injured by a stray dog ​​in Coloane.
The body stressed to have highlighted staff to “intensify daily patrols at black points” frequented by stray dogs, including the Concordia Industrial Park, the Vale das Butterflies in Seac Pai Van, the village of Coloane, the Ká-Hó Dam and the Hac Sá Dam, having led caught in these places through regular inspections.
It is recalled that a 60-year-old resident was injured after a dog's assault and was sent to the Conde de São Januário hospital center. The case took place on Tuesday morning, when the woman was going through Marginal Street of Concórdia and Rua de Cypresso, where she was surrounded by a group of stray dogs in Berma da Estrada.
The injured report says that one of the dogs suddenly attacked her and bit, resulting in a laceration in the left leg. The woman eventually left the scene and asked the police authorities for help. Police and firefighters arrived at the scene and the victim was transported to the hospital. However, police, after an investigation at the scene, found no dog.
In the statement, AMI ensures that in recent years it has “actively cooperated” with animal protection organizations to promote the implementation of the “Open Adoption” model, and Open Adoption ”(TNA), with a view to reducing the number of stray animals.
"AMI continues to sensitize the community, through promotion activities, for the care and protection of animals, the responsible animal breeding by owners, the non -capacity of animals, as well as the sterilization of animals as early as possible, to reduce the reproduction of stray animals from the source," he noted.
Authorities, in the note, appeal to the population to avoid feeding stray animals in public places. According to AMI, if bitten or scratched by an animal, the resident should immediately wash the wound with soap and water and seek medical assistance for proper treatment.
 
Group calls for more surveillance to irresponsible owners
 
The organization 'Everyone Stray Dogs Macau Volunteer Group' had a meeting with AMI where animal protection -related issues were addressed. Quoted by the association, AMI has ensured that it has paid attention and importance to animal policies and welfare, as the public is increasingly sensitized for the protection of animals with the increase in the number of pet owners in Macao. The group has advanced that it discussed with AMI the statistics related to stray animals in Macao, as well as the need to reduce the reproduction of stray animals and monitor the irresponsible behaviors by the owners, to improve the welfare and protection of animals.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:19:22</pubDate></item><item><title>"Cooking is taking care, and that's what I'm trying to do in Macau"</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/cozinhar-e-cuidar-e-e-isso-que-estou-a-tentar-fazer-em-macau/</link><description>Between 'jet lag' and the pressure of representing Portugal worldwide, chef José Avillez continues to bring an innovative Portuguese high and increasingly influenced by local flavors at the Mesa Restaurante at Resort Grand Lisboa Palace. In an interview with the final point, it speaks of sustainability, the importance of mental health and the growing prestige of Portuguese gastronomy in the world - which, more than just food, is a valuable heritage that represents “the memory of our mothers and grandparents”.
 
José Avillez's visits to Macau are unharmed. The problem is “going to the future,” he says: trips are strenuous, sleep little, force the body to adapt to a time zone with seven hours of difference. Sometimes it is just to prepare a dinner and soon part of the past to Lisbon or Dubai, where it also has a restaurant. But ensures that travel always compensates: more than gastronomy, it is representing a piece of Portuguese culture and hospitality on the other side of the world. A world where the Portuguese have arrived half a millennium and where the one that will probably be the first fusion kitchen in the world will probably be.
The Mesa by José Avillez restaurant, located at The Karl Lagerfeld Macao hotel, continues to proudly assume its Portuguese matrix, as at the opening in 2019. In 2023, raised the restrictions of the Covid-19 pandemic, the Portuguese chef finally visited the space-hitherto only known as table-and coined it with his name. The changes did not go around: after two years of consecutive trips between Europe and Asia, José Avillez wants to crave louder and create a new kitchen that honor Portuguese origins and, at the same time, mirror the cultural diversity of the region.
It is a mission that assumes with equal honor and sense of responsibility, well aware that the profession of chef always entails a certain dissatisfaction: if 95% of customers recommend restaurants under their wandering, they tend to focus on the 5% they could not snatch. It is for knowing the idiosyncrasies of the craft that values, above all, the mental health of the team. One of its spaces in Chiado, Vegetarian Encanto, has just received a Michelin Green Star last March, but the main focus of the acclaimed Portuguese chef - already distinguished with several stars of the guide - is “social sustainability”. After all, "if we do not save people, we do nothing to save the world."
 
The last time you spoke with the end point was in 2023. What balance do what has happened in the restaurant in the last two years? Was there many changes?
We have always made some changes, but the deepest will have been in January this year, when I last. In fact, this project began in 2019, and then the Covid-19 pandemic ended up the opening greatly. The considerations I took from the local market were changing as I started coming here more often. Today, as I commented on with Herlander [Fernandes], the resident chef here, I feel that we are… maybe with some pretense, but I feel that we are making a new macanese kitchen, or walking to it. This wants to say a Portuguese kitchen adapted to the territory, with great affection for all local traditions. 500 years ago, Macanese cuisine has perhaps became the first fusion kitchen in the world: it was born not only from Portuguese influences, but also from the influences of Africa and Brazil and other Asian countries here around. Having Herlander in the team, which has been a cook in Macao for eight years, has been interesting to find a little more from the local kitchen. When I say place, I am not just talking about Macanese cuisine, but Cantonesa, Chinese, and even the Japanese… We have an essentially Portuguese matrix, but gradually we also begin to have local influences. It is not overnight; It is over time, to better understand what we do and to ensure that it makes sense. Maybe, in 200 years, what we are doing will also be considered an evolution in Macao cuisine.
 
Can you give us examples of dishes that demonstrate this approach to the local kitchen?
On the one hand, there are very Portuguese dishes. It would have a hard time adapting, for example, cod to Brás, which is a dish of my childhood where it would not make sense to add local ingredients. But then we have a carbineiro with boiler broth and a wont made with shrimp and pork, more typical here… I think the big changes are related to the cooking point of things. In the old days-and I think this is important-the kitchen was made from a perspective of conservation; It was mainly to feed. It was created for lack of resources, not to innovate. The refrigerator only came to the home of people more or less in World War II and, before that, everything that was created depended on the healing with salt, the drying to the sun… Today, technological evolution makes the cook much more availability to be creative. Reaching Macau and seeing names in Portuguese, influences of Portuguese architecture… All this tells the story of our route, and that's why a huge taste for me to be here and being part of the history of Portugal and Portuguese cuisine, long after the first Portuguese who arrived here. Introducing a contemporary Portuguese kitchen, too, because 90% of the Portuguese kitchen in Macau is more traditional. Although there are good restaurants, it is a kitchen still greatly clinging to long cooking, to products a little punished - because some were bought here to be cheaper and do not have the essence of our kitchen. It has been a fun process, although also challenging, because it is a very different market.
 
Table by José Avillez was the only Portuguese kitchen restaurant to appear on the 100 best restaurants in Macau and Hong Kong from South China Morning Post. Do you feel pressure on representing Portugal in this region, worldwide celebrated by the rich gastronomic scene?
My life has always been this commitment. A great pride in somehow having opened the Portuguese cuisine on the map, but a huge responsibility that is lived very seriously. I feel that no one is up to a new kitchen of a country and make it a symbol-so I don't either. I remember when The New York Times dedicated a whole page to a Belcanto dish in 2012, and in two weeks the restaurant was filled with people who came on purpose for reading the article. Even if we want to relativize and relax, this brings a lot of responsibility. Today, as I have a great team, I try to give some responsibility to their shoulders, not to be only in my (laughs). We are a thousand people in Portugal and even a little more in Macau and Dubai. But sometimes it seems that the good parts are shared by everyone, and the bad parts are a little more mine… well or bad, it's my name that is associated with. Last year, there was a day when we served 650,000 people in the restaurants that have my name. We have a number of quality and obvious objectives that we are happy when 95% of people are satisfied with restaurants. It's great. But five thousand dissatisfied people are over 30,000 a year, and when I think there are 30,000 people who were not satisfied with what they ate… It's a huge sense of helplessness. That's why we always try to give a little more every day. Not only for us, but for the representation of Portuguese cuisine, which is a heritage that transcends food. It is culture; It is the memory of our mothers, our grandparents. I remember that my first contemporary versions of a Portuguese booked or a cream pastry have been worth letters from all over the country to insult me. It is not that they had even proven them; They just saw the news and felt insulted for daring to move her grandmother's recipes.
 
So sometimes public satisfaction does not always depend on the quality of the food. Sometimes people already come with a negative attitude…
It's true, it's true. There are many customers who spoil room services because they treat people badly, come here to drop their frustrations. I've seen it with every thing… racist attitudes, xenophobas; Parents telling their children "do you want to end like him, a table employee?" But serving is a very noble art. We, Portuguese, face hospitality as an art, because much of our economy is tourism. I have many times in Chiado, where I have most of the restaurants, and I cross with many people every day-some repeated, some new-and do the exercise of "good morning", "good afternoon". The "thank you", the "please"… I think all this makes society work much better. And when it comes to gastronomy and restoration, this concept is very present. I started cooking because I really like eating, but also because I like to take care of people. Cooking is taking care, and that's what I'm trying to do in Macau. The jet lag is hard, I always get very tired in the early days… I've even come to cook a lunch or dinner and go away. But the goal is this: bring a little of Portuguese culture, our hospitality, to the other side of the world. One side of the world that was once a little of ours and where we still left some memories.
 
Note changes in customer behavior and profile from pandemic?
People started going home early at night. The lunches are also faster… No one has five hours to stay at the table. Before, a whiskey was asked at the end of the meal, and today is able to be one in 100 customers. On the other hand, there are people who have now started experiencing this type of restaurants and the public is being replaced. With the “MasterChef” programs, released on televisions around the world, people get an interest in the kitchen and want to have this experience. Suddenly I have 12 -year -old kids who ask parents to go to Belcanto on the day of years… that changes everything. And, as it is now possible to find flights to other countries for less than 20 euros, people prefer to save on plane tickets and then spend a hundred euros at dinner. They want to be cared for, and we also want people to feel at home. This is why I stopped having the function of table employee and started using the term “host”: I want to form people who are proud of what they do and who take their role as if they were receiving guests in their own home.
 
Regarding customer requests, do you notice any difference between the most popular dishes in Macao and Portugal? I saw that the table has three vegetarian dishes, although this kind of food may not be the most popular in Macau…
No. Here, almost no one asks for vegetarian dishes. When they ask, it is like a garrison, a complement to the main course of meat or fish. Here we sell a lot of seafood, rice, carbineiro, piglet, chicken with piri-piri… it's the basics, people don't change customs easily. Choose what they are already used to. I opened a vegetarian restaurant, the charm, less than three years ago, precisely to challenge me and grow. It is like returning to that essence of ancient creation in Portugal, which is the result of necessity… The team has to create dishes with much less ingredients than normally have available; You have to work fermentations to develop different flavors and textures in vegetables… You need to make a series of preparations so that customers don't miss fish or meat, even those who are not vegetarian.
 
The charm received a green star Michelin in this year's edition. Here in Macau also strive to bet on sustainability?
Here it is much more difficult, because the territory produces less things. Just because we had a fish from Portugal or even Japan, we would hardly win a green star… only if it was adapted to this market. But there is, in fact, a concern in this sense, even in the use of veal hands or pork. We try to use all parts of the animal, without lying out, and this use also has some sustainability. But since we play at this point, I would also like to talk about social sustainability. It is a theme that interests me a lot: the well-being of our teams, our people, who are often mothers and fathers and have to convey that well-being to their children. We live in a time with more mental diseases than ever recorded. If we do not save people, we do nothing to save the world. Last year, in our company, we started a program to help take care of teams: we do group therapies, with the support of psychotherapy clinics, in order to guide and try to unlock a series of topics. The green star was important, we were very grateful, but I look at social, human, mental, mental well-being as even more important than environmental sustainability.
 
And mental health is particularly important in the sector of the high school, isn't it? At least this is the idea that comes to the public, with productions like "The Bear" or "The Menu", where the team is constantly under pressure…
Yeah, it's a very stressful profession. We work with perishable products that travel from many parts of the world and have to ensure quality, turn them, serve them, take care of people, spread the restaurant… and, on top of that, many Portuguese chefs have become public figures, so they also have to learn to manage this image. There are many possibilities of error; We are always being judged. That's why the chef of "The Menu" goes crazy at the end (laughs). In parallel, there is an artistic side in what we do, which creates some egos. The culture of the abuse in the kitchen began to undo, fortunately, but the chef-especially in France-was seen as a tyrant, with military behavior, which shouted with everyone… Today will disappear, even because there are no people who act it. I would say that there was a meeting of both parties, where chefs became aware that they cannot treat people badly and the team also refuses to be mistreated.
 
To end, a positive note: Portugal won eight new Michelin stars in 2025, including the first attributed to a woman, Marlene Vieira. Do you think Portuguese cuisine is being increasingly valued worldwide?
Yes, no doubt. We have taken a very important step with the tourist increase, because "Fine Dining" only develops with tourism. It is very rare the country whose audience is more local than international. Also on top of Portugal, where there is no level of living to attend these establishments regularly… and it is not that Portuguese cuisine is only made of "Fine Dining", but this promotes the rest of what is done in Portugal. People experience traditional, regional kitchens, breweries, shellfish… and suddenly we begin to become better known. We also have a lot of people outside living in Portugal, precisely for the gastronomy and hospitality we demonstrate to those who visit us. The kitchen increasingly begins to assume itself as an essential decision point in a series of areas. The Michelin Galas from Portugal and Spain were always in the neighboring country, but now we started to have an exclusive gala in Portugal. This makes at least on this occasion journalists and international chefs come to our country to follow the gala. This year was also special, with Marlene [Vieira] becoming the first woman in Portugal in the last 30 years… I say of the last 30, but it's like the first woman ever to win the Michelin star, because in the old days the guide's molds were different. It was an important step for Portugal and will surely open paths to other women who will be inspired by it and want to go through the same route.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>The ossuary of the brother of Jesus Christ</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/o-ossario-do-irmao-de-jesus-cristo/</link><description>In September 2002, it was announced at a conference in Washington, organized by the Society of Biblical Archeology and the Discovery Channel, the existence of an ossuary that would represent the first archaeological proof related to the family of Jesus of Nazareth.
It is a small box boss, usually stone, used in Palestine by the wealthier classes during the Roman period to keep the bones of their families after the decomposition of bodies on earth.
In Palestine there are thousands of ossaries like this; What makes this Ossar, which can be seen in the image that accompanies this article, in something so special is the inscription on one of its faces. The inscription in Aramaic, the language that the ordinary people spoke in the time of Jesus Christ in Palestine, says 'Iacob, son of Ioseph, brother of Ieshua', or translating the names into modern Portuguese, James, son of Joseph, brother of Jesus.
After its existence was announced, this Ossar was shown to the public for the first time in an exhibition at the Royal Ontario Museum in Canada, from November 2002 to January 2003. Around the same time, André Lemaire, an expert in Semitic epigraphy, published an article at Biblical Archaeology Review, confirming that both the ossuary and the inscription were authentic. Then, a real frenzy in the academic community, especially among biblical archaeologists and scholars. Although the historical existence of Jesus Christ is accepted by almost the entire academic community-very rare exceptions, and the few that exist are usually pseudo-academics with anti-religious agendas that are not serious-there are no archaeological findings directly related to the person of Jesus Christ or their families. To be true that this Ossar is an authentic artifact, this could represent the first archaeological finding directly related to the historical figure of Jesus of Nazareth.
However, its authenticity was put in question as a result of doubts related to another archaeological artifact, also of high historical significance.
 
YEHOASH REGISTRATION
In the year prior to the appearance of Jacob's ossuary, that is, in 2001, an inscription appeared in Jerusalem in Black Stone, and still written in Paleo-Hebreu alphabet, which, to be authentic, would confirm the existence, now contested by many archaeologists and historians, and the original location of the Temple of Solomon. Like Jacob's ossuary, this inscription would also be of great historical value by being the only archaeological artifact that confirmed an important segment of the biblical narrative. For Judaism in general, but also to the State of Israel, the confirmation of the existence of the Temple of Solomon, which in the Jewish religious imagination represented the abode of God in his elected city, is of great ethnic-religious and political value.
The inscription in question became known as Yehoash's inscription because it confirmed the information conveyed in the twelve chapter of the second book of kings, where King Yehoash is said to have raised funds to make repairs to Solomon's temple.
After a first geological analysis, the registration was considered authentic and the news covered the covers of the newspapers and opened the television news in Israel. Negotiations began to the Israel Museum in Jerusalem to acquire the inscription.
During the negotiations, conducted in secret, the issue of the provenance of the registration was raised. Archaeological artifacts, such as works of art, who put themselves for sale, especially those who suddenly appear, almost out of nowhere, have to prove their pedigree, which is done trying to return the path of these artifacts from their discovery to the client. In the case of a registration that certifies that the temple will have actually existed, more than confirming its pedigree, its origin would also inform about its location. Traditionally, it is considered that the temple of Solomon was located in the hill where the Al-Aqsa mosque, the third most sacred to Muslims, after Mecca and Medina, both in the Arabian peninsula. Thus, it would be expected that the inscription had been found somewhere in its surroundings.
The museum, asking for details about the origin of this artifact, caused the bearer of the registration and the registration itself to disappear suddenly from the map. This itself was already suspicious, but concerned that the inscription would leave Israel and be sold abroad, the Israelite authority for antiques was called to intervene and, after nine months of investigation, it was discovered that the inscription belonged to Oded Golan, the largest collector of archaeological artifacts of Israel, even at first, denied its inscription.
What has raised suspicions regarding the inscription is that, in the space of, about two years, two archaeological artifacts of such importance, Jacob's ossuary and the inscription of Yehoash, to have appeared and belong to the same person. As you say in English, too good to be tis! Not only that, the origin of these two artifacts seemed to be involved in mystery and stories that are difficult to confirm.
Given their importance and importance that many attribute to archeology in justifying the existence of the modern state of Israel, the Israeli authorities took over the case and pursued the collector's house where the inscription, which had suddenly disappeared, and that Golan refused to be his or her current location, was found in a box over his secretary. Jacob's ossuary was found in a bathroom resting on the toilet.
In possession of both artifacts, the Israelite authority for antiques ordered an opinion to linguists and geologists to determine the authenticity of both the registration and the Ossar.
With regard to the Ossar, what was in question was the authenticity of the registration. Although a little smaller (50 x 25 x 30 cm) than usual, the limestone stone box in itself did not raise any problem, not even the first part of the inscription, ie Iacob, the son of ioseph since, both Iacob and yepeph, are common names of the time in question and it is normal that the name of the person within the ossuary is accompanied by the name of the father, because the Jews were identified. Including the brother's name, that was extraordinary; Of course, when you have a brother as famous as Jesus, it could happen well!
In June 2003, the committee published its opinion, the two artifacts were false. The ossuary in limestone and the registration stone were, in fact, authentic and from the correct time, but the registration was recent. The main question was the patina about the letters that did not coincide with the patina over the rest of the surface. The counterfeit will have, after recording the letters to the stone, applied an artificial patina created to mimic the ancient patina that covered the original artifacts. However, although it is composed of correct elements, such as microscopic remains of gold that would have adhered to the inscription when the fire that destroyed the first temple, the patina on the letters did not coincide with the rest of the piece. Moreover, one of the elements of this artificial patina contained microscopic marine fossils that should not exist if the inscription had been recorded in Jerusalem, to kilometers of the sea, and maintained in the soil of the same region for centuries.
As a result, in December 2003, Oded Golan was charged with 44 crimes including forgery, fraud and burla. In 2005, an independent opinion in question the conclusions of the opinion of the Israeli Authority Committee for antiques, considering that even though it could not be concluded that the artifacts were authentic, it could not be concluded either that they were undoubtedly false.
The trial lasted several years and the verdict, who came out in 2012, acquitted Oded Golan from the counterfeit crimes. However, the judge said that acquittal was not proof that the artifacts were authentic, but that it was the impossibility of being able to prove, beyond reasonable doubt, that they were false.
When in the summer of 2003, Golan was arrested, Israeli police searched his residence and found in the basement an antique manufacturing atelier, where several pieces were found still in the production process, as well as already finished and packaged pieces, ready to be sent to international auction and museums, or even private customers. This raised a terrible problem in Israel. Since Oded Golan was not only a collector, but was also one of the largest archaeological artifacts in the world, which the police found in his house suggests that many of the archaeological pieces from Israel and the Middle East currently exposed in museums, either in Israel and the rest of the world, or in private collections, may be falsification created in this gentleman.
 
James, brother of Jesus?
Jacob's ossuary again raises an old linguistic-theological problem, whether or not Jesus has brothers. There are instances in the New Testament where we talk about the brothers of Jesus (Matt. 13:55) and St. Paul, in his letter to the Galatians (1:19), he even says he met in Jerusalem with the Lord's brother.
First let's look at the name. The Hebrew name Iacob gives rise to various forms in Portuguese, including James. This Portuguese name comes from the incorrect cut of two words. The names of the saints are preceded by, in medieval Portuguese San, when the name begins with consonant, e.g. St. Peter, or saint, when it begins with vowel, e.g. Santo António, pronounced Sant'António. The Hebrew IACOB gives rise to both the Jacob form, used above all in the Old Testament, and to the ancient Galaico-Portuguese form Iago, (Esp. Yago), which, incidentally, is the name of the villain of Shakespeare's Othello. The name Iago, when he began with a vowel, was preceded by a saint, thus giving rise to the synchopaded form Sant'iago. When it was later, in Portugal, to name the saint to the children, the holy element was withdrew. However, it was considered that the name was not Sant'iago, but San James, the medieval form equivalent to our modern St. James. Thus came the name James from the Hebrew Iacob.
In the New Testament reference is referred to three James, namely: James, son of Zebedeu and brother of John, which, according to tradition, is buried in Santiago de Compostela, also known as Santiago Maior, James, son of Alfeu, also known as Santiago Minor, and finally James of Jesus, Joseph and Judas, known as the just.
James, the largest, and James, the smallest, are listed as two of the twelve apostles of Christ, the first of which, after being beheaded, in the year 44, by order of Herod Agrippa, his disciples would have brought him by boat to hispania, where, once his tomb discovered in the Stellae campus, or 'field of star' Impulse to the Christian reconquest, which earned him a new title, that of Santiago Matamaros. His head was in Palestine and is buried at the Armenian Patriarchal Church of Santiago Maior in Jerusalem. [There is a delicious story of a dispute between the Archbishop of Braga and the Archbishop of Santiago de Compostela over the saint's head, but I have no space here to tell, it is next time.]
The third James, the one known as the righteous, was the leader, or Epískopos, the Greek word that would give our bishop of the Christian community of Jerusalem after the apostle St. Peter had departed to Antioch and then, finally, to Rome. This same James, described in some texts as the brother of Jesus, will have supposedly written the Epistle of St. James who is in the New Testament; I say supposedly because there are no certainties about the authorship of most of the New Testament texts.
It is part of the tradition of the Church that the Virgin Mary has given birth to a single son, and there are no testimonies or reports that deny this reality, except for this same fact, that there is someone who is described as the brother of Jesus. How is this explaining?
There are two possible explanations. The first of linguistic character is that Aramaic and Hebrew do not have a specific word for cousin or other kinship degrees; The word father can be translated as father, grandfather, ancestor or father -in -law; The word son may mean son or descendant, as, in fact, in Portuguese, and the word brother and sister may refer to the brothers of blood, cousins ​​or even sisters -in -law. This reality is not unique to these languages. Something similar happens, for example, in English, a modern European language, where brother-in-law is said to be Brother in Law and sister-in-law sister in law or in French with the expressions Beau-Frère and Belle-Sunt.
The author of this text was once wrapped in confusion because one of his students, of Burmese origin, spoke of a person in his family referring to her, sometimes as a sister, sometimes as a cousin. When the conversation reached too surrealistic, I had no choice but to ask if the person in question was a sister or cousin, or if we were talking about two different people with the same name and with the same biographical data. The answer was simple and enlightening in Burmese, cousins ​​are called brothers, that is, the word to brother is for brother and cousin. In our conversation in English, he used the Burmese terminology, sometimes his own English terminology, hence apparent confusion.
This is exactly what one may be going through with the question of Jesus' brothers. When the Greek text speaks of Jesus' brother (s) is using the nomenclature of the original language of those who are counting the story, that is, the Aramaic, but using the respective Greek word. Thus James could be a cousin, or familiar close to Jesus, referred to in the text as a brother.
The Gospel refers to another cousin of Jesus, John the Evangelist, son of Isabel, an advanced cousin of the Mother of Jesus. In the case of a gospel of St. Luke, in the narrative of the announcement, the angel uses the correct Greek word to describe Isabel, saying 'your cousin Isabel'.
The extension of family degrees names is typical in many cultures. We in Portugal we have the Tis, Ti-Maria, Aunt-Encarna, etc., many are not anyone's aunts. Sometimes friends introduce us to their children as this is Uncle John, although no blood bonds exist. In many cultures, the use of the word brother is a normal way for people to address others with a certain degree of proximity; In India, everyone is the sister of everyone. Also in Muslim countries, it is customary to treat everyone of the same age as a brother or sister, it is, in fact, considered a form of respectful treatment.
The other explanation, which, by the way, is accepted by the Greeks Orthodox, is that St. Joseph, the Father of Jesus, when he married Mary would be widowed and brought with him a son, or children, of the first marriage. This possibility is perfectly credible because, at the time, it was very common women to die during delivery and their husbands marry again with young girls.
This possibility seems to be corroborated by the fact that in the adult of Jesus, St. Joseph is never mentioned and Mary, her mother, seems to be accompanying Jesus in her public life, probably hosted at the home of the many disciples of Jesus. This would be because it was up to the eldest son, in this case, the only son, to take care of his mother after the death of his father, if he were already an adult. The crucifixion scene seems to confirm this scenario. First, if Mary were not with Jesus during her public life, what would she be doing in Jerusalem when the crucifixion? And in the dialogue next to the cross, Jesus says Mary and John, the beloved disciple, 'Here is your mother' and 'here your son' here '. The text says that from that moment, 'the disciple received Mary in his home'. John would thus be replacing Jesus' duty to his mother. This would only make sense if St. Joseph had already died, which he might suggest, although not necessarily, that he was considerably older than Mary. This possible age difference between St. Joseph and the Virgin Mary may suggest, in turn, that Joseph had been married before taking Mary as his wife, as the Jews were married, both men and women, very early so that they could begin to breed as soon as possible, since child death and birth was very high then. Trying to have many children was the only way to ensure the continuity of the family line.
This is the version offered by (proto-) Gospel of James, an apocryphal account of the childhood of Jesus and his family life, attributed to James, brother of Jesus, leader of the Christian community of Jerusalem, but most likely written in the second century of our age.
Jacob's ossuary was never taken as evidence that Jesus had brothers of flesh or that the Virgin Mary had not always been virred, even if these facts are of a theological-religious and non-historical character; Annunciation and incarnation cannot be historically proved, as, by the way, Said St. Thomas, in his Summa against Gentiles.
As once again you can see here, the biblical narrative is no joke for amateurs.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:12:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Cautious industrial entrepreneurs in the face of the future</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/empresarios-industriais-cautelosos-face-ao-futuro/</link><description>At the end of last year, the industrial entrepreneurs of Macao had a “prudent and observer attitude” regarding export prospects for the next six months, according to the results of the industrial sector inquiry by the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT).
According to the results of the investigation, carried out at the end of the fourth quarter of last year, 23% of entrepreneurs in anticipation anticipated an optimistic perspective against the future, representing a decrease of 25 percentage points compared to the 3rd quarter of 2024 (48%). None predicted a sharp increase. Entrepreneurs who anticipated a less favorable evolution were 23.1%, raising 4.1 percentage points over the previous quarter (27.2%). In addition, 53.9% of the entrepreneurs inquired predicted a similar situation in the quarter under analysis, corresponding to a growth of 29.1 percentage points compared to the previous quarter (24.8%).
The results of the inquiry also show that the average duration of the order portfolio detained by the industrial entrepreneurs inquired was 3.4 months in the quarter under analysis, representing a rise of 1.1 months compared to the previous quarter. The orders portfolio detained by the pharmaceutical product sector, which occupied first place, was 5.4 months, while the ordering portfolios detained by clothing and clothing sectors, electronic/electric equipment and other non -textile products were 3.5 months, 3.4 months and 2.1 months, respectively.
Regarding the destination markets of exports, according to the general index of the situation of quarterly orders by markets, the Asia Pacific region was the destination market of Macao exports with relatively better performance, with the 21%rate. However, the performance of US markets was relatively less favorable, with rates of less 19.9%.
Regarding the employment market, the number of workers of industrial companies inquired registered a 4.6% reduction compared to the previous quarter and an increase of 1.9% compared to the year 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:19:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Overweight and obesity rate continues to rise, warn health services</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/taxa-de-excesso-de-peso-e-de-obesidade-continua-a-subir-alertam-os-servicos-de-saude/</link><description>Macao residents live longer, but health risk is increasing. Health services indicate that more than half of local adults are “above the ideal weight range”, providing for the excess weight and obesity rate among the population to continue to increase, which is an important factor for chronic diseases such as hypertension, hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia.
 
Health services estimate that the rate of overweight and obese local population will continue to climb in the short future. Authorities yesterday launched an alert to the increased risk of overweight and obesity, as well as hypertension, hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia, although residents have a longer life than in the past.
According to Wong Weng Man, head of the health promotion division of this services, the average life expectancy in Macau increased 0.24% last year to 83.3 years (80.4 years for males and 86.1 years for females).
"They live on average five more years from the period prior to sovereignty transfer. But in recent years, the reduction of exercise and the popularity of" fast food ", take-away and other food crops have gradually increased the prevalence of overweight and obesity," said Wong in the Macao Macau forum for Radio Macau channel.
The head of health services cited data from the 2016 health inquiry to stress that more than half of Macau adults are overweight and the executive intends to suppress this growing trend.
It also indicated that one in four residents suffers from chronic diseases such as hypertension, diabetes, cardiovascular disease or cancer. "Obesity is an important factor that results in chronic diseases, which are also the main causes of death in Macao. About 80% of deaths in 2024 were caused by chronic diseases," he said.
This investigation carried out in 2016 indicated that 21.3% of adults aged 18 or over were considered to be overweight (body mass index - 23 to 24.9) and 30.6% as obese (BMI - 25 or more).
The government had also advanced that the rate of overweight and obesity among young locals was 21.7% in the academic year of 2022/2023, a light increase of 0.5% compared to data obtained in 2017, according to the results of the “health behavior in Macao student health behavior”, performed every five years.
Wong Weng Man has admitted that the criteria related to overweight and obesity established in Macau are more "restricted" compared to other regions, "hoping to remind residents that they should pay attention to their weight at an early phase." Thus, health services say they will work to integrate health measures in the lives of residents, workplaces and schools, through the creation of programs such as “Healthy Community”, “Healthy Company” and “Healthy School”.
"We planned to widen the medical team in the area of ​​family medicine, at the same time providing training to private doctors, to support the health management of residents," he said. On the other hand, the body pointed out that weight loss has to be scientific and gradual, remembering the public that it should start a weekly exercise program.
Already the Macao New Youth Association, which was in the same radio program, said that obesity became common among young people in Macao, since “lack knowledge about health and exercise”, being easily influenced by the internet and their peers to consume unhealthy foods.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:18:18</pubDate></item><item><title>China says criticism of the maneuvers in Taiwan is interference in internal affairs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/china-diz-que-criticas-as-manobras-em-taiwan-sao-interferencia-em-assuntos-internos/</link><description>The Chinese government yesterday criticized “a minority of countries” of interference in China's internal affairs, after some nations condemned the Chinese army maneuvers around Taiwan.
 
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said at a press conference that "Taiwan's issue is a purely internal issue in China and does not admit foreign interference."
Guo stated that "what undermines peace and stability in Taiwan's narrow is the" separatist "activities in favor of Taiwan's independence and the connivance and support of external forces." "If you really want peace and stability in the Taiwan Strait, they have to follow the general trend of the international community," added the spokesman, appealing to "respect for sovereignty and territorial integrity of China."
Guo said that "defending Taiwan's independence is to divide the country, supporting it is to interfere with China's internal affairs and to approve it is to undermine the stability in Taiwan's Strait" and stressed that the maneuvers of Chinese forces constitute "a resolute disciplinary action against the provocations" led by Taiwan leader, William Lai, for the "unbridled attempts of independence." "While the provocations in favor of Taiwan's independence continues, the punishment against 'independentists' will not cease," the spokesman warned, claiming that Beijing "will never allow someone or any force to separate Taiwan from China by any means."
On Tuesday, Washington condemned Chinese maneuvers around Taiwan and assured that US President Donald Trump insists on the importance of "maintaining peace" in the narrow.
For its part, the European Union's external action service has lamented that Chinese maneuvers “increase tensions in the Taiwan Strait.”
The Chinese army announced yesterday the holding of new military exercises in downtown and southern Taiwan's Strait to “test troop capabilities” following Tuesday's maneuvers.
The exercises, called “Thunder-2025a Straits”, focused on “identification and verification”, “warning and expulsion” and “interception and detention” tasks to “test troop capabilities” in domains such as “air control, block and accuracy attacks on key targets”.
Experts cited in the Chinese official press stated that the exercises show that the Chinese military has “broad deterioration options” and that Beijing has chosen to “tighten the siege of the secessionist forces” with “harder measures and energetic actions”.
The exercises are taking place weeks after William Lai, considered “pro-independence and disorderly” by the Chinese authorities, dubbed China as “hostile external force” and announced initiatives to lock Beijing's “infiltration” operations on the island. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:19:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese group started building a condominium of 6,000 homes in Maputo by 1,850 me</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/grupo-chines-comecou-a-construir-condominio-de-6-000-casas-em-maputo-por-1-850-me/</link><description>A Chinese group is building a condominium with 6,000 apartments on the outskirts of Maputo, a delutational project for young people, launched yesterday by the Mozambican President, valued at $ 2 billion (1,850 million euros). Located next to the Costa do Sol neighborhood, the project has already started to be built by the Chinese company Phoenix International Group, based in Hong Kong, resulting from a strategic partnership between the government of Mozambique and the private sector, and should be completed in two and a half years. "The project will create about 25,000 employment posts in the maximum period of its implementation, contributing significantly to the reduction of poverty in the families of those involved, and, above all, in the surroundings, where about 1,500 have already benefited at this time, in the phase of the compensation of improvements that the company has already done, and cleaning the land," said Daniel Chapo, intervening in the launch of the Felinix housing project. The private enterprise, he explained, aims to “build a housing community of conventional standard, essentially intended for young people, and of an international and modern standard”, with the head of state to highlight the contribution to the housing policy in the country. "The main objective of this policy is to facilitate the provision of adequate housing and a healthy life environment for our youth, at a cost accessible to all social groups, especially to young people, promoting a quality housing, but at low cost. So this project involves about 6,000 dwellings or apartments of various typologies to allow each one, according to their pocket, can live in a condominium house," he said.
The president stressed that the new government's housing policy, in office since January, “provides for the promotion and facilitation” of national and foreign investments for the construction of accessible housing complexes for all segments of the population, “including low -income layers”. "Our vision and objective is to make a replica of this type and level of housing, or even more appropriate, with each place and the purchasing power of each place, throughout the country, throughout this five -year [mandate started in January] that the Mozambican people entrusted us to drive," he said. Daniel Chapo pointed out that the company responsible for the project “has experience” in this type of venture in Africa: “We have heard from the centralities of our country Brother Angola, such as the talaton-like condominiums and other projects that were carried out in this friend and brother. It is this company that took this project. So we had to invite them to do projects of the same dimension, but with better respect for all respect for Engineering, and, above all, to the environment here in the city of Maputo and all over Mozambique ”. In addition to the housing component, he explained that the project includes the construction of a shopping center, restaurants and towers, including a “panoramic structure from the entire city of Maputo”. "The lagoons that are in this area, none of them will be moved. They will serve for boat ride, playground, physical maintenance circuit (…) throughout the condominium, so that each one, in the morning, upon waking, can walk, do their physical maintenance within this large neighborhood, a large city.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:12:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Young man rescued with life five days after the earthquake in Myanmar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/jovem-resgatado-com-vida-cinco-dias-depois-do-sismo-em-myanmar/</link><description>A young man was rescued yesterday with the rubble of the rubble in Myanmar, five days after the earthquake that killed at least 2,886 people in the country, the firefighters announced.
 
The 20 -year -old was rescued by a team of Burmese and Turkish rescuers from a ruined hotel in the Naypyidaw capital around 00:30, firefighters and rescue services and the Military Junta in Power in Myanmar said.
However, the operation continues as they look for a second person, according to a statement published by the Myanmar Fire Department on the Facebook social network, where they shared images of the rescue.
Currently, 25 search and rescue teams from 13 countries are operating in Myanmar, while their efforts continue to rescue people trapped under buildings.
The head of the military junta, General Min Aung Hlaing, said on Tuesday, in a forum in the capital, Naypyidaw, that 2,719 people were found dead, with 4,600 injured and 441 missing, according to the US Associated Press (AP) news agency. According to experts, the probability of finding survivors dramatically decreases after 72 hours.
The earthquake also shook neighboring Thailand and caused a building to fall under construction, burialing many workers.
About 70 people remain missing under the rubble, with no signs of life detected in the last 24 hours after confirming the death of 15 more people. "This is a rescue operation focused on saving lives. In rescue operations, the limit is 72 hours, but in many cases people can survive up to five or six days," the governor of the Thai capital, Chadchart Sittipunt, said almost 120 hours after the incident. The Bang of Bangkok Balance was yesterday of 29 dead and 34 injured, 22 of which at the construction site.
The UN said on Tuesday that it has been able to mobilize vital help for the population affected in Myanmar, without blockages of the parts involved in the ongoing civil war since the military seized power in 2021.
The head of the Military Junta de Myanmar rejected a truce announced by the Burmese rebel alliance in response to Friday's earthquake, saying that the military would continue their "defensive operations." "We know that some armed ethnic groups are not currently fighting, but they are organizing and training for attacks, so the Army will continue their defensive operations necessary," said Min Aung Hlaing on Tuesday, in the capital, Naypyidaw, in a speech quoted yesterday by the official media.
The alliance composed of the army of the National Democratic Alliance, the Taang National Liberation Army and the Arakan Army announced a unilateral and temporary ceasefire.
 
Losses may represent a 0.06% break in Thailand GDP
 
The strong earthquake that hit Thailand on Friday will have caused losses of at least 20 billion Baht (about 541 million euros), according to estimates from the Thai Research Center Kasikorn. The damage may cause a 0.06% break in Gross Domestic Product (GDP) of the Southeast Asian kingdom, the center said in a statement quoted by the Spanish news agency EFE.
The Thai center said that losses result from the suspension or postponement of economic activities, especially in the services sector, which will cause GDP to increase less than 2.4%.
The Financial Institute, which depends on Kasikorn Bank, said the purchasing power of families and companies will decrease due to reparation for damages. The institute also predicted a break in tourism due to some areas and announced that it will review the country's forecast of 37.5 million tourists by low in 2025.
If the United States confirms import rates of 25% on Wednesday, Thailand GDP will fall 0.3% more, warned the Kasikorn Center. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:19:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Pregnancy and Chinese culture</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/gravidez-e-a-cultura-chinesa/</link><description>As with other cultures, pregnancy is considered a phase of great importance and with certain care, but practices and beliefs differ around the world.
In Chinese culture it is believed that the mother's age is a determining factor in the baby's sex. Thus, according to this belief, the likelihood of having a boy or girl is dictated by crossing the mother's age with the month of conception.
Since red is considered an auspicious color and often associated with good luck and happiness, during the pregnancy period it is common for Chinese to wear interior clothing of this color or tie a red tape in the belly to protect the baby and attract positive energy.
With regard to the diet the pregnant diet should prioritize food considered “hot” in Feng Shui, an example being ginger, garlic, pork, algae and chicken broths.
The pregnant woman is discouraged to practice physical exercise because it was believed that rest helps preserve the mother's vital energy and, consequently, the healthy development of the fetus.
During the pregnancy period they are also advised to attend funerals, sew, handle dirty and sharp objects, and these acts can bring negative energies and affect the temperament of the baby.
It is not surprising that the Chinese are stunned when they see pregnant western exercise, driving a belly, carrying the supermarket bags, or simply eating certain foods seen as harmful in local culture. In Macao, it is common, local Chinese pregnant women who walk slowly and carefully intersect with hasty western pregnant women and high heels. Still, if we pay attention, we cannot fail to notice the accomplice smile that both exchange, showing the happiness of having a baby in their belly and the mutual I wish that everything goes for the best.
Practices and beliefs aside is transverse, and given as maximum priority, the health and well-being of the fetus and pregnant woman.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:12:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong replaces US -target police chief police</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/hong-kong-substitui-chefe-da-policia-alvo-de-sancoes-dos-estados-unidos/</link><description>The Hong Kong government yesterday announced the replacement of the police chief after Raymond Siu Chak-Yee was the target of United States sanctions for the role in the repression of civil liberties.
 
Hong Kong Chief Executive, John Lee, said in a statement that Raymond Siu "entered a pre-reform license today after serving the Hong Kong police body for 36 years."
The commissioner "has demonstrated an unobailable dedication and determination to protect Hong Kong and defend the right to dealing with social agitation," said John Lee, in reference to the huge, sometimes violent old manifestations of 2019.
The announcement comes two days after the United States has imposed sanctions on the police chief and five public leaders of Hong Kong, including the secretary for justice, Paul Lam Ting-Kwok, under American law defending democracy in the Chinese region.
On Tuesday, Hong Kong condemned the imposition of sanctions and accused Washington of trying to “intimidate leaders in charge of protecting China's national security”. "This clearly exposed US barbarism ... Exactly the same as recent intimidation and coercion tactics from various countries and regions," said the government of the Special Chinese administrative region.
Hong Kong's chief executive was already subject to US sanctions, but the city's authorities ensured that "they are not intimidated by this negligible behavior."
The US Secretary of State, Marco Rubio, said that the sanctions "demonstrate the commitment of the [President Donald] administration Trump to blame those who deprive Hong Kong residents of protected rights and freedoms or who commit acts of transnational repression on American soil or against American people."
Hong Kong authorities also indicated that the Chinese central government approved the appointment of Joe Chow Yat-Min, so far Deputy Commissioner, to lead the territory police.
John Lee pointed out that 52 -year -old Joe Chow has "a vast experience in criminal investigation, information gathering, policy formulation, as well as personnel management."
According to the Hong Kong press yesterday, at the first conference as a new commissioner, Chow pointed to national security as the priority, given what he called "hidden currents" of resistance to the current regime.
The manager criticized the sanctions against Raymond Siu as an act of intimidation and argued to be a reflection of the success of Hong Kong police efforts to capture fugitives to justice.
Beijing imposed on 2020 Hong Kong the National Security Act, which led to the end of political dissent, a year after a larger place of protests from the transition of administration of the former British colony in 1997. Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:19:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Internet users reveal little self-control in the use of the internet</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/03/internautas-revelam-pouco-auto-controlo-no-uso-da-internet/</link><description>The Macao Internet Study Association carried out an inquiry to evaluate the digital literacy of minors, whose results reveal that Macao Internet users have ethics in the use of the internet, but little self-control. It is also found that Macao Internet users are poorly aware of the risks of the use of artificial intelligence (AI).
 
The results of an inquiry carried out by the Macau Internet Study Association show that Internet users in the region have ethics and are aware of their online safety, but at the same time have little self-control in the use of the internet.
This inquiry, made at 1,000 residents aged between 6 and 84, intended to evaluate the digital literacy of Macao Internet users, especially of the minors. According to the Association, 80% of children between 6 and 11 have contact with the internet, and all respondents between 12 and 17 also have online presence.
Regarding online literacy, the association, based on the responses to the inquiry, says that, overall, Internet users in the region have a score of 3.8 (on a scale of 1 to 5) regarding the application of techniques in the use of the internet. In awareness of internet security - the ability to distinguish whether information is true or false or personal data protection, for example - users have a 3.6 score. The ethics associated with the use of the internet - respect for the privacy of other users, the non -use of offensive expressions or the disclosure of false information, for example - was punctuated with 3.8. The score of self-control capacity-anxiety when not accessing the internet or the dependence of the mobile phone-is lower: 3.1.
Dividing the results of the age group inquiry, the association scores consciousness for the group's Internet security between 6 and 11 years with 3.6, the 12 to 17 range had 3.5 and 18 to 84 also pointed out 3.6 in security.
Already the age group with greater ethics on the internet was the 12 to 17, with 3.9. The other tracks scored 3.8. Finally, according to the association, children from 6 to 11 are the most self-control in the use of the internet, with a score of 3.3. The remaining groups had 3.1.
The inquiry also addressed literacy regarding the use of artificial intelligence tools (AI). Overall, Internet users punctuated 3.3 in the category of fundamental knowledge about this type of technology, 3.5 in the capacity to apply knowledge and 3.1 in the risks of its use.
The age group from 6 to 17 years old is the one that has the most knowledge about AI, with a score of 3.5. The group of 18 to 84 scored only 3.2. The minors also had the highest score regarding the application of their knowledge (3.8), while the highest Internet users had 3.4. Young people are also more aware of the risks of AI (3.5) than the layer from 18 to 84 (3.1).
In conclusion, the association also leaves recommendations, for example: "Society should help minors widen the scope and depth of their applications and reinforce the ethical education on the Internet to help them be responsible online." On the other hand, the group suggests, "parents and in charge of education should set an example, demonstrating a reasonable use of the internet before their children, and to establish, in collaboration, rules of internet use to increase self-control awareness of minors." In conclusion, the association advises that the education sector will continue to “reinforce education for the literacy of the Internet and AI for minors, creating a collaborative educational ecosystem in which AI and human intelligence work together”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 01:16:11</pubDate></item></channel></rss>