<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/investigacao-de-aluno-da-upm-seleccionada-para-conferencia-internacional/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Open registrations for medical residency admission contest</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/abertas-inscricoes-para-concurso-de-admissao-a-residencia-medica/</link><description>Today open the registration for the competition of the Integrated Medical Competence Evaluation Procedure, for admission to the Medical Residency 2025. Candidates who have been enjoying this competition may apply for the procedure for access to medical residency. This contest covers 33 specialties categories with a total of 79 vacancies, inform the health services.
Admitted candidates will be subject to systematic training in service, lasting six years, including two years of basic training and four years of complementary training, which will take place at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, the Department of Community Health Care, at the Kiang Wu Hospital Prevention and Control Center, or at the Macao Medical Macao Medical Care Complex - Macao Medical Center Hospital.
Authorities say that after the inauguration of the 4th Specialties Council of the Macao Medical Academy in March this year, the preparatory work for a new medical residency immediately began. "In the future, the procedure for access to medical residency will continue to prepare the reserve of talents from different specialties and raise the general level of Macao medical services," the health officials say in a statement.
In addition, “the mechanism of cooperation with the various training institutions will be deepened, at the same time, by optimizing the allocation of training resources and increasing the number of training vacancies, among other ways, the work of contest, which not only creates a broader professional development platform for young doctors in Macau, but also forms a hierarchical team of high quality experts for the development of the sector. Macao's health, thus providing strong support for the physical and mental health of Macao residents ”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:02:48</pubDate></item><item><title>AI admits impact on the elimination of mosquitoes due to rain</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/iam-admite-impacto-na-eliminacao-de-mosquitos-devido-a-chuva/</link><description>Authorities again appealed to reinforce the prevention of chikungunya fever as well as dengue, warning of increased risk of infection in the territory. The institute for municipal affairs admits that recent rain is making it difficult to eliminate mosquitoes in outdoor spaces, as used substances take time to take effect.

Rainfall in recent days have been having difficulties in the work of eliminating mosquitoes, especially in the outdoor spaces, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) admitted. "Mosquito eradication medications should be fixed on the devices and left over a period before they have effect, and recent rains have impact on mosquito control work," Pang Sao Hun said, a substitute chief of the AMI environmental hygiene division, which spoke yesterday about the prevention of chikungunya and dengue fever during a program on Macau radio channel.
The official said that it is necessary to choose the right time to spray repellents against mosquitoes, ensuring that it has reinforced control against these insects.
Regarding parks and outdoor enclosures, AMI said it had communicated with the award -to -manage management entities to carry out the measures against mosquitoes, presenting reports about their work. The executive also sent employees to inspect the implementation of mosquito control measures in these enclosures.
Pang Sao Hun recalled that the frequency of chemical elimination of mosquitoes has been increased two to three times a month since July this year. In the case of private areas or disapproved terrain, which health services consider to represent risks, and when owners cannot be contacted, the AI will cooperate in cleaning stagnant water containers and waste to prevent mosquito reproduction and disease spread.
In the same morning program, health services have recalled that Macau has so far registered eight confirmed cases of chikungunya fever, six imported cases and two local cases, and local cases associated with workers of the construction shipyard of the new landfills.
"There is currently no community transmission in Macao, but the risk of importing the disease and local transmission from imported cases will continue to exist," warned Chai Wan, head of the Division of Prevention and Control of Communicable Diseases of Health Services.
The doctor stressed that cases of chikungunya fever in neighboring regions continue to rise, at a time when trips are frequent between Guangdong and Macau due to summer holidays. High temperatures and precipitation are favorable conditions for the reproduction of Aedes albopictus, a usual carrier of the chikungunya and dengue virus.
He also reiterated that chikungunya and dengue fever are transmitted through the mosquito bite and not directly between humans. "Macao is in the early and critical phase of chikungunya fever outbreak, and we hope residents reinforce the prevention of mosquito reproduction at home," he said.
In turn, another doctor from the Ieong Chon Kit disease center, stressed that chikungunya fever infection mainly causes light cases, while serious cases can occur in babies, children and the elderly, "but they are usually rare," he said. He added that the two locally diagnosed cases are still hospitalized and are both slight cases.
Asked about the possibility of being infected with dengue and chikungunya at the same time, Ieong Chon Kit said that in some regions the infection of these two fevers are prevalent, whose patients have even more evident symptoms. However, there is no data that show that there will be more serious causes due to a double infection.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:13:53</pubDate></item><item><title>STD social networks exceeded 10 million followers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/redes-sociais-da-dst-ultrapassaram-os-10-milhoes-de-seguidores/</link><description>Recently, the accounts of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) in social networks have exceeded the barrier of 10 million followers. The body also said that at the end of the year, a “great international event with Renowned digital influencers from Asia will be held.

The 28 accounts of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) on social networks recently reached the mark of the 10 million followers, the body said yesterday. In a statement, STD says the strategy aims to attract visitors to generation Z.
STD has an account on the following social networks: Facebook, Instagram, Tiktok and YouTube in the world markets; Wechat's public account, wechat video account, Weibo, Douyin and XiaoHongShu in the interior of China; Facebook and Instagram in Hong Kong; Facebook, Instagram and Line in the Taiwan region; Facebook, Instagram, Kakaotalk, Youtube, Naver Blog in South Korea; Facebook, Instagram, Line in Thailand; Facebook, Instagram in Portugal; And Facebook, Instagram, X, Youtube in Japan.
On the other hand, to “further increase promotional effectiveness” in recent years, STD has invited digital influencers from abroad, inland China and Hong Kong to participate in major face -to -face events, to publicize their own social networking platforms through short broadcasts, images or short videos, to increase the exposure of events to further increase the effectiveness of disclosure.
STD highlights that, recently, the body's account in Tiktok has released a series of short dramas in Indonesian, filmed in Macao and directed to the young audience, which accumulated about 100 million views in the trailers and ten episodes.
In the fourth quarter of this year, there will be a “great international event with Renowned Digital Influencers from Asia with global influence”, which will aim to “further increase the attractiveness of Macao,” says STD statement.
STD also says that "it takes advantage of the vast scope of its disclosures to launch various promotional activities and special offers, with the aim of attracting the two visiting roads around the world." These actions include the large -scale promotional campaign for the International Market “Feeling Macau Limited Edition”, free bus and boat tickets under the “Ticket Offer to Macau”, and launching airplane tickets in cooperation with various Macao, regional and international airlines. At the same time, STD cooperates with large online travel agencies and online tourism platforms, such as Agoda, Skyscanner, Trip.com, Traveloka, Ctrip.com, Ly.com, Kkday and Klook, offering discounts on hotels, airplane tickets, itineraries, restoration, experiences, among others, thus attracting visitors from all over the world to Macau.
These projects serve to “show the world, in a diverse and innovative way, the Macao unique charm to consolidate the Greater China market, to continue to expand the sources of international visitors and, in articulation with the proper economy's diversification plan, raise the name of Macau at the international level, widen the sources of visitors and promote diversified development of the Macau tourist industry”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:10:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Hong Kong promise to deepen cooperation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/macau-e-hong-kong-prometem-aprofundar-cooperacao/</link><description>John Lee, head of the Hong Kong Executive, was visiting Macau last Tuesday, where he met with the sinhboard, Sam Hou Fai. During the meeting, the two leaders from the Chinese Special Administrative Regions promised to deepen cooperation in various areas. According to the chief executive of Macao, both regions have reached "successful development worldwide notable development."

Hong Kong's chief executive was on Tuesday in Macau. John Lee met with Sam Hou Fai, head of the Executive of MSAR, having been promised to reinforce cooperation between the two regions in areas such as Tourism, the Great Bay project and the in-depth cooperation zone.
In a statement issued by the Government of Macao, it is read that Sam Hou Fai and John Lee came to a “consensus on the great directions” of bilateral cooperation in order to inject “greater dynamism in practical cooperation” between the two regions.
During the meeting, Sam Hou Fai took the opportunity to highlight that both Macao and Hong Kong "have fully enjoyed the unique advantages of" one country, two systems ", having achieved success in world notable development." The Macao government leader said he hoped the two regions "promote the coordination of transfronist policies, reinforce internal and external links, and contribute together to create a high -level abroad conjuncture in the country."
Describing the two cities as “nuclear motors of regional development”, the head of the Executive of the MSAR stressed that the two regions “continually improve the level of cooperation, especially the joint promotion of high quality development in industry areas and scientific and technological innovation, providing a greater contribution to mutual benefits, shared gains among all members of the large bay”.
Sam said that the in -depth cooperation zone is "an important platform for Macau's participation in the integrated development of the great bay and the promotion of the proper diversification of the Macao economy." The head of the MSAR Executive then invited more Hong Kong companies to participate in the construction of the in -depth cooperation zone to "join new opportunities in the second phase of the cooperation zone together to share the benefits of high quality development."
Sam Hou Fai also recalled that the decreasing count of 100 days has already begun to the 15th edition of the National Games and the 12th edition of the National Games for people with disabilities and the 9th edition of the National Special Olympic Games. “Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau will continue to work hand in hand to advance with the preparation work, to present to the country a spectacular sports event,” said the local official, adding that both territories “can take advantage of the opportunities of the 15th edition of the National Games to hold more sporting events, promoting the joint development of the Grande Bay sports, and thus attracting more and different tourists and tourist Visit Hong Kong, Macao and the whole big bay. ”
In the scope of tourism, the boss indicated that the two regions have “distinct advantages” in their position, suggesting that both parties can “reinforce the connectivity of the transport network to provide greater facilities to residents and tourists circulating between the two territories, and well enhance the complementary roles of their tourist advantages to attract more visitors through the model‘ an itinerary with multi-desectins ’”. On the other hand, “both parties are determined to collaborate to promote the tourist brands of the Great Bay, launch more tourist products and promotional plans, and thus further boost the joint development of regional tourism”, reads in the statement released by the local executive.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:11:31</pubDate></item><item><title>New measures for day care centers in Macau aim to encourage birth</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/novas-medidas-para-creches-em-macau-visam-incentivar-a-natalidade/</link><description>The next phase of the day care center development plan, corresponding to the period between 2026 and 2030, is currently being developed by the Institute of Social Action (IAS). In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U, the body clarifies that the measures projected for the second half of the decade aim to relieve pressure from families and, consequently, to encourage couples to have children, at a time when the number of births in Macao beating negative records.

The day care center development plan for the years 2026 to 2030 is currently planning and collecting opinion, with the present completion of the current year 2025. The information was advanced by the Institute of Social Action (IAS) in response to written interpeação of Chan U law, in which the deputy referred to the government some issues related to the development plans and services provided by the macao day care centers.
In the response document, Hon Wai, the president of IAS, clarifies that the plan for the second half of the decade will be objectives to “provide adequate support in child care to families, support parents in the participation of children's care and education, and establish a quality day care management system”. The leader foresees that the next phase of the plan will be finalized “during the course” this year, after the summary of the experience of implementing the plan still in force (referring to the years 2023 to 2025) and the collection of opinions by the sector.
Deputy Lei Chan U also mentioned that, in addition to economic support subsidies to families with newborns, the improvement of day care services stands out as a “fundamental element of birth incentive policies”, especially for families in which both spouses work. Given this theme, IAS ensures that the measures designed for 2026 to 2030 aim to relieve "the pressure in family care" and, as a result, encourage "young people to have children."
It is recalled that, according to advanced information in the day before yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the number of undebreente in Macao in the second quarter of this year was only 671, representing a new historical minimum in the region.

500 training vacancies for parents and professionals in 2025

In response to a last question presented by Deputy Lei Chan U, regarding services intended for “children with slight special needs”, IAS underlines that the three subsidized day care centers that provide inclusive child care services - Caritas day care center, the Fai Chi Kei day care center and the day care center are already playing 70 children with development difficulties.
"IAS continues to analyze the needs of service and practical experience, planning to establish an operational model of support and monitoring of children with developmental difficulties for day care, with a view to implementing it progressively on all Macao day care centers," the response document reads.
Within the topic of inclusive care, Deputy Lei Chan U's interpellation also referred to “personnel formation” and “allocation of resources” in supporting families in need. The president of IAS mentions that, by the end of 2024, about 220 day care professionals and 250 parents completed the formations provided by the body, planning the opening of 500 training vacancies for both groups in 2025.
Family training and support measures will continue to be developed “according to needs” in order to continually improve the day care center service system and enable “children with developmental difficulties to receive day care care with other children of the same age, promoting their happy growth and, at the same time, helping to alleviate parents' pressure on children”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:14:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Artm Gathers Exercise and Social Consciousness in “Hiking with a Purpose 2025”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/artm-junta-exercicio-e-consciencia-social-no-hiking-with-a-purpose-2025/</link><description>The second edition of “Hiking with a Purpose” is scheduled for October 12 at the Hac Sá Natural Park in Colaane, an initiative that combines sports and social awareness. Organized by ArtM in partnership with Trailman 100, the event offers 14km and 8km tests to promote healthy lifestyles and alert to the risks of toxicodependence, highlighting the association's work within the therapeutic community. With a limited participation to 400 people, this action aims to demonstrate how sport can be an effective tool in “social prevention and reintegration”.

The “Hiking With a Purpose” sports-social event, which in 2022 gathered participants around a common cause, now returns with renewed proposals. The Macao Toxicode Pedestrian Rehabilitation Association, a pioneering organization in the treatment of premises in Macau since 1993, joins the Trailman 100 again to transform Hac Sá rails into a positive stage. Through the races scheduled for October 12, organizers not only encourage sports, but also establish an open dialogue on the dangers of drug use, aligning physical action with the therapeutic mission that characterizes the association.
Starting at 6:30 am and ending at noon, the event offers two participation modalities: a 14 km race challenge for individual athletes over 16, and a fun 8 km race for groups of three people (minimum age of 8). Both tests, limited to 200 participants each, include awards for the best classifieds, but the true objective focuses on the message of union and overcoming. The initiative reflects the Mission of ArtM, which since 1993 (initially as “Being East”) has been based on the Therapeutic Community model (therapeutic community), combining treatment, prevention, risk reduction and damage minimization and political law to support dependents and their families.
The choice of a race in a natural environment is not casual. According to the organization, contact with nature and sports are important tools in social reintegration and the promotion of mental health.
In addition to the sports aspect, the event serves as a platform to sensitize society on artm pillars: treatment, prevention, risk reduction and damage minimization and defense of public policies. The participation of families and young people is particularly encouraged, reinforcing the idea that recovery is a collective process.
With a multidisciplinary team that includes psychologists, social workers and former recovering deposits, the artm underlines the importance of transparency and scientific evidence in their programs. Hiking with purpose is another example of this approach, using sports as a catalyst for discussions about public health. While participants roam the hacked Dam rails, each step will bring Macao closer to a reality -free reality. An objective that, like a long -distance race, requires persistence.
As the date is approaching, expectation grows not only among trail running enthusiasts, but also between educators, health professionals and families affected by the scourge of toxicodependence. The event represents more than one morning of exercise, and can be proof that recovery and prevention can be accessible paths to everyone, the organizers say.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:09:22</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 1,000 obtained certificate of professional techniques recognized in the interior of China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/mais-de-1-000-obtiveram-certificado-de-tecnicas-profissionais-reconhecido-no-interior-da-china/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs (DSAL), in cooperation with the Instructions Center on the Evaluation of Professional Guangdong Techniques, began, in 2022, the work of direct recognition of the certificates of professional elementary and intermediate maintenance techniques of Macao, issuing the equivalent certificate of the level of professional competences in China. Until June this year, more than 1,000 people obtained, through this measure, the certificate of professional techniques recognized in the interior of China, said Dsal.
From July this year, Guangdong and Macao have cooperated in widening professional recognition of elementary -level electrical equipment installers. Residents of 16 years of age and who have the certificate of professional elementary-level electrical equipment installers issued by DSAL may require the Macao Productivity and Technology Center to issue the corresponding certificate of professional competences in China or enroll in the assessment of advanced level certification of professional level in the interior of China.
Guangdong and Macau organize, based on the national standards of professional skills and through the evaluation content of elementary -level electrical equipment installers from both locations, their experts to proceed with professional demonstration and evaluation, recognizing guangdong directly the certificate of professional elementary equipment installers issued by DSAL, and issuing the certificate of professional level installers techniques of electrical equipment installers Elementary, recognized in the interior of China, by the appointed entity Instructions on the training of professional techniques in the city of Zhuhai (Highly Qualified Public Training Center in the city of Zhuhai). After assessment and approval of the certificate data, the “National Network for the Assessment of Technical Talent Certificate” can be appointed.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:53</pubDate></item><item><title>China applies measures to combat the outbreak of the chikungunya virus after thousands of infections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/china-aplica-medidas-de-combate-ao-surto-do-virus-chikungunya-apos-milhares-de-infeccoes/</link><description>An outbreak of the Chikungunya virus in China led authorities to implement strict preventive measures, including use of mosquitoes, drones and disinfectant. More than 7,000 cases were reported until yesterday, concentrated mainly in the industrial city of Foshan.

An outbreak of the Chikungunya virus in China led authorities to implement strict preventive measures, including use of mosquitoes, drones and disinfectant, with threats of fines and electricity cuts for those who do not eliminate standing waters.
More than 7,000 cases were reported until yesterday, concentrated mainly in the industrial city of Foshan, near Macau and Hong Kong, which recorded only one case. Authorities indicated a slight reduction trend in new contagion.
Transmitted by mosquitoes, chikungunya causes fever and joint pain, with symptoms similar to dengue, affecting children, elderly and people with pre-existing diseases.
Chinese state television has displayed images of teams to spray disinfectant in streets, residential areas, construction shipyards and other places where transmitting mosquitoes can be reproduced in stagnant waters.
In some office buildings, spraying was made before employee entry into a reminiscent approach to restrictive tactics applied during the Covid-19 pandemic.
Local authorities threaten to apply fines up to 10,000 yuan and electricity cuts to residents who do not eliminate external containers with water such as bottles or vessels.
The United States issued a warning advice to travel to the Chinese province of Guangdong - where Foshan, Dongguan and other industrial centers - as well as countries such as Bolivia, Brazil, and the Indian Ocean nations, also affected by the virus.
Intense rainfall and high temperatures aggravated the situation in China, where Chikungunya, common in tropical areas, came up with unusual force this year.
Since the outbreak of Sars in 2003, China has resorted to coercive measures considered excessive by many countries.
In Foshan, those infected are required to stay in the hospital for at least one week.
Authorities even imposed two -week home quarantines, however suspended that the virus is not transmitted between humans.
According to reports, fish that feed on larvae and even larger mosquitoes have been used to hunt the vectors of the virus.
Meetings and defined national protocols were held, in a demonstration of Chinese determination to contain the outbreak and avoid internal and international criticism. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:04</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM Student Investigation selected for International Conference</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/07/investigacao-de-aluno-da-upm-seleccionada-para-conferencia-internacional/</link><description>The results of an investigation by Li Yanfeng, a doctoral student in Applied Informatics Technology at the Faculty of Applied Sciences at Macau Polytechnic University (UPM), were selected for the International Conference “Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition” (CVPR).
The investigation presented an innovative image editing algorithm “Chef”, in collaboration with researchers at the John Hopcroft Informatics Center of the Jiaotong University of Shanghai, the University of Grande Baía, the University of Fuzhou and the University of Sichuan.
UPM explains that the investigation proposes solutions to the main challenges currently faced in editing multi-object images. When dealing with complex scenes containing various objects, traditional image editing methods cannot simultaneously balance the unique properties of each object with the structural consistency of the global scene, resulting in problems such as quantitative errors, visual distortion, and blurred properties of objects in the results of editing. In addition, traditional editing methods often require auxiliary tools for the operation, such as masks and delimiting boxes, which increases the complexity of the operation and limits the flexibility of application scenarios.
To solve the problems, the investigation team conceived two crucial modules: “Fecom” and “QTTN”. The “Fecom” module effectively separates and preserves the unique characteristics of each object, avoiding the confusion between them. The “QTTN” module uses “Fecom” improved image information to detect and automatically maintain the consistency of the number of objects in the image without depending on external auxiliary tools. This breakthrough allows the case to perform excellent performance in various image editing tasks, such as the transfer of styles, object remodeling, and background reconstruction. The results of the research provide content creators, designers and industries that depend on visual content such as electronic trade, an efficient, intelligent and easy -to -use image processing tool, says UPM, which provides that this tool is “widely used in digital media production domains, product exposure, intelligent image processing and other fields”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:01:42</pubDate></item></channel></rss>