<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/os-pontos-dos-massoretas/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Chinese Mixue breaks funding record on an initial public offering in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/chinesa-mixue-bate-recorde-de-financiamento-em-oferta-publica-inicial-em-hong-kong/</link><description>The subscription phase of the initial public offering (opinion) of actions of the Chinese company of Mixue Bingcheng beverages ended yesterday, with the amount of financing to set a new record in the Hong Kong Stock Exceeding.
At the present time, Mixue Bingcheng, headquartered in Zhengzhou, the capital of Henan Province in downtown China, plans to issue nearly 17.1 million shares, with 1.7 million shares awarded to Hong Kong's public offering and 15.4 million actions given to international supply at a price of 202.5 dollars of Hong Kong per action.
Mixue Bingcheng said Opi's recipes in Hong Kong will be used to improve the supply chain, increase production capacity, update logistics agility, and establish a global supply network to feed growth abroad.
On December 31, Mixue Bingcheng had a total of 46,479 stores worldwide - with about nine billion drinks sold in 2024.
These numbers exceed better global names, such as McDonald's and Starbucks, which are the only ones to surpass the mark of 40,000 stores worldwide.
The fourth to first place jump from the table took place at the end of the third quarter of 2024, according to Singapore's Momentum Works consultant, who recalls that the vast majority of points of sale is in China, with only about 4,800 spread through Vietnam, Malaysia and Thailand.
However, the Chinese chain remains the fourth largest in the world in terms of sales in the global beverage sector: the $ 6.59 billion (6.28 billion euros) that sold it by 2023 put it behind Starbucks, the Dunkin 'Dunuts and Baskin-Robins-and Tim Hortons.
Mixue focuses on low-cost drinks, maintaining product prices usually below 10 yuan (1.31 euros), a segment that expects annual growth of 17.6%by 2028, when this market will reach the equivalent of about $ 160 billion (152 billion euros).
Mixue is expected to debut on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange on March 3. Financial news agency Bloomberg recalled that several local rivals also launched stock offerings in 2024 and that in all of them the anticipation has given way to stock prices, compared to strong competition in the sector.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:23+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pairing sessions will make available 72 vacancies in the hotel sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/sessoes-de-emparelhamento-vao-disponibilizar-72-vagas-no-sector-da-hotelaria/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and the Federation of the Macao Workers Association (Faom) will again collaborate in the organization of three job pairing sessions, all directed to the hotel sector. In total, sessions will make 72 jobs available. Entries take place between 09:00 on February 28 and the midday of the 5th March.
The first session will take place on March 6, at Sands Venetian Limited Security, with 35 job offers for the position of security guard in the hotel sector.
On the morning of March 7, at the new Macau Landmark - Management Society, Lda., The second pairing session for the hotel sector, with 17 job openings for shift manager, accountant, warehouse employee, engineer assistant, floors and public area receptionist, among others will be held.
On March 10, in the morning and afternoon, the SJM Resorts, S.A., once again centered on the hotel sector, will be held, with the offer of 20 job vacancies for the positions of Chief VIP Service, Electromechanical Technician, Audiovisual Entertainment Technician, Receptionist and Concierge, among others.
Registration for pairing sessions can be done through the DSSA theme page dedicated to the event, entitled “Local Employment Offers”. DSAL and FAOM will notify the candidates enrolled through SMS. As the number of vacancies is limited, interested parties are advised to register as soon as possible.
These pairing sessions, often organized together by Dsal and Faom, aim to help residents of Macao who are looking for employment to integrate into the job market.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:46+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea highlighted more troops to fight in Kursk</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/coreia-do-norte-destacou-mais-tropas-para-combater-em-kursk/</link><description>South Korea's intelligence agency said yesterday that the north neighbor sent more troops to help Russia repel the forces of Ukraine that control part of the Russian region of Kursk. “After a break of about a month, North Korean troops were transferred to the front line in the Kursk region since the first week of February. An additional detachment seems to have occurred, but its size is still being studied, ”the service said in a statement cited by the South Korean public news agency Yonhap.
Military sources told Yonhap that Pyongyang recently sent more than 1,000 soldiers to Russia and added signs that the North Korean regime was preparing for more mobilization.
In early February, South Korea's intelligence agency said North Korean troops were not seen in front of Kursk's combat since mid-January. Ukraine claimed that they were removed after heavy losses.
South Korea estimates that about 300 North Korean soldiers have been died so far in the Ukraine army, while another 2,700 will have been injured in the conflict.
Since signed a mutual defense treaty last year, Pyongyang and Moscow have reinforced bilateral cooperation in defense, economy, sports and various other fields.
Relations between North Korea and Russia, which share 20 kilometers of border, intensified by mid-204, with Russian President Vladimir Putin's first visit to Pyongyang since 2000.
According to South Korean, Ukrainian and Western sources, Pyongyang provided Moscow large amounts of ammunition in exchange for the transfer of civil, spatial and military technology.
In addition, both countries have signed a strategic treaty that provides for mutual military assistance in case of aggression and more than 10,000 North Korean soldiers will have been sent to Russian territory to combat Ukrainian troops in the Russian border regions.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 5,000 commercial flights recorded in January</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/registados-quase-5-000-voos-comerciais-em-janeiro/</link><description>In January, 4,961 commercial flights were registered at Macau International Airport, ie 10.4% compared to January 2024. The data, released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), also show that the movement of passenger vessels last January was 6,997, ie 9.5% more than last year.
Regarding the transfrontic transport movement of automobiles at border posts totaled 872,900 in January of this year, plus 19.1%, in annual terms. The Light Passenger Automobile Movement at the border stations equivalent to 825,916 (20.7%more than January 2024), of which 164 thousands of entries and exits were from Macao's single registration that circulated between Macau and Hengqin and 132 thousands of entrances and outputs were from automobiles to the circulation of vehicles of macao na vehicles at the shelter Guangdong Province, registering homologous additions of 38.6% and 15.2%, respectively.
In January, the number of vehicles with new enrollments was 1,106, with 358 were electrical, less 16.5%, compared to the same month of 2024. This is explained by DSEC with decreasing the number of heavy and motorcycle cars, with new enrollment. In January of this year, the number of road accidents totaled 1,345 (less 0.4%in annual terms), with 449 injured.
DSEC statistics also refer to telecommunications and show that at the end of January there were 81,193 Fixed Network Users, less 6.5%, compared to the end of the same month of 2024. The number of mobile users was 1,450,419, corresponding to a homologous increase of 5.1%.
It is emphasized that the number of users of postpaid services (1,043,011) and mobile users with prepaid cards (407,408) rose 3.8% and 8.5%, respectively. In late January of this year there were 774,963 subscribers registered with internet services, another 5.2%, regarding the end of the identical month of 2024. In the month under analysis, 143 million hours of these services were used, having slightly down 0.1%, in relation to the identical month of 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientists warn that China can lose 35% of the aurable lands up to 2100</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/cientistas-advertem-que-china-pode-perder-35-das-terras-araveis-ate-2100/</link><description>China may lose up to 35% of the lands aurable up to 2100 due to climate change, even if the Paris Agreement commitments are met. The most affected regions are the Sichuan basin and the northeast and northeast plains of the country, according to the report.
 
China may lose up to 35% of the lands aurable up to 2100 due to climate change, even if Paris's agreement are met, according to a study published in Science China Earth Sciences.
The investigation, conducted by the Center for Geographic Analysis and Data of the Normal University of Beijing, was funded by the National Foundation of Natural Sciences of China and led by researcher Gao Peichao, reported South China Morning Post, a Hong Kong newspaper.
The report warns that the most affected regions are the Sichuan Basin (downtown China) and the northeast and northeast plains of the country, where many agricultural land will be transformed into humid areas and forests.
In addition, a significant reduction in the lands cultivated in the south and coastal zones are expected, with an expansion of wet zones in the east and south of the country.
Consequently, the areas of high density cultivation would be reduced to almost half, significantly affecting cereal production.
Researchers used, for the study, the clmond and the global change assessment model to evaluate the impact of soil changes in a global temperature increase of 1.5 degrees Celsius above pre-industrial levels, the threshold established by the Paris Agreement in 2016 to avoid the worst climate impacts.
The investigation underlines the need for countries to increase their emission reduction efforts by 2030, reaching a minimum decarbonization of 8% per year from that date.
The study proposes measures such as more rigorous monitoring of vulnerable zones, improving the quality of agricultural soils and optimizing agricultural resource management to mitigate the effects of cultivated land loss.
The world context aggravates the situation. The world weather organization reported that 2023 was the hottest year of registration, with an average temperature 1.55 ° C above the pre-industrial time.
Nevertheless, only 13 of 195 countries that signed the Paris Agreement delivered their emission reduction plans on time, while large economies such as China, the European Union and India have not yet fulfilled this commitment.
The Chinese government has received the results of the study, which can lead to an update of its agricultural land protection policies, shortly before the annual meeting of the National Popular Assembly, a body that has no supervision power and is subject to the control of the Chinese Communist Party. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:27+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The resilient tradition of bamboo scaffolding in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/a-resiliente-tradicao-dos-andaimes-de-bambu-em-macau/</link><description>Immersed in the urban scene of Macao, where skyscrapers coexist with centenary historical buildings, bamboo scaffolding remains prominent as a resistant and versatile tradition. These scaffolding, made of simple but robust material, are an intrinsic part of the region's construction landscape, representing a unique symbiosis between tradition and innovation.
When you go through the busy streets of Macau, it is impossible to be indifferent to bamboo buildings that embrace buildings as if art facilities, forming complex structures that intertwine vertiginly parallel to the facades. Bamboo, with its characteristics of flexibility and durability, is the election material for local builders for generations and its presence continues to echo the history and culture of the region.
During the typhoons, when angry winds and torrential rainfall plagues the city, bamboo scaffolding has been shown to resilient to such resistance tests.
In addition to its practical functionality, sustainability, low cost, lightness in ease of transport, reduced assembly and disassembly time, bamboo constructions also evoke a unique visual harmony aesthetics where simplicity and lightness of the material contrasts with casinos and compact contemporary buildings.
More than simple support structures, bamboo scaffolding in Macau are testimonials of the artisanal skill and resilience of the local community. They embody the ability to adapt ancient traditions in the face of modern challenges, preserving the cultural essence of Macau, a region characterized by constant change and galloping growth.
Year after year, typhoon after typhoon, change and evolution, bamboo scaffolding remains silent guardians of the past and future, supporting not only buildings, but also the identity and soul of this singular region.
It is inevitable the smile that escapes me when my eyes attach to the tangle of Bambus that travel the buildings. I feel a certain identification that perhaps all Portuguese emigrants feel it too. We remain faithful to our identity and values, flexible in adversity, but always erected about our Lusitanian soul.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:22+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>War and politics: the means and the ends</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/a-guerra-e-a-politica-os-meios-e-os-fins/</link><description>Since the end of World War II, the international order has been built based on the principles of peace, cooperation between states and respect for international law. The creation of the UN, Bretton Woods agreements, and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights were attempts to give a more stable and predictable world structure. However, the logic of global evolution and the nature of man followed ways that challenge these principles, reflecting national interests, geopolitical and economic dynamic disputes that rude early postwar stability.
The competition between great powers, as the Cold War has shown, highlighted that the dominant logic in international life is not that of peace, but the dispute for power and sometimes the periclitant balance of power. Rivalry between the United States and the Soviet Union has generated conflicts for power of attorney, arms race and the development of military strategies that sought to ensure advantages over the opponent. Even after the collapse of the Soviet world, US unipolarity did not result in an era of global peace as their theorists announced, as new threats, such as terrorism and regional conflicts, continued to challenge the international system.
The main proponents of US unipolarity included intellectuals and strategists such as Charles Krauthammer, which invented the term “moment unipolar” in the 1990s and figures such as Robert Kagan or William Kristol who defended US interventionism worldwide to ensure a liberal global order. Its argumentia base was based on the idea that after the end of the Cold War, the United States was the only superpower capable of maintaining international stability, promoting democracy and containing threats to global security. These intellectuals sustained that the maintenance of US hegemony is essential to prevent multipolar chaos and the rise of revisionist powers such as China and Russia, who intend to challenge the order based on liberal rules.
The theory of unipolarity defended by Robert Kagan and William Kristol failed due to a series of geopolitical, economic and military factors that challenged the absolute hegemony of the United States. First, the belief that the US could impose its liberal-democratic order, globally, found significant resistance, especially in the Middle East, where interventions such as the Iraq War (2003) generated instability, military wear and loss of international credibility.
On the other hand, the rise of great powers, such as China and Russia, directly challenged the idea of ​​a unipolar world, promoting a more anarchic order, with large and medium -sized countries to compete for influence. The failure of globalization in American and global plans has resulted in the growing of inequalities, deindustrialization and weakened internal consensus on US interventionist role. On the other hand, crises such as the War of Afghanistan, the 2008 financial crisis, and the internal political polarization between Democrats and Republicans showed the limits of US capacity to support an undisputed hegemonic position.
In addition, international institutions, designed to ensure peace and stability systematically failed to contain conflicts and ensure peace. The UN Security Council, paralyzed by divergent interests between its permanent members and the fragile leadership of its secretary general can effectively alleviate the most serious crises.
The strategic alliance between Donald Trump and Vladimir Putin that takes the first steps will have profound consequences in the evolution of Europe, especially regarding the luck of Ukraine and the crisis in the NATO. Trump repeatedly demonstrated skepticism about the Atlantic alliance, threatening to reduce US commitment to European defense and demanding his allies increase their military spending. It is predictable that Trump weakens Western support to Ukraine, reducing the sending of weapons and financial assistance and pressing Kiev to accept an absolutely unfavorable agreement with significant territorial losses.
All of this will strengthen the Russian position by subverting Ukrainian sovereignty and creating conditions for nuclear and conventional rearmament of Russia with greater pressure on nations, now part of the European Union, which are its neighbors. In addition, the NATO faces an existential dilemma, as European countries such as Germany, France Poland, the Baltic States and the United Kingdom will have to assume greater responsibilities for regional security, which implies the significant rearmament of several of these countries, the creation of a coordination structure of common defense within the born or eventually. In the long run, US removal from Europe could encourage Russia to intensify its territorial ambitions, exploring divisions within the European Union and the Atlantic Alliance.
A scenario of growing insecurity could accelerate a arms race in Europe and if a NATO country is directly attacked, the principle of collective defense can be tested, risking a climb that will involve various countries and turn conflict into a large regional war. Apparently out of this strategic dilemma China will see its ability to present itself as a third hub of the rebalancing of great powers.
Thus, the evolution of the world does not follow a path governed exclusively by the logic of peace, law and cooperation. Instead, it is shaped by a complex interaction between power, technology and national interests, often resulting in instability and new forms of conflict. The order established in the postwar is about to crumble, requiring constant adaptations to deal with an international scenario that becomes unpredictably.
 
ARNALDO GONÇALVES
Jurist and former teacher of political science and international relations
 
 
EMPHASIS
 
"The rise of great powers, such as China and Russia, directly challenged the idea of ​​a unipolar world, promoting a more anarchic order, with large and medium -sized countries to compete for influence."</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:23+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SINO-TAILENDESA COOPERATION-Myanmar in the fight against the Burla Unions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/cooperacao-sino-tailandesa-myanmar-na-luta-contra-os-sindicatos-de-burla/</link><description>The appearance and proliferation of burla unions triggered tripartite cooperation between China, Thailand and Myanmar in the fight against their illegal activities that victimized hundreds of thousands of people, mostly of Chinese ethnic origin. This cooperation marked at least one temporary triumph of transnational governance in containing the growth of Burlons unions along the border between Myanmar and Thailand. It remains to be seen whether the current dynamic in the joint struggle against the Burla Unions will remain.
On February 14, the border guard forces, which are Tatmadaw's subdivisions (Myanmar's Armed Forces) composed of Myanmar's former rebels under the instructions of the regional military commands after 2008, decided to expel the criminal elements involved in Fraudulent Activities (United Daily News, February 14, 2025). If Thai authorities are willing to accept the extradition of these suspects of crimes, Mianmar will transfer 50 suspects daily to Thai authorities, who will communicate with employees of the Popular Republic of China (RPC) in Thailand. In fact, in November 2024, it was reported that the Mianmar part returned about 10,000 suspects and victims of Chinese RPC crimes, whose law enforcement officials eventually sued 29 000 Chinese Chinese, which was a serious warning for those who organize burla unions in northern Myanmar. According to Thai authorities, the Myanmar government would release 261 innocent victims and then 7,000 people to Thailand, who would hand them over to RPC employees.
On February 17, RPC Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun referred to fraudulent activities along the border between Thailand and Myanmar as being harmful to life, properties and security of RPC, Thailand and other countries. According to Guo, these fraudulent activities also disturbed the normal interactions and cooperation between the countries of the region. As such, China is determined to combat burla unions, implement the idea of ​​people centered on people, protect the common interests of the countries of the region, and to act according to the common aspirations of the citizens of these countries (Wen Wei Po, February 17, 2025).
At the same time, high employees of Myanmar, China and Thailand went to the fraud parks in Myawaddy. They created a joint working group to combat the crime of burla and the crime on the Internet and to accelerate the process of extradition of the criminal elements and victims of Myanmar to China through Thailand. From January 30 to February 16, 2025, about 1 030 foreigners who were in a situation of illegal immigration were inspected and controlled in Myanmar. These people were the subject of further investigation by the Sino-Tailar-Tailar-Humianmar joint working group, responsible for identifying suspects and victims and the application of extradition procedures (Wen Wei PO, February 17, 2025).
On February 20, 2025, a group of 200 Chinese was resubmitted to China by Myanmar through Thailand (United Daily News, February 21, 2025). They caught the Chinese airline to return to Nanjing International Airport. Most repatrias were the victim of burla crimes, while a minority belonged to the organizers of the burla unions. According to Thai Defense Minister Phumtham Wechayachai, in February 20, 600 Chinese returned from Myanmar to China through Thailand, which constitutes a clear evidence of the Sino-Taieiraland-Myanmar combat victory against the burla unions.
Thai royal police estimated that 10,000 foreign citizens, including Chinese, will be rescued from Myanmar burla parks. Police General Thatchai Pitaneelabott, who was also the director of the Traffic Trafficking Center and the Thai Police Cyber ​​Working Group, added that Thai authorities were discussing their homologists from Myanmar, under the national reference mechanism, the verification and return of the victims of human beings to their countries of origin. (Bangkok Post, February 17, 2025). He also said that Thailand acted as a facilitator, helping in the victim verification process and identifying those who may want to process traffickers and burns - a legal process in which they must submit their legal complaints to Myanmar's authorities.
It is noteworthy that thatchai Pitaneelabott had previously informed the representatives of foreign embassies, including the United Nations Office against the Drug and Crime and the US Embassy Internal Safety Investigation Office, not only about the situation of circumstances and trafficking in humans, but also about the location of the burns and how to distinguish victims from criminals.
On the other hand, the Deputy Minister of Public Security at RPC, Liu Zhongyi, arrived in Thailand on February 17 with 26 other Chinese delegates to participate in the joint operation of three countries against the Chinese-led by the Burla-based and based on Myanmar. The joint operation began its work for two months. Operatively, the members of the Burla Unions were separated from the victims and were formally detained. The operation of combating the combat to the circumvents began with the interruption of the supply of electricity, oil and the internet in the affected regions of East of Myanmar. This action has forced the government of Myanmar and ethnic groups to quickly take action to repress Burlões gangs in their territories - a chain reaction that demonstrates the effectiveness of cutting the supply of electricity, oil and internet.
In fact, it was reported that, in Kanchanaburi, the democratic Buddhist army Karen arrested 86 Chinese suspected of operating burla unions in the municipality of Payathonzu. These Chinese were arrested in a place where an anthro of in line was still operating. Apparently, the end of the supply of electricity and oil has forced the local war lords of Myanmar to suppress the unions of the burla.
On February 17, a local Myanmar employee stated that a combined security force had rescued 731 people from eight countries, including victims from China, Thailand, Indonesia, India, Malaysia, Pakistan, Vietnam and Ethiopia (Bangkok Post, February 17, 2025). Apparently, the victims were spread across different Asian countries, which implies that the burla operators were probably from different countries.
On February 18, Thai police detained ten suspects of belonging to a Thai-Chinese union of Bang of Bangkok investment and in other local provinces. They were accused of fraud, computer crime, capital bleaching and illegal montage. Crime suspects included not only Thai owners of “mule” accounts, but also Chinese and even Korean money porns and launders. Obviously, crimes suspects involved transionic actors who took advantage of their personal networks to get involved in Bangkok Post, February 18, 2025).
On February 20, Thai authorities pondered new restrictions on internet access along the border between Thailand and Mianmar. They created a committee with members who visited the Mae Sot district in Tak province to assess the potential impact of restricting internet access on residents. The National Telecom Public Company Limited employees, telecommunications operators and National Broadcasting and Telecommunications and Telecommunications Commission (Bangkok Post, February 20, 2025), participated in the work of the National Telecommunications. A challenge in the crusade against fraudulent unions is the trend of fraudulent bands to convert their stolen assets into cryptographic currency - a complex process of recovery of illegal digital assets.
On February 21, the Thai government invited representatives of social networking platforms, including Facebook and Tiktok, to discuss methods to combat the crime of burla in line, because a growing number of people was the victim of online scams on Facebook and Tiktok (Bangkok Post, February 21, 2025).
In conclusion, joint tripartite efforts involving China, Thailand and Myanmar to combat the burla unions seem to have achieved fruitful results. The efforts made by the Thai authorities to combat the Burla unions in the eastern part of Myanmar through intergovernmental cooperation with Myanmar and China must be praised. However, it remains to be seen how the dynamics of the joint operation of the three countries will be maintained, to minimize the victims of Asian countries and continue to extradite and penalize the criminal elements involved in fraudulent operations. In addition to the joint operation that surrounds China, Thailand and Myanmar, it should be launched simultaneously in China, Thailand and other Asian countries a vast educational campaign to alert citizens against circumvents, so that victims remain minimized to the fullest.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Computer scams and crimes made crime grow last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/burlas-e-crimes-informaticos-fizeram-crescer-criminalidade-no-ano-passado/</link><description>Last year, Macao's police authorities made a total of 14,298 criminal investigations, which means an increase of 6% compared to 2023. Cases classified as violent crimes grew 7.4% and computer crime increased by 71.6%.
 
In 2024, 14,298 criminal inquiries were established, which means that crime increased not only compared to 2023 but compared to 2019. Last year's crime data were presented yesterday by Wong Sio Chak, secretary for security, which justified this increase with the growth of computer crimes and circumvents.
Last year, Macao's police authorities made a total of 14,298 criminal inquiries, which represents an increase of 6% over 2023, and a rise of 0.8% compared to 2019.
In 2024, there was a total of 290 cases of violent crime, which translated an increase of 7.4 % compared to 2023. However, compared to 2019, there was a decrease of 56.9 %. In the context of crimes of severe violence, such as abduction, homicide and serious body offenses, a “zero rate or a very low occurrence rate” is maintained.
Last year, 1,115 cases of simple offense crimes to physical integrity were reported, a number similar to the previous year; 48 cases of violation crimes, plus 17.1% compared to 2023; 22 cases of crimes of sexual abuse of children, a decrease of 38.9%; and 61 cases of kidnapping crimes, an increase of 48.8%.
In the context of crimes against heritage, 2,800 circumvents were found, 12.2% more than 2023 and, compared to 2019, an exponential increase of 83.6%. There were also 2,001 theft crimes, identical to last year; 48 thefts, more 29.7% than in 2023; 170 extortion crimes, ie less 27.4% than in the previous year; and 265 usury crimes, more than twice the recorded in 2023. There was also an increase of 71.6% in computer crime between 2023 and 2024, and last year was registered 992 cases. Compared to 2019, computer crime rose 267.4%.
During police operations and investigation operations last year, 5,401 people were detained and present to the Public Prosecution Service, which reflects an increase of 21.5%compared to 2023, but compared to 2019, it represents a decrease of 18.9%.
In 2024, there were 131 cases of youth delinquency, which represents an increase 21.3% and 1.18 times compared to 2023 and 2019, respectively. The number of young people involved was 181, which, compared to 2023 and 2019, reflects an increase of 19.9% ​​and 1.01 times, respectively.
Regarding domestic violence, authorities accounted for 133 records last year. However, until February 4, only 12 cases were classified as crimes of domestic violence, and 111 were classified as offense crimes to physical integrity.
Yesterday, in the presentation of crime data, Wong Sio Chak explained the increase in crime last year with the "continuous increase in burla crimes and computer crimes."
On the other hand, the secretary for security pointed out that, as for severe violent crime, drug -related crimes and the game, as well as crimes that affect the daily life of the population, namely theft and theft, the numbers were significantly lower than the year 2019, which leads to the security environment remains “stable and good”.
 
Number of game -related crimes recorded an “inevitable” increase
 
Wong Sio Chak also made known the statistics of crime related to the game industry. Last year, 1,456 inquiries were opened for game -related crimes, which, compared to 2023, means an annual increase of 31.5%. However, when compared to 2019, there is a decrease of 32.5% in these crimes. "Compared to 2023, last year there was also an increase in uncertain factors, which may eventually impair the security of society," said the ruler, explaining that "the gradual increase in tourists and the recovery of tourism and game sectors, as well as the law to combat illicit play crimes, which led to the end of the illegal money exchange, led to a criminalization of the illegal money exchange, led to one inevitable climb of the number of game -related crimes ”. Still, the number of cases in 2024 was "remarkably inferior" to 2019, "which demonstrates that the work of preventing and combating specific crime, performed by the police, has had effective results and has had deteriorated effects on potential criminals."
Among the game-related crimes, the number of circumvents crimes continued to be the highest, with 333 cases, which constitutes 22.9% of the total, followed by 252 cases of usury, which represent 17.3% of the total, from 202 cases of illegitimate appropriation, 13.9% of the total, 10.2% of the total, 79 cases of disobedience to access to access to Casinos, 5.4% of the total, from 89 cases of exploitation of illicit exchange exchange rate, 6.1% of the total, from 52 cases of physical integrity offenses, 3.6% of the total, 47 cases of kidnapping, 3.2% of the total, and the remaining crimes represent less than 3% of the total.
Wong Sio Chak talked about the "money exchange burns," which reveal a "high professionalism." However, with the entry into force of the illicit -playing crimes and joint operations with the police authorities in the interior of China, there was a “clearance of the security environment in the Macao game industry and leisure”.
Authorities detailed that among the 1,752 suspects of crimes related to the game area, the large majority (1,316) came from the interior of China. The proportion between resident and non-resident suspects was 1: 4.5. The victims were also, mostly, from the interior of China. Among the 1,108 victims of game -related crimes, 856 were from the continent and only 146 were residents of Macao.
In conclusion, the Secretary for Security stated that "the prevention and combat work of the specific crime carried out by the police has obtained effective results," which, according to Wong Sio Chak, "means that the risk of security with origin in this sector is predictable and controllable."
 
“Eyes in the sky” system supported the investigation of 9,724 cases
 
In the presentation of crime data, Wong Sio Chak pointed out that the video surveillance system commonly known as “eyes in the sky” supported the investigation of 9,724 cases, including cases of severe violent crime, namely crimes of homicide, theft and set fire. Authorities plan to install another 680 video surveillance chambers by 2027.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:20:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“The House of Dancing Water” announces show in May with “forgetfulness” to the Macao Media</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/the-house-of-dancing-water-anuncia-espectaculo-em-maio-com-esquecimento-aos-media-de-macau/</link><description>The new show of The House of Dancing Water will officially return in May. The date was announced yesterday at a press conference, for which much of Macao's media were not invited, including Portuguese and English -speaking newspapers, and also had a backstage visit. According to the final point, the company's management intends to focus more on the Chinese press to promote events. "Where Water Dances, Legends Come Alive" is the title chosen for the new acrobatic show that aims to "attract tourists from around the world," according to the president and CEO of Melco Resorts and Entertainment, Lawrence Ho.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Galaxy profit rises 22% in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/lucro-da-galaxy-sobe-22-em-2024/</link><description>Galaxy game concessionaire announced yesterday an increase of 22% in both profits and revenues in 2024. The company had returned in 2023 to a positive situation after three years of loss due to the restrictions imposed in Macao at the entrance of tourists under the “Zero Covid” policy.
 
Galaxy Entertainment Group registered a profit before taxes, interest, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) of 12.2 billion Hong Kong last year. Thus, Galaxy got a 22% increase in both profits and revenues in 2024.
The company had returned in 2023 to positive land after three years of damage due to the restrictions imposed in Macau at the entrance of tourists within the scope of the “Zero Covid” policy.
Galaxy registered 2024 revenues of Hong Kong's $ 43.4 billion, also an increase of 22%.
The Macao game sector had total revenues of 226.8 billion Patacas last year, a 23.9% increase in 2023, even far from the amount recorded before the COVID-19 pandemic began.
Galaxy President Francis Lui Yiu Tung said in a statement sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange that the Galaxy Macao venture hosted about 460 shows and events.
Francis Lui added that the company continues to advance in the construction of the fourth phase of Galaxy Macao, with “a strong focus [in activities] non-game, mainly aiming at entertainment [and] family facilities”.
The bet on non -playing elements and foreign visitors were some of the requirements of the Macao authorities for the renewal for 10 years of licenses of the six concessionaires operating in the territory, which came into force on 1 January 2023.
Francis Lui stressed that the company's financial balance reached $ 27.1 billion from Hong Kong, with a $ 4.2 billion debt from Hong Kong.
A “healthy and liquid” balance that allows the company to finance the development plan and continue the “international expansion ambition,” said the executive.
At the end of June, CSA consultancy said in a report that the Galaxy was one of the four game dealers in Macao that had shown interest in legalizing casinos in Thailand. Days later, the Galaxy told the Ggrasia news portal that it "kept the options open", but admitted that Thailand "would attract a lot of attention" if deciding to allow the game in casino. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:46+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of births in Japan falls to a new record and sums nine years of decline</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/numero-de-nascimentos-no-japao-cai-para-novo-recorde-e-soma-nove-anos-de-declinio/</link><description>The number of births in Japan fell to a new record, increasing the challenge related to increasing social security costs in an aging society, with an increasingly reduced group of workers who pay taxes.
 
The number of newborns in 2024 fell 5% over the previous year to 720,988, extending a number of nine years of decline, according to preliminary data on the population released yesterday by the Japan Ministry of Health.
This reading marks the lowest value since these records started in 1899.
Also the deaths increased by 1.8% to a record of 1.62 million in the same period, resulting in the largest annual decline as always in the total population, according to the report.
The sustained decline of births in the country increases the urgency felt by a government that is already supporting the heaviest debt among developed countries. Japan's public debt will be 232.7% of the country's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) this year, according to the International Monetary Fund (IMF).
The demographic situation in Japan is in tune with a growing global trend. South Korea's fertility rate increased last year for the first time in nine years, but with 0.75, it is still far below the rate required to maintain the population.
The fall in birth in France accelerated in 2023, reaching the fastest rhythm in half a century, while China's population decreased for three consecutive years.
Fewer workers means fewer tax revenues for niponic state coffers, while pressuring companies, which face staff shortages.
Since the active age population of Japan has reached their maximum in 1995, their labor market has been relatively tight. The unemployment rate is 2.4%, the lowest among OECD countries, and has been maintained below 3% for almost four years. By 2040, Japan is expected to face a labor deficit of 11 million people, according to an estimated Recruit Works Institute, quoted by Bloomberg.
In 2024, a record number of 342 Japanese companies went bankrupt due to labor shortages, according to a teikoku Databank inquiry, according to the news agency.
However, Japan's social security costs continue to increase as a growing proportion of the population exceeds the age of reform.
For the fiscal year that begins in April, the government has attributed 37.7 billion from yen (241 billion euros) to social security, an increase of almost 20% over the last decade.
Japan's pension system is also under pressure, with fewer contributors and more beneficiaries. Over the past two decades, the number of taxpayers has decreased by about 3 million, while the number of beneficiaries has increased by almost 40%, according to the Japanese Ministry of Social Security.
The continuous decline in the number of births reflects, in part, the reluctance of younger generations to have children, despite recent government efforts.
Based on an initiative of his predecessor, Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba is promoting a package of child care policies worth 3.6 billion yen (23 billion euros), which includes support for future parents and improvements in day care care conditions.
Despite the increase in expenses, the births were far short of the main scenario expected to 2024 by the National Institute for Population Studies and Social Security. The institute had projected 779,000 births for this year. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>A lower rate of birth, more imported workers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/uma-menor-taxa-de-natalidade-mais-trabalhadores-importados/</link><description>The low birth rate in Macao generates the aging of the population and changes in the demographic structure, but its economic effects can be attenuated with greater immigration. Still, experts warn you, you will always have an economic impact.
 
If on the one hand, there are those who say that the deceleration of the Chinese economy and the uncertainty about the future are the origin of a low birth rate in the territory, others associate it with the increasing demands of society with women. With the 2024 Macao numbers to reach a historical descent and the poorly optimistic predictions for 2025, the end point wanted to know what is behind and what is the short, medium and long term impact.
As with the neighboring region and east Asia, for demographer Stuart Gietel Basten, there are three factors behind these low fertility numbers. "The direct cost of having children and marries, which are the high expectations around education and others-the financial cost, but also the psychological, that children have to be successful," he says.
There is also an opportunity cost. "If you are a woman, it is probably one of the worst things you can do to your career," says the Hong Kong University Science and Technology researcher, who adds a third factor, related: "In an environment with defined gender roles, women are expected to work, but also to assume the main responsibilities of home and home work, as well as taking care of children and parents as well." To this are added the difficulties that young people in the territory have to begin life. “It's very difficult to get home in Macau,” he exemplifies. If all goes wrong, not being a social state, a type of organization that places the government as an agent of social promotion and the economy organizer, add various concerns, including "reform or finding a decent job."
 
Economic motives: Yes or no?
 
The economic growth of mainland China has reached the 5% goal of Beijing by 5%, but some economists claim that the economy is expanding at a slower pace than indicated in official estimates. Still, for Gietel Basten, behind there is now no added fear linked to economic conditions. "The birth rate is low now, but in fact it has been very low for a long time-in the largest economic boom, 10-15 years ago, it was already extremely low," he says.
Looking at Macau, the demographer says that it is not just a matter of money. "It's about abdicating your dignity, work as an interesting part of your life, and that's why policies like bonuses to have babies don't work," he reveals, explaining: "They don't meet key issues, which is having to give up something very important in your life."
In turn, the professor at the University of Macao, Spencer de Li, considers that the reasons behind the low birth rate are also economic. "Young people get married later, because in this part of the world it's all so competitive and if you want to have a good life, you need a good education and study for a long time," says the sociologist. Housing is also a factor. “Most young people live with parents until late, because it is very expensive to buy home,” he adds. "If they do not have a place to live alone, they will have difficulty constituting a family and even marrying, and if not married, in this part of the world, you will usually have no children," he says.
According to Chinese tradition, it is expected to have family and many children, but given these factors, the attitude has changed in recent years. “It is no longer thought to transmit family genes - people have little performance and little time and want to use the time available in themselves,” he reveals.
 
A more family -oriented social policy lacks
 
And if, for Gietel Basten, there is not exactly a connection between fertility and economic changes, the same is not true of social support policies. "If something goes wrong - running out of job, a divorce, then there is no security network, there is a risk of taking a relationship, getting married and having children," he says. "In Europe, for example, the risk of choosing the wrong partner is lower than in Macau and Hong Kong," he opposes. In addition, there is a lack of day care centers on this side of the world. "The existing offer is not adequate, especially for the younger ones, between six months and one year," he explains.
In addition, the license of parenting in the territory, but is also marked by society itself on this side of the world. "There are limits to what a government can do - for example, in Japan and Korea, no woman will take a one -year license because the work culture is such, that this is seen as the wrong thing to do," he says.
Macao, as in the rest of East and Southeast Asia, there is not exactly a development towards a social state. "Everything is built around growth, there is no real interest in defining family policies, gender equality," he says, adding: "Everything in health and education is thought as a means of making labor more productive and the economy stronger."
Moreover, contrary to what is already thought of the West, on this side of the world, the balance between work and personal life is not yet privileged. "In having this balance, it is considered a failure-either if it is a bad worker or a bad mother," he says.
Spencer de Li considers that the territory's social support system is quite good. “It does not seem to me that social incentives are lacking,” he says, stating that there are, for example, support for the tuition fees. By the way, looking at the region where Macau is inserted, the teacher considers that the territory "is even in a good position."
But the low birth rate is actually a challenge for the territory, just as it is for the rest of the world. "It's a universal problem for developed countries," he says, adding "not knowing the more the governments can do to reverse the trend."
 
The fight against aging through immigration
 
With the low birth rate, the population should be decreasing and aging very quickly, but this is not the case. "Of course the population is aging, but it is not decreasing, given immigration," says Gietel Bhenten. Still, it can raise some issues, linked to the composition of society, the survival of the places and even the Cantonese.
Whatever it will happen in the coming years, for the researcher in the neighboring region, it may be “a problem of difficult resolution”, but a crossing of policies between the different government departments will always be necessary. Still, he says, there are very positive points in the territory. “The average life expectancy is very high in Macao and is a good place for the elderly,” he says.
For Spencer de Li, the impact is visible, for example, on the universities themselves. In turn of the century, with the transfer of administration, there was a decline in the birth rate, which two or three years ago began to feel. "These babies are now young adults and I, as a professor at the University of Macao, saw the impact," he reveals, explaining: "There were not enough young people for places in all universities and, as a result, we had to recruit more from mainland China and other places."
Por isso, diz, daqui a 17 anos, esses mesmos problemas repetir-se-ão. "The low birth rate will affect schools, the infantry - perhaps, some will have to close and people will be without jobs," he speculates. Sobre um impacto maior na economia, o investigador afirma que isso ainda terá de se avaliar, já que Macau depende largamente da imigração. “Pode sempre contratar-se mais gente de outros locais”, salienta.
In the long run, there will be, of course, an aged population and people will be needed to take over the elderly, especially with the average life expectancy to be increasing. "This can cause huge pressure on young people," he says.
 
Impact on education and the economy
 
For economist Henry Law, low fertility can have a negative impact in different areas. For example, everything that is related to education can be affected, even in childhood health. And none of this is new when you think about the rest of the world.
However, when it comes to contributions to social security and taxes, Macau is a special case, as it is the game to finance this system and, therefore, is probably free from this negative impact. “In mainland China, Korea and Japan, for example, there will be a huge pressure of tax revenues, when we have young people to pay for taxes that support the social security system,” he says.
Still, in the long run, even if Macao's fiscal system does not suffer, it will have an impact on the supply of local labor. "Once again, due to the special situation of Macau, which is based mainly on imported workers, there will probably not be a lack of people to work, but there will be other issues," says the professor at the University of Macao. "If we only depend on imported workers, of course they can choose to say goodbye and leave the territory, if economic performance is not good, especially for qualified labor," he explains. If this is the case, there will be no local workers, given at a low birth rate to support the economy.
Moreover, with workers imported to the weekends and their holidays in their home territories, there may be “abandonment of consumption outside the territory”, also affecting the local economy. For all this, says Henry Law, it is important to have “a healthy fertility that supports economic development”, thus ensuring a stable demand.
 
Economic and social motives
 
It happens in all developed economies, especially with the increase in the number of people with higher education levels and high income. “This class is not stuck with typical community practices, they think independently and may not want houses and have children,” argues Henry Law.
Moreover, considering high life standards, many young people “are facing tremendous pressure, especially in the early phase of career development” and, more recently, after the pandemic, there is some “uncertainty in the face of the future of the economy”.
Economist José Isaac Duarte also argues that this is a worldwide trend, related to the enrichment of people. Considering that this phenomenon is not new in the territory, the analyst states that the population is aging and, as such, has fewer children. With the economic situation deteriorating in mainland China, there is nothing to be reversed of the fertility rate trend. "There is no factor at the departure that encourages or suggest an inversion of this trend, so much so that the local Macao population in the last three or four years has practically stagnated," he says.
On the impact on the future, Isaac Duarte states that there will be, in 20 years, "serious flaws" in the labor market of resident workers. “Breaking birth will have effects on the job market in 20 years,” he says.
Looking at the history of the territory, the analyst states that the number of non -resident workers increases because "the economic boom could not be sustained with local labor, which did not exist." In fact, in the late 1980s and 90s, at the gates of the transfer of administration, there was a “brutal breach of birth”, which only now has repercussions in the labor market.
In a context of a pandemic, which has also had psychological effects to evaluate, and in the face of economic uncertainty in mainland and general China in the world geopolitics, it seems that "young people are deciding not having children."
 
The lowest rate since 2004
 
By 2024, the total number of newborns was 3,603, less 109 babies (2.9%) than the previous year. The forecast, however, is even less optimistic for 2025. According to the director of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), Kuok Cheong U, quoted by the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, there should be less than 3,500 births this year, which would be the lowest since 2004.
According to official data, in 2023 there were 3,712 births in Macao, 43.5% less than 10 years ago (6,571) and out of a maximum of 7,913 fixed in 1988, which was a lunar year of the dragon. Macao's birth rate reached the peak in 2012 with 12.9% and marked a continuous breaking trend since 2014. In 2022 he first hit the lowest record of births in recent years.
LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, has recently found the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) and, during the meeting, guarantees that the government will try to combat the birth rate and consider measures to cope with the aging of the population.
In a note sent to the end, the direction of statistics and census services said that the birth rate is linked to factors such as the number of divorces and marriages, the median age of the first marriage for men and women and the median age of mothers who have their first child, as well as the age of women who have children, who is between 15 and 49 years old.
About certain social support measures could be implemented to try to reverse this trend, contacted by the end point, until the closing time of this edition, there was no response from the Institute of Social Action.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:19:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Police departs murder after man was found dead in a fire in Seac Pai Van</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/policia-afasta-homicidio-apos-homem-ter-sido-encontrado-morto-num-incendio-em-seac-pai-van/</link><description>A man was found dead and with his body burned in a social housing unit in Seac Pai Van, where he launched a fire on Wednesday. The firefighters report that the entrance door of the fraction in question was locked and blocked by a television furniture and that the victim's legs were tied. The Judicial Police preliminarily excluded the hypothesis of being a case of murder, indicating that the deceased had mental disturbance. The Institute of Social Action confirmed that the man was a case that was being accompanied.
 
The Judicial Police (PJ) is investigating a case on Wednesday in which a burned corpse was discovered in a fire in a fraction in Seac Pai Van, and for now the possibility of murder. This fire took place on Wednesday in the late afternoon in block 4 of the Lok Kuan building, which is part of the government's social housing project.
The victim of the case is a 61 -year -old resident man who was found dead in a chair in a room in the house with her legs tied.
The Fire Department said it had received the fire notification around 7:30 pm and sent a team to the scene to deal with the situation. According to the body, firefighters tried to enter the fraction to extinguish the flames, but found that the input metal door "was locked inside" and "blocked by the television furniture."
"It was necessary to use tools to open the metal door and the wooden door, as well as to remove the obstacle objects, before [the firefighters] was able to enter the apartment," said PJ, indicating that the fire was later extinguished and a burned corpse was found.
According to the authorities, the Fire Department notified the case to the PJ at 7:53 pm on Wednesday and requested a judicial investigation.
At about 1 am yesterday, the PJ released the preliminary information of the investigation through a message sent to the press, stating that the deceased was “a carrier of longtime mental problems and with a self -mutilation history” and lived with his family in the fraction where the incident occurred, but his family members had recently left home for a few days.
The PJ assured that the deceased was being accompanied by social services staff and recently received medical treatment with the person. On Wednesday, social services staff moved to the deceased's house for a visit and accompanied their situation, leaving only in the late afternoon.
"Around 7 pm and such, the social services staff received a telephone call from the deceased and, during the conversation, found that the state of the deceased was abnormal and suddenly stopped being contactable," he said. Social services assistants immediately asked the police to help.
An examination and investigation of the site was conducted and the PJ confirmed that no signs of fighting or searching in the apartment were found. "After examining the corpse by the PJ and Forensic doctor agents, it appears that the deceased's injuries were consistent with the circumstances of the site and no other suspicious injuries were found," he said.
Police authorities, in this sense, point out that the possibility of murder has been excluded and the determination of the cause of death awaits the forensic examination, and the case is being accompanied by the PJ.
 
“Strict Investigation”
 
Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Security, in turn, left the guarantee that police investigation and evidence collection is “clear” and “subject to inspection”. The issue was raised at a press conference yesterday held by security guard, where the secretary reiterated the preliminary conclusion of not being a case of murder and dismissed the concern of a possible lapse regarding rescue work.
He said the police received the notification of the case while the Fire Department, also around 7:30 pm. It is recalled that in the press message, the PJ said it was notified of the fire by firefighters at 7:53 pm. “Some details of the investigation should not be made public because they involve the means of investigation. If all the details are made public, how will the case be investigated in the future? ”Indicated Wong Sio Chak, stressing that the police, in all kinds of cases, is very rigorous in all investigation procedures. Wong has ensured close communication with PJ on the details of the case and that the entire process of investigation of evidence and analysis is subject to supervision.
 
Accompanies the case
 
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) said that the family involved in the fatal fire is a case that is being accompanied by social work institutions subsidized by the body. He assured that, after becoming aware of the incident, he immediately came into contact with the competent institutions and maintains close cooperation with them, with the aim of providing the necessary assistance to the deceased's family.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:18:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Photography is, more than anything, a passport to travel”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/a-fotografia-e-mais-que-tudo-um-passaporte-para-viajar/</link><description>Photography as a reason to travel. In his first contact with cameras and the craft of photojournalism, at the age of 19 in Pakistan, Chris Stowers came across a passion that would take him around the world. Three decades of presence in conflicts and passages for violent humanitarian crises, have shaped the career of a storyteller, now renowned photojournalist of a practice that he himself says is in danger of extinction. On the other hand, he left his vision, in an interview with the final point, about the resistance of photography in the current global context. A practice that lives in the “present and future” unlike the new technologies that feed on what already exists.
 
Chris Stowers is a renowned British photojournalist based on Taiwan, whose career covers more than three decades to capture the essence of human condition in scenarios of crisis and conflict. Born in an environment that fostered curiosity for visual narrative, Stowers perfected his skills in over 70 countries, focusing on areas where the struggle for survival is a daily reality. Through their lenses, it brought to light the stories of people who would otherwise remain invisible in the world.
This Sunday launches his new book, “Shoot, Ask… and Run!”, Which works as a reflection on the ethos of photojournalism, through a compilation of his overwhelming experiences around the world. With a style that alternates between serious and ironic, Stowers transports readers for episodes ranging from gang confrontations in Indonesia to the distressing moment when he was captured by militias during the war in Bosnia, revealing the duality between terror and the absurdity of life in extreme situations.
Stowers stresses the relevance of photojournalism as a means of giving voice to those who face injustice, arguing that the image has the unique power of humanizing harsh statistics and telling stories that could otherwise go unnoticed. It considers that each photograph can cause a question and reflection on the complex realities that surround us.
In an interview with the end point, Chris Stowers said he will share with the public not only the challenges faced during his media coverage, but also the purpose of purpose that moves him incessant seeking to capture the truth. It explores the intersection between art and activism, and how, through photography, it is possible to shape empathy and understanding of contemporary crises that affect humanity in a deep and comprehensive way.
 
How does your first trip to Pakistan in 1987 shaped your perspective on humanitarian crisis zones?
I was 19, I was in the United Kingdom, but suddenly I gave myself in Pakistan, on the border with Afghanistan in an area of ​​war in 1987. There was a camera with me, which was a great luck. I ended up to a cheap hotel where many other excellent but not very successful photographers were waiting for Afghanistan and others who returned with their stories. I was able to play with their photographic equipment and their objectives. I was addicted to hearing their stories and the advice that gave about photography. I thought I couldn't put the teachings into practice until I had some adventures, which took a few years until I became a professional photographer and sell my first stories and words. But in terms of conflict zones, I mean, it may seem in the new book that it is war, but in fact I cover more refugee crises, environmental emergencies, earthquakes and issues of this genre, than war zones. But in the end, the result of all these human problems are displaced or traumatized people in one way or another. Therefore, it is the human element that I consider interesting to photograph in all these different conditions and, in a war, one sees this more easily… On the surface, in our civilized world, we disguise all our emotions, but in a situation of war, it is a little addictive, because we feel we bind to people without filters. I find the most honest and affectionate people, sometimes in the most terrible situations, which is a great contradiction. From the earliest times to photograph, that is certainly what attracted me, I think. It was a way of quickly understanding what was going on in the situation and mind of people in a foreign country.
 
You can share a specific experience in which your mantra “fires, asks… and runs away!” Did you help you overcome a dangerous situation?
It is in the last part of the book, where I am returning home after six years of travel and I felt that I had to establish my credentials and go to a dangerous war zone. I was trying to photograph some Bosnian refugees. They were Bosnia's Serbian refugees. And the fact that they dislike being photographed is not because they hate the camera, but they are very proud people and did not like to be photographed in this humiliating situation. Began to be shot. I started to take them off photographs and they didn't like anything. But I was a journalist, but it didn't seem like a real journalist. It was out of money, with a dirty and unimportant air, without interpreter. So I asked if I could photograph, but not even that helped. So I ran away. I followed a combat doctor who called me into a hospital. I thought, great, I can go and take some photographs of the injured, and get away from these other types that don't like me very much. But the type of hospital said that he had basically told the hospital authorities, "This man has been photographing the roads, signs and people, must be a spy, a bosom spy." They handcuffed my hands behind my back, pushed me into a car. The type behind me put a pistol on my head and took me. It was thinking, when, when the car slows down, can I go out the door and start running? And in this case, in fact, the mantra would not have worked. If I had tried to escape, they would have an excuse to shoot me. Therefore, in this case, in this case, I did not obey the mantra, sometimes does not work, the escape, we have to consider very carefully the time to escape, otherwise we can even get more problems. But the first one, shooting and asking, usually works. So it shoots first and asks later. Shooting first means capturing the true emotion of a face. As soon as someone sees us, even if we have not asked them, they know and start acting and nothing is real again, it could be good, but it is not, not as good as the first time. That's why this is the initial impetus for this mantra, always photograph first. What I found is that if you invest some time, and especially if you have two cameras, not one, but two cameras, you are a photographer, with one, you are a tourist, people seem to understand it, and if we spend half an hour on a corner, and if we forget that we are there, we become invisible and then we can really escape with a lot and, slowly, we get closer and further.
 
What similarities did you find in human experience in different conflict zones?
This is where it is very important to be a photographer and perhaps not just a journalist, because a journalist can often make the story from the news the photographer brings back to the office. The photographer provides the information firsthand, because the newsroom does not go to the place, but to take a photograph one must be there, it is necessary to suffer the situation, if one can not find a water supply or if there are tremors of land, one lives with the people who are suffering. Therefore, I think there is a kind of reluctant acceptance or respect that the local population has for a photographer who went there and dirty with them and suffered with them. What we find is that, and this is the hardest, if we are photographing a refugee situation, we sympathize with the people we are photographing. We absorb the emotional problems of their lives for a few days, but we can always leave and they have to stay there. And there are sites that photographed on the border between Thailand and Burma in 1988, where they are still in refugee camps almost 40 years later, they have not yet returned. However, they do not lose hope of returning. This is a waste of human potential, all these wartime zones end up moving people and is a waste of human potential.
 
What role does photojournalism play today, taking into account new technologies?
I think, in a way, we are all under the threat of artificial intelligence, but I still believe it can only work with images and words that have already been written and photographed. So we still have to go outside and do the hard work to get the real material. Does a photograph save lives? It can change lives, no doubt. But I don't know if it really helps to save people. Sometimes, if we photograph an ethnic group and our history become famous in the international press, their government can become harder with them because it is expressing an unapproved point of view by the government. You need to be very careful. There is a quote from Emile Zola, the French writer: "It cannot be said that if we really saw something until we have photographed it." I see this more and more. You have to be a photographer to see, not only human experience, but also to recognize a city, to enjoy a city while we go through it. We see it differently from other people with different professions. The photograph, in fact, honestly, is the passport to travel. It's the excuse I needed. The excuse I needed to go out. Because sometimes we think: “I'm taking a photograph of this terrible situation. But am I a tourist? That means I'm a terrible person. ” But if I'm doing a job and I'm someone who will use these photographs, maybe you can help the person I'm photographing. So I'm being part of a long-term solution, so I feel more honest about what I do.
 
For younger photographers now starting, what kind of teachings or ideas would you give them?
I can photograph what I see in front of me, I'm not an artistic photographer. If we have an artist's brain, we can always invent a new method, a new kind of photography that people like to see and the instruments for it, technology is now much better and infinite than when I was starting, I just photographed in film until 2006, I was one of the last people to move to digital in my type of work. So now, someone who grows surrounded by computers has many opportunities. But we must have this creative state of mind. I still think it takes the basics. We need to work in a laboratory, know how to reveal negatives. We must understand the composition of light and shadows, these basic things. Unless we know this instinctively, we will not be able to move to the next phase. Therefore, some kind of training is required. I mean, I think a more formal training can be positive, but I received training from the people I met on the way. But I also made many mistakes. It takes time. So don't hurry. Nowadays, the equipment is expensive. They paid me I think for a photograph at South China Morning Post in 1990, $ 500 of Hong Kong. Well, they can guess how much I get today by a photograph at South China Morning Post? 500 dollars of Hong Kong, the same for 30 years.
 
Any of the great photographers of the past that has inspired him?
Among personal friends, in terms of photographers, I like Robert Capa's style of photography. Perhaps because it quickly photographs with small equipment and captures only emotion, it doesn't have to be exactly clear, as with Cartier-Bresson. There is a kind of division between the two sides of the brain: one is art and the other is only reality. I like the side of reality. Therefore, I am definitely a supporter of Robert Capa, James Nathway and all these types. When I saw some photographs in 1980 of Stephen McCurry, photographs of Afghanistan, just looking at National Geographic, where they were published, I thought this was sparkle and we tried to recreate this kind of lighting conditions. Finding these landscapes that makes the imagination boil and we have to go outside to catch “that” photography. It's so good, we were happy to get a good photography. Therefore, Steve McCurry and James Knack are two other influences. But in the end, everything is always summarized to people.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Services like Didi or Uber would provoke “social conflicts” in Macau, defend taxi drivers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/servicos-como-a-didi-ou-uber-provocariam-conflitos-sociais-em-macau-defendem-taxistas/</link><description>Taxi drivers' association argues that application transportation services, such as Didi or Uber, are inadequate to the social and road characteristics of the MSAR and that would negatively impact the taxis sector. The alternative may go through the development of an application to call taxis, benefiting both passengers and drivers.
 
The Association of Taxi Professionals and Operators in Macau has rejected the implementation of a passenger transport service by application in the region, claiming that private companies such as Didi or Uber are incompatible with Macao's social and road conditions.
Speaking on the sidelines of a Chinese New Year event organized last Wednesday, the Association's president, Wong Peng Kei, reiterated that this transport model would result in “social conflicts” and would “seriously” the subsistence means of MSAR taxi drivers. The same responsible argues that these online transport services, although popular in the interior of China, would not be able to adapt to the specific conditions of the region. On the other hand, the taxis sector has always been “linked” to the realities of Macao society and road environment - characterized, for narrow roads where there are not always pedestrian walks.
The impact of this type of platform would also extend to about 1,750 taxis in Macau. While public competitions for taxi operation are often slow and expensive, the registration of a driver on the Didi platform does not require payment. As a result, the association explains, licenses for this type of transportation services would shoot and cause traffic jams and constraints in the flow of traffic in Macau.
 
Taxi drivers admit application creation to call taxis
 
Wong Peng Kei recognized, however, the need to implement measures that make it easier for taxis to be so -called Macao, a problem that justified with the insufficient number of vehicles, traffic congestion and road conditions, as well as the inconvenience of calling a taxi through a hand nod.
The solution that the Association proposes - and that it is worth discussing with relevant institutions - involves developing an application to call taxis, covering drivers from all sectors. If the current number of vehicles proves to be insufficient compared to the growing number of tourists in Macao, the association admits more taxi licenses to the competition to satisfy the demand.
In the last public tender for the taxi operation, licenses were assigned to ten companies to the operation of a total of 500 vehicles. The public contest caused controversy and was the subject of complaints by some of the candidates, who claimed lack of transparency of the process. In the contest, almost half of the 40 proposals submitted were not allowed, and some were accepted and then rejected.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:17:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MASORTAS POINTS</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/28/os-pontos-dos-massoretas/</link><description>In the past column, we saw as the only library in the classic world that came to us intact, save, came with a huge caveat, that we can't even open the books that Vesuvius "preserved." It may be that now, technology will finally allow us to have access to these literary works, some of which, we hope that many, unknown to this day. In fact, the large amount of texts of classical antiquity we have represents only a small fraction of the literary production of the Greeks and the Romans. We know it, because the ancient authors quoted each other, which demonstrates, besides, that the ancient literary production circulated. There were even stores specializing in the sale of books where they were copied by hand, most of the time by slaves, and sold to the interested public. Around the first century of our era, in the early days of the Roman Empire, books with the most popular literary works of the time were not even too expensive and having books was not a special sign of wealth. This situation, which did not last long, would only be repeated in the sixteenth century when the English translation of the Bible, known as Geneva Bible, so called for being compiled and published in 1560 in Geneva by Protestants exiled during the reign of Mary Túdor, became the first book to be acquired by the ordinary people as an copy cost only the equivalent of two or three weeks of salary. At the time, the Geneva Bible cost about ten xelins; Per week, on average, an ordinary worker would earn between 36 and 48 cents and twelve cents made a xelim. Already in the Middle Ages, the possession of books was a sign of considerable wealth, although the situation had improved slightly, especially from the fourteenth century, when the bourgeoisie entered the bookstore, both producers and consumers, but it is only with the invention of the press by mobile characters by Gutenberg, in 1440, that the possession of books would come, as it is said to democratize. They would have to pass several centuries, however, until the lower layers of the population could buy books.
Returning to the Romans, it is thanks to this sociocultural aspect of the principles of the Empire, this demand for books as a cultural and commercial product, and the ability to produce them as a commodity, that various copies of the most important works, those that most captivated the public, began to walk around, which increases the likelihood that these works arrive at us.
There were also renowned authors whose works were necessary to have them in the libraries of the wealthier houses and many, such as the poems of Virgílio and Horace, were even used in teaching. The only tragedies of Esquilo, Sophocles and Euripides who arrived to us complete, did so because they were included in a school collection or sebenta that contained the most famous works of these authors.
We also know of the existence of works and authors who did not come to us through the catalogs of the great libraries of antiquity, such as the Library of Alexandria, the largest library of antiquity that burned in the year 48 BC, as a result of the attack that Julius Caesar and his army made Alexandria, then the capital of Egypt Ptolemaic, when it was called to resolve the dispute Dynastics by the Egyptian crown between Cleopatra VII, the last queen of independent Egypt, and her brother and husband Ptolemy XIII. Other large libraries of antiquity were that of pergamum, Ephesus and Constantinople. These libraries, such as the Greek word Bibliotheke 'Book Box', suggests, were not public libraries, such as the ones we have today, but rather from great book repositories whose goal was to collect and store all the written knowledge that existed then.
Do not think that these things were only going on in the past. In the glorious times of Hollywood, movie studios produced thousands of movies a year. There were then different categories of films, not all of the caliber of the Ten Commandments (1956), whose director Cecil Demille (1881-1959) had a heart attack during the filming that lasted years, or from and all the wind took, which had to end without an end because the movie was already too long and there was no money. There was a much cheaper production movie B, whose filming, always in the studio, could not exceed a week and that were made to the hundreds to satisfy the avid audience of entertainment in the years prior to the television revolution. A great percentage of these films has been lost forever because, stored in the studios archives for decades, often poorly conditioned, the film of the movies spoiled; Some are so bad that they disintegrate to the touch. Something very similar to what is going on with Herculaneum's papyrus. There are films of this category B of which only the titles and actors are left, that having participated in some of these films, in their work there is no image, we only know their names.
 
 
The transmission of religious texts
Many of the texts and authors who have not reached us-a large percentage of the literary production of the past-unfortunately will be lost forever. Those who have come, did so because in many cases, responding to the aesthetic or thematic expectations of their time, were being copied and marketed, thus increasing their chances of resisting the accidents of history.
Since for a long time religion played a much more active role in western societies than literature or philosophy, among the texts that have best preserved themselves are religious texts.
Among the oldest and most important religious texts are the scriptures of the ancient Hebrew people who constitute what we call ancient or old testament, the first part of the Christian Bible, and that the adherents of rabbinic Judaism call Tanach or Mikrah.
The Hebrew Scriptures are not only among the most important ancient texts, they are also among the most preserved goods, unlike many classic texts that came to us in incomplete or even fragmentary form. Two are the main problems around the Old Testament texts, one of its composition process and another, its transmission.
The composition process of these texts is too complex to deal with it here; We can do it at another time, to say that the biblical texts, both the Old Testament books and those of the new, were not written by an author, are the product of a long process of compilation and writing that, in some cases, led to centuries to complete.
In the case of the transmission of Old Testament texts, a particular aspect interests us here, that of its writing system. The Old Testament in its latest wording, that is, the one that has come to us, is written in an ancient Hebrew language, with some small parts in Aramaic, and written in a Silabário called Square Scripture (Quadrata Scriptura). This name derives from the fact that the letters seem to each fit inside a square; In English it is called Square Writing.
 
Syllable writing systems
We have already had the opportunity to talk about the origin of writing and how it has developed from small designs or ideograms to signs, or letters, which represent, no longer complete ideas, but the individual sounds that, once combined, express the words that previously the ideograms represented.
The first ways of representing sounds were, as we have seen, the syllabaries from which the alphabets that the Greeks invented when they adapted the syllable of the Phoenicians (at first, the Greeks had more than one alphabet) came out.
Unlike alphabets, whose linguistic signs represent the individual sounds with which we form words, syllables represent syllables. These are divided into two types, those who denotes the vowels, called abugous, an Ethiopian word that brings together the first four letters of their syllable, and the Silabaries Abjad, a term that derives from the first four letters of the alifth or Arabic Silabário, which only denote the consonants.
The difference between an alphabet and an abugitive syllable is that in the alphabet the vowels are independent and we combine them with the consonants to form syllables and hence words, while in the silabaries added, the vowels are part of the design of the lyrics it denotes, not an independent sound, but two sounds together, one consonant and one vocal. In an alphabetic system, BA is equal to B + A, in an abugous syllable, BA cannot decompose; This means that with an alphabet we can write BBA or BAA while in a pure abugous syllable, we could only write drool. Already in a syllable Abjad, the BA syllable is written only B, such as the be or bi or bi syllables; Knowing which vowel should be pronounced with B that is written is the competence of the person who reads. Phoenician writing from which the Greek and Latin alphabet derive, which serves Portuguese, and modern abugous and Abjad syllabaries was also originally an Abjad Silabário.
Silabaries abugous can be more or less perfect depending on how they are able to represent simple closed syllables, such as -Por-, or complex, such as trans-, in the Portuguese word transfers. In fact, some modern abugous syllabaries, such as those of Indostão and southern Asia, were so much developed that it is almost impossible to distinguish them from alphabetic systems, were it not for the fact that the symbols are drawn. To give an example, in Devanagari, the writing system used by Sanskrit and modern Hindustani, if we wanted to write the BI syllable with I-Breve, what we would actually write would be IB, because the symbol that denotes the I-Breve comes before what denotes B B; The BI syllable with I-Longo, writes BI, with its elements in the same order as alphabetic systems follow. If we want to write Bu, the symbol for the brief or long vowel, writes under the consonant. In the famous word karma, the r that closes the first syllable Kar-writes over the syllable -ma. Still, there is no syllabic structure, however complex, that a Silabário of the type of Devanagari is not able to represent. Silabaries like this are often designated in the bibliography as alphabetic abugus.
Most modern syllables, whether abugous or Abjad, derive from the imperial Aramaic writing, including the southern Asian Silabaries. Thus, with the exception of the ideographic systems of Chinese origin, the Korean phonetic system and the Japanese syllabic, most of the Asian writing systems derive from the wire, and as such, share the same origin as the Portuguese alphabet, although with it they do not have the slightest external opinion. India's writing systems, both northern, who serve the Indo-European languages, as well as the southern ones, which serve the dravidic, derive from the ancient Brahmi writing that was introduced into the Indostan subcontinent by Emperor Ashoka (304-232 BC) of the Maurian dynasty. Brahmi was in itself an Abjad writing system, but it developed so as not only to denote the vowels, but also closed syllables and complex syllables. Through the expansion of Buddhism, this syllabic writing system expanded in southern Asia being responsible for the writings of Thailand, Burma, Laos, Khmer's writing of Cambodia.
The surface systems of Indostão and Asia are almost perfect and their adaptation to the languages ​​of the region was even able to include the tones, typical of the Sino-Tibetan languages ​​spoken in southern Asia. Already a pure abugous system, such as that used by the Ethiopian language, if he wanted to write the Portuguese word transportation, he would write it Teraneseporete, given its inability to denote closed syllables. The syllaric's syllabic structure, the official language of Ethiopia, and the gueen, the classic language of Ethiopia, is very different from that of Portuguese and as such, the Ethiopian sylabary as it works, serves the needs of this language perfectly well; The example given here only serves to demonstrate the difference between the two types of silabaries.
The Arab alifth, which not only serves the Arabic language, but also many cautionic and even Indo-European languages, such as Persia's farrsi, Urdu, the language of Pakistan and Muslims of India, the Pashtum of Afghanistan, among others, is a Silabário Abjad.
In addition to the Arabic language, modern and classic Hebrew, as well as the various modern Aramaic dialects, spoken in parts of Turkey, Lebanon, Syria or Iraq, are written through Silabaries Abjad.
These tongues, at least in their classic versions, had only three vowels, A, I and U, which could be brief or long (the difference between brief and long vowels can be seen in English, in words like 'suitable' with i-Breve that opposes the feet 'feet' with i-east. Silabaries Arabic, Hebrew and Warm, in addition to writing the consonants, also write the long vowels.
 
The massoretas niqqudot
Every day thousands, if not millions, of people read newspapers in the Arab countries and Israel without any problem understanding what is written even though written words do not have vowels.
If suddenly the Portuguese had to start reading their tongue without vowels, it would surely reveal an almost impossible task at least at first. However, if we had been trained since children, or writing without vowels, or with just a few vowels, for example, the sharp, as we do not have long vowels, we, like Arabic speakers and modern Hebrew, would be perfectly able to do it without any difficulty. For speakers of other languages, who were interested in learning Portuguese, it would be quite different, just as it is not easy for non-speakers of the language to learn to write Arabic.
The ancient Hebrew, the tongue of the Old Testament, was one of the languages ​​spoken in Palestine where the vast majority of the Old Testament books were written. Due to the conquest of Palestine, at one point the ordinary people stopped speaking Hebrew in their daily lives and began to speak Aramaic, the frank language of the Babylonians. Hebrew continued to be spoken by priestly caste, aristocracy and was used as a liturgical and academic language.
Around the third or fourth century of our era, after the Kokhba Bar Revolt, also known as the Third Jewish -Roman War (132-135), when the remaining Jews were expelled from Palestine, Hebrew was no longer spoken at all. As the Jews dispersed around the Mediterranean basin began to adopt the national languages ​​of the areas where they settled, and over time, local Jewish communities began to develop their own dialects of these languages-the most famous case is that of Yiddish that is no more than a high-alemal dialect of the Low Middle Ages-while Hebrew was confined to religious use.
Now that Hebrew was no longer a spoken language, its Abjad type writing could become a problem. However, this was not the first concern that the Jews had when they decided to reform their writing system. The great concern of the Jews, now scattered around the world, was to maintain the integrity of their sacred scriptures so that their meaning could not be tampered with.
To realize the problem, let's see just one example, the written word mlkh in Hebrew Silabário Abjad. This word could read Malkâh, which means 'queen', or Malekah, which means 'she reigned', or Malkah, that is, 'her king'. This "flexibility" could compromise the understanding of the text and make it open to "wrong" interpretations.
Another problem was the maintenance of the correct pronouncement of the text; Now that the Jews spoke different languages, and as such they were used to different sounds, the original pronunciation of the language of their scriptures was at risk of getting lost.
However, any attempt to reform the writing system came across enormous difficulty, namely the consonant text, the one that the rabbinic Judaism had inherited from the second temple Judaism, but had acquired the sacred text character and as such could not be modified or manipulated. This also included the way it was written.
Aware of all these problems, at the end of the century. V, Jewish-academic scribes groups began to appear in the East who were dedicated to trying to resolve these difficulties; They became known as masoretes or masters of tradition.
At least three masoretes schools are known: the Palestinian school, the Babylonian and the Tiberian. Around the century. X, the three had already developed different Niqqudôt systems. These systems consisted of small points and lines, among other small signs, called in niqqud Hebrew, in the singular, and niqquidôt, in the plural, which were placed on top, below and even within the consonants of the original text, as can be seen in the image that follows this text. These points or niqqudôt that the massoretes have invented serve to denote the vowels that the original Silabário of Hebrew does not contemplate, they still denotes accents and punctuation. In addition, there are also signs for recitation of the text, a kind of cantem, not only to be used in synagogues during liturgical ceremonies, but also serves as an aid to memorization of the text. The great advantage of this system is that it does not interfere with the consonants of the inherited text.
In the end it was the masoretas notation system of the Tiberiad School that avenged, having been universally adopted by rabbinic Judaism. Babylonical notation is partially used by Yemeni Jews and Palestinian is used in the Targumin, or pentateuch aramaic translations.
These scribes were capable of, without interfering with the original text, for them sacred, introducing signals to the vowels and the accents of a language that was no longer spoken. This makes the niqquidôt or points invented by the tiberiad massoretes one of the best examples of linguistic analysis carried out before the birth of linguistics as science in the nineteenth century. What the masoretes did, and which took them almost five centuries to achieve, was to transform the ancient Silabário Abjad of Hebrew into a perfect abugous syllable. This system is only used for religious texts, modern Hebrew continues to be written without vowels
For those who can be curious about this writing system and, above all, the language it serves, in mid-March, will open a Biblical Hebrew course at a post-Labor time, open to the general public, organized by China Macau Theological Learning Center and the University of St. Joseph, taught by the author of this text. It also opens a Bible Greek course. All are welcome!</description><pubDate>2025-02-28T07:21:22+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>