<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/londoner-recebe-evento-sobre-transformacao-tecnologica-em-macau-e-hengqin/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Data review reviews to 0.2% Japanese GDP contraction in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/revisao-dos-dados-reve-para-02-contracao-do-pib-japones-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>The Japanese economy registered a contraction in the first quarter of the year lower than initially estimated, due to the improvement of consumption data, although the Japan Bank remains cautious.
Gross Domestic Product (GDP) contracted 0.2%, in homologous terms, between January and March, the Japanese government said yesterday compared to a 0.7% decrease in preliminary data. Economists hoped that the initial value would be maintained.
Private consumption rose 0.1%, while companies' expenses increased by 1.1%. Net exports registered a 0.8%retreat.
The Japanese government also reviewed the estimate of public investment in the first three months of 2025, which, according to yesterday's reviewed data, registered a contraction of 0.6%.
The reviewed numbers confirmed that the world's fourth largest economy contracted even before US President Donald Trump launched his trade war against the rest of the world in April.
The Japanese Central Bank said it will wait, for now, to decide changes in monetary policy, particularly after reducing growth forecast for this year at the last policy meeting.
Bank employees remain cautious about the impact of tariffs, with Governor Kazuo Ueda to consider “extremely high” uncertainties. Last week, Kazuo Ueda warned that tariffs could affect the Japanese economy through multiple channels, committing to assessing economic and prices based on a vast set of indicators.
Most economists expect the Central Bank to postpone new rates of rates, providing for no changes in the coming months. The bank of Japan defines its policy on June 17.
Japan faces a 10% rate on its products, which will increase to 24% in early July if there is no trade agreement with Washington.
Specific sectoral rates are revealed especially heavy, namely 25% tariffs on cars and components, which are corroding exporting profit margins.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Tropical Storm may affect Macau at the end of this week</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/tempestade-tropical-podera-afectar-macau-no-final-desta-semana/</link><description>It is developing in the waters near the eastern Philippines an area of ​​low pressures that should become a tropical storm. This storm, which will be named “Wutip”, could affect the southern area of ​​China later this week.
An area of ​​low pressures is developing in the waters near Luzon, in the Philippines, and should become a tropical storm in the coming days. This storm, which will be named “Wutip”, could go through southern China and be the first of the year to affect Macau.
The Hong Kong Observatory says this tropical storm "will be moved from the general direction of the Western coast of Guangdong to the island of Haião, between the middle and the end of this week." By the end of this week, heavy rainfall should be recorded in this area. The neighboring region will be signal No. 1 tonight.
Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) note that “there are still great divergences between models, namely, whether the system will enter the southern sea of ​​China or, the possibility of another area of ​​low pressure form in the same region”.
The neighboring region's body foresees that, later this week, the southern coast of China has more sudden clouds and devices, with a slight decrease in high temperatures. In the coming days, the intense heat will continue to feel.
SMGs indicate that the high subtropical pressure will intensify. Some departments may also occur at the beginning of the period. The maximum temperatures will continue in the 33 degrees Celsius. The SMG portal details that today and tomorrow temperatures should oscillate between 27 and 33 degrees Celsius, and tomorrow scattered water can occur. On Thursday, Friday and Saturday, the temperature low slightly but the showers and thunderstorms appear.
With the continuity of the influence of high underptopical pressure on the southern region of China, abundant sun is expected and weak wind. The weather will be very hot during the day, with the maximum temperature to increase another or two degrees Celsius in urban areas, predict Macao authorities, warning that people who need to remain outdoors for long periods should be aware of the risk of sunshine and drink water in adequate amount.
The SMG had already warned that the beginning of this year's tuft season would start in June and end in October or until later. According to official forecasts, between five and eight tropical storms may affect Macao this year, and any of them can reach the level of severe or higher typhoon. Last year Macau was affected by seven tropical storms, including the Super Typhoon “Yagi”, which forced the SMG to issue signal No. 8 of tropical storms.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:16</pubDate></item><item><title>China records deflation for the fourth consecutive month in May</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/china-regista-deflacao-pelo-quatro-mes-consecutivo-em-maio/</link><description>The consumer price index (IPC), the main indicator of inflation in China, fell for the fourth consecutive month in May, down 0.1% in homologous terms, the same amount recorded in April and March.
Still, the indicator, released yesterday by the National Statistics Office (NBS) of the Asian country, suffered a less sharp drop than the predictions of most analysts, who expected a decrease of 0.2%.
On the other hand, analysts expected prices to keep at the same level as April, but the monthly trend in May was also negative: consumer prices fell 0.2% over the fourth month of 2025.
The risk of deflation in China, the world's second largest economy, worsened last year, raised by a profound real estate crisis, which affected investment and consumption.
Deflation consists of a drop in prices over time, as opposed to a climb (inflation). The phenomenon reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly dangerous, as a drop in the price of assets, as a lawsuit under credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
Dong Lijuan, NBS statistical, preferred to stress that underlying inflation - a measure that eliminates the effect of food and energy prices due to their volatility - rose 0.6%in homologous terms. "The IPC went from discharge to a drop in monthly comparison, mainly due to the fall in energy prices," explained the expert, who insisted that "policies to increase consumption continue to be effective, as prices in some areas have had positive variations."
China's authorities have repeatedly underlined in recent months that boosting poor internal demand is one of the main economic priorities for 2025, which has been marked by the US trade war.
In mid-May, the United States reduced customs rights to Chinese products from 145% to 30%, in exchange for a similar cut by Beijing, from 125% to 10% of US products.
However, the reduction was only temporary, valid for a period of 90 days, and on Wednesday US President Donald Trump accused China not to respect the terms of a permanent agreement being negotiated.
The price index in the producer in China, which measures prices in industry, registered a homologous descent of 3.3% in May, a sharper drop than recorded in April (2.7%), NBS said.
This indicator was also slightly below expectations by analysts, who predicted a less significant drop to 3.2% in the annual comparison.
Although industry prices have been falling for more than two and a half years, the NBS justified yesterday the May decrease with the effect of “imported factors”, a veiled reference to the tariff conflict with the United States.
The cabinet also pointed out for the fall in Crude's international prices and the low time of internal coal demand. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite casinos end until the end of the year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/casinos-satelite-encerram-ate-ao-fim-do-ano/</link><description>The government announced yesterday that, until December 31, will end the 11 satellite casinos that currently operate in Macao. In addition, three of Melco's six Mocha clubs will also end. Operators' decision will affect nearly 6,000 resident workers in total, and the government requires dealers to absorb these employees.
 
SJM, Melco and Galaxy have decided that by the end of the year they will fail to explore the 11 satellite casinos that operate currently. The decision was announced yesterday by the operators and later confirmed by the government at a press conference, noting that the concessionaires that exploit these casinos should absorb their workers.
At question are 11 satellite casinos: the grandview casino, the Legend Palace casino, the fortune casino, the Landmark casino, the Casino Ponte 16, the Le Royal Arc Casino, the Casino Emperor Palace, the Kam Pek Paradise Casino and the Casa Royal Casino, which belong to SJM Resorts; Melco Resorts's Grand Dragon Casino; and Casino Waldo, from Galaxy Casino.
It should be noted that the SJM nominated the government that it intended to acquire the ownership of the Hotels of Casino Ponte 16 and Casino Le Royal Arc, operating them directly and not as a satellite casinos.
In addition, from the six Melco Mocha clubs, three will be closed -Grand Dragon, Royal and Kuong Fat -while the other three will continue to be explored by the operator by hiring a Management Society -Golden Dragon, inner and Sintra Porto.
On the basis of these game operators decisions is the review of the 2022 game law, which stipulates that, after a three-year transient period-which ends on December 31, 2025-if the dealers intend to continue to explore casinos-satellite, this exploration can only be done by hiring a management society. In this case, the concessionaire can only pay the management society the remuneration related to management, and cannot share the revenues of casinos with it, or pay commissions.
 
Decision affects almost 6,000 workers
 
At yesterday's press conference, Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, indicated that the satellite casinos currently employ 5,600 local workers and 400 non-residents. Of the 5,600 local workers in the satellite casinos, 4,800 are hired by the game concessionaires and highlighted in the satellite casinos, with the remaining 800 local workers hired by the satellite casinos themselves. Mocha clubs employ about 300 locations and 50 non-residents.
The secretary recalled that the operators pledged to absorb workers who run out of employment following the end of the satellite casinos and ensured that the government will oversee the process. In addition, Tai said that workers from the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) have already been highlighted to provide legal support to workers who need it.
"The government requires the three game dealers to relevant the situation and fully welcome their highlighted workers, ensuring their employment continuation," reads a statement released by the authorities, adding that "the owners of satellite should be adequately managing the present case and further continuing the subsequent treatment of the contractors concerned."
The government also recalled that, in addition to the workers of these spaces, there are about 320 commercial and small and medium-sized companies that operate with the satellite casinos and that can be affected by closing, but the secretary for the economy and finance said that business projects are being prepared in these zones. These establishments currently employ 320 workers.
Chan Un Tong, director of Dsal, said authorities will closely monitor the transition from workers, also referring that, in the future, three employment pair -up sessions will be held per week with the six game operators.
 
Negative impact on game recipes
 
André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice, assured that the closure of the satellite casinos will not harm game recipes. In fact, it will have a “positive impact on the exploration of game activities”, he stressed.
It is recalled that the executive board recently presented a proposal for a change to the budget to 2025 that reviews the game revenue forecast for this year. The government now foresees that casinos gross revenues are in the 228 billion Patacas, instead of the 240 billion that were registered in the budget presented in December last year. Between January and May, the casinos invoiced 97.7 billion of patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:54:16</pubDate></item><item><title>“Societies where criticism can be expressed are happier and more successful,” argues EU ambassador to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/sociedades-onde-se-pode-expressar-criticas-sao-mais-felizes-e-mais-bem-sucedidas-defende-embaixador-da-ue-em-macau/</link><description>In an interview with Macao Business, Harvey Rouse, head of the European Union's office in Hong Kong and Macau since September last year, he argues that European influence has been a valuable piece for the multiple goals that Macao proposes from diversification of the economy to decarbonization work. Asked about the annual report that the EU issues annually on the political and economic situation of the territory, the ambassador guarantees: "Whenever we consider it necessary, we will continue to pronounce respectively and constructive."
Harvey Rouse, head of the European Union Office (EU) in Hong Kong and Macao, defended the importance of preserving the uniqueness of special administrative regions, enshrined in the principle of 'a country two systems', and acknowledged that the organization will continue to “express criticism in a respectful and constructive way” whenever it considers pertinent. In an interview with Macau Business magazine-the first since taking office previously held by Thomas Gnocchi in September-Rouse also emphasizes that cooperation with Brussels is a key element for the economic diversification of the territory and the declining objectives fixed by 2050.
The last report prepared by the EU about Macao in 2024 warned of the “continuous increase in the focus on national security” that could “weaken fundamental rights”. Regarding this topic, the official recalled that the economic bloc has been closely monitored Macau's political and economic development since the transfer of sovereignty, ”in 1999, admitting“ growing challenges ”in recent years. Still, “as regards political rights and fundamental freedoms, it is not for me to say what will be included in the next report” of 2025, he stressed.
"Whenever we consider it necessary, we will continue to pronounce respectively and constructive. We are sure that open societies, where criticism can be expressed, are happier, more attractive and more successful," he said, noting that even "good friends" have divergence points. "Among friends, it is important that there is more communication, no less. It is important to talk to each other constructively and with mutual respect."
It is recalled that in June last year, the Government of MSAR reacted with “deep displeasure” and “firm opposition” to the EU report, while mourning the absence of “positive and useful elements” over the region. "Macao affairs are China's internal affairs, so the European Union has no right to interfere," the government wrote in a statement warning that criticism of territory management or alleged erosion of freedoms could impair bilateral relations.
European companies “contribute a lot to the economy of Macau”
Throughout the interview, Harvey Rouse has highlighted multiple times that his role as an ambassador to Hong Kong and Macau is promoting the “diversification, openness and uniqueness” of the regions under the motto 'One country, two systems'. This intention is not to be made to the political level, extending to the economic one: "It is in the interest of Macao to seek new perspectives, but also to maintain its uniqueness and promote an open and diverse society."
The economic diversification of the region and the transition to a decarbonized economy are the two main objectives that the EU official identifies in Macao, following various events where he had the opportunity to dialogue with government elements such as Ho Iat Seng, former Chief Executive, Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, or André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice. Although he finds "a clear recognition of the importance of the relationship between the EU and Macao" by the Government of Mashes, Harvey Rouse emphasizes that the intensification of European influence would play "a vital role in supporting the diversification of Macao and its transition to a decarbonized economy."
"[European] companies are already very active in a wide range of sectors, contributing to game -related industries, such as bank, financial services and food and beverage products," he said. According to the diplomat, the development of Macao also involves importing foreign talents and highly qualified labor, with beneficial effects for both local companies and the foreign business community. It is also the intention of the EU to reinforce the offer of academic exchanges with European higher education institutes - namely, through the Erasmus Mundus program - further projecting the image of Macao on an international level.
“For my part, I believe that European companies are already contributing a lot to the economy of Macao,” he assumed. "We are already a very strong commercial partner, but we are also present in many sectors of the local economy." The future plans of the European economic bloc will be discussed “soon” at a meeting alone with the current Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, who is expected to visit the Iberian Peninsula in the coming months. On this trip, without confirmed dates, Harvey Rouse is peremptory: "If there is a visit to Brussels, it will also be a very welcome visit."</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:49:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Tourism Promotion in Bangcoque attracted more than 175 thousand people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/promocao-turistica-de-macau-em-banguecoque-atraiu-mais-de-175-mil-pessoas/</link><description>The Macao tourism dissemination action that took place in Bangcoque last weekend attracted more than 175,000 people, indicated the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD). During the three days of promotion, more than a thousand packages of hotel and plane tickets were sold.
 
The Board of Tourism Services (STD) organized, between June 6 and 8, a large -scale Macao promotion action in Bangcoque, the capital of Thailand. The initiative attracted more than 175 thousand visitors in total, the authorities indicated in a balance sheet released yesterday.
Authorities indicated that Thai online and face -to -face travel agencies, alongside airlines and the six major Macao's Integrated Tourism and Leisure Companies, participated together on the promotion, promoting Macao tourist products on site, encouraging participants to buy on site, expanding sources of international visitors, “in another step to stimulate the Macao tourism economy”.
During the three days of the promotion, a total of 1,006 hotel packages and airplane tickets were sold online and in person, in a global value of about 1.6 million patacas.
Alongside the main event at Siam Paragon, several shows were also held on stage and interactive sessions, with local stars and digital influencers as guests, with a view to increasing the effectiveness of the promotion. The Macao Tourism Mascot, “Mak Mak”, and the Thai character “Warbie Yama” were also present. Several creative projects were launched for promoting the promotion.
Through cooperation with a Thailand electronic payment platform, immediate consumption discounts were also released during a visit to Macau to promote the development of tourism and the economy of Macao.
On the other hand, STD has placed 128 electronic screen in the Bangkok Center commercial and Metro stations, among other multimedia channels, to show the main visual and animation advertisements of the promotion, and generate greater animation around the event, which were broadcast over 19.8 million times.
This Bangkok campaign followed the similar initiatives in Tokyo and Seoul. The goal is to try to attract Macau visitors from abroad. Subsequently, STD will continue to organize large -scale promotions in Southeast Asia, to promote Macao's “Tourism+” elements, added the authorities, adding that the body will continue to participate in the main regional and international tourism fairs, “to raise Macao's name, maintaining macao exhibition as a tourist destination and seeking to expand the visitors market”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:52:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese exports go up less than expected under the influence of trade war</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/exportacoes-chinesas-sobem-menos-do-que-esperado-sob-efeito-da-guerra-comercial/</link><description>China exports have increased less than expected in May, repercussion to decrease the volume of goods sent to the US in the middle of trade war. According to Chinese customs, exports increased 4.8% in homologous terms last month
 
China's exports increased less than expected in May, according to official statistics revealed yesterday, reverberating the volume of goods sent to the US in the middle of trade war.
According to Chinese customs, exports increased 4.8% in homologous terms last month. The amount was below the predictions of the economists inquired by the Bloomberg Financial News Agency, who expected growth of 6%.
After Geneva in May, Americans and Chinese yesterday began a new round of conversations in London, with the aim of prolonging the commercial truce and reaching a lasting agreement on reducing the custom customs supervised.
Chinese exports to the United States totaled $ 28.8 billion in May, compared to $ 33 billion in April, a registration equivalent to a drop of 12.7%. On the other hand, Chinese exports to Vietname increased slightly in May, reaching $ 17.3 billion.
“The trade war between China and the United States has led to a sharp drop in exports to the US, but this was offset by an increase in exports to other countries,” writes Zhang Zhiwei, an economist at Pinpoint Asset Management, in a note.
"Commercial perspectives remain very uncertain at this stage" and problems may arise "as the anticipation effect fades," Zhang noted, referring to foreign buyers who had increased Chinese products in anticipation of possible increases in the United States.
In the other trade scale dish, Chinese imports fell 3.4% in May, reflecting the weak demand and growing commercial pressures on the world's second largest economy.
The Sino-American conversations in London have marked the second formal negotiations between the two countries, since US President Donald Trump launched a global commercial offensive in April.
On the American side, the delegation will include Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, Trade Secretary Howard Lutnick, and White House commercial representative Jamieson Greer. As in Geneva, Chinese vice-master-master, he Lifeng, leads the Beijing delegation.
These discussions follow a telephone exchange on Thursday between Donald Trump and Chinese counterpart Xi Jinping, which the president of the United States described as "very positive." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Sébastien Ogier dominates in the sardine</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/sebastien-ogier-domina-na-sardenha/</link><description>Toyota added sixth consecutive victory. Only Ott Tänak (Hyundai) struggled to the French driver who shortened the disadvantage at the World Cup to teammate Elfyn Evans. Hardness of the route left a lot of people along the way.
 
Six events, six wins for Toyota at the World Cup. The overwhelming mastery of the Japanese builder in the WRC main category extended to the Sardinian's riot, with the triumph, on the last weekend, of Sébastien Ogier and Vincent Landais. It was the second consecutive victory of the French duo at the World Cup (the third of the season and the fifth in Sardinia), although Ogier continues to say that he will not change the outlined plans at the beginning of the season, that is, he will remain in 'part-time' in the championship.
"It was an intense battle to the end with OTT. For now I just want to enjoy this victory. I will be in Greece, but after that there will be a break," Ogier warned.
The French pilot dominated practically from beginning to end, but always with Ott Tänak's Hyundai around. Estonium was the only one to fight the octa world champion. The two ended the rally separated by just 7.9 seconds. Toyota director Jari-Matti Latvala still took his hands to his head when he saw heavenly heavenly on a tree during the ultimate rally, the Wolf Power Stage, but it was just a scare. Gr Yaris Rally1 was not damaged and Ogier took advantage of his seconds for his friend Tänak.
Ogier now adds 114 points. It occupies the second position of the World Cup just behind Elfyn Evans (133). The Welsh fulfilled the difficult task of cleaning the road and finished the rally in fourth place, behind teammate Kalle Rovanperä (113). Despite finishing in the last place on the podium, the young Finnish even scored more points than Tänak, as it was the fastest on 'Super Sunday' and 'Wolf Power Stage', the special rally that ensures points for the fastest five. Toyota put four cars in the top five, with Japanese Takamoto Katsuta in fifth. The advantage has increased at the World Cup. Add now 312 points against the 243 of Hyundai.
 
Hyundai and Ford in trouble
 
Hyundai went to the sardine gravil under pressure. The South Korean builder has not yet won any race in 2025 and will have to wait for the Greece event for a new attempt. World Champion duo Thierry Neuville and Martijn Wydaeghe showed a very strong progress on Friday but went to the way after a very narrow and classificative error that made several victims. The damage caused by the impact on the left rear axis of the Hyundai i20 n rally1 were so visible that the Belgian duo abandoned the day right there, having returned on Saturday under the regulations, but already with an irrecoverable delay. Neuville still 'saved' five points during 'Super Sunday'. It is at this time fifth at the 83 -point World Cup, just behind Tänak, who has 108. It's still early, but it is true that it will have a hard time holding back the title achieved last year.
Unlucky also for Adrien Fourmaux and Alex Coria. Hyundai's French duo continues to disappoint after a promising championship start with a podium in Monte Carlo. Between holes and road exits, it was another weekend to forget, especially when Hyundai showed in the first classifications that had a progress to fight the Toyota. The South Korean manufacturer had only missed Sardinia victory for two occasions since 2016.
The M-Sport Fords all over the same special (Telti-Calangianus-Berchidda) that left Neuville along the way. Gégoire Munster's Puma Rally1, Joshua Mcerlean and Martins Sesks did not survive the road exits. In the case of Latto Sesks and Co-Pilot Renars Francis the accident was so violent that it was not even possible for the team to recover the car to the rest of the rally. It survived only Jourdan Serderidis, although the Greek billionaire walks more at a rhythm of a walk than properly fighting for the top places in the table of times. Munster and Mcerlean still returned, but only in a kind of test session for the Greece rally, scheduled for the end of the month.
Daprà wins in WRC2
Roberto daPrà benefited from the misfortune of others to win in the WRC2 category. The Italian driver, behind the wheel of a Skoda Fabia RS Rally2, survived the chaos of the last day that left several leaders along the way, cases of Emil Lindholm and Lauri Joona. Kajetan Kajetanowicz (Toyota) and Martin Prokop (Skoda) completed the podium. Oliver Solberg (second in the category) and Nikolay Gryazin even finished ahead, sixth and eighth in the overall standings, but were not submitted to add points in WRC2, in what was a test for Greece.
The acropolis rally goes to the road between June 26 and 29.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:17</pubDate></item><item><title>CCAC follows 17 cases related to legislative elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/ccac-acompanha-17-casos-relacionados-as-eleicoes-legislativas/</link><description>The commissioner against corruption has so far received more than 50 complaints and complaints related to legislative elections, of which 17 are being accompanied after the instruction of proceedings. To Ieong Seong, a corruption commissioner, has not revealed further details about the complaints that they are under investigation. It was said, however, that more than a thousand inspections have been carried out to associations and their activities, and no electoral irregularities were detected.
The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) is following 17 cases of eventual corruption related to the next elections for the Legislative Assembly scheduled for September 14. To Ieong Seong, a corruption commissioner, revealed that the body received, up to 50 complaints and complaints about the elections, but not all had proceedings open for investigation.
"There have been more than 50 complaints to date [to CCAC], and 17 of them have gathered conditions to instruct processes to be accompanied," he said. The official, quoted by Radio Macau in Chinese language, said that most cases are still being investigated, so "it is not appropriate to disclose the details of the cases now."
To Ieong Seong reiterated that, in addition to the direct line, CCAC receives complaints about the elections through a system for the submission of complaints, and some are also sent by the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) or other authorities.
On the sidelines of an event about the elections held on Sunday, Ieong Seong also reacted to a case that was previously reported in a program of the Chinese Radio Macao channel, noting that a family member of a CCAC volunteer team “will have received benefits to sign a proposition bulletin” from a list.
Ieong Seong stressed that the situation was debated in the volunteer communication group and CCAC has already dealt with the case. According to the Commissioner, CCAC's monitoring and investigation show that the fact in which a social services association "distributed assistance money and" red envelopes "to the elderly during the Lunar New Year.
However, the CCAC preliminarily excluded the possibility of bribery in the election of this case since it considers that “there is a period of time between the Lunar New Year and the construction of the application committee,” he explained. It is recalled that, according to this year's calendar, the Lunar New Year's period took place in the second half of January and the election candidacy began in early March.
To Ieong Seong, however, recalled local organizations that should be aware of any possibility of electoral corruption when they launched associative events or social assistance activities, stressing that activities should never be linked to elections. "CCAC has a well -established protection mechanism for complaints, encouraging residents to communicate to the body any suspected electoral corruption cases," he said.
At the time, the spokesman added that CCAC, since the beginning of the legislative election candidates period, has already made more than 1,000 inspections to local associations and restoration activities, and no electoral irregularities have been detected. "CCAC does the best not to affect the course of activities while performing the inspections, so some of the inspections will be communicated in advance," he said.
In terms of inspection work and possible irregularities on hengqin legislative elections, Ieong Seong has ensured that “Macau is not extralegal territory” and CCAC has a systematic investigation and a coordination mechanism with different law enforcement bodies to follow up on cases, even if electoral offenses are committed outside the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:53:13</pubDate></item><item><title>A trip for the colors of Goa in Miguel Quental's photograph</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/uma-viagem-pelas-cores-de-goa-na-fotografia-de-miguel-quental/</link><description>"What really caught my attention was the colors, that beauty." It was from a spontaneous walk through the alleys of Goa that Miguel Quental began a photographic trip that expresses the vibrant cultural heritage of the ancient imperial city. The exhibition “Colors of Goa”, which will be inaugurated this Saturday at Creative Macau, reveals the richness of colors, history and faith that characterize this territory in southwest India.
 
Creative Macao is preparing to receive, next Saturday, June 14, the photographic exhibition entitled “Colors of Goa”, an artistic show of lawyer Miguel Quental who will be evident in the gallery on the ground floor of the Cultural Center until July 5. A selection of images captured during a visit to Goa, the ancient city that left a multicultural legacy of an "extraordinary" wealth, marked by colors, aromas, flavors and beliefs that seem to "transcend the imagination." “I left a little to discover UNESCO's heritage. But what really caught my attention was the colors. That beauty…” recalls Quental.
In the artist's words, his discovery was spontaneous, made as he walked through ordinary routes, without much planning, but which revealed an impressive beauty. "I have not been looking for very remote sites. Within all that heritage, the colors are extraordinary, as well as the conservation of buildings."
Quental's attention was immediately captured by the vivid colors of ancient churches, Catholic symbols and manorial houses, which seem to remain majestic and impassive. "It was then that I began to photograph mainly the colors, but also those religious objects that really reflect the faith of the people. It is extraordinary. The conservation of the churches, the way everything is well maintained, aroused interest to me," he said to the end.
For the photographer, this experience was not just a simple trip, but an opportunity to share a cultural heritage that believes deserves the attention of the public of Macao. “I liked these images to be an invitation for people to visit Goa. It deserves it, for their cultural diversity, flavors, smells. It's a little like Macau, for those who arrive here, is dazzled by our colors as well. And deep down, being able to share with others what I saw in my experience, though short, is what motivates me the most,” he shares.
Goa's connection to Macao, both with “remnants” from a past linked to Portugal, reinforces this sense of similarity between the heritage, although Quental points out that Goa is different enough to justify the trip. "People are very friendly and we really are very well received. In the end, it is a pride on the part of the population of Goa to receive the Portuguese and show what is history and the past," he said.
 
Passion for photography
 
His passion for photography has been following him for some time, having started since he arrived in Macau. “I always enjoyed doing photography,” he reveals. Recently, his interest has evolved into a more conscious practice, seeking to capture the best moment. "Last year I traveled to Angola and Mozambique, an experience I also wanted to share through my lens." On his visit to Goa, he used various types of chambers, including mobile phones, with the aim of capturing the essence of the moment spontaneously. “I use my mobile phone much more than Sony. Sometimes with the mobile phone it's easier to zoom, capture details,” he explains.
Despite considering himself an amateur, Miguel Quental manifests his passion for photography and the desire to continue to work in this form of expression. “I am interested in possibly joining a group or photographic association, another incentive to improve,” he says, thanking his support from his images, such as Francisco Ricarte, who helped him in post-production. "Shooting, but then, when it is with the mobile phone, it does not have great quality. So I seek to share knowledge with other photographers that help in the editions," he adds.
The exhibition “Colors de Goa” comes as well as an opportunity to explore an inheritance that mixes history, art and faith, through the look of an artist who, besides being a lawyer, is also a passionate of images that encourage the senses. Quental expects your photographs to invite the audience to discover a different culture, which brings other expressions, both in colors and food. “I hope people enjoy and that this will be invited. The diversity of cultures, flavors, smells… All of this makes the experience complete, like a trip of meanings,” he reinforces.
The inauguration event takes place this Saturday, at 18:30, at Creative Macau. During the exhibition period, until July 5, visitors will have the opportunity to know this visual trip that reveals the beauty and history of Goa, an ancient imperial city that, despite the time, keeps its cultural essence intact.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tokyo reveals that Chinese aircraft carrier entered waters from the Japan economic zone</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/toquio-revela-que-porta-avioes-chines-entrou-em-aguas-da-zona-economica-do-japao/</link><description>The Japan's Ministry of Defense revealed that a Chinese and remaining fleet aircraft carrier entered waters from the Japanese exclusive economic zone last Saturday at a time of tensions in the relationship between the two countries.
 
According to the Japanese Defense Ministry, the aircraft carrier Liaoning, two guided missile resetters and a fast refueling ship sailed about 300 kilometers from the easterniest point of Japan, Minamitori Island on Saturday.
According to a statement, after Liaoning and the accompanying ships had left the Japanese ZEE, they performed on Sunday to take off and landing exercises of fighters and helicopters. The Japanese Ministry of Defense said it highlighted a ship to the area to follow the situation.
This was the first time a Chinese aircraft carrier has entered this part of Japan's EEE in the Pacific Ocean, a ministry spokesman told France-Presse news agency. "We believe that Chinese military is trying to improve their operational capabilities and their ability to conduct operations in remote areas," he added.
China's growing military presence and the use of naval and air means to claim disputed territories are worrying the United States and its allies in the Asia-Pacific region.
Government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi said yesterday at a press conference that the Japanese government "conveyed an appropriate message to the Chinese part," without specifying whether he had presented a formal protest.
In May, the Liaoning navigated between two Japanese islands to the south, inside the EEE, and performed maneuvers.
In September, the same aircraft carrier also sailed between two Japanese islands near Taiwan and entered the territorial waters of Japan, the area located up to 24 nautical miles (about 45 kilometers) from its coast. At the time, Tokyo classified the maneuvers as "unacceptable" and expressed "serious concerns."
According to international law, a coastal state exercises rights over economic resources and activities within its EEE, which extends up to 200 nautical miles (370 kilometers) from its back.
Bilateral relations, already tense due to historical and territorial disputes, recently deteriorated, especially after, in December, Japan required the removal of a new Chinese float on its EEE, south of Yonaguni Island, near Taiwan.
On May 29, Japan said China had removed the float.
In February, Beijing also removed another float he had installed in July 2023 in Japanese EEE, near disputed areas, namely the Senkaku Islands in the East China Sea, controlled by Japan but claimed by China under the name of Diaoyu.
Also in late May, Tokyo accused Beijing of conducting unauthorized maritime scientific investigation in his EEE around his southernmost point in the Pacific Ocean, Okinotori's remote. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong will maintain local currency connection to the US dollar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/hong-kong-vai-manter-ligacao-da-moeda-local-ao-dolar-norte-americano/</link><description>Hong Kong's chief executive guaranteed an excerpt from an interview released yesterday that he will keep the local currency linked to the US dollar despite the trade war between Washington and Beijing.
In an interview with Hong Kong South China Morning Post, John Lee said the indexing of the local dollar to the US currency has been "one of the fundamental factors for the region's success."
Since 1983, even before the UK administration transition to China, that the Hong Kong dollar is linked exclusively to the US currency and can float in a range between 7.75 and 7.85 units per dollar.
Something that also means that the territory's financial regulator, the monetary authority of Hong Kong (HKMA), follows the uphill and fall rates of the reference interest rate imposed by the United States federal reserve.
In May, HKMA had to intervene several times in the market, buying a total of US $ 16.7 billion to weaken local currency. This after the Hong Kong dollar has reached the top limit of the fluctuation range due to the appreciation of Asian currencies and increasing investment in actions listed in the city's stock market.
In addition to foreign investors, continental China investors have bought more local actions, in part thanks to a mechanism, launched in 2014, which connects the Hong Kong and Shanghai scholarships, Chinese 'financial capital'.
In an interview with the third anniversary of his administration, John Lee denied that the financial system depends solely on the US dollar connection.
The chief executive has promised to create more financial products to reinforce the role of Hong Kong as the world's largest center for mainstream China Business, Renminbi.
John Lee devalued HKMA's interventions and said the US dollar connection was always under pressure, especially in times of uncertainty. The indexing also affects Macao, whose currency, Pataca, is indexed to the dollar of Hong Kong.
John Lee rejected appeals to the end of the local dollar indexing to the US currency, made at a time of tariff conflict between China and the United States.
Washington imposed customs rights on 145% Chinese products, leading Beijing to respond with similar rates of 125% on US products.
In mid -May, the United States and China agreed to reduce customs rights to 30% and 10%, respectively, for 90 days, during which the two countries are trying to negotiate a permanent agreement.
In another excerpt from the same interview, released on Sunday, John Lee assured that the tensions between Beijing and Washington will not make the city adopt retaliation measures, which would compromise their “successful DNA” and free port zone status.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal opened investigation against 68 alleged illegal workers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/dsal-abriu-averiguacao-contra-68-alegados-trabalhadores-ilegais/</link><description>Investigating the case of alleged illegal workers in the concerts of South Korean rapper G-Dragon, in the Galaxy Arena, Continue. Authorities revealed that a process of investigation against 68 of non -residents was opened, who are now subject to verification of work authorization in Macao.
The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and the Public Security Police (CPSP) issued yesterday, at midnight, a statement updating the situation of the case. They indicated, in the joint operation on Saturday, the Merchandise Sale of Concerts, to the Identity Inspection of 107 workers, of which 68 need more detailed investigation. The authorities are reiterated that they are treating the case seriously and there will be no tolerance if irregularities and violation of the law are confirmed.
The Executive also clarified that any non -resident who performs work or activities in Macau is obliged by law to previously obtain the respective work authorization.
The clarification follows a comment on the social networks of a person who presented himself as one of the investigated workers, who claimed that nothing has happened to him as a result of investigation, since all employees "are fans of the singer and volunteers of concerts, not receiving any compensation."
In this sense, Dsal stressed that volunteering is only applicable to non -profit public social assistance activities and that participants cannot receive any compensation. “Any attempt to circumvent the work authorization system on behalf of 'volunteers' constitutes a violation of the law,” argues Dsal. According to the body, in this case, the employer can commit the crime of irregular employment, which is punishable by a prison penalty up to two years, while non -residents who get involved in illegal work can commit an administrative offense, punishable with a fine up to 10,000 patacas.
It is recalled that, in addition to the investigation to alleged illegal workers, CPSP also led to the squadron on Saturday two responsible for the event. The organizing entity of the shows of singer G-Dragon, TME Live, Tencent Music, has not yet reacted to the incident.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:49:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazil prepares unprecedented emission of public debt in Yuan in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/brasil-prepara-emissao-inedita-de-divida-publica-em-yuan-na-china/</link><description>Brazil aims to issue sovereign debt titles in the Chinese market later this year, in an unprecedented operation, when President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva reinforces commercial and investment ties with China.
Brasilia plans to issue titles called Chinese currency, Yuan, in the mainland China capital market, and also wants to return to the market of obligations called euros, yesterday revealed the deputy secretary of the Ministry of Finance, Dario Durigan, quoted by the British newspaper Financial Times.
"The idea is that this year, we will make a new sustainable emission in dollars, such as last year, as well as emissions in Europe and 'Panda obligations' in China," Durigan said in an interview with FT. "The European Union wants to negotiate with Brazil the expansion of bilateral trade, both in terms of transactions and also enabling Brazil the option of issuing debt in Europe," he added. "The same can happen to China," he said.
The Brazilian government has been reinforcing commercial ties with Brussels and consolidating Beijing relations in a context of the trade war launched by US President Donald Trump.
The South American Block Mercosur, of which Brazil is part, expects the long-awaited trade agreement with the European Union to be approved by the end of the year.
On Thursday, Lula met with French President Emmanuel Macron in Paris and appealed to Paris's support to the deal. Macron has resisted the ratification of the treaty, the target of strong opposition by French farmers.
Plans to issue sovereign debt titles in China come at a time when the Brazilian government seeks to attract more investment in the Asian country, which is by far the largest commercial partner in Brazil.
China is also trying to reinforce its economic influence on Latin America.
Operation will also test the appetite of international investors for Brazilian debt, in a context of growing skepticism in the face of Lula's economic policy, which has been betting on a larger state role in the economy to boost growth and reduce inequality.
The strategy of increasing expense has generated criticism between entrepreneurs who accuse the government to aggravate inflation, raise interest rates and endanger the sustainability of public debt.
This week, Brazil placed $ 1.5 billion in obligations to five years with a interest rate of 5.68% and $ 1.25 billion in debt to ten years to 6.73% in the second offshore debt issuance in 2025.
Funding costs in Brazil increased after the Central Bank raised the director rate to 14.75%in an attempt to contain inflation. Critics accuse Brasilia's executive not to act firmly to resolve the chronic budget deficit and debt growth.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Investigated for any administrative irregularity in the suspension of subsidy to daycare</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/ias-investigado-por-eventual-irregularidade-administrativa-na-suspensao-de-subsidio-a-creche/</link><description>The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) received a complaint made by the Smart Nursry day care center against the Institute of Social Action (IAS), being investigating any administrative irregularity practiced by this body in a decision to suspend the attribution of financial support to the day care center. According to the Ieong Seong, a commissioner against corruption, the investigation is being carried out under the Justice Ombudsman.
The controversy between Smart Nursry and IAS began in March this year, when IAS announced that it would leave, from August 26, to provide financial support to the day care and that it would recover their subsidized facilities, as well as the equipment in their space.
The case is now in legal process. As had been advanced by this newspaper, Smart Nursry criticized the lack of legality of IAS action and filed a defense to the decision. Christiana Ieong, director of the daycare center, pointed out that IAS never explained the subsidy cut and “informed, not to mention the institution, the parents of the children that the day care was to close”, thus caused the concern of the guardians.
The Court suspended IAS's decision in April and the president of IAS filed an appeal, and the court of second instance dismissed the appeal.
The Zonta Club de Macao, Smart Nursery's management entity, issued a statement on Sunday to greet the court's decision and urges IAS president to comply with the judicial body's decision. "We hope that IAS will fulfill their fundamental duties and support the normal functioning of day care centers, and do not continue to waste public money with these unnecessary processes and deprive children of their learning opportunities and parents of their right to choose," he said.
On the other hand, as to the sudden resignation of Su Kun, deputy chief of the executive committee of the Secretary's and Finance's in -depth cooperation and officers' cooperation and advisor, CCAC refused to reveal if there was any investigation into the matter.
Su Kun resigned in May "for personal reasons," according to the government, after the renewal of appointments of these positions in late March and early April, respectively. There were speculation that his resignation would be related to a criminal case in Hengqin, but CCAC did not comment on the situation.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:49:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Londoner hosts event on technological transformation in Macau and Hengqin</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/10/londoner-recebe-evento-sobre-transformacao-tecnologica-em-macau-e-hengqin/</link><description>The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), the Fund for the Development of Sciences and Technology (FDCT) and Sands China held at the end of May at the Greenwich Macau Hall, a meeting on commercial correspondence between Macau and Hengqin in the sectors of innovation and technology.
In a joint statement issued yesterday, DSEDT and FDCT explain that the event aimed, “through correspondence activities between industry, gym and research, to support Macao and Hengqin companies in their bet on I&amp;D [Research and Technological Development], the transformation of scientific research results from higher education institutions and the collaboration between industry and research, further promoting integrated and deepened development of the industry in industry Macao and Hengqin ”.
The event was attended by representatives of technological companies in Macau and Hengqin and higher education institutions who, through the resources provided by Sands China, hope to transform the scientific and technological results of their research into innovative solutions for intelligent tourism. Also present were the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, and the executive director and administrator of Sands China, Cheang Kuan Nok.
Speaking at the time, Tai Kin IP argued that the development of an exchange platform between the tourism and technology industries is “a central priority” of the Government of MSAR, by injecting “new dynamism to sustainable development” of the territory. In turn, Cheang Kuan Nok has qualified technological innovation as “the central engine of the high quality development of society” and has been committed, as Sands China's executive director, implementing Macao's “1+4” economic diversification strategy and creating more opportunities for small and medium-sized entrepreneurs.
After the speeches, Sands China organized a questions and answers session between the technological companies of Macau and Hengqin and the representatives of higher education institutions, who could present proposals and exchange ideas. According to the statement, both parties "will maintain close communication and accompany the progress of projects" during the six months after launch, "with the aim of establishing a sustainable and effective communication platform."</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 02:55:15</pubDate></item></channel></rss>