<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/reserva-financeira-atingiu-valor-mais-elevado-desde-final-de-2021/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Hong Kong receives first Harvard students prevented from staying in the USA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/hong-kong-recebe-primeiros-estudantes-de-harvard-impedidos-de-permanecer-nos-eua/</link><description>Harvard graduate students accepted scholarships to continue research at the University of Science and Technology of Hong Kong, after being affected by the ban on foreign entry into US institutions, the institution confirmed yesterday.
 
A spokeswoman for the University of Science and Technology of Hong Kong (HKUST) told the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper that the five students from Pakistan, Georgia and Barra China received financial support to develop projects in science, technology and humanities.
Internationally recognized for academic excellence and strategic position as a bridge between China and the World, HKUST has received about 200 demonstrations of interest from foreign students since the announcement of new restrictions in the United States, consolidating itself as a possible academic refuge in the limitations imposed by Washington.
In May, the US internal security department ordered the departure or transfer of international students from Harvard, alleging bonds to structures associated with the Chinese Communist Party. The measure, driven by the administration of Donald Trump, intensified tensions with the University of Massachusetts. However, a federal court suspended its application on Monday.
Hong Kong universities speeded up the registration processes to welcome affected students, issuing unconditional acceptance letters and creating support teams to deal with the transition, including accommodation and visas, to facilitate integration into the local system.
HKUST registered a record number of 20,000 international applications for the 2025-2026 school year compared to 15,000 of the previous year. Candidates come from 85 countries, including Germany, France, Kazakhstan, Mongolia and Vietnam, vying about 800 vacancies available.
The increase in applications reflects Hong Kong's growing appeal as an academic pole, in a context marked by geopolitical friction. Hong Kong's secretary of education, Christine Choi, said her office encouraged local higher education institutions to facilitate the integration of affected students.
In October 2023, the Government of the Special Administrative Region doubled the limit of international admissions in public establishments to 40%, as part of a strategy to position Hong Kong as a global formation center.
The Secretariat of Education has ensured that it will continue to follow the needs of students affected by international migratory policies, while HKUST stressed that it was the first institution in the region to formalize the integration of students from Harvard.
 
USA accuse Hong Kong of repressing US Independence Day celebrations
 
The United States condemned “the repression” by the Hong Kong authorities of US Independence Day celebrations, after reports that teachers and students were discouraged to participate in events. Quoted by the Associated Press agency, the US consulate in Hong Kong accused the executive of interfering with the activities promoted by the diplomatic mission, stressing that US embassies and consulates around the world annually celebrate July 4 with receptions and other festivities. "We condemned the repression exercised by the Hong Kong executive to US Independence Day celebrations," the consulate. "Attempts to classify these activities as 'illegal' reveal only their insecurity and fear of freedom," he added.
The critic comes days after the “Edu Lancet” page on the Facebook social network, reported that the city's Office of Education sent “friendly reminders” to several schools, advising teachers not to participate lightly at the consulate's events and to be aware of possible violations of the National Security Law. The same message also suggested that schools determined students to participate in the celebrations.
AP could not independently verify the reports of the page, which usually disclose updates about the teaching sector. The local newspaper South China Morning Post also reported that authorities have recalled schools the need for surveillance in the face of any attempts to promote US Independence Day within schools.
In response to issues posed by the local press, the Hong Kong Education Office said it had issued administrative and pedagogical guidelines to schools, requiring them to adopt their own measures to safeguard national security, without confirming the exact content of the notices. "Schools have the responsibility of being good guardians and reinforcing the sensitivity of teachers and students in relation to national security," said the office. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:55:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Air Macao with a loss of 677 million Patacas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/air-macau-com-prejuizo-de-677-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>Last year Air Macau registered operating revenues of 3.5 billion patacas, slightly above the previous year, but saw the damage continued to get worse, with losses that rose from 236 million to 677 million patacas. The airline has been on a negative result since 2020, justifying that the loss in 2024 was due to the “intensification of competition in the market” in the postpandeia period.
 
Last year was the fifth consecutive year in which Air Macao suffered damage to its annual exercise, with a negative net result of 677 million patacas, substantially above the loss of 236 million patacas registered the previous year, treating an increase in losses of 186% in annual terms.
The result of the operations of the Air Transport Company Air Macau was yesterday in advance in its annual report of the Board of Directors, published in an official bulletin. The company, the main airline of Macao that has the local market monopoly since 1995, being the only one based in the city, explained in the report that the aggravation of losses was related to the impact of “multiple factors in the postpandy period”, namely the “intensification of competition in the market”.
Air Macao returned last year to have no distributable profits to shareholders, a situation verified since 2020.
In the document it is also highlighted that the company registered operating revenues of 3.53 billion patacas in 2024, a light growth (+12%) compared to the previous year of 3.13 billion patacas.
It is recalled that the government revealed in December last year to plan another public capital injection at Air Macao with a budget expense of 340 million patacas, which is intended to strengthen the capital of this company. The government said Air Macau has “has faced a difficult exploration situation that led to relevant losses” due to the accumulation of “several unfavorable factors”, as well as being in a situation of “absence of capital mobility” and feeling “reimbursement pressure” and payment of their interest.
 
More flights, more passengers
 
Regarding the operating situation, "the company maintained its excellent air safety history" last year, said Air Macau, "totaling 65,147 hours of safe flight during the year, with a stable security scenario." It is recalled that, the previous year, the flight operation hours corresponded to 52.045.
According to the company, 24,170 flights were operated and 3.21 million passengers transported over 2024, representing a 49% and 56% homologous increase, respectively, "keeping the market share leader at Macau Airport," he said.
Air Macao also indicated that two new routes were added to Kuala Lumpur and Taichung. According to information from the Civil Aviation Authority, so far, Air Macau is operating 26 passenger flight routes that connect Macau to the cities of the interior of China, Taiwan, Japan, Singapore, Vietname, Thailand, South Korea, Malaysia, Philippines, Cambodia, Palau and Indonesia.
The company last year marked its 30th anniversary. “With a continuous commitment to high quality and innovation services,” according to Air Macau, the company was distinguished with six brand awards by its services in 2024. According to the report, the company continued to hold the local cadet drivers training program and has recruited 8 groups, with about 50 trainees since its inception in 2016, which “constitutes a solid and stable team of qualified professionals for the Civil Aviation industry. Macao ”, he stressed.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:53:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping will miss the Brics Summit in Brazil for the first time</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/xi-jinping-vai-faltar-a-cimeira-dos-brics-no-brasil-pela-primeira-vez/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping will be missing the next summit of leaders of the Brics Emerging Block in Rio de Janeiro, for the first time since it reached power, yesterday indicated Brazilian official source.
Cited by Bloomberg agency, the source - which did not want to be identified because the information is not yet public - said China has officially reported the decision to Brazil. The Asian country will be represented by the Prime Minister, I read Qiang. Li previously replaced Xi Jinping at the G20 summit in India in 2023.
The Hong Kong Journal South China Morning Post indicated that the reason for the absence is attached to an agenda conflict. Chinese sources cited by the newspaper also mentioned that the fact that XI and Brazilian president, Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, had frequent meetings last year also weighed in the decision.
The two leaders gathered during the G20 summit in Brazil last November, before a state visit to Brasilia. A few months later, Lula moved to Beijing to a meeting with Latin American countries and Caribbean. Xi rarely visits the same country two consecutive years, except Russia.
The absence of XI could weaken Beijing's efforts to reinforce China's global influence through the BRICS group and build an alternative to the United States's international order. The summit could also provide to the Chinese leader a first meeting with Iran's guardians since the beginning of the war with Israel, after temering the block in 2024.
Under the Chinese leadership, the Brics group doubled in size last year, joining nine members with the entry of the United Arab Emirates, Iran Egypt and Ethiopia, who joined Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa. Lula is considered one of Xi's closest partners, along with Russian President Vladimir Putin.
Open is the possibility of Xi Jinping to participate in the United Nations Climate Conference, which will be held in Brazil later this year, although Beijing has not yet confirmed the trip.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:55:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Transmac and TCM profited more than 86 million in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/transmac-e-tcm-lucraram-mais-de-86-milhoes-em-2024/</link><description>Transmac and the Macao Collective Transport Society (TCM) recorded a total of over 86 million patacas last year, a significant increase of 64% over the previous year. The companies revealed in the annual reports that they transported, over 2024, a total of 227 million passengers.
 
The two public bus companies in Macao ended the year 2024 with a total profit of 86.87 million patacas, according to the annual reports of Transmac and the Macao Collective Transport Society (TCM), published yesterday in an official bulletin. Last year's operating results show a very positive growth of 64%compared to the previous year, when they totaled 52.82 million patacas.
Transmac - Macao Urban Transports announced that it has registered net profit after taxes of more than 40.7 million patacas, a slight increase of 5% in annual terms. According to the Board of Directors report, the company said it was able to maintain profit “through efficiency management and cost control”, although operating costs were high and fuel prices in the first three quarters of the year have remained above 2023.
Indicating that the total volume of bus passengers in Macao saw an annual growth of more than 6% last year, Transmac revealed that it has transported more than 108 million passengers during the year 2024, with a daily average of 298,000 passengers, representing an increase of almost 7% in homologous terms.
The mileage of operation of this public bus concessionaire increased by about 5% compared to 2023. "Last year, Transmac intensified the frequency of services provided during the end hours in order to improve passenger transport efficiency," he said.
In turn, (TCM) accumulated net profit of 46.17 million patacas, operating results that were far higher than 2023, 13.96 million patacas, translating an exponential increase of 230% in annual terms.
According to the company, over the last year, the total number of passengers reached 119 million, with a 6% increase over the previous year, recovering 97% of the total number of passengers in 2019. “We continue to increase operational capacity, optimize routes and fully support diversified electronic payments. Fluidity of passenger travel, ”said the company in the document.
 
Investments and plans
 
Transmac, on the other hand, said that last year acquired 80 new electric buses with autonomy, also completing the replacement of 410 public buses powered by new energies, which came into full operation.
He also installed vehicle inspection line equipment, in accordance with government specifications. The company stressed that the work aims to reinforce the efficiency in the use and maintenance of the fleet and can help reduce waiting time for inspection at the vehicle inspection center starting this year.
Transmac has assumed that it will continue in the future to improve the formation of bus drivers and team formation, as well as the digitization of systems.
Already TCM reported that it had updated the operational fleet and increased the proportion of vehicles powered by new energy to 95%, and 100% of buses are moved to new energies. "The new ecological buses have significantly improved the travel environment of passengers, contributing to accelerate the construction of green public transport in Macau," he said.  “We continue to promote safety through technology, raising security management standards,” said TCM, noting that he plans to perform more security training, emergency simulations, emotion management and vocational training to drivers.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:54:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Abolished death penalty in Vietname for eight crimes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/abolida-pena-de-morte-no-vietname-para-oito-crimes/</link><description>Vietname has reduced the number of crimes punishable by the death penalty, now ten against the previous 18 predicted. According to local authorities, people already sentenced to death under one of the eight articles in question will not be executed.
 
Vietnam has reduced the number of crimes punishable by the death penalty, now ten against the previous 18 expected, the official press said. Among the crimes that are now punishable by life imprisonment are the “activities designed to overthrow the popular government”, “spying” and passive corruption, according to a law passed by the National Assembly of the Communist country.
People already sentenced to death under one of the eight articles in question will not be executed, the official media reported.
The number of executions made in Vietname is classified as a state secret, but the Non -Government Organization (NGO) Amnesty International states that the capital penalty was applied in 2024.
In 2023, the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights also stressed that the country continued to apply the death penalty, largely in a secret manner.
Other infractions concern the manufacture and marketing of counterfeit medicines, drug transport, diversion of funds, or “sabotage of state material and techniques” and “peace sabotage, conducting aggression wars”. "The current structure of capital punishment is problematic and, in some cases, is not aligned with the socioeconomic conditions, which have evolved, and with the realities of crime prevention," said Minister of Public Security, Luong Tam Quang.
For the crimes mentioned, the courts pronounced, in fact, life imprisonment, the Minister of Justice, Nguyen Hai Ninh, continued. "The abolition of the death penalty for various crimes will also serve the work of international cooperation, especially when Vietnam promotes narrower relationships based on mutual trust," the official continued, in statements released by the state press.
Vietnam condemned to death more than 150 people last year, more than 80% for drug -related crimes. More than 1,200 people were in the corridor of death at the end of 2024, according to the annual report of Amnesty International.
Vietname is one of five countries in the Asia Pacific region who performed executions in 2024, along with China, North Korea, Afghanistan and Singapore, the NGO highlighted. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:55:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Clarity, trust and control: expert teaches the “formula” to speak well in public</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/clareza-confianca-e-controlo-especialista-ensina-a-formula-para-falar-bem-em-publico/</link><description>The art of developing effective communicative skills was the highlighted topic in another morning meetings organized by the France Macau Chamber of Commerce (FMCC). Howard Paley, an actor with more than 30 years of experience and a trainer in oratory techniques, presented yesterday morning the ingredients who, when applied together, build a convincing speech and raise the speaker's image in any situation, from a working meeting to high -risk negotiations.
 
Communication between friends seems to us fluid and natural. We do not need to think about what to say or how to express it - the words sprout spontaneously, with the tone and charisma appropriate to the context. We now change the scenario: instead of a group of friends, we are facing a fixed eye audience in us. For most people, to a lesser or greater degree, the posture changes radically. We are invaded by a wave of adrenaline and cortisol, the heart rhythm shoots, the palms sweat, the words suddenly disappear from the mouth. How to develop, then, the ability to speak in public?
This was the proposed theme for the June session of lectures and breakfasts organized monthly by the France Macau Chamber of Commerce (FMCC) at the Sofitel Hotel. For about an hour, guest speaker Howard Paley, a professional actor and trainer in oratory techniques, summarized the essential points for engaging and effective communication, particularly relevant in the business world. The first lesson was immediate: instead of staying on the stage for speakers, Paley chose to walk between the audience while talking and interacting with those present.
“The expression 'public speaking' I don't like anything - a four -year -old can talk in public,” he said, tearing up laughs - which turned out to be quite frequent - to the audience. "This is more a leadership competence, which must be perfected through practice and training." The foundations that support this competence may seem obvious, admits, although in practical terms they are often neglected. Firstly, clarity arises - a quality that is difficult to ensure, even when the interlocutors speak the same language. "How many times have we been drinking coffee with a person we know and speaks the same language and yet arise misunderstandings?"
The second notion to take into account, while also seems like a commonplace, deserves to be underlined and repeated several times: a speaker who seems safe in what he says and keeps honest and full communication will be interpreted as more convincing than someone who seems to doubt his own words. "Say What You Mean, Mean What You Say," summarizes Howard Paley, using a frequent expression in the English language.
The third base is not only in the voice, but throughout the body as an instrument of communication. "Speaking is not a brain exercise - it is an activity that involves the whole body. In my 'workshops', I do a lot of theater exercises and I try to connect the brain to the body so that my students can achieve 3D communication." This type of communication, as the name implies, goes far beyond the mere verbalization of facts: it requires an engaging speech, in which the speaker becomes an accountant and even body posture plays an essential role in what is intended to express to the public.
"When I go to a conference and the speaker speaks of 2D, it seems that my presence is unnecessary; I almost prefer to ask for a copy of the notes and read them at home with a cup of coffee. A 3D presentation changes everything. It is knowing how to tell a story from available information." Howard Paley exemplifies: "About today's conference, a 2D announcer would say we met at 9:00, we started at 9:02, we saw a slide at 9:30 ... This does not mean that three -dimensional information intends to add non -factual information - the veracity of the data remains unchanging, simply narrated more engagingly.
The lesson, summarized, is this: "If we want to be efficient and conquer people, especially in the current age of social networks where we can get instant information, we have to do more than just utter words."
 
Clarity, confidence, control - the three pillars of oratory
 
Imagine a lone speaker taking a stage. In the first 30 seconds, even before reaching the strengths of the speech, while members of the hearing outlined a mental “criticism” to the person who contemplate based on factors such as tone of voice, posture or even physical presentation.
This idea, although applicable to any context, is even more important in the business world, where the oratory capacity of companies or business representatives can determine their success or extinction. "We are being judged, whether we want not, and often even because of factors that have nothing to do with our speech. Why let the audience have all this power over us? Why not try to change the way others see us?"
As for the physical dimension, it is naturally important to maintain a careful presentation and respect the 'dress code' that the event or circumstance requires. The psychological dimension is the most difficult to manipulate - and also the one that most determines whether others perceive us as clear and confident or anxious and busy. Keywords to take into account in this situation are three: "clarity, trust, control." “If these three qualities are somehow anchored in the speeches, we will have a higher success rate,” says the trainer.
Howard Paley explains that while there is no “uniform rule” that applies to all public communication contexts, there are some tricks that facilitate the “mastery” of any situation. Successful communication depends on a discourse with clear objectives and adapted to receptors (not always the same discourse would work in different countries and cultural contexts, for example). Almost as important as the content of discourse is the way voice is projected and used to emphasize the words, which are eventually received differently depending on the tone, volume and rhythm of speech. Body language, one of the most significant aspects of three -dimensional communication, is the icing at the top of the cake.
The experience of public speaking can guarantee the confidence of the speaker, but does not guarantee that the way the message is transmitted is successful. The formula is different - and accessible to all, regardless of age, professional branch or prior experience in public presentations. "It is necessary to carefully choose the words to get the utmost impact, mix them with the appropriate vocal dynamics and body language and 'voila': we are giving an impactful talk. It may seem simple, but it requires effort."</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:51:37</pubDate></item><item><title>New Hope: Coutinho remains as a head-range, Rita Santos is left out</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/nova-esperanca-coutinho-mantem-se-como-cabeca-de-lista-rita-santos-fica-de-fora/</link><description>Yesterday was presented the list of candidacy to the Legislative Assembly of Nova Esperança, linked to the Association of Macao Public Function Workers (ATFPM). Number 1 remains José Pereira Coutinho, who was entitled yesterday Cristiano Ronaldo from the list. Rita Santos, on the other hand, is left out, at a time when she will be investigated by the prosecutor due to a suspicion of violation of the electoral law of Portugal.
 
José Pereira Coutinho will be again the head of the new hope in the race to the legislative elections that take place on September 14-even because he is the group's CR7, as his himself was entitled. “Humblely, I think I'm Cristiano Ronaldo [from the New Hope list],” said the leader of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM).
The list, delivered yesterday to the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), has as 2 Chan Hao Weng, shooting Che Sai Wang to third place. Rita Santos's presence in the places of election had been guaranteed several times in recent months, but has not been confirmed. The first time Coutinho said Rita Santos would be in the first places of New Hope was in August last year. Over the following months, the information has always been reiterated. Now it is found that Rita Santos is not among the 11 names presented to Caeal. The official assured that this has nothing to do with the information that recently came to public, that it will be investigated for alleged violations of the Portuguese Electoral Law.
 
Rita Santos says that absence is due to the family and not the investigation that it is
 
Last week the Public Prosecution Service (MP) of Macau confirmed that he received a request for judicial cooperation made by the judicial body of Portugal relating to an individual who will have committed a crime against the electoral law of Portugal in Macau. The agency did not indicate the identity of the suspect, but it will be Rita Santos, since it was the subject of a complaint by alleged irregularities in the Portuguese legislative elections of 2024.
Asked if Rita Santos's absence from the list was linked to the investigation that she is targeted, Coutinho assured no. "Rita Santos likes her grandson a lot, has her family, always on the internet to put pictures of her grandson. We are childhood friends, but bread bread, cheese cheese," he said, stressing that "she has limitations, she has no time."
Having Rita Santos on the list would be a handicap, said Coutinho, justifying that, in addition to the family connection, the president of the Atfpm General Assembly continues to work for Macao's relations with Portuguese-speaking countries, so "any of these things would be affected." Coutinho revealed, by the way, that recently Rita Santos met with the President of the Republic of Guinea-Bissau and several ministers of that country.
Yesterday afternoon, Rita Santos shared a video on her Facebook page justifying that she had to dedicate herself more to her family and, therefore, had no time for the Legislative Assembly (AL).
The pair assured that there was no political interference in choosing the members on the list. “Do you think I'm not free? I never suffered pressures,” said Coutinho.
 
Public scrape to che sa wang
 
In 2021, the number 2 of the New Hope list was Che Sa Sa Wang. The list linked to the ATFPM got more than 18,000 votes in direct suffrage and, therefore, got two seats in the hemiciclo. Now, although he was Coutinho's bench colleague over the past four years, Che Sai Wang has been pushed to third on the list, being overtaken by Chan Hao Weng.
Asked why Che Sa Sai Wang was replaced, Coutinho left criticism of his colleague's performance: "The position of deputy is demanding, he has to intervene, work. Not everyone can follow the pedaling. My colleague Che Sai has not been able to follow the past."
Pereira Coutinho stressed that, to be a deputy to AL, it is necessary to have dedication and be aware that the group does not have “a luxury advisory to do the job”. "I have to know who is best prepared to be my colleague in AL, in the event of two voices," he said.
Chan Hao Weng is born in Guangdong and a degree in Physical Education and Sports from the Polytechnic Institute of Macao and a master's degree in Management and Public Administration from the Macao University of Science and Technology. He is also a civil servant since 1994. Coutinho said that the number 2 on the list will be an asset in sports, young people and civil service.
 
Pecuniary check of 15 thousand patacas and 10,000 consumer card in the political program
 
From the political program delivered yesterday to Caeal, we highlight the proposal of the creation of a permanent cash planning plan with a value of at least 15 thousand patacas and also a consumer card of 10,000 patacas.
The retroactive assignment of 21 thousand patacas of the central pension fund is also suggested not mandatory to the elderly and the increase of pensions to 4,500 patacas.
Within housing, New Hope suggests that there is “a public housing for each resident anchored to the birth rate, reducing the price of economic housing”. In the employment area, Pereira Coutinho's list reiterates that priority should be given to residents in game dealers and heads. The period of unemployment allowance to 120 days must also be extended and an annual increases of 10% in the minimum wage.
New Hope also challenges the government to improve working conditions in the game sector, as well as the development of culture and sport in the region.
As for the role of Macao's platform, the New Hope says that “there should be further realization of the role of Macau in economic, cultural and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries with the greater participation of the population and entrepreneurs” and the Macao Forum is expected to raise its level of influence.
 
Rita Santos will return to the position of Community Counselor
 
Yesterday, the president of the ATFPM also said that, since it is not part of the list, Rita Santos will again be a counselor of the Portuguese communities of the Circle of China. The official had suspended her mandate as a counselor in October last year, justifying the decision at the time with the fact that she was preparing the MSAR legislative elections.
 
Coutinho says ATFPM was not called by the MP
 
The complaint of irregularities in the Portuguese legislative elections of 2024 did not only fall on Rita Santos, the ATFPM was also aimed at this complaint that the Portuguese authorities are investigating. However, contrary to what happened to Rita Santos, Coutinho was not called upon to make statements by the prosecutor on behalf of the association, yesterday assured himself. "Someone wanted, but no," he left, not revealing who this "someone" would be.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:55:38</pubDate></item><item><title>China asks to avoid “jungle law” in the global economy and defends cooperation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/china-pede-que-se-evite-lei-da-selva-na-economia-global-e-defende-cooperacao/</link><description>Chinese prime minister warned the risks of growing economic and commercial fragmentation, defending cooperation and multilateralism in the face of containment and risk reduction policies promoted by Western powers. In his speech, I read Qiang also warned of "deep changes" in the international economy.
 
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang warned yesterday against the risks of increasing economic and commercial fragmentation, defending cooperation and multilateralism in the face of containment and risk reduction policies promoted by Western powers.
"What the world needs is not the jungle law, but of mutual success through cooperation," Li said, in an implicit reference to protectionist tensions and measures led by the United States to reduce China's dependence in strategic sectors.
I was speaking at the inaugural session of the Annual Meeting of New Champions, known as the “Summer Davos” and promoted by the World Economic Forum, which takes place this week in Tianjin, in northeastern China, and brings together political and business leaders from over 90 countries and regions.
In his speech, Chinese prime minister warned of “deep changes” in the international economy, driven by geopolitical tensions, technological transformation and reconfiguration of global supply chains. "The world cannot be a set of isolated islands again. We need more cooperation bridges in which we all win," he said.
In a context marked by increasing customs rates, restrictions on foreign investment and calls to economic 'dissociation' with China, I read that global trade and investment should not be politicized or transformed into confrontation instruments. ”
He also stressed that China remains committed to dialogue, economic integration and promoting an open multilateral system. "Economic globalization will not stop. It can go through ups and downs, but will continue to advance," he said. Li also highlighted the growing role of emerging economies such as “new engines” of international trade, recalling that they represent about 70% of the world's population.
China will continue to open it abroad, Li said, promising more cooperation in the areas of technological innovation and energy transition and improvement in the environment for foreign investors with clear and predictable rules.
This year's edition of “Summer Davos” takes place under the sign of geoeconomic uncertainty and increased protectionism, placing the tonic in the opportunities offered by entrepreneurship and new technologies to boost economic growth and resilience. Participants include heads of government from countries such as Ecuador, Singapore and Vietnam. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:55:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Reggae night with performances by Betchy Barros and Nana Kofi Asare on roadhouse</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/noite-de-reggae-com-performances-de-betchy-barros-e-nana-kofi-asare-no-roadhouse/</link><description>This Friday, June 27, the Roadhouse Macau bar hosts a night dedicated to reggae, the famous musical genre of Jamaican roots that promotes messages of peace, resistance and unity. With performances of two talents of African music and free admission, the event celebrates the Caribbean culture through taxes to recognized genre. A moment of relaxation to complete the week starting at 9 pm.
 
The Roadhouse Macau Bar offers this Friday, June 27, a night of music and fun through reggae, a musical genre that was immortalized by Bob Marley in the world cultural scenario. Titled “An Evening of Ecletic Vibes: Reggae Night!”, The event promises a diverse musical experience, with three sets of 45 minutes each, played by a full band led by artists Betchy Barros on the microphone and Nana Kofi Asare on drums. The initiative reinforces the role of reggae as a vehicle for messages of peace, resistance and unity, on a night that favors accessibility with free admission to all who want to enjoy the event.
The performances start at 21h. However, before the start of the show, from 18h to 21h, visitors can enjoy a beverage promotion, offering a second drink in the purchase of the first.
Reggae is a musical genre characterized by synchopaded rhythms, a dancing beat and lyrics that often address social, political and spiritual themes. Originated in Jamaica in the 1960s with its origin in Calypso and Mento, the style combines SKA influences, Rocksteady and 'Rhythm and Blues', creating a sound that mixes a striking 'groove' and messages of hope. His unmistakable pace and lyrics of denunciation and resistance made him a tool of expression for various generations, promoting values ​​of equality, freedom and solidarity, so pertinent to the current global situation. Artists like Jimmy Cliff and Peter Tosh raised the reggae to a cultural symbol status whose influence extends around the world.
The genre and its classics will now be honored in this programming that includes the presence of a duo with great experience in Macau, singer Betchy Barros, born in Guinea-Bissau, and drummer Nana Kofi Asare, from Ghana.
Betchy Barros, graduated from London’s Academy of Contemporary Music, began his career at 15 years in traditional African music. Currently based in Macao, he often participates in cultural events, festivals and exhibitions, leading his voice to several international stages. With a strong connection with African roots, the interpretation of reggae and other genres reflects a fusion of influences that enriches their musical experience.
Nana Kofi Asare, in turn, is a young 29-year-old Ghanaian musician who, besides acting as a drummer, is in the final phase of the master's degree in research, showing a facet of talent and dedication that transcends the musical universe, introducing himself into biodiversity studies. You are leaving Macau, but does not say goodbye without first leaving your mark in Macao's music.
This event represents a second collaboration between the two artists. The selection of classic and contemporary themes promises to provide a sound trip that crosses different eras and styles, reinforcing the universal character of reggae and its ability to promote intercultural understanding. Positive energy for the beginning of the weekend.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Former coalition partner presents a motion of censorship to the leader of Thailand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/antigo-parceiro-de-coligacao-apresenta-mocao-de-censura-a-lider-da-tailandia/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Thailand will face a motion of censorship supported by the Bhumjaithai party, which abandoned the government coalition after the conversation of Paetongtarn Shinawatra with a Cambodian leader, yesterday said local media. "The motion will be presented as soon as the third parliamentary session is opened on July 3," said Nan Boonthida Somchai spokesman, after a meeting on Tuesday between the Executive Committee and party deputies, quoted by the Thai press.
Bhumjaithai, led by the hitherto powerful interior minister, Anutin Charnvirakul, abandoned the coalition government, formed by ten groups, after becoming a telephone conversation between Shinawatra and former Cambodian Prime Minister and current Senate President Hun Sen.
In the audio, the agent questioned the role of a high commander of the Thai army, in the context of the border conflict between Bangcoque and Phnom Penh, who intensified since the end of May after the death of a Cambodian soldier in a disputed area.
The conservative formation, which was the second with the highest representation in the executive, became part of the opposition after the departure, which led other government partners to meet to evaluate whether support for the Prime Minister.
Senate President Mongkol Suurasajja asked the Constitutional Court to analyze whether the leader committed "a serious violation of ethical norms" in criticizing the military.
Bhumjaithai's spokeswoman encouraged opposition formations-a popular party, Paracharath, the Justice Party and Thai Sang Thai-to sign the motion and support the 38-year-old censorship debate, which reached power in August 2024.
Shinawatra succeeded the same party Srettha Thavisin, Pheu Thai, after being dismissed by the Constitutional Court for violating the Code of Ethics by appointing as a minister a convict for corruption.
The conversation with Hun Sen also originated requests for resignation. A civil group, a government critic, called a protest for Saturday to demand the resignation of the Prime Minister.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:55:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Financial Reserve has reached higher value since the end of 2021</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/26/reserva-financeira-atingiu-valor-mais-elevado-desde-final-de-2021/</link><description>Macao's financial reserve assets reached 632.6 billion Patacas at the end of April, the highest value since the end of 2021. The reserve began the year on the rise, with the value of assets rising 16.3 billion patacas in the first four months.
 
Macao's financial reserve assets reached 632.6 billion Patacas at the end of April, the highest value since the end of 2021, was announced yesterday.
According to a balance sheet published in an official bulletin by the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the reserve has been at the highest level since registered in December 2021: 643.2 billion patacas.
Still, it remains far from the historical record of 663.6 billion patacas, reached in late February 2021, although the territory is in the middle of covid-19 pandemic.
The reserve began 2025 high, with the value of assets rising 16.3 billion patacas in the first four months. More than half of this amount (8.99 billion of patacas) was won only in April.
Official data show that it is the best start of year since the first four months of 2021, when the reserve valued at 42.7 billion patacas.
According to AMCM, the reserve had registered in 2024 the best year since the pandemic, earning 35.7 billion patacas. This was the highest annual increase since 2019, when the value of the reserve increased by 70.6 billion patacas.
The value of the extraordinary reserve at the end of April this year was 459.7 billion Patacas and the basic reserve, equivalent to 150% of Macao's public budget, was 164.2 billion Patacas.
The initial budget of the territory for 2025 foresees a 7% increase in total expenses, to 109.4 billion patacas.
The Legislative Assembly, the Macao Parliament, is currently discussing a proposal presented by the government for a new budget, which includes an extra increase of 2.86 billion patacas in expenses.
The Macao Financial Reserve is mostly composed of 257.8 billion Patacas in subcontracted investments, deposits and current accounts of 252.9 billion patacas and even credit securities in the amount of 116.6 billion.
In 2024, investments yielded to the financial reserve nearly 31 billion patacas, corresponding to a profitability rate of 5.3%, AMCM said in late February. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 07:52:39</pubDate></item></channel></rss>