<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/valerio-romao-muito-contente-com-adaptacao-de-a-medida-que-fomos-recuperando-a-mae/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Falling worker and construction machine at sea suspends works in zone A</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/queda-de-trabalhador-e-de-maquina-de-construcao-no-mar-suspende-obras-na-zona-a/</link><description>The total suspension of the A3 access road construction was ordered between the new landfills and the Macao Peninsula, due to an incident in which a worker and a building machine fell into the sea.
The incident took place last Friday morning and, according to the authorities, was caused by the partial collapse of the provisional easel bridge at the access road shipyard shipyard. Quoted by a joint statement of public works (DSOP) services, maritime and water (DSAMA) services and services for labor affairs (DSAL), the worker involved fell into the sea when the construction machine was operating.
The operator was able to leave the water on his own and was transported to the hospital by the contractor. Authorities indicate that the non-resident worker was slightly injured and was conscious after the incident, undergoing a detailed medical examination.
Authorities guarantee to be aware of the incident and highlighted employees to find out the situation at the scene, issuing a warning of suspension of work to the respective contractor. They ensured that they will do the search and rescue work of the building machine, taking the necessary measures to avoid causing pollution in the maritime area during search work.
According to the press release, DSOP required the contractor and the supervisory entity to collaborate with the administration in the investigation of the causes of the incident, and to present their reports on the short -term incident. "In case of involvement in the act of offense and work with insecurity, responsibilities will be required and the respective treatment under the law," he reiterated.
Dsal said it will provide help to the worker in monitoring the indemnity process by the work incident. Dsama, on Friday, sent a team and a public service boat to proceed with the security inspection at the site and in the maritime area, and found that the incident did not involve any vessels, nor affected the safety of navigation on public channels. The body also required the contractor to install oil containment barriers and signaling buoys to prevent oil spill.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:43:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.05.06</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/ponto-fatal-2025-05-06/</link><description>The total suspension of the A3 access road construction was ordered between the new landfills and the Macao Peninsula, due to an incident in which a worker and a building machine fell into the sea.
The incident took place last Friday morning and, according to the authorities, was caused by the partial collapse of the provisional easel bridge at the access road shipyard shipyard. Quoted by a joint statement of public works (DSOP) services, maritime and water (DSAMA) services and services for labor affairs (DSAL), the worker involved fell into the sea when the construction machine was operating.
The operator was able to leave the water on his own and was transported to the hospital by the contractor. Authorities indicate that the non-resident worker was slightly injured and was conscious after the incident, undergoing a detailed medical examination.
Authorities guarantee to be aware of the incident and highlighted employees to find out the situation at the scene, issuing a warning of suspension of work to the respective contractor. They ensured that they will do the search and rescue work of the building machine, taking the necessary measures to avoid causing pollution in the maritime area during search work.
According to the press release, DSOP required the contractor and the supervisory entity to collaborate with the administration in the investigation of the causes of the incident, and to present their reports on the short -term incident. "In case of involvement in the act of offense and work with insecurity, responsibilities will be required and the respective treatment under the law," he reiterated.
Dsal said it will provide help to the worker in monitoring the indemnity process by the work incident. Dsama, on Friday, sent a team and a public service boat to proceed with the security inspection at the site and in the maritime area, and found that the incident did not involve any vessels, nor affected the safety of navigation on public channels. The body also required the contractor to install oil containment barriers and signaling buoys to prevent oil spill.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:42:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim took local entrepreneurs to the Portuguese food export fair in Lisbon</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/ipim-levou-empresarios-locais-a-feira-de-exportacao-de-produtos-alimentares-de-portugal-em-lisboa/</link><description>The Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) organized a delegation of 12 businessmen from Macao to participate in the 4th Export Fair of the Farms of Portugal (Sagalexpo), which took place from April 28 to 30 at the Lisbon International Fair.
According to IPIM, the delegation of local entrepreneurs featured representatives of commercial associations and companies dedicated to trade and processing of food products, including four companies participated for the first time in the event.
The 4th Sagaxpo was organized by Exposalão S.A. and attracted this year the participation of about 400 Portuguese food companies, as well as more than 1,100 international buying companies. The fair dedicated itself to the display of agricultural products, food and alcohol, being “the largest export fair of food products in the country,” said IPIM.
In a statement, the body also revealed that during the fair three Portuguese companies reached cooperation intentions with small and medium -sized companies in Macau, covering products such as drinks, frozen foods and wines. He said that a Ginja liqueur brand will be first introduced in Macau, according to IPIM, with the plan to make Macau the “premiere place” for products from Portuguese -speaking countries in the Greater Bay market.
During the same visit to Lisbon, Ipim also held the Roadshow of the “2nd China Economic and Commercial Exhibition-Parades of Portuguese Language (Macau) (2nd C-PLPEX)” and a promotion session on the Macao business environment, which was attended by about 80 representatives of commercial associations and Portuguese companies. It was the third stop of promotional activity in Portuguese-speaking countries of IPIM, after the 2nd C-PPLPEX Roadshow in Angola and Brazil.
IPIM said that at the event were representatives of commercial associations and local companies from the sectors of new energy, agriculture, food and beverage, professional services and blue economy, among others. In addition to “providing an exchange space between Macao and Portugal companies”, IPIM said that business advantages were promoted in the territory and the 2nd C-PLPEX that will take place from October 22 to 25 in Macao, “in order to attract more PLP companies to become investors and exhibitors at the exhibition in Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:46:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan will disagree with any deal with the US without a tariff review</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/japao-discordara-de-qualquer-acordo-com-os-eua-sem-uma-revisao-das-tarifas/</link><description>The Japanese tariff negotiator said the country has no intention of reaching any agreement with the administration of the president of the United States without a revision of the new tariffs imposed.
 
Ryosi Akazawa, Japan's tariff negotiator, said the country has no intention of reaching any agreement with the US President's administration without a revision of the new tariffs imposed.
"We have pressured the United States to reconsider the rate of tariffs and we will not be able to reach an agreement if they are not properly approached," said Akazawa, minister responsible for economic revitalization and new capitalism, on the way to that Asian country after a second round of tariff negotiations in Washington and quoted by the local news agency Kyodo.
Government sources have said that the US has been reluctant to grant exemptions or any special treatment to Japan on customs rights, which would mean that the 25% increase in vehicle imports, an issue that particularly worries Japan, would not be negotiable.
The automotive industry is one of the most important in Japan, especially in trade with the US, which represents about 30% of Japanese exports to that country. Before the increase, customs rights to these products were 2.5%.
In a new setback for Tokyo, 25% customs rights to US imports of Japanese cars have come in effect.
Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba lamented the application of the new tax and ensured that Japan will continue to ask the US to reconsider its new customs measures.
The Japanese leader agreed with Akazawa and assured that his country is negotiating all tariffs, including those that focus on engines, steel and aluminum, as well as the general 10% aggravation recently established by Washington.
Since returning to the White House in January, Donald Trump has imposed a 25% rise in foreign imports of foreign vehicles and an identical climb on steel and aluminum produced outside the US.
Its administration has also announced what it calls “reciprocal tariffs,” a series of rates imposed on business partners with whom it has a deficit and other countries that accuse of adopting non -unfair barriers to US companies, and that in Japan's case it rises to 24%.
This tariff remains partially and temporarily suspended-the 10% general fare is still in force-as long as bilateral trade negotiations take place, in which the US has preferably gave Japan. It is expected that a third round of conversations, among negotiators from both countries, will happen until the 31st.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:47:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao bank profits rise 44.8% in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/lucros-dos-bancos-de-macau-sobem-448-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Macao banks made profits of 3.76 billion in the first quarter, 44.8% more than in the same period of 2024. Financial investments, in turn, yielded 528.6 million Patacas, three times more than in the first three months of last year.
 
According to official data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the main reason was banking services and operations, whose revenues increased by 42.1% to 2.76 billion patacas.
The data, released on Friday, also reveal that financial investments yielded 528.6 million Patacas, three times more than in the first three months of last year.
In the opposite direction, the Macau banking fell from 3.1%to 3.75 billion patacas, on the interest margin, the difference between loan revenues and deposit expenses.
This after the AMCM approved three descents of the main reference interest rate in the last three months of 2024, the last of which a 0.25 percentage points, introduced on December 19, following the US Federal Reserve.
Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas by 2024, a drop of 21.3% and the lowest value since 2010, especially due to the fall of the interest margin.
The loans, the main source of revenue from the worldwide banking, decreased 4.7% in the last 12 months, settling in 1.02 billion of Patacas in late March. On the contrary, deposits with Macau banks increased by 10.3% to 1.36 billions of patacas, AMCM said.
Macao has two currency broadcasters: the local Chinese state bank branch Banco da China and the National Bank Overseas (BNU), which belongs to the Caixa Geral de Depósitos group. BNU announced in February net profits of 585.1 million patacas by 2024, a decrease of 0.4%, in part due to the “context of current interest rates”.
Macau Banking Credit fell 2.7% in March to 56.1 billion patacas, after February had reached the highest value since AMCM began compiling this data in 1990, still during the Portuguese territory administration.
In March, expired loans accounted for 5.5% of Macao banks loans, 1.3 more percentage points than in the same month as 2023. A percentage that reaches 6.7% in the case of credit to institutions or individuals outside the Chinese region.
The European Banking Authority, the EU regulatory agency, for example, considers that banks with at least 5% of bad loans have “high exposure” at risk and should establish a strategy to solve the problem.
Still, the percentage of bank credit overdue in Macau is far from the 25.3% record reached in mid -2001, in the middle of the world economic crisis caused by the outbreak of the speculative bubble of companies linked to the internet. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:43:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese President Xi Jinping visits Russia from Wednesday to Saturday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/presidente-chines-xi-jinping-visita-russia-de-quarta-feira-a-sabado/</link><description>Russia has announced that Chinese President Xi Jinping will visit the country from Wednesday to Saturday in the 80th anniversary of World War II victory against Germany Nazi, also addressing the Ukrainian conflict.
According to a statement issued by Kremlin and quoted by France-Presse (AFP), Xi Jinping will also participate in bilateral discussions on “the development of world partnership relations and strategic interaction” and “current problems in the order of International and Regional Day”. "It is expected that a series of bilateral documents, between governments and ministries, be signed," added the Kremlin.
The visit takes place at a time of commercial confrontation between Beijing and Washington, reaffirming the alliance between Russia and China.
In addition to Xi Jinping, leaders from about 20 countries are expected to watch the military parade on 9 May in Red Square, including Brazilian President Lula da Silva and other traditional international allies in Moscow. One of whom is Cuban President Miguel Díaz-Canel, who arrived in St. Petersburg, where he was received by local governor Alexandr Beglov.
On Saturday, Kremlin accused Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky of threatening the celebrations of World War II on May 9 after stating that Kiev could not ensure the safety of international leaders in Moscow.
Volodymyr Zelensky “has made an unambiguous threat to world leaders” who will participate in the ceremony, Russian diplomacy spokesman Maria Zakharova said on social networks, according to Russian news agency Tass.
Zakharova commented on statements made on Friday night by Zelensky about the celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the victory over Germany Nazi, presided by Vladimir Putin.
Zelensky said Kiev could not guarantee the safety of the international leaders present, suggesting that Moscow can do something to blame Ukraine. "We do not know what Russia will do on that date. You can take several measures, such as fires or explosions, and then accuse us," said the Ukrainian President.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:43:28</pubDate></item><item><title>May week of May brings more than 830,000 visitors to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/semana-dourada-de-maio-traz-mais-de-830-mil-visitantes-a-macau/</link><description>Macau received 833,694 visitors between May 1st and 17:00 yesterday, Buddha day, according to data released by the Public Security Police (CPSP). This year's daily average exceeded 2024 numbers by about 60% and also exceeded the government's predictions, which pointed to the entry of 630 to 700 thousand visitors in this period.
 
In the first five days of the month, between Thursday and 17:00 yesterday, 833,694 visitors entered Macau, according to data released by the Public Security Police (CPSP). In total, 3,505,476 border movements were counted during the golden week of Labor Day, a high time of travel corresponding to five days of holidays in the interior of China.
The busiest day was Friday, the 2nd, with the entry of 221,968 visitors. Ordering the holidays in a decreasing order of influx, continue Saturday, May 3 (204,078); Thursday, May 1 (176,921); and Sunday, May 4 (154,462). Yesterday, CPSP registered the entry of 76,265 tourists until 17:00. Considering the data of the first four days, it is possible to calculate that the daily average surrounding 189,357 visitors, meaning this a substantial increase of about 60% compared to the same period last year.
Among the nine borders of access to the territory, the most popular were the terrestrial borders of the doors of the siege and Hengqin, highlighting the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge. The doors of the siege received 109,312 visitors on the busiest day, Friday, while 39,570 people opted for the Hengqin border post. On the same day, 29,888 entries were registered through the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge. Yesterday, on Buddha Day, 30,067 visitors entered Macao through the doors of the siege until 17:00.
In total, 3,505,476 entries and exits in the region were counted during the five days of the golden week, including both visitors and non-visitors. The number of crossings fits the CPSP forecasts, which in late April anticipated between 3.4 and 3.5 million border movements for this period of holidays. On the other hand, the number of tourists anticipated by the authorities surpassed the April forecasts, which were at 630 to 700,000 visitors.
Last year, it is recalled, 589,634 visitors came to Macau during the holidays of Labor Day, making a daily average of only 117,926 people. The 2024 data fell short of the estimates of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), which pointed to an average of 130,000 visitors per day in this period.
 
STD conducted inspection actions during the holidays
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) has made inspection at Macao border and sights of sights over the five days of holiday, in order to ensure the stability and normal functioning of services. Inspection actions were organized and executed in conjunction with several competent entities, such as CPSP, the Fire Department, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), the Consumer Council and Customs Services. At the same time, the body maintained contact with tourist operators from Macao and the interior of China, to ensure that the hotel industry was prepared to welcome the flow of visitors and to maintain the proper functioning of tourist excursions. In a statement, STD informs that any suspicious incident or case - such as illegal provision of accommodation to tourists - must be reported by completing the form available on its official electronic page.
 
Old Bairro da Taipa creates provisional pedestrian zone
 
The Government of MSA inaugurated a temporary pedestrian zone in the old neighborhood of Taipa between May 1 and 5, with the aim of ensuring the ordered circulation of pawns and vehicles. The initiative resulted from a joint effort of various organisms, such as the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), which was concerned with the auscultation of opinions and the monitoring of traffic and hygiene in the area; The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), which supervised the change in the career paths of buses; The Public Security Police (CPSP), which mobilized agents to maintain the order of the flow of people in the area; And finally, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), which provided workers to reinforce the cleaning of streets and public bathrooms. Also the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) and the Cultural Institute (IC) participated in the initiative with the installation of a fair with the former Panchões IEC Long factory, where activities such as street performances, musical shows, or interactions with the “Mak Mak” mascot and the goblin “MICAF” were promoted.
 
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:44:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Association gave up the demonstration of 1 May after police warnings</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/associacao-desistiu-da-manifestacao-de-1-de-maio-depois-de-advertencias-da-policia/</link><description>This year, once again, no manifestations of Labor Day were organized. The Power of the People Association also delivered a prior notice to the Public Security Police (CPSP), but eventually gave up the initiative, as the police authorities asked the group to "carefully" on the subject, warning that if there were any kind of disorder, the organizing entity could be held responsible. According to the association, the authorities warned that the demonstration could even violate the National Security Act.
 
For the sixth consecutive year, no manifestation was held at the time of the Labor Day. There was an association that still tried to organize a march on May 1, but after police warnings, eventually gave up the intention.
The final point had reported last week that a notice was presented for a march on this year's Labor Day, but it was removed by the prosecutor “on his own initiative,” the Public Security Police (CPSP) was at the time.
The group that presented the notice was the Power of the People's Association. Lam Weng Ioi, president of the group, told All About Macau that he presented the previous notice in mid -April, and after that, police authorities asked for various details about the intentions of the march, via telephone, Wechat or even asking prosecutors to attend a squad.
According to the president of the Association to the portal, CPSP required details on “the preparations of the march, possible scenarios and eventual consequences”, and was asked the group to pondere “carefully” on the subject. Police have warned that some protesters could eventually take advantage of problems and violate the law.
The Power of the People Association assured that the situation was controlled, but the police authorities did not seem convinced, indicating that, in case of disorder, the organizers would be held responsible, mentioning until the National Security Law. Lam Weng Ioi stressed that CPSP did not explicitly say that the association should give up the demonstration, but made the group feel that it would be very difficult to satisfy their requirements.
On the other hand, “it is the responsibility of the police to maintain social order, but now it seems that all responsibility has been transferred to the organizers of the demonstration,” said the association's president.
The group eventually gave up on the intention, replacing the march with the delivery of a petition to the government where claims such as the priority of places in access to employment and the reduction of the number of non-resident workers in the territory.
On May 1, a man protested alone, in front of the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs (DSAL), against the presence of migrant workers in the region and was detained by CPSP agents. To Lusa agency, CPSP justified the detention by saying that the man displayed 'slogans' and chanting chants to demand the reduction of migrant workers. A video that circulates on social networks shows the man to put eight sheets of paper on the floor with the message “Government, cut on migrant workers! next to the flags of Macao and China. According to CPSP, police officers have repeatedly made warnings for violations of the Law of Meeting and Manifestation Law, but the man refused to obey and was taken to the squad to be identified.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:45:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Entrance to the economic housing of zone a expected for the third quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/entrada-na-habitacao-economica-da-zona-a-prevista-para-o-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>The 2019 Economic Housing Fractions in Zone A will start hosting inhabitants in the third quarter of this year, Iam Leng, president of the Housing Institute said. Among the eligible applications, by the end of last month, 750 households had already chosen the units. Five commercial spaces of the place will also be open to a public tender soon, in order to articulate with the entry of residents.
 
The delivery of keys to the 2019 Economic Housing Competition Fractions is scheduled for the third quarter of this year, ie, eligible residents will be able to live in zone A of new landfills from that time.
The information was advanced by Iam Lei Leng, president of the Housing Institute (IH), who also revealed that by the end of last month, nearly 750 households have already chosen the fractions, and more than 400 selected T3 fractions and more than 200 opted for T2 units.
It is recalled that the Economic Housing Contest opened in 2019 is the last contest held under the former “Economic Housing Law”, and the houses available for acquisition are located in Zone A of the new landfills, in the Tong Seng Building (Lot B4), in the Tong Chong building (lot B9) and Tong Kai Building (lot B10), a total of 3.017 fragments, which include 760 of the 760 fragments, which include 760 of da Tyology T1, 1,000 of T2 typology and 1,257 of T3 typology.
According to information from the authorities, until February this year, and after substantial assessment, it was found that 2,993 selected acquirers gather the respective requirements, and may choose the choice of fractions since March.
The president of IH, in statements to Radio Macau in Chinese language, also said that stores in the public housing lots B9 and B10 in zone A will be put in public tender by phases, to coincide with the entry of residents scheduled for the third quarter.
Iam Leng Leng indicated that five commercial spaces should be placed by public tender by June, for restoration purposes, supermarket, bank, pharmacy and commerce in general. "The body will briefly announce the contest of these stores and will advance with the contest program of more stores, based on the evaluation of the occupation situation of residents in the area," he said.
According to the order published in an official bulletin, for the three residential buildings of Economic Housing, the price of T1 apartments ranges from 1.18 million patacas and 1.46 million patacas. T2 houses cost between 1.55 million patacas and 1.82 million patacas, while the price of T3 units is set from 1.93 million patacas to 2.37 million patacas. All values ​​enjoy a bonus ratio greater than 64%.
In this case, after the period of the 16 -year inalienability burden, counted from the date of issuance of the license, if the acquirer intends to dispose of the fraction, he /
Iam Law Leng also recalled that the government launched three rounds of candidacies for economic housing in 2009, 2021 and 2023, providing a total of over 13,600 units. He stressed that, among the candidacies for economic housing, the search for houses T2 and T3 represents about 80% of the total number, so the T2 and T3 units will remain the main types of economic housing apartments in the future.
The official added that IH has already begun the feasibility study on the exchange of fractions by the residents of economic housing, especially of fractions of different typology. The study is still in a preliminary phase and iam Leng said it was open to residents' opinions about this policy.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:42:41</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Japan accuse themselves of violation of the airspace of islands</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/china-e-japao-acusam-se-de-violacao-do-espaco-aereo-de-ilhas-disputadas/</link><description>China and Japan accused each other of an intrusion in the airspace of islands disputed by the two countries in the East China Sea. The islands, known as Diaoyu in China and Senkaku in Japan, are administered by Tokyo, but claimed by Beijing
 
Chinese and Japanese authorities have launched mutual accusations due to an alleged intrusion on Saturday in the airspace of islands played by the two countries in the East China Sea.
The uninhabited islands, known as Diaoyu in China and Senkaku in Japan, are administered by Tokyo, but claimed by Beijing, being a point of regular tension between the two countries.
Chinese diplomacy announced that it presented a formal protest to the Japan embassy in Beijing, arguing that "a civil plane illegally entered the airspace around the Diaoyu Islands." "The Diaoyu islands and the affiliated islands are a territory belonging to China, and we install Japan immediately ceasing all illegal activities," said Chinese Coast Guard spokesman Liu Dejun. Liu said “a ship-based helicopter” was mobilized to warn and expel the Japanese plane, according to France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
Japanese Foreign Deputy Minister Takehiro Funakoshi, in turn, presented a "vigorous protest" to the Chinese ambassador in Tokyo. He cited the "intrusion of four Chinese coastal guard ships in the Japanese territorial waters around the Senkaku islands and the violation of Japanese airspace by a helicopter."
According to the Japan Ministry of Defense, the Chinese helicopter invaded Japanese airspace for about 15 minutes. "The [Japanese] self -defense forces reacted by sending fighters," said the ministry, also quoted by AFP.
According to Japanese public broadcaster NHK and other local media, it is the first time a helicopter of Chinese authorities violates Japanese airspace on dispute islands.
China often announces that it has expelled Japanese ships and planes in the vicinity of the islands, but Japanese officials told AFP that Chinese authorities sometimes announce expulsions that have not occurred.
Tensions between China and other countries that claim territories in the Sea of ​​China led Japan to develop ties with the Philippines and the United States.
Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba and Filipino President Ferdinand Marcos agreed last week to deepen security ties between the two countries. They also agreed to oppose “attempts to alter the 'status quo' in the East China Sea and the southern China Sea by strength or coercion,” in a reference to China.
United States Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth reaffirmed in January that Senkaku islands are covered by the security treaty with decades of existence that forces the United States to defend Japan in case of attack. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:46:22</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 40% of Taiwanese doubts the US security guarantee, says poll</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/mais-de-40-dos-taiwaneses-duvidam-da-garantia-de-seguranca-dos-eua-diz-sondagem/</link><description>More than 40% of Taiwanese believe that the United States's commitment to Taiwan's defense will decrease during Donald Trump's second term, according to a poll.
 
The results, published by the Sinica Academy, the island's main research center show that 21.1% and 23.3% of respondents believe that Washington will provide “much less” and “slightly”, respectively, for Taiwan's defense compared to the last years of Democrat Joe Biden's mandate (2021-2025).
In contrast, 5.7% believe the US will show “a little more” of involvement, and 4.6% believe it will be “much more” while the largest group (38.5%) believes the level of protection will remain the same.
When asked if they were concerned that the United States and China could reach agreements that would harm Taiwan's interests, 59% of respondents responded affirmatively.
Regarding the possibility of Washington sending troops to the island to repel a Beijing attack, 18.7% said that "definitely no" would do so, and another 23.7% said that "it would probably not do it."
The results of the study, conducted in mid-March and involving more than 1,200 respondents, were released on Friday by Wu Wen-Chin, researcher at the Academy Sinica Institute of Political Science, during a seminar in Taipé.
According to the expert, quoted by state news agency CNA, the results of the poll reflect how Trump's approach to foreign policy “increased anxiety” among the Taiwanese about Taiwan-mea relations.
The poll was performed after, at the end of February, Trump avoided committing to prevent a Beijing attack on Taiwan and recognized that he had a "great relationship" with Chinese homologist Xi Jinping.
For over seven decades, the US have been involved in disputes between both sides, as Washington is the main gun supplier for Taipei and, although it has no diplomatic ties with the island, could defend it in case of conflict with Beijing.
This posture has caused constant friction between the US and China, whose government has defined the “Taiwanese question” as the “red line” in relations between the two powers.
 
First round of negotiations between Taiwan and USA
 
Taiwan said he had concluded the first round of negotiations with the United States on “reciprocal tariffs and other economic and commercial issues,” adding that meetings took place in a “cordial and cordial” environment, official sources.
In a statement, Taiwan's commercial negotiation office said the talks, which ended on Thursday in Washington, focused on customs rights, commercial barriers and "various forms of economic and commercial cooperation between Taiwan and the United States." "Both parties expressed the common expectation of reinforcing bilateral economic and commercial cooperation and expressed their desire to create more opportunities for industrial and economic development of both countries based on mutual benefit," said the government agency, cited by EFE.
They also “agreed to continue short-term consultations on various issues, with the aim of actively seeking consensus and exploring deeper cooperation,” says the official text, without revealing specific details about the content of the conversations or the US employees.
Quoted in the statement, a guardian of the Taiwan authorities stressed the confidence that, through a “continuous and open dialogue based on mutual understanding”, it will be possible to “consolidate as much consensus as possible” between the two parts.
This face -to -face meeting took place three weeks after both parties had a first video conferencing on “reciprocal tariffs” announced on April 2 by US President Donald Trump against Washington's major business partners, an amount of 32% for the island.
Taiwan leader William Lai proposed to stress negotiations with the US based on the premise of "zero tariffs", following the model of the Mexico-Eu-Canada treaty.
According to the ruler, Taipé "will seek to reduce commercial imbalance" with Washington through the acquisition of energy, agricultural products, industrial goods and weapons, as well as increase investment in American territory and "eliminate non -military commercial barriers."
If these lines of negotiations fail and the US imposes rights on semiconductors - the island's main export asset - or reactivating its “reciprocal tariffs”, the impact on Taiwan's economy would be significant and the government has admitted it would have difficulty growing above 03%. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:46:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau's economy shrinks for the first time in two years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/economia-de-macau-encolhe-pela-primeira-vez-em-dois-anos/</link><description>Macao's economy shrank 1.3% in homologous terms in the first quarter, the first drop since the end of 2022, when the region began to raise restrictions due to pandemic.
Between January and March, Macao Gross Domestic Product (GDP) reached 99.78 billion Patacas, the Board of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said.
In a statement, DSEC pointed to reasons for decreasing the “relatively high comparison base” of the first trimester of 2024 and the “change of visitors' consumption pattern”.
The economic benefit of tourist services - the sector that dominates the economy of Macao - fell 3.8%, although the first quarter was the second best ever about the number of visitors.
According to official data, Macau received 9.86 million tourists by March 11.1% more than in the same period of 2024, but visitors have spent less in the city. The latest data point to a 14.6% drop in tourist per capita expense over the last year.
Macao's economy grew 23% in the first quarter of 2024 and ended the year up 8.8%.
The last time the region's GDP was at the end of 2022. Continental China-by far the main source of visitors from Macau-began to gradually raise all restrictions due to Covid-19 pandemic in mid-December 2022.
Still, DSEC stressed that internal demand was “relatively stable”, with private investment rising 7.8%, government expenses increasing 1%and private consumption to grow 0.6%.
On April 10, the University of Macao (one) reviewed the forecast for the region's economic growth, in part due to the potential impact of the tariffs imposed by the United States (US) on Chinese tourists.
Macao's Center for Studies and the Economics Department of the one foresee that the territory's GDP rise 6.8%, 1.1 percentage points than in the previous forecast, made in January.
Project coordinator and economist Kwan Fung said the low overhaul is due to the decline in the consumption of visitors and the “American tariffs on the world”, something that “has an indirect impact on Macao's economy”.
The UM Department of Economics professor said that tariffs will "affect the growth of all economies, especially the consumption of tours of mainland China."
In early March, the Financial notation Agency Fitch predicted that the growth of the economy of Macau will slow down to 6.9% this year, due to a “slower” recovery of tourism and game. "However, a sharp slowdown in the Chinese economy, such as the substantial increases in US tariffs, and a strong devaluation of Yuan [Chinese currency] pose negative risks to Macao's perspectives," the Fitch said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:46:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Tai Kin IP went to Europe to develop international cooperation network</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/tai-kin-ip-foi-a-europa-para-desenvolver-rede-de-cooperacao-internacional/</link><description>Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, went to France, Monaco and Luxembourg to “further expand Macao's international cooperation network”. The government says the visit "has reinforced communication with Europe in the areas of state -of -the -art technology and finance."
 
A delegation from Macao, led by the secretary to the economy and finance, was last week in Europe in search of reinforcing the mashed international cooperation network. Tai Kin IP passed through France, Monaco and Luxembourg. In the end, the authorities indicated that communication with Europe was reinforced in the areas of state -of -the -art technology and finance, "having been consolidated the foundations to boost the proper diversification of Macao's economy, deepen international cooperation and exchange, and increase Macao's influence on the international stage."
On April 25, the delegation moved to Paris to meet Deng Li, China Ambassador in France, having performed “an in-depth exchange” on bilateral cooperation between Macao and France. According to the press release released yesterday by the Tai Kin IP Office, opportunities for cooperation were studied in the transionic electronic trade domains, traditional Chinese medicine, technological innovation and training of young qualified staff, among others.
It is expected that through Macao as a cooperation platform for cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, "the development of industries in the country, Macao and France, or even Europe, and exploited cooperation spaces with Latin -speaking countries be promoted."
During the visit to Monaco, between April 26 and 29, the delegation was present at Monaco Clean Fusion Forum, with the intention of “knowing the latest situation of green technology development and reinforcing exchange with representatives of topic and international scientific research institutions”. In this event, the secretary for the economy and finance exchanged impressions with Prince Alberto II of Monaco on issues such as marine protection technology.
The delegation also visited the Center for Science and Technology of Monaco, to find out the results of the Principality Studies in the areas of environmental protection, marine ecosystem and sustainable development, among others.
Between April 29 and May 2, the delegation was in Luxembourg to meet China's ambassador to Luxembourg, Hua Ning, with the parties exchanged opinions on the reinforcement of economic and financial cooperation between Luxembourg and Macao. The delegation also visited Banco Clearstream, the International Securities Deposit Center (ICSD) and the largest local law firm, to “study the legislation and regulatory policies related to Luxembourg investment funds, as well as the latest situation in the market of obligations, in order to contribute to the advancement of law proposals entitled Investment Funds and Law.
The Government of MSAR wants to refer to Luxembourg's experiences and “continue to promote the articulation and cooperation between the Macao Macau Deposit and Settlement Center Limited Society (MCSD) and ICSD, to promote the exchange on interconnection between the obligations of the two territories”.
The delegation of Macau participated in a lecture by local Chinese financial institutions (namely Banco da China, China Commercial and Industrial Bank, China Agricultural Bank, China's construction bank and China's communications bank), alarming the joint activity of the financial sectors of both territories and proposals on the reinforcement of financial cooperation between Luxemburgo and Macau.
During the meeting with representatives of the Luxembourg Fund Industry (Alfo), Luxembourg for Finance and Luxembourg Exchange (Luxembourg), the delegation was known to the experiences of the local investment and investment funds market. Tai Kin IP indicated that the Macao Securities Deposit Center (CSD) completed direct interconnection with Hong Kong's The Central Moneymarkets (CMU), and expressed hope that in the future, international cooperation with the use of Luxembourg's experiences and forces, inviting the luxembourg parts to share examples of successful obligations to the successful obligations to the successful obligations for the successful obligations to the lost forced obligations to Financial sector of Macau.
On the other hand, both parties also negotiated about the quotation of Macao obligations on the Luxembourg Stock Exchange and the creation of conditions for the consequent transaction, as well as cooperation in the formation of financial qualified frames, with the aim of boosting the development of the Macao obligations market and forming financial qualified frames.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 03:43:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Heritage Ambassadors Association organized a visit to Jiangsu</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/associacao-dos-embaixadores-do-patrimonio-de-macau-organizou-visita-a-jiangsu/</link><description>The Macau Heritage Ambassadors Association organized a visit to the Jiangsu Coastal Province between April 17 and 21, 2025, with the aim of promoting the cultural development of Macao young people and reinforcing cooperation between the two regions.
The delegation was made up of sixteen young people, led by the president of the NG Chi Wai Association, the president of the General Assembly Tam Chi Kuong and the president of the fiscal board Wallace Kwah. The first stop at the itinerary was the capital city of Nanjing, where the group met with the Jiangsu Provincial Department of Culture and Tourism and visited some of the region's main points of interest, such as the Memorial of Nanjing Massacre victims or the Confucius Temple.
In the second part of the program, Macao's young people met with the Institute of Training and Research on World Heritage for the Asia and Pacific region in Suzhou, a city located southeast of Jiangsu Province. Among the exploited sights included the Jardim do Leão, the Pingjiang Historic Street and the Master of the Network Garden. In a statement, the Association said that the night tour of this last garden, in particular, provided a “multisensory experience” that could inspire the development of tourist projects in Macao.
"This visit allowed not only that young people from Macao enjoy the country's cultural richness, but also strengthened collaboration between heritage preservation professionals in the two regions. We hope to reinforce this contact through regular visits and study programs," said Association President NG Chi Wai, quoted in the same statement. One of the exchange participants, Deng Ying Shi, adds "impressed" with the fusion of historical heritage with modern technology and compares the visit to both cities with the immersion "in a roller of ancient painting."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Valério Romão “very happy” with adaptation of “as we were recovering the mother”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/06/valerio-romao-muito-contente-com-adaptacao-de-a-medida-que-fomos-recuperando-a-mae/</link><description>“As we recovering our mother” was considered the best short film in the Sophia awards. Valério Romão, author of the tale in which Gonçalo Waddington was based to make the film, commented, in statements to the end, that he was surprised by the prize, adding to be “very happy” with the end result. The film was recently screened in Macau, as part of the Rota das Letras Literary Festival.
 
In this year's edition of Sophia awards, the winning film in the best short film category was “as we recovering the mother”, made by Gonçalo Waddington. The short is based on a tale of the same name as Valério Romão who, at the end, comments that “he was not, at all, waiting” of the prize.
"In fact, it was not even expecting Gonçalo's desire to adapt to him to become the necessary support to do so," the author points out, adding: "Fortunately, we were selected by the ICA [Institute of Cinema and Audiovisual] and the tale eventually saw the daylight in the famous cinema of the cinema."
The story follows the attempts of four children to encourage his father after his mother died. Asked how the process for the adaptation of the history of the tale to the cinema, Romão points out that there was nothing to do with it. "Gonçalo took the tale, rewritten him in the shape of the script, respecting him in full, and threw himself to film him as if it were his," he says, "and very happy I had the process and the result; not only had to do anything, but I have ever been on his adaptation."
“À Medida que Fomos Recuperando a Mãe” foi recentemente exibido em Macau no âmbito do Festival Literário Rota das Letras. Valério Romão esteve presente na exibição de “À Medida Que Fomos Recuperando a Mãe” em Macau, no Teatro Capitol, no dia 26 de Março.
The writer says that "it is always interesting - and funny - measuring the pulse to the public in the room as the story turns from a classic drama into a kind of grotesque mirror, in which the unspeakable one sees himself in some way reflected." Then the silence settles down. In Macau it was like this, he recalls. In Macao, "there were still those who asked the origin of that bizarre story, which in fact has roots in a no less strange event but certainly less disturbing." "I won't tell you, it's‘ spoiler, "he said.
Valério Romão was in Macao to present “another disappointment”, a book that reflects on today's Portugal. The writer, who has come to Macao regularly, either for literary residences or for appearances on the route, also takes the opportunity to applaud the festival, which "always makes multiple efforts to continue to be the cultural bridge between Macau, Portugal and China."</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>