<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/zona-de-espectaculos-ao-ar-livre-vai-inaugurar-campos-de-basquetebol-em-breve/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>SCM Hostel begins Year of the Horse with lantern night and Calligraphy exhibition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/albergue-scm-inicia-ano-do-cavalo-com-noite-de-lanternas-e-exposicao-de-caligrafia/</link><description>The Círculo dos Amigos da Cultura de Macau (CAC) and Albergue SCM once again mark the Lantern Festival with a celebration open to the community. On the 3rd of March, starting at 6:30 pm, the courtyard of Albergue SCM, in the picturesque Parish of São Lázaro, will serve as a meeting point for an evening that combines festive gastronomy, live music, riddles and an exhibition of Chinese calligraphy dedicated to the Year of the Horse. Entry is free.

On the night of the first full moon of the Lunar New Year, the traditional Lantern Festival (or Mooncake Festival, as it is also known in some contexts) once again lights up the São Lázaro neighborhood. CAC – Círculo dos Amigos da Cultura de Macau, in partnership with Albergue SCM, organizes on March 3rd, a Tuesday, from 6:30 pm, its “Celebration of the Chinese New Year of the Horse”. The event celebrates the festive date that marks, on the lunar calendar, the culmination of the Chinese New Year festivities.
This year, the festival has as its central figure the auspicious animal of the year, the horse, the zodiac that rules the lunar year 2026, known as the Year of Bingwu. The program includes the offering of various festive delicacies to visitors, ambient music and the traditional game of deciphering riddles written on lanterns. In the Albergue courtyard, participants will also be able to leave their wishes in the Wishing Well and the Tree of Love, in a symbolic gesture of hope for the new cycle.
One of the highlights of the evening will be the presence of Macau's renowned calligrapher, Choi Chun Heng, who will be on site writing fai-chun, traditional welcome couplets, for the visitors present, offering personalized wishes of prosperity and happiness.
Parallel to the party, and lasting until April 16th, the CAC also opens on the night of the 3rd the exhibition “Success with the Horse – Works by Choi Chun Heng and his Precious Collection”. The exhibition, on view at Gallery A2 at Albergue SCM, is the result of a partnership with Tai Fung Tong Art House and brings together a vast and diverse set of calligraphy works by master Choi, as well as pieces from his personal collection, considered rarities in the calligraphic universe.
The exhibition explores the theme of the horse in the art of Chinese writing, associating the animal's strength and elegance with the vigorous strokes and aesthetic precision of traditional calligraphy. Through ink and brush, Choi Chun Heng embodies the spirit of Chinese characters, revealing the cultural depth and timeless beauty of this ancient Chinese art.
The CAC, founded in 1985 by a group of artists and intellectuals such as Carlos Marreiros, Mio Pang Fei or Victor Marreiros, has the mission of promoting Macau's culture, arts and heritage. The current initiative, which has the support of the Macau Foundation, is part of this aim, combining popular celebration with the praise of Chinese erudite traditions.
Entrance to all evening activities is free. The Albergue SCM operates daily as a cultural space, and the calligraphy exhibition can be visited between March 3rd and April 16th, every day from 12pm to 7pm, with the exception of Mondays, when it only opens from 3pm to 7pm.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Council of Portuguese Communities congratulates Seguro on his election as President of the Republic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/conselho-das-comunidades-portuguesas-felicita-seguro-pela-eleicao-como-presidente-da-republica/</link><description>The Council of Portuguese Communities in the Circle of China, Singapore, Tokyo, Seoul and Bangkok sent a letter to António José Seguro congratulating the future President of the Republic of Portugal on his election. “This moment constitutes a stage of hope and renewal for our country, and we are confident that your leadership will contribute to the strengthening of Portugal, both internally and internationally”, can be read in the letter, which is signed by counselors Luís Nunes, Maria João Gregório and Félix Teixeira.
In the letter, the advisors also say that they believe that, under the guidance of António José Seguro as President of the Republic, “Portugal will continue to assert itself as a united nation, promoting the interests of its emigrant citizens and consolidating its prominent role at a global level”.
"We recognize that the role of the President of the Republic is of utmost importance in promoting national unity, defending the Constitution and representing Portugal in the world. He is a figure with a high sense of responsibility, whose mission includes inspiring confidence, acting as a mediator and guaranteeing democratic stability, promoting values of solidarity, justice and progress for all Portuguese, regardless of their geographical location", says the Council of Portuguese Communities in the letter, reiterating the commitment to collaborate in the construction of a Portugal that is "more prosperous, united and supportive.”
In another letter, this time addressed to Portuguese Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, the Council of Portuguese Communities of the Circle of China, Singapore, Tokyo, Seoul and Bangkok conveyed “the most heartfelt condolences and words of solidarity” to the victims of the floods that devastated several regions of Portugal. The organization took advantage of this letter to thank the Portuguese Prime Minister for updating the pensions of pensioners residing abroad.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:52:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputies agree with model for using unused land</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/deputados-concordam-com-modelo-de-utilizacao-de-terrenos-desaproveitados/</link><description>The Monitoring Committee for Land Affairs and Public Concessions of the Legislative Assembly (AL) agrees with the “development planning + provisional use” model adopted by the Government to deal with Macao SAR lands that are yet to be developed. According to the commission chaired by Ella Lei, this model “allows the good use of precious soil resources”.

The specialized group of the Monitoring Committee for Land Affairs and Public Concessions of the Legislative Assembly (AL) visited on Tuesday several of the unused lands on the peninsula, in Taipa and in Coloane, with members of the competent services accompanying the deputies. After the visit, Ella Lei, president of the commission, said that “the specialized group agrees with the Government's adoption of the 'use planning + provisional use' model for unused land, which allows the good use of precious soil resources”.
This model, indicated the deputy cited in a Government note released yesterday, “contributes to increasing the effectiveness of the use of unused land”. Ella Lei also said she hopes that the authorities “do their planning well, in order to coordinate with the needs of social development and, at the same time, respond to the community's demands regarding public facilities and leisure spaces”.
This “use planning + provisional use” model means that the Government intends to give the land a provisional use while the final use is being decided.
Remember that in mid-January the Government indicated that 30 of the 39 unused plots of land already have a defined destination. Thirteen of them for temporary leisure areas, 12 for outdoor parking for light and heavy vehicles, one for sports facilities, one for an environmental protection and leisure center, and three for other mixed-use developments.
At the beginning of last month, the AL's Monitoring Committee for Land Affairs and Public Concessions held its first meeting, in which two specialized groups were created to monitor the construction of the Macau International Air Transport Hub (Port) on the west bank of the Pearl River and also the planning and use of unused land, having invited the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, and the respective members of the Government, to present the situation of the 39 unused land. The two specialized groups have already started monitoring work, with deputy Nick Lei coordinating the specialized group for land.
In the statement released yesterday, it is stated that the specialized group will continue to collect society's opinions on how to best use unused land and reinforce communication with the competent Government services, “with the aim of, together, improving the planning and use of these lands”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:55:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau received more than 1.5 million visitors on Chinese New Year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/macau-recebeu-mais-de-15-milhoes-de-visitantes-no-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>The golden week of the New Year of the Horse brought more than 1.5 million visitors to Macau, 78% of them from inland China. The average of around 173 thousand tourists per day corresponds to the Government's forecasts, which at the beginning of the month predicted the arrival of 158 thousand to 175 thousand visitors per day.

Macau welcomed a total of 1,554,285 visitors during the golden week of Chinese New Year, which this year took place from the 15th to the 23rd of February. The daily average of 172,699 tourists exceeded last year's figures by 5.5% and corresponded to the authorities' expectations, which estimated an average of between 158,000 and 175,000 visitors per day.
The provisional statistical data were revealed yesterday by the Tourism Services Directorate (DST), based on information collected by the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP). The busiest border crossings were Portas do Cerco (with a total of 603,529 entries), the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge (330,758) and the Hengqin checkpoint (295,779), with emphasis on the 94,841 visitors who landed at Macau Airport.
The fifth day of holidays, marked on February 19th, was the one with the greatest tourist flow. Authorities' data indicate that 227,943 visitors entered Macau on the day in question, thus setting a new historical high in the region. The previous record had been reached in 2025, during the golden week of Labor Day, when Macau's border posts registered 221,968 visitors.
On the other hand, the 23rd of February had the biggest year-on-year increase in visitors among the nine days of celebration, with an increase of 14.6% compared to the corresponding date of the previous year.
The data released yesterday by DST also shows the number of arrivals of tourists from the interior of China, which represent around 78% of total visitors. The daily average of 133,990 people reveals an increase of 7.2% compared to last year – with particular emphasis on Chinese New Year's Day, February 17th, when the number of tourist arrivals from the mainland rose 16% compared to 2025.
Visitors to Hong Kong showed the opposite trend, with a year-on-year decline of 3.5% to 27,878 daily visitors. Even so, there were 37,045 entries on the 21st, a Saturday, which means a year-on-year increase of 40.9%.
This year's numbers fit into the forecasts made by the authorities, although they do not exceed them. At the beginning of the month, the director of DST, Helena de Senna Fernandes, had estimated that between 1.4 and 1.5 million visitors should enter Macau over the nine holiday days, which would mean a daily average of 158 thousand to 175 thousand visitors.
Chinese New Year 2025 lasted eight days, between January 28th and February 3rd, and saw the arrival of almost 1.31 million visitors, totaling a daily average of around 163,700 people. It is worth remembering that the number of visitors received during the New Year of the Snake celebrations was lower than expected, with a drop of 3.5% compared to the same period in 2024.
Chinese New Year is one of three peak seasons for Macau's tourism and casinos, along with the golden weeks of Labor Day and Chinese National Day.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 00:27:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese NGO asks the Public Ministry to independently investigate the complaint against Myanmar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/ong-timorense-pede-ao-ministerio-publico-investigacao-independente-a-queixa-contra-o-myanmar/</link><description>The Timorese non-governmental organization La’o Hamutuk yesterday asked the Public Ministry to carry out an independent investigation into the criminal complaint filed against the Myanmar military and asked the political authorities to respect the separation of powers.

“The investigation process must be autonomous and professional, in accordance with applicable legal procedures and standards of evidence”, can be read in an open letter, released to the press.
La’o Hamutuk emphasizes that the “preliminary assessment is a normal step to determine whether there is sufficient legal basis to proceed to subsequent stages, and is essential to impartially protect the rights of victims and suspects”.
The Timorese NGO also asked political authorities to avoid influencing judicial processes. "Public statements must be made with caution so as not to create negative perceptions about the case. Respect for the separation of powers between the executive and judicial branches reinforces public trust and protects the credibility of the rule of law", says La'o Hamutuk.
Timorese Prime Minister, Xanana Gusmão, said last week that he hopes that judicial authorities, such as the court or the Public Ministry of Timor-Leste, will close the case related to crimes that occurred in Myanmar. "If they make a decision, we respect it. We also say that justice is a matter for justice itself. But we feel that we do not have the competence to judge events that occurred in another country. Therefore, we hope that the court or the Public Prosecutor's Office will close the case", said Xanana Gusmão.
On February 3, the CHRO – which represents the Chin minority, who live in northwestern Myanmar, along the border with India and Bangladesh – announced that the East Timor Public Prosecutor's Office had initiated legal proceedings against the military junta. “We welcome this initiative and look forward to collaborating with the Timorese authorities, as well as civil society groups in Timor-Leste, to promote justice for the Chin people and all peoples of Myanmar,” said CHRO director Salai Za Uk.
Two weeks earlier, the organization had filed a criminal complaint with the Public Ministry of Timor-Leste against a group of military personnel from that country for war crimes and crimes against humanity.
According to Timorese lawyers, who represent the CHRO, crimes against humanity are covered by article 124 of the Penal Code and war crimes are also classified in the Penal Code in article 125 (war crime against people), crimes involving the use of prohibited methods of war (article 126) and war crimes against property.
This was the first time that a member of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) initiated an action of this type against a member state of the organization itself.
Both Timor-Leste and Myanmar are members of ASEAN, the organization that suspended the former Burma, following the February 2021 coup, when the military overthrew the Government led by Aung San Suu Kyi, Nobel Peace Prize winner, and plunged the country into civil war.
Data released by a Chin State human rights organization indicates that the military junta carried out more than 1,000 air strikes in that region, which caused the death of 478 civilians, including 91 women and 79 children, and destroyed several health units, schools and religious buildings. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:47:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Executive once again rejects entry of dogs on Macau beaches</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/executivo-volta-a-rejeitar-entrada-de-caes-nas-praias-de-macau/</link><description>The Government rejected the review of the measure that prohibits the entry of dogs on Macau's beaches, arguing that the presence of animals in these spaces could present environmental and health risks.
The information comes in response to a written question from deputy Chan Hao Weng, in which he pointed out the incompatibility between the prohibition of dogs on beaches and the Animal Protection Law in force in the territory. According to the law, domestic animals can enter public spaces in Macau as long as they are properly accompanied by the owner and respect the mandatory use of a leash.
Regarding potential public health threats, the deputy recalled that vaccination is mandatory, as is the use of a leash and the disposal of waste by guardians.
In response to the points raised by the deputy, the chairman of the Board of Directors for Municipal Affairs, Chao Wai Ieng, says that “the beach is an important public leisure space in Macau, and it is essential to keep it clean and ensure good order in the area”. Therefore, “the presence of dogs or other animals on beaches may pose risks to the safety of citizens and visitors, and their waste may affect environmental and sanitary conditions”.
The official emphasizes that the rules of conduct on beaches aim to maintain a clean and orderly environment, and that the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) will continue to monitor the situation and review the relevant rules “based on the needs of beach users, safety and environmental hygiene”.
Chan Hao Weng's interpellation also mentioned the need to improve public infrastructure so that they increasingly allow the presence of pets and the coexistence between different species. Regarding this point, the chairman of the Board of Directors for Municipal Affairs indicates that there are 17 areas designated for dog walking in Macau, in addition to several green areas in gardens and parks where citizens can circulate with their pets.
In turn, stray animals that roam these areas are sent to the Municipal Kennel, where they will undergo examinations and be made available for adoption if they are “healthy and calm”. Chao Wai Ieng details that, over the past year, 523 dogs and cats were claimed or adopted by Macau residents.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:50:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Photography by Lúcia Lemos on display at Creative Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/fotografia-de-lucia-lemos-em-exposicao-na-creative-macau/</link><description>The exhibition “A White Diamond” opens on March 5th at Creative Macau, which brings together photographs taken by Lúcia Lemos at Casa da Música in Porto. The exhibition will be on display until March 28th.
Lúcia Lemos is an award-winning multidisciplinary visual artist whose black and white photographs have been exhibited in solo exhibitions held in Berkeley, Curitiba, Lisbon, Monza, Palermo, Porto, Salzburg and Shanghai, as well as Macau. Lúcia Lemos has also participated in group exhibitions with her video works, engravings, jewelry, ceramics, sculpture and artistic installations. The artist “expresses her creativity by applying organic materials in other artistic languages ​​to convey her thoughts”, states Creative's press release sent to the newsrooms yesterday.
In a statement, Lúcia Lemos explains that photographing with black and white film exerts an “uncontrollable fascination for the tiny moment between framing and shooting” – “a sudden and indecipherable happiness invades me”.
The focus of this exhibition is Casa da Música, in Porto. "The magnificent Casa da Música in Porto awakened in me an exceptional curiosity to photograph it on film. In 2006, I stopped in front of that huge diamond-shaped building, made of white cement, and took some photos with my old Rolleiflex. Under the intense sunlight, its white structure, surrounded by dark three-story granite houses from the beginning of the 20th century, illuminates all sides, glorifying the city. This makes the Casa da Música even more resplendent", says the artist mentioned in the statement, also adding that she was able to photograph the interior of the building, which left her “dazzled by its luminosity”. This project “allows handcrafted Portuguese materials, glass and tiles, to come to life in a minimalist architectural structure, providing a beautiful and luminous symbiosis between tradition and modernity”.
In this exhibition, Lúcia Lemos shows some images of the exterior of this “incomparable and incredible diamond, built in Portugal specifically for music, which generated extreme controversy at the time and is now loved by citizens”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Public tender launched to explore parking meters</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/arrancou-concurso-publico-para-explorar-parquimetros/</link><description>The public tender for the concession of the operation of parking spaces on public roads began yesterday, informed the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT).
The term of this concession is seven years, being operated by a single concessionary entity that must provide multiple payment methods and a dedicated application and corresponding system, “in order to reinforce the management and intelligent development of metered parking spaces in Macau, allowing drivers to pay and use the metered parking service more conveniently”, say the authorities.
The public tender also requires the concessionary entity to simultaneously provide local and non-local electronic means of payment, including Simple Pay, credit cards, electronic purses, among others; the acquisition and installation of vehicle detection sensors in all parking spaces with parking meters for light and heavy vehicles in Macau; public consultation on the status of use of metered parking spaces and support for remote payment, through the creation of a specific mobile application and website. Furthermore, the concessionary entity must fully bear the costs of purchasing and installing a charging system to replace the current charging system and equipment.
Interested companies must submit their application documents to the DSAT Public Relations Division by 5pm on April 10th. The opening of proposals will take place on April 13th. DSAT will then carry out the evaluation and award based on the value proposed by the competitors, the implementation plan for the charging system and hardware and software equipment, the deadline for carrying out the works, additional projects for operating the public parking service, the personnel plan and relevant experience in the activity. Competitors must be companies based in Macau that carry out parking management and operation activities, participation in the form of a consortium contract is not permitted.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:51:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Li Aixiao explores human connections at Armazém do Boi</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/li-aixiao-explora-as-conexoes-humanas-no-armazem-do-boi/</link><description>Who inhabits our meeting? In a city made of passages, traffic and fleeting encounters, the question “who am I with?” takes on an almost philosophical dimension. It is this question that runs through the exhibition “Who Am I With: Li Aixiao”, on display at Armazém do Boi (formerly Estábulo Municipal) until March 15. Chinese artist Li Aixiao presents the result of her artistic residency in Macau, carried out within the scope of the “2+0/1+1” program in 2025, in a work that starts from the “self” to delve into the life, language and objects of others.
The exhibition, curated by Wendy Wong, is part of a triad of exhibitions that Armazém do Boi opened on February 13th, all the result of artistic residencies held the previous year. But Li Aixiao's work is distinguished by the performative and relational nature of his research. Using photography, performance and direct interaction, the artist does not limit herself to observing the other, but places herself in a situation of encounter, proximity and also distance, exploring the tension between what is established and what remains to be established in a relationship.
The COVID-19 pandemic, as the artist herself reveals, was a turning point in her practice. In a world forced to distance, Li Aixiao felt the urgency to look for new ways of (re)connection. This impulse is now reflected in Macau, in an urban context that is particularly fertile for these issues. A territory of migration, cultural overlaps and often provisional ties, the city functions as a laboratory for the central question of the exhibition: who do we really connect with and how do we do it?
The Armazém do Boi residency program, which is supported by the Fund for Cultural Development and the Cultural Institute, serves as a platform for contemporary artistic exchange.
In addition to this exhibition, the space also hosts “O Viajante da Montagem”, by Liao Yu-An, and “Waste: Soup Without Water”, by Zhu Biyi, both also resulting from residencies. Together, the three exhibitions offer an expansive panorama of identity, memory and relationship with the territory. Until March 15th, Armazém do Boi, at the intersection of Avenida do Coronel Mesquita and Avenida Almirante Lacerda, is open to anyone who wants to think, through art, about the connections that inhabit (us). Entry is free.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>South Korea records a 6% increase in births, but continues to age</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/coreia-do-sul-regista-subida-de-6-nos-nascimentos-mas-continua-a-envelhecer/</link><description>South Korea yesterday announced an increase of more than 6% in the number of births in 2025, but the fertility rate remains below the minimum necessary to halt population decline.
According to official data released by the South Korean Ministry of Data and Statistics, the number of births grew for the second year in a row and recorded the largest annual increase since 2010.
As a result, South Korea's fertility rate, that is, the average number of children per woman, rose slightly, from 0.75 to 0.8. A value that remains below the minimum of 2.1 needed to maintain South Korea's current population.
The director of the ministry's demographic trends division, Park Hyun-jeong, said the increasing number of marriages in South Korea played an important role in this trend.
South Korea has one of the lowest fertility rates in the world. The Government has spent billions of euros to encourage women to have more children, with little success so far.
According to several projections, at the current rate, South Korea's population will increase from the current 51 million to almost half, 26.8 million, by the end of the century.
Experts say there are several reasons for South Korea's low birth rate, including the high cost of raising children and a competitive economy that makes it difficult to access well-paying jobs.
In early February, the mayor of Jindo (southwest), Kim Hee-soo, sparked controversy by suggesting that rural communities could combat demographic decline by attracting women from Vietnam or Sri Lanka.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:47:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Government wants airlines to provide more flights and open new routes from Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/governo-quer-que-companhias-aereas-disponibilizem-mais-voos-e-abram-novas-rotas-a-partir-de-macau/</link><description>The Government and Society of Macau International Airport (CAM) are planning to launch more attractive policies to encourage airlines to increase the frequency of their flights, open new routes from Macau or operate non-scheduled flights. The authorities specify that the objective is to reinforce air links with the interior of China and Southeast and Northeast Asia.

The Government and Society of Macau International Airport (CAM) want to strengthen the territory's air links with the interior of China and Southeast and Northeast Asia. To this end, current incentive measures are being reviewed and new policies are being planned to encourage airlines to increase the frequency of their flights, open new routes or operate non-scheduled flights.
The information was transmitted by the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM) in response to a written question from deputy Kou Ngon Seng, who asked for details on the Government's measures to promote the development of the region's civil aviation sector.
The nominated deputy questioned what concrete mechanisms and criteria would be adopted by the Government in the regulation of the public tender for the granting of licenses for commercial air transport of passengers, “in order to ensure the healthy and orderly development of the civil aviation sector, while liberalizing the market”. The AACM pointed out that, “currently, the air transport sector in Macau is still in a recovery phase”, and “the introduction of new passenger airlines based in Macau is directly related to the healthy development of the entire sector”.
Therefore, “relevant decisions must take into account the macroeconomic environment and the aviation recovery process”. The Government considers that, “as soon as the necessary conditions are met, a prudent decision will be taken on the timing and scale of issuing licenses, ensuring that the liberalization regime corresponds to the industry's support capacity”.
Still with regard to measures to stimulate the sector, the AACM also detailed that it has already reviewed the clauses of the air transport agreements in force and has started negotiations with the aeronautical authorities of the main destinations, “in order to make the clauses of the relevant agreements more flexible, creating greater freedom for airlines to increase the number of flights or open new routes”.
Kou Ngon Seng also asked what concrete measures the Government has to promote the construction of the Macau International Air Transport hub (Port) on the West bank of the Pearl River, one of the Government's major projects for the coming years. The authorities responded that the main projects in this area consist of the expansion of the airport and the construction of the Upstream cargo terminal in Hengqin, which are being implemented “in an orderly manner”. “In the future, these infrastructures will support the operation of cargo airlines, reinforcing the competitiveness of Macau International Airport in the region”, states the AACM response.
The authorities also said that a company has already formally submitted an application for an Air Cargo Operator Certificate to the AACM, and the respective approval process has already begun. “This demonstrates a positive response from investors to the opening policy, with the air freight transport industry expected to continue to develop”, reads the response.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:58:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Proposal to increase maternity leave has already received 8,000 opinions, mostly favorable</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/proposta-de-aumento-da-licenca-de-maternidade-ja-recolheu-8-000-opinioes-maioritariamente-favoraveis/</link><description>The Government has already received more than 8,000 views from the public on the proposed increase in maternity leave and annual leave, with the predominant opinion supporting the changes. The public consultation ends on March 16. The Directorate of Labor Affairs Services revealed that in the opinions collected, residents ask for a more flexible use of maternity leave days and an even greater increase in annual leave.

Public consultation on increasing maternity leave and annual leave is ongoing and the Government has already received more than 8,000 opinions on the proposal. The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) said that the predominant opinion received so far shows “support” and a “positive stance” for the legislative changes.
Chan Un Tong, director of DSAL, also indicated that he had organized, so far, three opinion consultation sessions that were attended by more than 300 people. Speaking yesterday on the morning program “Forum Macau” on the Chinese channel Radio Macau, the official added that two additional public consultation sessions will be held, tomorrow and on March 7th, and that the public consultation period ends on March 16th, hoping to hear more opinions and suggestions from all sectors of society on the content of the law review.
Remember that the Executive proposes to increase the number of days of paid maternity leave, from 70 days to 90 days, and that annual leave be increased by seniority, adding 1 working day to the number of annual leave days for every 2 completed years of service, up to a maximum of 12 working days.
The Government highlighted that the proposed changes to the Labor Relations Law aim to “continuously optimize the guarantee of labor rights and interests, so that workers can find a better balance between work and family life”.
Chan Un Tong, on the radio program, revealed that the feedback received raised concerns about whether maternity leave days could be taken early.
As proposed, of the 90 days of maternity leave, 60 days of leave must be taken immediately after birth, with the remaining 30 days being able to be taken, in whole or in part, before or after birth, at the worker's decision. The Government considers that the new measure can offer “more flexibility in taking maternity leave”.
In other opinions presented, residents asked to further increase the basic entitlement of six days of annual vacation and the maximum limit of vacation days, in addition to requesting other improvements to labor policies.
As Chan Un Tong explained, if the proposed legislative changes come into effect, employees' years of service would be taken into account when calculating annual leave, meaning that those with 12 years of service would be entitled to 12 days of annual leave per year. “Through this public consultation, we hope to achieve a balance and consensus between workers’ rights, financial accessibility for companies and social development, thus promoting harmonious labor relations”, he stressed.

SUBSIDY TO COMPANIES
 
The Government's consultation document, on the other hand, suggests continuing the supplementary subsidy to the remuneration paid during maternity leave, with which the Government grants small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) a subsidy of up to 20 days in relation to workers taking maternity leave, but only for residents.
In this case, a resident who called the program yesterday argued that the subsidy should be extended from 20 to 30 days, and it would also be more reasonable for the scheme to become a permanent measure. Chan Un Tong, in response, highlighted that the first edition of this temporary subsidy program was aimed at allowing companies to gradually assume responsibility for paying maternity leave. The second round was introduced to help businesses as it was still during the height of the pandemic.
The director assured that the authorities have already considered the impact of extending maternity leave on SMEs, which is why the proposed legislative change suggests increasing the allowance to a maximum of 20 days. “Employers, as central entities in labor relations, must assume social responsibilities”, argues the person in charge.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:56:47</pubDate></item><item><title>IMF urges China to prioritize consumption-led growth</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/fmi-insta-china-a-priorizar-crescimento-liderado-pelo-consumo/</link><description>The International Monetary Fund (IMF) yesterday called on China to make the transition to a growth model based on consumption a “central priority”, also urging Beijing to reduce an “unjustified industrial policy”, in the face of growing external imbalances. The recommendations of the IMF technical team, released before the annual meetings of the National People's Congress (China's highest legislative body), reinforce calls for economic rebalancing, especially after the record trade surplus recorded by China last year has intensified global concerns. “China needs to move decisively towards consumption-led growth,” said Sonali Jain-Chandra, head of the IMF mission for China, cited by the Hong Kong newspaper South China Morning Post. The official added that the IMF positively welcomes the emphasis given to consumption in the proposals of the 15th Five-Year Plan and in the statement from the December Central Economic Work Conference, which defined the priorities for the year.
In the annual report on the Chinese economy – the so-called consultation under Article IV – the IMF advocates a more robust fiscal stimulus to boost consumption and alleviate weaknesses in the real estate sector, along with greater social protection, new monetary relief and greater exchange rate flexibility. “The consumption-led growth model must be the central priority”, highlighted the IMF executive board, adding that an expansionist orientation must be maintained until deflationary pressures diminish on a lasting basis. The report considers that the measures adopted so far “remain insufficient given the scale of the challenges” and recommends an additional budgetary expansion equivalent to 0.8% of GDP in 2026, compared to the base scenario.
The IMF projects that Chinese economic growth will slow to 4.5% in 2026, after expanding 5% last year. The statements come before the so-called “two sessions”, the annual meetings of China's legislative and consultative bodies, at which announcements on growth and inflation targets, the budget deficit and public debt issuance quotas are expected. In the same statement, the executive directors of the IMF highlighted the need to “reduce unjustified industrial policy to reduce the misallocation of internal resources, reduce budgetary costs and mitigate external effects”. The Fund welcomed the Chinese campaign against so-called “involution” – excessive competition between sectors – but called for stronger incentives to contain excess investment by local governments.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:47:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai says that the cause of gender equality in Macau is “one of the most advanced in the world”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/sam-hou-fai-diz-que-a-causa-da-igualdade-entre-os-sexos-em-macau-e-das-mais-avancadas-do-mundo/</link><description>In connection with International Women's Day, marked on March 8, Sam Hou Fai gave a speech in which he highlighted the evolution of women's rights in Macau since the transfer of sovereignty, considering that equality between the sexes in the territory is “among the most advanced in the world”. According to the Chief Executive, future plans for the cause of women in Macau include a “healthy vision” of ideals such as romance, marriage, family and motherhood.
 
The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, was present yesterday at a reception organized by the Macau General Women's Association to commemorate International Women's Day. The Government leader praised the continued progress of the women's cause in Macau and assured that measures will continue to be launched for a more egalitarian and inclusive social environment, with an emphasis on promoting “healthy views on romance, marriage and family”.
At the opening of his speech, Sam Hou Fai highlighted that “the cause of women in Macau has entered an important phase of great development and prosperity” since the return to the Motherland in 1999, with the legal protection of their rights and the growing participation of women in political affairs and the job market. “Gender equality in Macau consistently remains among the most advanced in the world”, he states, highlighting that “the notable successes” achieved in the region contribute to “promoting the development of the cause of women throughout the world”.
Sam Hou Fai guarantees that the current Government “gives great importance to the development of women's causes”, as evidenced by the various maternity support policies launched recently. Examples include the birth allowance, recently increased to 6,500 patacas; the “Child Care Subsidy Plan”, which benefited around 15 thousand people in 2025; the “Medical Assisted Procreation Treatment Participation Program” at Macau Union Hospital; and the “Health Management Platform for Pregnant and Postpartum Women”.
The Chief Executive also highlights the role played by the Macau General Women's Association in uniting and mobilizing the territory's female population. “Since its founding, the association has remained aligned with the themes and tasks of the time linked to the development of the country and the MSAR, and, guided by the fundamental objective of serving women and the population of Macau in general, it has made extraordinary contributions to the development of the women's cause”, he praised.
As Macau develops and progresses, the approach of social service associations must also be updated. Thus, Sam Hou Fai presents “four expectations” for the new phase of the association, in order to “implement work in favor of women in the best way”. Firstly, he says, it is essential that the group continues to “energetically present opinions and suggestions that take into account the level of social development in Macau”, such as studies and investigations on topics related to the increase in the birth rate and the improvement of family support policies.
Secondly, the Chief Executive calls for the promotion of “love for the country and for Macau”, through the maintenance of “exemplary conduct and image” and the training of young talents made up of “suitable and competent people”. In addition to “serving the population in an attentive and meticulous manner”, the association must also “collaborate in improving the efficiency of Macau’s governance”.
The third point presented by the government official relates to the innovation of working methods, in order to “unite and guide the women's sector”. The aim here is to reconcile modernity – for example, artificial intelligence technologies – with “traditional Chinese family culture”, characterized by values ​​and “healthy views” on romance, marriage, family and, “especially”, motherhood.
Fourth and finally, and remembering that the Macao SAR is a signatory to several International Conventions on women and children, Sam Hou Fai hopes that the Women's Association will intensify participation in international and regional cooperation mechanisms. From Macau and Hengqin and to the international level, including the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, the leader of the Executive hopes that the association will help to “constantly deepen exchange and mutual learning, promoting a dynamic of shared prosperity, projecting Macau's voice abroad and telling China's story well”.
Sam Hou Fai concluded his speech with a reflection on the future, ensuring that the Government will reinforce its support for development and the defense of women's “legitimate rights and interests”. “We will increase resource allocation and investment for women and children, creating a more equal, inclusive and respectful social environment for women's development”, he concluded.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:57:28</pubDate></item><item><title>National Security: restriction on the choice of lawyers “does not affect the procedural rights” of defendants</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/seguranca-nacional-restricao-de-escolha-de-advogados-nao-afecta-direito-processual-de-arguidos/</link><description>Verifying the suitability of lawyers to participate in national security cases “will not have an impact” on their professional qualifications or on the procedural rights of interested parties, indicates the Government in its assessment of the proposed law for the Commission for the Defense of State Security, a body that will have binding power to decide whether or not a lawyer is able to defend the accused.

The Government denies possible negative impacts on the procedural rights of defendants in national security cases, despite the future law on the Commission for the Defense of State Security (CDSE) in the Macao SAR may prevent intervention in legal proceedings by lawyers who do not pass the authorities' assessment. “The verification carried out by the CDSE of lawyers' requests to participate in national security legal proceedings [...] does not compromise the safeguarding of the rights of those interested in the cases”, said the Executive, quoted by Leong Sun Iok, president of the 3rd Standing Committee of the Legislative Assembly, as reported by the Ou Mun newspaper. “If the lawyer chosen by the defendant does not pass the evaluation, the defendant continues to have the full right to hire other legal representation”, he explained.
The Permanent Committee yesterday began the analysis and discussion, in particular, of the CDSE law proposal. In the Government's opinion, even when the accused cannot choose a lawyer independently, the competent authorities will appoint or designate legal representatives in accordance with current legislation, which “fully safeguards procedural rights”.
The CDSE bill was generally approved unanimously by the AL two weeks ago. The diploma provides that, in cases of national security, judicial representatives must obtain special authorization from the competent judge before intervening in the process. The CDSE will issue a binding opinion to decide whether or not the lawyer can defend the accused, and that there will be no complaint or contentious appeal.
On this matter, according to Leong Sun Iok, the Government said that the CDSE's verification of their participation in relevant cases constitutes “just a case analysis”, but not an assessment of their professional qualifications. “Consequently, it will not affect the eligibility of lawyers to practice their profession in the Macao SAR as provided for in current legislation, nor will it have an impact on their participation in other legal proceedings”, he insisted.
The requirement for special authorization granted to lawyers to intervene in a procedural act will apply in cases where the competent judicial authority considers there to be a need to “protect the interests of State security”.
In the respective application, the lawyer will have to provide information regarding household members, nationality and connection with organizations or individuals abroad. The proposed law does not establish the criteria to be used by the CDSE to decide whether or not a lawyer is able to defend the accused.
On the other hand, the provision regarding hearings in the law stipulates that, when the competent judge considers that an open process would harm the interests of national security, certain procedural acts can be carried out behind closed doors.
Asked on the sidelines of the Standing Committee meeting about how the public can witness judicial impartiality if the trial is not public, Leong Sun Iok did not express a position, stating only that these details were not yet discussed at yesterday's meeting, but would be addressed in subsequent meetings with the Government.
Leong Sun Iok, when summarizing the discussion content of the proposed law, highlighted that the CDSE will have reinforced competencies and powers after the approval of this proposed law, which will allow “to strengthen the standardized and institutionalized defenses that safeguard national security”. “National security is no longer limited to traditional military domains, but will also encompass the economic, cultural and educational spheres,” noted Leong, pointing to the need to expand the composition of the CDSE to strengthen the Macao SAR’s capacity to defend State security.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:56:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai considers that the first year of the Executive ran smoothly, stable and innovatively</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/sam-hou-fai-considera-que-o-primeiro-ano-do-executivo-decorreu-de-forma-suave-estavel-e-inovadora/</link><description>The Chief Executive received, on Monday night, Macau's deputies to the National People's Assembly (NPC) and Macau's members of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC). On the occasion, Sam Hou Fai took the opportunity to praise the work carried out by his Government.

Sam Hou Fai received, on Monday night, Macau's deputies to the National People's Congress (NPC) and Macau's members of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC). In his speech given on the occasion, the Chief Executive said that “governmental work for this year is progressing steadily” and that the Macao SAR’s third five-year plan “is under intensive preparation”.
The Chief Executive said he hopes that APN deputies and CPPCC members “will contribute insightful opinions to help Macau open new horizons and reach new heights, promoting all projects to a new level”.
Sam also took the opportunity to praise the Government led by him, saying that “Macau's economic and social development has progressed stably” and that “the main objectives of governance have basically been achieved”.
In the Chief's opinion, “the Executive's first year went smoothly, stable, innovative, with achievements and positive results, marking a good start”. Sam stressed that these “successes” are “inseparable from the strong support and commitment of APN deputies and CPPCC members”.
Xi Jinping's words were not forgotten and Sam made three requests to NPC deputies and CPPCC members in line with the Chinese President's ideas: first, “guide with ideas to create consensus”. In this regard, the Chief expects APN deputies and members of the CPPCC to “expand the forms and deepen the content of exchange and interaction with residents, effectively strengthen unity and ties, fully play the role of bridge, connection, focus on the concerns of the population, convey public opinion and social aspirations”.
Secondly, Sam warned APN deputies and CPPCC members that they enjoy “recognized prestige, with a wide network of contacts”, therefore, “every word and action of theirs has influence and serves as an example”. The Chief expects them to “actively play a leadership role in their professional career, firmly defend the institutional arrangement of the predominance of the Executive Branch, and, taking into account the two main axes, the development of adequate diversification of the economy and the reform of Public Administration, support and collaborate with the Macao SAR Government in governing according to the law, and jointly promote the integrated development between Macau and Hengqin”. “When it comes to questions of principle, you need to be unequivocal and firm in your position”, he stressed.
The third request is for those responsible at the APN and CPPCC to present “opinions and suggestions with a sense of duty”, participate in “national affairs” and fulfill the “duties inherent to the position, it is an honor, but above all a responsibility”.
The Two National Sessions will soon be held and therefore Sam Hou Fai hopes that the APN deputies and members of the CPPCC will serve the country “with dedication and fulfilling their responsibilities towards the people, telling the truth and presenting frank opinions with constructive proposals”, in order to “fully demonstrate Macau’s sense of mission, wisdom and strength”.
Regarding the Year of the Horse, the Chief Executive stated that the Government will “unite and lead all sectors of society to deeply implement the spirit enshrined in President Xi Jinping's important speeches”. It will also actively coordinate with the country's 15th Five-Year Plan, prepare and implement the Macao SAR's 3rd Five-Year Plan well; “persist and improve the predominance of the Executive Branch”, “firmly defend national security and social stability, pragmatically promote the development of adequate diversification of the economy”; promote the construction of the Deep Cooperation Zone, concentrate efforts on promoting the “strengthening of the forces of love for the country and Macau and effectively increase the efficiency of the governance of the Macao SAR Government”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 00:27:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotel occupancy rate was 95.6% on Chinese New Year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/taxa-de-ocupacao-hoteleira-foi-de-956-no-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>The average occupancy rate of hotel establishments in Macau reached 95.6% during the golden week of Chinese New Year this year, between 15 and 23 February. The highest occupancy rate was recorded on February 20th, the fourth day of celebration of the Year of the Horse, with an almost total occupancy of 99.2%.
In a statement released yesterday, the Tourism Services Department (DST) also states that the Macau Grand Prix Museum received more than 10 thousand visitors during this celebratory period, an increase of 17.4% compared to the same period in 2025.
The peak in attendance will be related to the activity “Horses at Full Steam, Fortune at a Gallop”, held between the 17th and 23rd of February, in which visitors were able to produce couplets alluding to the Chinese New Year and ‘lai si’ envelopes. Furthermore, the museum remained open to the public on February 17th, not closing as usual on Tuesdays.
DST explains that it prepared for the golden week tourist influx by sending letters to tourism authorities in mainland China, with relevant information about activities taking place throughout the festive period, and by organizing meetings with local tour operators.
Security at border posts and tourist attractions was also reinforced, with 196 inspections carried out. In turn, visitors directly submitted 30 complaints to DST, most of them related to hotel reservations, room hygiene, service provision attitude and two complaints from residents about illegal provision of accommodation.</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:50:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong predicts end of deficit wave and economic growth of up to 3.5%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/hong-kong-preve-fim-de-vaga-deficitaria-e-crescimento-economico-de-ate-35/</link><description>Hong Kong's economy is expected to grow by up to 3.5% on the back of the return of a budget surplus, after three years of deficit, the region's Finance Secretary announced yesterday.

Hong Kong's economy was "on the rise" in 2025, with foreign trade remaining strong, private consumption recovering and fixed investment accelerating, said Paul Chan during the presentation of the budget for 2026, cited by the news portal Hong Kong Free Press (HKFP).
The person responsible for Finance predicted growth of 2.5% to 3.5% in the economy of the special administrative region in the current fiscal year (1 April 2025 to 31 March 2026). "In the medium term, protectionism will persist in some major economies, while the fragmentation of the global economy will continue. However, the rise of the Global South and the reshaping of the global trade and investment landscape will unlock new markets and new areas of growth", assessed the secretary, also according to HKFP.
Paul Chan also announced that the surplus in the 2025-26 fiscal year ends a three-year run of budget deficits. Driven by demand for electronic products, Hong Kong's exports of goods grew 12%, with notable increases in exports to mainland China and the countries of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), the portal wrote.
Also according to the HKFP, the city in southern China recorded a deficit of 80.3 billion Hong Kong dollars in the 2024-25 fiscal year, 101.6 billion Hong Kong dollars in 2023-24 and 122 billion in 2022-23.
The stock market presented an “excellent performance”, according to the person in charge. The Hang Seng index rose 28% over the year, while initial public offerings (IPO) raised 280 billion Hong Kong dollars, ranking first globally.
When presenting the budget, the Finance Secretary also stated that the Government is committed to attracting more companies to set up shop in the region.
Policy instruments, including land concession agreements, financial subsidies and tax incentives, will be implemented to promote industries and investment, he announced, according to public broadcaster RTHK [Radio Television Hong Kong].
The Hong Kong finance chief also highlighted the importance of increasing support for mainland Chinese companies that are expanding into international markets.
Another area of ​​focus, said Paul Chan, is to further promote Hong Kong as an international convention and exhibition center, with 100 million Hong Kong dollars being set aside to attract large-scale international exhibitions with new elements.
The broadcaster also reported that Paul Chan announced that he will chair the new “Committee on AI+ and Industry Development Strategy” as part of the work to ensure that all sectors of society understand and use artificial intelligence. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:48:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Friedrich Merz defends a more “fair” relationship with China in Beijing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/friedrich-merz-defende-em-pequim-relacao-mais-justa-com-a-china/</link><description>German Chancellor Friedrich Merz defended fairer cooperation with China yesterday in Beijing, at the start of a visit to Germany's main trading partner, increasingly seen in his country as a strong competitor.

“We have very concrete concerns regarding our cooperation, which we want to improve and make fairer,” said Merz at the start of talks with Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang at the Great Hall of the People in central Beijing.
The head of the Chinese Government called on Germany to work towards “jointly defending multilateralism and free trade”.
Merz, who arrived mid-morning with a large business delegation, met yesterday with the Chinese President, Xi Jinping, in what is his first visit to China since taking office in 2025. The chancellor stated that he sees “great growth potential” for two of the largest economies in the world, highlighting, however, the need for an “open” dialogue.
Before the match, Merz indicated that he intended to address several issues of divergence, such as competition rules, access to markets and security of supply of rare earths, essential raw materials for many German companies and whose production is dominated by China.
The German official also wants to discuss the war in Ukraine, counting on Beijing's good relations with Moscow. “Beijing’s voice is heard, even in Moscow,” he declared.
Merz is the latest foreign leader to travel to Beijing, at a time when US President Donald Trump has shaken up the international order with new tariffs and the review of old alliances. “Today, China has become unavoidable for everyone,” said Merz on Tuesday.
In the last three months, leaders from the United Kingdom, Finland, Canada, South Korea, Ireland or France have visited Beijing. At the same time, German industry faces increasing pressure from Chinese competition. Europe's largest economy, heavily dependent on exports and for years supported by the vast Chinese market, has seen its car manufacturers' sales decline significantly in China and is increasingly facing Chinese technological competition on a global level.
Like other European Union partners, Germany expresses concern about the expansion of Chinese electric vehicles and the flow of Chinese production surpluses to Europe.
Berlin also warns of Beijing's use of semiconductors and rare earths as instruments in the global trade dispute, as happened in 2025, severely affecting supply chains, particularly in the automotive industry. “We want and must adopt a risk reduction policy, not just in relation to China”, stated Merz, stressing, however, that it would be a mistake to associate this strategy with economic decoupling.
Germany and other countries criticize the restrictions on access to the Chinese market, the subsidies considered undue and the alleged undervaluation of the Chinese currency.
Xi Jinping has presented China as a reliable partner and defender of multilateralism and free trade, promoting a “win-win” relationship based on “mutual respect”. In 2025, China was engaged in an intense trade and diplomatic dispute with the United States under the presidency of Trump, whose visit to Beijing is scheduled for the end of March.
Merz traveled accompanied by the CEOs of Volkswagen, BMW and Mercedes. This Thursday, he will attend the presentation of autonomous vehicles by Mercedes and will then travel to Hangzhou, a technology hub, to visit the robotics group Unitree and the company Siemens Energy.
Last year, Germany's trade deficit with China increased by more than 22 billion euros, reaching around 89 billion euros. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-25 23:48:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Outdoor Entertainment Zone will open basketball courts soon</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/25/zona-de-espectaculos-ao-ar-livre-vai-inaugurar-campos-de-basquetebol-em-breve/</link><description>The Outdoor Entertainment Zone will have basketball courts in the first quarter of this year, revealed the Cultural Institute (IC) in response to a written inquiry. The initiative aims to maximize the advantages of the venue, allowing it to be reused for other purposes during periods of inactivity between concerts.

It will be possible to play basketball in the Outdoor Entertainment Zone, in Cotai, in the first quarter of this year. The sports fields will have equipment such as umbrellas and drinking water facilities, in addition to increased security.
The information was provided by the president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Leong Wai Man, in response to a written question from deputy Wong Kit Cheng. In the message she sent to the Government, the deputy linked to the General Women's Association welcomed the initiative to transform the venue into an area open to citizens, during periods of inactivity, to carry out community activities. He regretted, however, the lack of sanitary facilities, sun protection or public transport alternatives other than the Light Rail.
Wong Kit Cheng also suggested that Macau take as a reference the models already applied in some of the parks in neighboring regions – such as Victoria Park, in Hong Kong, where it is possible to request the rental of just a part of the space to carry out medium-scale activities. In this scenario, groups that rent a certain area of ​​the venue “could benefit from tariff reductions, exemptions or discounts”, proposes the deputy.
In response, the president of the IC begins by guaranteeing that the performance venue in Cotai “will be progressively improved in terms of hardware and software installations, and also in terms of management proposals through interdepartmental collaboration”. One of the main optimization measures involves the aforementioned project of readapting the space for various purposes, such as sports fields and sporting activities for families.
“The objective is to increase the flexibility and overall efficiency of the use of the site”, explains Leong Wai Man, ensuring that the IC and the Sports Institute have maintained a first collaboration regarding “the preparation of usage plans and instructions, the improvement of complementary equipment, contingency strategies for events and concrete management proposals, among other matters”.
The first project consists of the implementation of 3×3 basketball courts, which should come into operation in the first quarter of this year – that is, by the end of March. The space will be reinforced with the installation of “seats, umbrellas, night lighting, drinking water facilities”, in addition to the deployment of “more workers to operate on site and ensure the safety of users”. Other short-term plans include opening the public tender for the operation of the venue in the middle of this year, with the new contractor expected to take over the operation from 2027.
Regarding the proposals presented in the written interpellation, Leong Wai Man states that the Government “continues to listen and welcome the opinions of all sectors of society”, which includes the “rental proposals and fee reductions and exemptions” mentioned by the deputy. “The Macao SAR Government hopes, through various measures, to maximize the functions and benefits of the performance venue, creating a complementarity of functions with the public performance spaces and event facilities of existing integrated tourism and leisure companies, in order to extend the economic benefits of events and shows”, concludes the president of the IC.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>