<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/coreia-do-norte-anuncia-teste-de-misseis-de-cruzeiro-antes-da-visita-de-trump-a-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Wong Kit Cheng, Ip Sio Kai and Leong Sun Iok will chair AL standing committees</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/wong-kit-cheng-ip-sio-kai-e-leong-sun-iok-vao-presidir-as-comissoes-permanentes-da-al/</link><description>Deputies chose, on Tuesday, the presidents and secretaries of the Legislative Assembly committees for this legislature. The vote determined that Wong Kit Cheng will chair the 1st standing committee, Ip Sio Kai the 2nd and Leong Sun Iok the 3rd. The chairman of the rules and mandates committee is Chui Sai Peng.

Wong Kit Cheng, Ip Sio Kai and Leong Sun Iok were elected by deputies to chair the 1st, 2nd and 3rd standing committees of the Legislative Assembly (AL). The vote took place on Tuesday, at the second plenary meeting of the hemicycle of this VIII legislature. On that occasion, the secretaries of each committee were also chosen: Nick Lei was elected secretary of the 1st permanent committee; Lam Lon Wai secretary of the 2nd standing committee; and Leong Hong Sai secretary of the 3rd standing committee.
The regulations and mandates committee will have Chui Sai Peng as president and Iau Teng Pio as secretary. The monitoring committee for public land and concessions matters will be chaired by Ella Lei and secretary by Joey Lao. Song Pek Kei was chosen as chairman of the monitoring committee for public finance matters and will have Ngan Iek Hang as secretary.
Finally, the monitoring committee for public administration matters will be chaired by Ma Chi Seng and will have Kou Kam Fai as secretary. Angela Leong was chosen for the position of chairman of the AL board of directors.
The members of each commission were previously proposed by the AL Board. In addition to Wong Kit Cheng and Nick Lei, the 1st permanent committee will include Chui Sai Peng, Lam Fat Iam, Lei Wun Kong, Che Sai Wang, Wong Chon Kit, Kevin Ho, Ella Lei and Joey Lao.
The 2nd standing commission of the AL will include Vong Hou Piu, Kou Ngon Seng, Lee Koi Ian, Chao Ka Chon, Chan Hao Weng, Wong Ka Lon, Song Pek Kei and Ngan Iek Hang, in addition to Ip Sio Kai and Lam Lon Wai.
The 3rd standing committee of the AL will be composed of 11 deputies: Leong Sun Iok, Leong Hong Sai, Si Ka Lon, Angela Leong, Pereira Coutinho, Leong Pou U, Iau Teng Pio, Chan Lai Kei, Loi I Weng, Ma Chi Seng and Kou Kam Fai.
The monitoring committee for public land and concessions matters will include Ella Lei, Joey Lao, Chui Sai Peng, Lam Fat Iam, Lei Wun Kong, Che Sai Wang, Wong Chon Kit, Kevin Ho, Wong Kit Cheng and Nick Lei.
The monitoring committee for public finance matters will have Song Pek Kei, Ngan Iek Hang, Vong Hou Piu, Kou Ngon Seng, Lee Koi Ian, Chao Ka Chon, Chan Hao Weng, Wong Ka Lon, Ip Sio Kai and Lam Lon Wai as members.
Finally, the monitoring committee for public administration matters will have the following deputies: Ma Chi Seng, Kou Kam Fai, Si Ka Lon, Angela Leong, Pereira Coutinho, Leong Pou U, Iau Teng Pio, Chan Lai Kei, Loi I Weng, Leong Sun Iok and Leong Hong Sai.
The Board also defined the seven deputies who will be part of the Rules and Mandates Committee: Chui Sai Peng, Iau Teng Pio, Lei Wun Kong, Angela Leong, Ip Sio Kai, Wong Kit Cheng and Song Pek Kei.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:42:54</pubDate></item><item><title>“100 Paredes” concert fills Dili Portuguese Cultural Center</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/concerto-100-paredes-enche-centro-cultural-portugues-de-dili/</link><description>The Jorge Sampaio Cultural Center of the Embassy of Portugal in Timor-Leste was filled twice to attend the “100 Paredes” concert, part of the “Paredes Experience” project, which takes Carlos Paredes' work to the world.

The project's tour, created as part of the centenary of Carlos Paredes' birth, began in São Tomé and Príncipe, passed through Guinea-Bissau and arrived in Timor-Leste on the 21st, where it will remain until Thursday, then heading to the United States.
"Starting this tour through the PALOP and now through Timor-Leste is having enormous intensity. They are incredibly generous people, artistically we are in paradise and it has been incredible", said André Varandas, on Monday at the end of the second concert in Dili, which, like the first, held on Saturday, was full of Portuguese and Timorese.
In Timor-Leste, the project carried out five initiatives including creative workshops with local communities, with Timorese musicians and artists and with the Portuguese School of Díli. "The result has been incredible. There were two wonderful concerts, a full room at the Cultural Center, it was incredibly beautiful", said André Varandas.
In the hands of Bruno Costa, the Portuguese guitar enchanted the Centro Cultural Jorge Sampaio. “I think that this work, ‘100 Paredes’ and this ‘world tour’, which brings the Portuguese guitar almost to the entire world, has this purpose: to let people fall in love with an instrument that is so much ours, that carries the name Portugal, and that has a timbre, a unique sound”, highlighted Bruno Costa.
The guitarist also highlighted the “great pride” it is to do that work. “It is a work of generosity towards the instrument and Portuguese culture, but it gives us immense pleasure to have this audience clapping uninterruptedly for so long with each song that plays, it is very gratifying”, he said.
Uninterrupted applause and spectators standing, this is how both concerts in Dili ended. "I think it was an absolutely wonderful spectacle. For me it was a surprise. Carlos Paredes, who I had never seen live, was an absolutely virtuoso musician, an infinite maestro in that symbiotic relationship he had with the guitar", said the ambassador of Portugal, Duarte Bué Alves.
For the diplomat, the concert transported spectators to that “intimate, deep, dialoguing relationship with the music of Carlos Paredes”. “But they brought much more, because this show aims to be a bridge of cultural dialogue across the 10 or 12 countries it will take place in and that is perhaps one of the most interesting components, along with the tribute to Carlos Paredes”, he highlighted.
According to Duarte Bué Alves, what he witnessed at the Jorge Sampaio cultural center was also the dialogue with “Timorese music, with Timorese cultural expression, with Timorese plastic arts and Timorese textiles”. "And this is in fact the ultimate mission of a cultural center, like the Jorge Sampaio Portuguese cultural center at the Portuguese embassy in Dili, naturally to be a showcase of Portuguese culture, but to open up to dialogue with local culture. And truly today's show could not be more successful in this bridge that we want to foster and nurture", he added.
The project heads to the United States (USA) where it will take place between November 6th and 13th, with actions scheduled for New York, New Bedford and New Jersey.
Between November 27th and December 4th, Argentina is the destination, with performances scheduled for the capital, Buenos Aires, and Córdoba, the second most populous city in that South American country. Montevideo, in Uruguay, will host the “Paredes Experience” between December 5th and 9th, before a first return to Europe, in this case to Italian Tuscany, in the towns of Pontedera and Buti (December 11th to 14th).
At the beginning of 2026, Carlos Paredes' music will echo in Poland (in the capital Warsaw and in Rzeszów, in the southeast of the country), between the 9th and 17th of January, then heading to mainland China and the Chinese territories of Macau and Hong Kong, in locations yet to be announced, from the 19th to the 26th of the same month.
From February 11th to 16th, it will be Istanbul (Turkey)'s turn, followed by Cuba (in Havana and Matanzas, between February 25th and March 3rd) and five days in Paris (France), from March 5th to 9th.
The “Paredes Experience” world tour is scheduled to end in São Paulo, Brazil, with initiatives scheduled for March 12th to 23rd. Lusa</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sino-Lusophone university alliance wants to apply AI to “healthy longevity”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/alianca-universitaria-sino-lusofona-quer-aplicar-ia-na-longevidade-saudavel/</link><description>Nine universities from Portugal and China launched an alliance in Macau to study how to use new technologies, including artificial intelligence (AI), to guarantee “healthy longevity” for the population.

The agreement was signed at the University of São José (USJ), which gave rise to the initiative to create the Alliance for Innovation and Development in Health Technologies for Longevity between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries.
"We have very strong relations with Portuguese-speaking countries. It is natural that this idea was born here in Macau", the dean of the Academy for Innovation and Development in Smart Health and Longevity at USJ, Dai Jianbiao, told Lusa.
In addition to USJ, the alliance's founders include the Zunyi Medical University campus in Zhuhai, a city located next to Macau, and Xinhua University in Guangzhou, capital of neighboring Guangdong province.
On the Portuguese side, they include the University of Évora, the University of Aveiro, the University of Beira Interior, the University of Minho, the University of Algarve and the Portuguese Catholic University. But the vice-rector for Research, Innovation and Internationalization at the University of Évora stressed that the alliance is open to other Portuguese-speaking countries, with invitations already made to institutions in Brazil and Timor-Leste.
Despite admitting that, unlike Portugal, the remaining Portuguese-speaking countries still have relatively young populations, Paulo Quaresma believes that the alliance has “a theme that is transversal”. “Even in young countries like these, there is certainly an interest in their elderly people being able to live longer and in better health conditions, which is, in essence, the main objective”, said the researcher.
Macau's population is aging rapidly, mainly due to the lowest birth rate in the world, while mainland China's population declined in 2024, for the third year in a row. "In fact, this happens all over the world. So this is our very strong message to academics: We should be concerned about this", argued Dai Jianbiao. But Paulo Quaresma stressed that the alliance also wants to bring together companies and other institutions, both public and private, that can complement scientific research carried out in academia. This is because the ultimate objective is “to have real solutions that are transferred to society and then, honestly, no one knows how to reach everyone better than companies”, defended the researcher.
Quaresma mentioned, as an example of technological solutions that the alliance can study, a set of sensors, which, using AI, can alert to possible health problems in elderly people who live alone. “This could allow people to be in their environment, with their family, for longer, and not have to be displaced, whether admitted to hospitals or nursing homes”, explained the academic.
Furthermore, said Quaresma, AI can allow medical treatment to be personalized, extending something that is already done, through genetic analysis, for some types of cancer. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:39:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing launches plan to accelerate technological self-reliance before summit with Trump</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/pequim-lanca-plano-para-acelerar-autossuficiencia-tecnologica-antes-de-cimeira-com-trump/</link><description>The Chinese Communist Party called for a national mobilization to achieve “decisive” advances in semiconductors and key technologies, on the eve of the meeting between the country's President and his North American counterpart in South Korea.

The initiative comes at a time of renewed commercial tension with the United States, marked by the increasing use of technological controls and restrictions on access to strategic materials.
Beijing and Washington are expected to address these issues, including Chinese controls on the export of rare earths, at this Thursday's summit in South Korea, on the sidelines of the APEC (Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation) leaders' meeting.
In the text published by the PCC, which details the priorities for the 2026-2030 five-year plan, the party calls for “extraordinary measures” to achieve technological self-sufficiency in key areas.
The official version of Chinese President Xi Jinping's speech on the plan, released by the official Xinhua news agency, highlights the need to “accelerate high-level scientific and technological self-sufficiency”. “The proposals must promote original innovation and ensure that China maintains firm control of its growth trajectory”, stated the Chinese President, recognizing the challenges of an “increasingly adverse external environment”.
The new guidelines reinforce Xi Jinping's industrial policies focused on self-sufficiency and the strengthening of domestic production chains, identified by several Western partners as a source of mercantilist practices and the origin of the current trade war.
The document will serve as the basis for the preparation of the official plan by the State Council (Executive), the final version of which should be approved in March 2026.
In addition to investing in innovation, the plan proposes greater investment in “human capital”, including birth subsidies, expansion of free education, reinforcement of pensions and insurance and an increase in rural income.
Xi stated that these measures must be “integrated with investment in infrastructure”, to stimulate domestic consumption, a long-standing goal given the dependence on public investment and exports.
Economists in Beijing have defended the reorientation of economic policy towards consumption, hampered by the prolonged crisis in the real estate sector, but point out that previous plans for “common prosperity” fell short of expectations.
Among the new priority sectors are quantum computing, unmanned aerial vehicles ('drones'), biotechnology, hydrogen and fusion energy, humanoid robots with artificial intelligence, brain-machine interfaces and 6G mobile networks. The use of artificial intelligence across industries is equally highlighted as a priority for the next five years.
The document also establishes the goal of achieving, by 2035, a level of 'per capita' income comparable to that of moderately developed countries. Xi had already set the objective of doubling GDP between 2020 and 2035, which implies an average annual growth rate of around 4.8%.
The new guidelines were released a day after senior North American officials indicated that China may postpone the entry into force of controls on the export of rare metals, following negotiations in Kuala Lumpur, which increased optimism around a possible extension of the trade truce between the two countries. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:32:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing confirms meeting between Xi Jinping and Trump in South Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/pequim-confirma-reuniao-entre-xi-jinping-e-trump-na-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>Chinese diplomacy confirmed that President Xi Jinping will meet this Thursday with his North American counterpart, Donald Trump, in South Korea, in a meeting aimed at easing trade tension between the two countries.
Although Washington had already confirmed the meeting – with Trump already present in South Korea – Beijing has remained silent until now, in what will be the first meeting between the two leaders since the Republican's return to the White House, last January.
The meeting will take place on the sidelines of the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation Forum (APEC) summit and should address topics such as the trade war, the TikTok application, the Taiwan issue and the fight against fentanyl trafficking.
In recent days, both sides have signaled a willingness to compromise. Trump expressed confidence in a “good-for-both trade deal” and admitted lowering tariffs on China in exchange for greater cooperation in the fight against fentanyl, the drug responsible for a public health crisis in the USA. He was also evasive about the possibility of discussing Taiwan with Xi, stating: “Taiwan is Taiwan.”
The meeting follows technical negotiations held in Kuala Lumpur, in which Washington and Beijing reached a “preliminary agreement” to ease trade disputes, including Chinese controls on rare earth exports and US tariffs on Chinese products.
On Tuesday, the Central Committee of the Chinese Communist Party published new strategic guidelines that call for a national mobilization to achieve “decisive breakthroughs” in key technologies such as semiconductors, precision tools, basic software, artificial intelligence and fusion energy, under the 2026-2030 five-year plan.
On the diplomatic level, tension around Taiwan gained new momentum ahead of the summit. Beijing reiterated that it will “never renounce the use of force” to achieve reunification, while Taiwanese leader William Lai stated that “only peace through force” can guarantee regional stability and called for firmer opposition to Chinese “annexation”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:35:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputies want Macao SAR to be more aligned with Beijing's guidelines</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/deputados-querem-raem-mais-alinhada-com-as-orientacoes-de-pequim/</link><description>At the second plenary meeting of this VIII legislature – the first opportunity for deputies to the Legislative Assembly (AL) to present their ideas – a significant part of the hemicycle made a point of highlighting that “the spirit” of the 4th plenary session of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China must be the “compass” of the Macao SAR. Beijing's guidelines include implementing “high-quality development” and promoting the “prosperity” and “stability” of the territory, for example.

The Legislative Assembly (AL) resumed work for the VIII legislature. On Tuesday, the second plenary meeting was held – the first in which deputies were able to present interventions. Most of the deputies took the opportunity to ask the Macao SAR Government to comply with the guidelines issued by the 4th plenary session of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCP), which took place last week.
In this session, the proposals of the CPC Central Committee for the formulation of the 15th Five-Year Plan for national economic and social development were deliberated and approved, which establish that Macau should “maintain long-term prosperity and stability”, “promote the peaceful development of cross-strait relations”, “advance national reunification” and “build a community with a shared future for humanity”.

REINFORCEMENT OF THE POPULATION'S WELL-BEING

Ella Lei was the first to point to Beijing's guidelines and suggest that Macau achieves its objectives through, for example, the implementation of “multiple measures” to revitalize the community economy. In this context, the parliamentarian linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM) stated that “it is imperative to have more concrete policies to promote the valorization of traditional industries and boost the development of emerging industries”.
Regarding the aim of improving the well-being of the population, Ella Lei says that the Macao SAR Government must “reinforce investment in resources in the areas of health, education and social services”.
Song Pek Kei stated that, based on the guidelines that emerged from the 4th plenary session of the CPC Central Committee, Macau must “firmly grasp new development opportunities, coordinate with national strategies, fully take advantage of the advantages of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle and deepen its general reform”. It must also, added the deputy linked to the Fujian community, “commit to achieving the objectives of economic diversification” and “promoting its development with quality, in order to maintain prosperity and stability in the long term”.
Ip Sio Kai considers that the PCC plan constitutes “a crucial step towards basically realizing the socialist modernization of our country by 2035”, and also provides “unprecedented opportunities for the development of the Macao SAR”. The deputy elected indirectly proposed strengthening communication and coordination with authorities in the interior of China, the “development of new engines of growth” and the launch of campaigns among the local population so that there is “alignment with national development”.

“TELLING THE STORY OF CHINA AND MACAU WELL”

Ma Chi Seng pointed out that Macau should “seriously learn and implement the spirit of the 4th plenary session, actively integrate into national development and contribute to the development of China's modernization”. The parliamentarian suggested that the MSAR should “tell the history of China and Macau well”, use Hengqin to “accelerate the adequate diversification of the economy” and “create a high-level platform for opening up to the outside world”.
Lam Fat Iam, nominated deputy who makes his debut in the AL, began by saying that “we must inherit the spirit of loving the motherland and Macau, and develop a society characterized by cohesion, harmony and innovation”. This is because “love for the country and for Macau are our core values” that must be transmitted “from generation to generation, in a stable and lasting way”. Then, “it is necessary to promote, in a pragmatic and innovative way, the construction of ‘a base of exchange and cooperation to promote multicultural coexistence, with a predominance of Chinese culture”.
Ultimately, Lam suggested, Macau should contribute to “increasing the spread and influence of Chinese civilization.” “The spirit inherent in the 4th Plenary Session consolidates the direction of Macau's cultural development, and Macau must take it as guidance and opportunity, in order to join forces to, under a high degree of sense of responsibility and vocation, innovate and move forward with the construction, in an accelerated manner, of a 'cultural Macau'”, he concluded.
“It is urgent for Macau to align precisely with the country's plan”, highlighted Angela Leong, who continues in the AL as an indirect deputy. Leong stressed that the Macao SAR should “adopt the spirit of the 4th plenary session of the 20th Central Committee as the ‘compass’, the ‘1+4’ industrial strategy as the ‘driver’, and regional cooperative development as the ‘support’”. “Only in this way can Macau, in the wave of Chinese-style modernization, open a path of high-quality development that not only profoundly manifests Macau's own characteristics, but also articulates precisely with the country's strategic needs, with the aim of continuing to contribute to Macau's strengths for the construction of a strong country and national rejuvenation”, said Angela Leong.
Lei Wun Kong, also a newcomer to the hemicycle, stated that, in order to better implement the “spirit” of the PCC plenary session, the Macao SAR Government must “engage in the work of its 3rd Five-Year Plan, articulating the demands of Chinese modernization with the modernization of Macau under the principle of ‘one country, two systems'”. “Together with the people of the entire country, they will be able to basically achieve national modernization by 2035, with clear evidence of the advantages of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle, the consolidation of the rule of law and the implementation of the development of adequate diversification of Macau’s economy”, said the nominated deputy.

ALIGNMENT WITH NATIONAL STRATEGIES

“Macau must align itself precisely with national strategies”, said Wong Kit Cheng, explaining that the Macao SAR Government must “focus on promoting the adequate diversification of its economy, actively build ‘a center, a platform and a base’ and demonstrate greater contributions within the country’s comprehensive advancement towards high-quality development”.
Iau Teng Pio asked the Macao SAR Government to focus on four aspects: optimizing human resources management mechanisms in the Civil Service, digitalizing administrative matters, articulating the mechanism for assessing the population's living needs and strengthening coordination between services. These suggestions would make it possible to comply with Beijing's guidelines from the PCC plenary session.
Lee Koi Ian said that “Macau must proactively articulate itself” with the conclusions of the 4th plenary session of the PCC Central Committee. Ho Ion Sang considers the Beijing guidelines to be “an important guidance and inspiration for Maca”. Finally, Vong Hou Piu said that the Macao SAR must take advantage of the “good winds” of the PCC plenary session.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:43:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Association proposes regulations to protect minors in cyberspace</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/associacao-propoe-regulamentos-para-proteccao-de-menores-no-ciberespaco/</link><description>The General Association of Chong Wa Students of Macau defends the need to introduce legislation on the protection of minors in cyberspace, in response to the increase in crimes involving youth. The phenomenon is also worrying authorities, who warn of young people's weak legal awareness and the saturation of “inappropriate and harmful content” on the internet.

The increase in juvenile delinquency and young victims of crimes led the General Association of Chong Wa Students of Macau to suggest regulations on the protection of minors in cyberspace, hoping to “reduce impacts caused by online content harmful to young people”.
Sio Hin Wa, director of the Association, argues that a similar law has already been implemented in the interior of China and Macau should take it as a reference to introduce regulations on the conduct of suppliers of online products and services.
"Teenagers are frequent users of the Internet, thus being susceptible to the influence of online information and may even unconsciously adopt behaviors observed on the Internet. Therefore, it is essential that young people cultivate correct concepts about the use of online information", he highlighted.
On the morning program of Radio Macau's Chinese channel yesterday, Sio Hin Wa highlighted the importance of clarifying, in legal terms, the responsibilities and obligations in protecting minors, while society should pay more attention to the psychological pressures, values ​​and family concepts that young people face while growing up.
It is recalled that the regulations aimed at protecting minors in cyberspace in force in mainland China provide for measures to prevent online addiction among minors, particularly addiction to video games, as well as provisions to protect minors' personal information and combat content that is harmful to children's physical and mental health.
The association's representative, however, recognized that excessive legal restrictions could provoke rebellious attitudes among young people, making them more curious about prohibited content. “Legislation must be the last resort and the priority task is to guide young people to use the Internet correctly”, he emphasized.
In the same radio program, the Judiciary Police assured that it was aware of the rise in crime involving young people, both perpetrators and victims. Authorities agree that the internet is full of “inappropriate content” such as pornography and violence, and in this case, prolonged exposure to this type of material can subtly influence young people over time.
“Juvenile delinquency focuses on crimes of assault or theft, however, there is an upward trend in sexual crimes committed by teenagers,” said Cheong Un Hong, criminal investigator at the Judicial Police.
According to the representative, there has been an increase in cases of sexual abuse against children, which reflects the trend towards early sexual activity, with half of these cases involving consensual sexual conduct. Additionally, some cases of child pornography have involved victims being enticed to take photographs without clothes on. "The teenagers involved often demonstrate poor legal knowledge and may be unaware of legal provisions, in particular the concept that sexual activity with minors under the age of 16 constitutes a crime. This also highlights changes in teenagers' sexual values ​​and an insufficient awareness of self-protection, which requires the collective attention of society", he asserted.
Police authorities admitted that guardians, schools and the community must contribute to raising awareness among young people about crimes, revealing that they organized more than 150 lectures on crime prevention in schools during the first three quarters of this year, with an accumulated participation of 24,000 students.
On the other hand, throughout the first half of this year, the police received reports of fraud and false customer service on shopping platforms, which injured six victims, primary and secondary school students, with a total loss of around 480,000 Hong Kong dollars. The authorities guarantee that they will continue to carry out awareness campaigns against fraud, focusing on young people.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:41:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Airport freight terminal expected to enter service in 2027</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/terminal-de-mercadorias-do-aeroporto-de-macau-devera-entrar-em-servico-em-2027/</link><description>Macau International Airport will have a freight terminal in Hengqin, which is scheduled to come into operation in the first half of 2027. The facility will have the capacity to handle up to 300,000 tons of air cargo per year. The authorities highlight that the project will promote commercial connectivity in the Greater Bay Area, also enhancing air logistics for cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.

Construction work on the Macau Airport freight terminal has begun in Hengqin. With the completion of the project scheduled for the end of next year, and the start of operations in the first half of 2027, the infrastructure foresees the annual capacity to move up to 300,000 tons of air cargo.
The laying of the first stone ceremony took place on Tuesday. On the occasion, the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, pointed out that the project will allow rapid interconnection for Guangdong-Macao import and export cargo, in addition to stimulating the local employment market and attracting the agglomeration of industries related to air cargo transport, giving a “significant boost” to cross-border trade and related industries in Macau and the Mountain Island.
The main objective of the new freight terminal at Macau International Airport in Hengqin is to extend security control, palletizing and cargo consolidation operations from Macau Airport to Ilha da Montanha, with these air logistics procedures now being carried out at Macau Airport itself.
“Taking advantage of the favorable customs supervision measures in Hengqin, perfect air logistics connectivity between Macau and the Deep Cooperation Zone will be achieved”, highlighted the secretary in his speech, cited by Jornal Ou Mun.
Tai Kin Ip added that the project will also facilitate deeper logistical, commercial and technological integration between Macau, Hengqin and the Greater Bay Area, but also create differentiated competitive advantages for the city to “strengthen the air logistics corridor for economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries”.
According to the secretary, the freight terminal is created jointly by local companies and central state-owned companies, and is also a “strategic step” towards Macau’s economic diversification.
It is recalled that the cargo volume of Macau International Airport reached 108,000 tons last year, which represents an increase of almost 70% compared to 2023 and significantly exceeds the 42,000 tons recorded in 2019. The Macau International Airport Society (CAM) justified the expansion of activities to Hengqin with the rapid development of e-commerce and the continuous growth in demand for air freight.

INVESTMENT OF 700 MILLION RMB
 
According to the project presentation, Macau Airport's Hengqin freight terminal is located on the west side of Mountain Island, adjacent to the Guangdong-Macau Cooperation Traditional Chinese Medicine Industrial Park and Nam Kwong Logistics Park, with Macau International Airport approximately 13 kilometers away. The facility occupies a total land area of ​​66,700 square meters, while the gross area totals 97,600 square meters. The development comprises logistics warehouses, a comprehensive office building and support facilities.
Previously released information shows that Macau International Airport acquired the Hengqin land in 2024 for 129 million renminbi for the aforementioned construction, with a total investment in the project of around 700 million renminbi.
In turn, the chairman of the Board of Directors of CAM, Ma Iao Hang, stated that the creation of the new freight terminal will help increase efficiency and reduce logistics costs, providing efficient support for cargo transportation for industries such as cross-border e-commerce and high-tech manufacturing.
The official also highlighted that Macau Airport began operating three decades ago and has seen constant growth in its cargo operations, meaning that, in the future, it will “consolidate its position as a regional logistics center” and “improve the economic efficiency of its air logistics operations”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:41:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau can help bring products from Qinghai to Portuguese-speaking countries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/macau-pode-ajudar-a-levar-produtos-de-qinghai-para-os-paises-de-lingua-portuguesa/</link><description>The Chief Executive met on Monday afternoon with Luo Dongchuan, deputy secretary of the provincial committee of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) and governor of Qinghai province. At the meeting, which took place at the Macao SAR Government headquarters, both parties promised to strengthen cooperation.
At the meeting, Sam Hou Fai began by pointing out that Macau is going through a “critical phase in advancing the development strategy of adequate diversification of the ‘1+4’ economy and accelerating the construction of the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin”. The Chief Executive invited Qinghai to participate in the development of the Cooperation Zone “in order to jointly explore business opportunities”.
Sam Hou Fai indicated that Macau, as a “precision interlocutor” for Portuguese-speaking countries, can “actively play the role of a service platform for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries as a way to help Qinghai's characteristic products explore more promotion and sales channels within Portuguese-speaking countries”.
The Chief pointed out that Qinghai province has “abundant ecotourism resources” and, as a tourism destination sought after by Macau residents, “both parties can work together to explore more tourism products to realize mutual complementarity of advantages and common development”.
On the other hand, “Macau has accumulated a certain experience in the area of ​​higher education and professional training in the tourism and service sectors, reserving a large number of highly qualified staff in the tourism area”, which “could deepen the training of human resources from Qinghai and improve the level of service in the sector to contribute to the growth of Macau”. Finally, views were exchanged on ways to further expand the scope of the supply of agricultural products from Qinghai to Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:38:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Government plans to launch pre-hospital stroke assessment and notification mechanism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/governo-planeia-lancar-mecanismo-de-avaliacao-e-notificacao-pre-hospitalar-de-avc/</link><description>The Health Services, in cooperation with the Fire Department, are planning to create a pre-hospital Cerebrovascular Accident (CVA) assessment and notification mechanism. The plan was announced by the Health Services in a statement on Tuesday issued as part of the celebration of World Stroke Day, which was celebrated yesterday.
De acordo com o organismo, o referido mecanismo irá permitir que, durante o transporte de doentes com suspeita de AVC para o hospital em ambulância, seja efectuada uma notificação prévia ao hospital, possibilitando que os profissionais de saúde mobilizem os recursos humanos e preparem os recursos necessários antes da chegada do doente.
“Isto permite a administração atempada de trombólise intravenosa a doentes com AVC isquémico agudo, ou a realização de terapias de reperfusão vascular, como a trombectomia intervencionista, encurtando eficazmente o tempo de espera do tratamento e melhorando a taxa de sucesso dos esforços de resgate”, salientou.
O AVC é uma das principais causas de morte e incapacidade em todo o mundo, sendo que as doenças cardiovasculares e cerebrovasculares são actualmente a segunda principal causa de morte em Macau, enfatizam os Serviços de Saúde.
According to the Executive, the Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário created, in 2016, the Stroke Prevention Group and a green route for stroke in the Emergency Department, with the aim of shortening the time needed for treatment, providing patients with intravenous thrombolysis and interventional thrombectomy treatment 24 hours a day.
Statistics show that last year, more than 300 people activated the green route, more than 100 successfully underwent intravenous thrombolysis treatment, and around 40 people completed interventional thrombectomy treatment. Furthermore, the proportion of hospitalized stroke patients who can receive intravenous thrombolytic treatment also increased from 1.9% in 2016 to more than 30% currently, which “is better than in neighboring regions”, he added.
The Health Services warn citizens to identify the signs of a stroke early, for example, the face drops suddenly or the corner of the mouth tilts when laughing; they should check whether the upper arm or lower limbs have lateral weakness or numbness; speak badly or have difficulty understanding the words of others; and note the time the symptoms occurred, immediately calling 999 for emergency medical assistance.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:37:14</pubDate></item><item><title>ASEAN and China expand free trade agreement during summit in Malaysia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/asean-e-china-ampliam-acordo-de-comercio-livre-durante-cimeira-na-malasia/</link><description>The Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) and China expanded their free trade agreement, after a year of negotiations, at a time when they seek to diversify partnerships in the face of tariffs imposed by the United States.
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang, who leads Beijing's delegation at the summit of heads of state and government of ASEAN and partners, in Kuala Lumpur, was present at the signing ceremony of the new version of the “free trade area” between China and the bloc, of which it is the main trading partner.
The “3.0” version of the agreement, signed by the Chinese Minister of Commerce, Wang Wentao, and the Malaysian Minister of Investment, Trade and Industry, Zafrul Aziz, introduces “improvements” in trade facilitation and access to services markets, among other areas, according to an ASEAN statement.
The objectives of the new agreement include strengthening the “resilience and solidity of supply chains” and maintaining “markets open to trade and investment”.
Chinese exports to Southeast Asia have soared in recent months, following the tariffs that North American President Donald Trump began announcing in April for trading partners, registering a year-on-year increase of 14.7% in September, according to China's General Administration of Customs.
China takes the lead on the last day of the ASEAN and partners summit in Kuala Lumpur, after the United States was highlighted on Sunday, with the presence of Trump, in a context of geopolitical rivalry between the world's two largest economies in Southeast Asia.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:32:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Book that reveals Macau as an urban architectural laboratory will be launched at Livraria Portuguesa</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/livro-que-revela-macau-como-laboratorio-urbano-de-arquitectura-sera-lancado-na-livraria-portuguesa/</link><description>“Layering the City” will be presented tomorrow, at 6:45 pm, at Livraria Portuguesa, after its international debut at the Venice Biennale. Published by the international Actar Books, the work reveals how Macau has become an “interesting laboratory” for rethinking public space in contexts of extreme density. Authored by architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni, the book summarizes twenty years of research and professional practice by the LBA Architecture and Planning studio in the territory, proposing an in-depth reflection on infrastructure and public space, the result of the dialogue between two doctoral dissertations.

Two decades of urban transformation in Macau are now condensed into the 360 ​​pages of “Layering the City”, a book that will be launched tomorrow, October 31st, at Livraria Portuguesa, after having recently been presented at the Venice Biennale. The work of architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni, founders of the LBA Architecture and Planning studio, represents the culmination of an in-depth investigation into infrastructure and public space in the territory, based on their doctoral dissertations at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology.
The launch event in Macau, scheduled for 6:45 pm, will feature a presentation by professor Ana Vaz Milheiro and an overview by the authors of this work that puts into dialogue “two theses about the city and how architecture can work, intervene and qualify the city”, as Rui Leão describes. The work works as “a kind of dialogue between the two dissertations”, arising from a reflection on the work built and the contribution of the LBA studio to the city.
The concept of “layering” (creation of layers) emerges as the guiding thread of the publication. “The term arose from our collaboration”, explains Rui Leão in an interview with the publisher Actar. “We wanted to describe this collaboration as two people with two different approaches on a single project.” This perspective extends to the city itself, where “the way we work has to do with overlapping layers in a very complex city that is not easy to work with”.
Rui Leão’s dissertation, “Designing by Increments”, focused on the Nam Van lakes area, an area that he describes as “a little abandoned in terms of strategic vision”. Its “design by increments” approach allowed it to “create a highly qualified public space on a very important scale” where previously there was only “a road system” that “could be an abandoned area”.
Carlotta Bruni, in “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space”, analyzed how “the city is very overdensified” and “spaces for people end up being very disregarded”. The architect detected a “lack of systematic space availability” and an “institutional void in the sense of creating quality of life through public space”.
The authors highlight specific projects where they applied these principles, such as the Bairro da Vitória and Ilha social housing buildings, where they created common spaces on each floor to compensate for the “very claustrophobic” houses. In a recent project that challenged construction close to historical monuments, in what is now the new Barra station, they managed to bury the bus station 20 meters underground to preserve the view of the old coast, creating an urban park on the roof that keeps the space better utilized.
The work also reveals how Macau serves as an “interesting laboratory” for rethinking architecture, with its extreme density allowing for the overlapping and multiplication of ground floors. Faced with the administration's lack of strategic vision, the architects developed a master plan of “resistance”, taking on the responsibility of reintroducing public and collective spaces “forgotten” by the administration into the projects.
The book, edited by Ricardo Devesa and graphic designed by Olga Pipnik, includes contributions from Jorge Figueira, Jun Jiang, Nicholas Boyarsky and Ana Vaz Milheiro, offering a comprehensive view of how architectural practice can respond to the unique challenges of Macau, a territory where the juxtaposition between old and new continues to define urban identity.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Almost 62 thousand individuals identified in the “Trovoada 2025” operation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/quase-62-mil-individuos-identificados-na-operacao-trovoada-2025/</link><description>The joint operation “Trovoada 2025”, between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, began on April 4th and, so far, 833 surprise police actions have been carried out, having mobilized more than 11,763 officers in action in more than 2,011 locations. Furthermore, reported the Unitary Police Services (SPU), more than 61,900 individuals were subject to identification, among which 755 individuals were referred to the judicial bodies to be charged. At issue are suspected cases of fraud, exploitation of illicit exchange for gambling, theft, illicit lending for gambling, attacks on physical integrity, money laundering, among others.
As part of the joint operation, the SPU, together with the Customs Service (SA), the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Judiciary Police (PJ), recently carried out large-scale inspections at various locations, namely casinos, nightlife establishments, saunas and bars located in Macau and Cotai. The various police units sent more than 360 police officers and six kinesthetic teams, and the SA also deployed a patrol vessel, four speedboats and a team of drones to participate in the operations.
During these actions, 2,633 individuals were subject to identification, of which 36 were taken to the police for investigation purposes. Among the individuals investigated, eight were overstayed and were taken to the CPSP Border Control Department for proper referral. In addition, the SA discovered two cases of violation of the foreign trade law at the border posts, involving 200 cigarettes and 60 old computer central processing units, worth around 30,000 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:38:10</pubDate></item><item><title>China registers record number of billionaires in 2025 with one new per day</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/china-regista-numero-recorde-de-bilionarios-em-2025-com-um-novo-por-dia/</link><description>China recorded a record increase in the number of billionaires in 2025, with a new entry every day, driven by the appreciation of stock markets and the rise of companies in the so-called “new economy”, according to the Hurun research unit.

The latest edition of the “Hurun China Rich List” includes 1,434 individuals with fortunes exceeding five billion yuan (around 601 million euros), 340 more than last year, representing a growth of 31%.
The combined wealth of these billionaires totals 30 billion yuan (almost 3.6 billion euros), an increase of 42% compared to the previous year.
At the top of the list was Zhong Shanshan, founder of bottled water producer Nongfu Spring, whose fortune soared 56% to 530 billion yuan (64 billion euros). It is the fourth time that Zhong has led the ranking.
Zhang Yiming, founder of ByteDance – the company that owns TikTok – fell to second place, despite having increased his fortune by 34%, to 470 billion yuan (56 billion euros).
Li Ka-shing, 97, and his son Victor Li Tzar-kuoi, 61, continue to be the richest in Hong Kong, with a combined fortune of 235 billion yuan (28 billion euros), 18% more than last year, although they fell from sixth to ninth place in the overall table.
The Hurun investigative unit has been compiling this list since 1999, covering billionaires from mainland China, Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan. “This year's list surprised by reaching a record number, driven above all by the strong performance of stock markets and the emergence of new figures in the technology and export sectors,” said Rupert Hoogewerf, president of Hurun.
The number of fortunes above 100 billion yuan (12 billion euros) rose from 26 to 41, an increase of 59%. The total number of people with assets above one billion dollars (857 million euros) increased by 36%, to 1,021.
The appreciation of shares in Shanghai, Shenzhen and Hong Kong reflected investor enthusiasm for sectors such as electric vehicles, biotechnology and computing. The Shenzhen index rose 54% and the Shanghai index 36% through September. Hong Kong's Hang Seng advanced 42%.
China's GDP grew 4.8% in the third quarter, less than the 5.2% recorded in the previous quarter. Trade tensions with the United States and problems in the real estate sector continue to weigh on the economic recovery. Still, Chinese companies with global ambitions – especially in the areas of batteries, healthcare and mining – have attracted market interest. By the end of September, 66 companies (mostly from mainland China) had raised US$23.27 billion (€19.95 billion) through initial public offerings on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, the largest figure in the world this year. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:35:38</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea announces cruise missile test ahead of Trump's visit to South Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/29/coreia-do-norte-anuncia-teste-de-misseis-de-cruzeiro-antes-da-visita-de-trump-a-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>North Korea fired cruise missiles into its western waters in a demonstration of military capabilities hours before Trump arrived in South Korea for a regional summit. The American president has however confirmed that he will not meet with Kim Jong-un due to scheduling incompatibility.

North Korea announced on Tuesday that it fired cruise missiles into its western waters, in a demonstration of military capabilities hours before the US President arrived in South Korea for a regional summit.
The Korean Central News Agency, Pyongyang's official body, described the military test as a success and stated that the weapon would contribute to expanding the operational sphere of the country's armed forces, which have nuclear weapons.   The South Korean army did not immediately confirm whether it had detected the tests.
North Korea had already launched, on October 22, several short-range ballistic missiles, in the first test since the inauguration of South Korean President Lee Jae-myung, and a week before Trump's visit.
According to South Korea's Joint Chiefs of Staff (JCS), the missiles were launched northeast, apparently toward the Sea of ​​Japan – known in both Koreas as the East Sea.
Inter-Korean communication channels have remained cut off since 2022, and Pyongyang has repeatedly rejected calls from Lee Jae-myung's administration to reopen dialogue.

Trump does not meet with Kim Jong-un on visit to Korea

US President Donald Trump has clarified that he will not meet with his North Korean counterpart, Kim Jong-un, during his current visit to the Korean peninsula, justifying it due to scheduling incompatibilities. "I know Kim Jong-un very well. We get along very well. It really won't be possible to meet this time. President [Chinese] Xi [Jinping] arrives tomorrow [Thursday] and that is very important for the world, for all of us," Trump said during a lunch with his South Korean counterpart, Lee Jae-myung, in the city of Gyeongjiyu.
The North American head of state added that he wants to be with the leader of North Korea and had that objective in this tour, but “there are other commitments”, although his desire is to “work hard with Kim Jong-un and the whole world to resolve things”.
The current South Korean head of state, in office since June, has been more favorable to dialogue with his northern neighbor than his predecessor and praised Donald Trump's diplomatic efforts.
In his first term, the president of the United States of America met three times with Pyongyang's highest representative, between 2018 and 2019, and they both held a symbolic handshake in the demilitarized zone of the Korean peninsula, although without any practical results. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-29 23:31:45</pubDate></item></channel></rss>