<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/governos-locais-da-china-comecam-a-utilizar-deepseek-para-aumentar-eficiencia/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Universities are “the main battlefields” to attract talent, defends the Lam</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/universidades-sao-os-principais-campos-de-batalha-para-atrair-talentos-defende-o-lam/</link><description>For LAM, higher education institutions are “the most important platforms and the main battlefields” in pursuing the objective of attracting international qualified frames. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture met last Friday with local higher education institutions and highlighted the “crucial of higher education institutions in the realization of the strategic objective of 'a place of aggregation of international qualified staff. highlighted '”.
The secretary asked for efforts to “firmly” to implement the spirit of the words of Xi Jinping when his recent passage through Macau and do “a good work in higher education, the construction of scientific research platforms and the internationalization of teaching staff, and continue to Macao's unique advantage of 'a country, two systems' and its role as an exchange platform. ” The objective is, he said, "making Macau in a place of aggregation of international qualified staff, contributing to the strengths of Macau to the construction of a strong nation."
According to LAM, “it was unanimous the recognition of participants regarding the request of President XI Jinping in order to coordinate and promote the integrated development of education, science and technology”.
Finally, those responsible for higher education institutions presented to the government “a series of important and viable suggestions” on the planning of the future development of higher education institutions, the cultivation and reserve of qualified scientific and technological frames, strategy Internationalization of higher education, the improvement of the qualified staff capture plan, the facilitation measures of the mobilization of qualified staff in the Great Bay and the promotion of industry development-university-investment, as well as regional cooperation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:46:31+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China does not confirm conversation that Trump says he had with Xi Jinping</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/china-nao-confirma-conversa-que-trump-diz-ter-tido-com-xi-jinping/</link><description>China did not confirm yesterday that Chinese President Xi Jinping spoke to the US counterpart after his inauguration on January 20, as Donald Trump revealed on Monday.
A meeting between the leaders of the two worldwide powers could facilitate bilateral relations, still threatened by a potential trade war initiated by Donald Trump.
In an interview broadcast by US television channel Fox News on Monday, a journalist asked Donald Trump if he had spoken with Xi Jinping since the beginning of his second term. "Yes, I talked to him and also talked to the people of his team," said the US President, although neither Washington nor Beijing had ever reported that call.
Asked yesterday if the conversation actually happened, a Beoing spokesman merely remembered the conversation that took place three days before Trump's inauguration. “President Xi Jinping had a telephone conversation with US President Donald Trump on January 17. China has issued a statement on the subject, ”said Guo Jiakun, spokesman for the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, at a press conference.
Since taking office, Trump has announced the imposition of punitive fees on his main trading partners, including China, Mexico and Canada.
Mexico and Canada were able to get a 30 -day postponement thanks to last -minute agreements with Donald Trump.
However, Chinese products that enter the United States are now subject to additional 10%rates, beyond the ones already in force.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:49:04+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM and industry representatives participate in a conference of the Global Association of Exhibition Industry</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/ipim-e-representantes-da-industria-participam-em-conferencia-da-associacao-global-da-industria-de-exposicoes/</link><description>The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) and about 50 representatives of the Great Bay Convention and Exhibition Industry will be present at this year's edition of the Asia Pacific Conference of the Global Exhibition Industry Association (UFI, in the acronym English), which will take place on February 13 and 14 in Melbourne, Australia.
In addition to the IPIM, representatives of the Directorate of Tourism Services, the Macao Convention and Exhibition Industry and - for the first time - representatives from nine cities in the Great Bay. In a statement, IPIM clarifies that this will be an opportunity to “support the companies of the Great Bay to internationalize, strengthen internal and external links, expand their 'circles of international friends', grasp abroad opportunities and increase their competitiveness, just as they focus on the emerging industries. ”
In this sense, the body announces that it has set up a “stand exhibitor” at the event venue in Australia to publicize the advantages of Macau and Hengqin industries with UFI members and international sector leaders, as well as coordinating a visit The event “Asia-Pacific Encourages &amp; Meetings Expo” (AIME) in order to “expand the international cooperation space” and “promote the moderate diversification of Macao's economy”.
Organized annually in different regions of Asia, last year's conference took place at MSAR and promoted debates and various thematic activities, accompanied by cultural and sports initiatives. At the time, IPIM highlighted the importance of the event to stimulate business and investments in the territory and raise the international visibility of the region's conventions and exhibitions.
In this year's edition, more than 200 global convention and exhibition industry leaders are expected to participate.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:52:25+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste government will build a new prison in the municipality of Same</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/governo-de-timor-leste-vai-construir-nova-prisao-no-municipio-de-same/</link><description>Justice Minister Sérgio Hornai said yesterday that the government of Timor-Leste intends to build a new prison in the municipality of Same, south of Dili, which will also make available vocational training courses. "We want to open the arrest of Wedaberek, in the municipality of Same, because we want to transfer the prisoners to an appropriate place, where they can develop their talents and abilities, so that they can contribute to society when they leave the prison," said the minister.
Sérgio Hornai spoke to Lusa in Parliament, on the fringes of discussion and vote in the generality of the law proposal on the first change to the transient recruitment regime of non -Timorese magistrates and public defenders.
According to the leader, the government intends to direct prisoners to vocational training, considering that it is fundamental to their future. “A rehabilitation center or prison should not be a place where a person is placed without allowing them to develop knowledge, but a Space where prisoners are oriented to acquire higher abilities so that they can have adequate skills when they end the penalty, ”explained the minister.
Sérgio Hornai pointed out that prisoners will have access to various activities, including arts, carpentry, construction and other areas of formation.
The minister also pointed out that the future penitentiary will have a large space and will therefore allow to guide the prisoners to other activities. "Our territory is vast and, therefore, it is also necessary to contribute to agriculture," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:46:51+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Hong Kong Post Office resume orders to the United States</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/correios-de-macau-e-hong-kong-retomam-envio-de-encomendas-para-os-estados-unidos/</link><description>The Post Office of Macao and Hong Kong announced the recovery of small packages and orders to the United States after five days of suspension.
 
In a statement, the Hong Kong Post Office said they were "formally notified" by the US Postal Service (USPS) that US authorities "currently" does not impose additional rates on postal articles with goods. "
On January 5, the company said it had been notified by USPS that it could only send packages or orders that customers had registered with customs and the protection of US borders (CBP).
The registration would require “the necessary import documents and the payment of fees made through a customs dispatcher,” added the Hong Kong Post Office.
After the suspension of shipping, the company "continued to negotiate" with USPS and "can temporarily resume" the postal service for the United States on Tuesday, refers to the announced statement. Hours later, Macao Post (CTT) also announced that they will accept again, from February 11, "all mail objects (…) for the United States."
In a statement issued by the Macao Post and Telecommunications Directorate Directorate, the CTT recalled that the suspension "may have originated a correspondence, which will possibly result in delays in the delivery of US -destined shipments." "Additionally, the possibility of any changes to the policies of US postal services cannot be excluded at any time," the company warned.
On February 4, USPS announced that it would temporarily stop accepting orders from China and Hong Kong (without any reference to Macao) “until new order”.
But hours later, USPS reversed the decision, without justifying, just stating that it was going to work with the CBP to implement a collection process for the new rates imposed on Chinese goods in order to avoid interruptions in delivery.
The new US President Donald Trump increased customs rates on China's imports by 10%after retreating in the plans to charge Canada and Mexico.
The vast majority of goods sent from China arrive outside the mail system, but Trump's order specifically eliminated a tariff exemption for low -value products, purchased directly by consumers and sent through postal service. This exemption encompassed articles of less than $ 800.
The USPS measurement could block or delay orders made through Chinese e -commerce platforms Shein and Temu. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:46:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China reinforces rules for publication of military information on the internet</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/china-reforca-regras-para-publicacao-de-informacoes-militares-na-internet/</link><description>China will impose new rules that limit information that can be shared about the Popular Liberation Army (ELP) on the Internet, which may make it difficult to monitor its development and evolution.
 
According to a circular issued by the Armed Forces of the Asian country, “military information suppliers on the Internet” will be prohibited from March 1 of “producing, copying, publishing or disclosing“ previously not disclosed information, including details about weapons systems and military facilities.
The new rules prohibit the publication of information involving “military secrets and national defense technology”, such as “research and development, production, testing, transportation, equipment and maintenance of weapons and equipment, [as well as] tactical performance and weapons and equipment technician ”.
It also prohibits the dissemination of information about the organizational structure of the Armed Forces, their chain of command, previous commanders and details on military units that have not been officially disclosed.
The rules, which also aim at “false military information and the escape of military secrets on the Internet”, were adopted by the Central Military Commission and the China Cyberspace Administration on Saturday.
According to experts cited by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper, many internet users who follow the ELP served as a valuable information source about their development, publishing photographs of new equipment such as fighters and aircraft carrier.
However, authorities now consider that this information "endangers national security" and can make data sensitive "vulnerable to foreign spy exploration."
The new directive also prohibits the publication of information that "deny or attack China's national defense and military strategy and military strategy," including "construction, development and use of strategic nuclear forces."
The circular also establishes that users of social networks wishing to be identified as “military accounts” must meet a series of requirements, including the provision of personal data and registration with military authorities and cyberspace.
In recent years, China has called for mobilization of “whole society” to “prevent and combat espionage” and announced a series of measures to “reinforce national defense” against “foreign secret services activities”.
Since 2024, the ELP has been carried out a broad anti -corruption campaign that resulted in the dismissal of at least nine generals and several defense industry executives. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:49:13+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Tesla storage battery factory starts working in Shanghai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/nova-fabrica-de-baterias-de-armazenamento-da-tesla-comeca-a-funcionar-em-xangai/</link><description>Tesla yesterday began production in a new storage battery factory in the Shanghai metropolis. The complex began to be built at the end of May 2024 and should have started to work before the end of the year.
 
The American Tesla electric vehicle manufacturer began production yesterday in a new storage battery factory at the Xangai metropolis in eastern China, official Chinese news agency Xinhua said.
The complex began to be built at the end of May 2024 and should have started to work before the end of the year, with the aim of becoming a “very important production and export base”, according to one company official.
The official press stressed, however, that the time elapsed between the launch of the first stone and the opening of the facilities was just eight months, and praised what it described as “Tesla Speed”: in 2019, the North Company's 'gigable' -American in Shanghai was built in just one year.
In this new complex, Tesla will manufacture its megapacks, energy storage batteries used to stabilize electrical grids and avoid power cuts.
According to the company, each megapack can store more than three energy megawatts (MWh) of energy, "enough to feed an average of 3,600 homes for one hour."
Initial production capacity is estimated at about 10,000 units of the device per year, which is equivalent to the annual electricity consumption of 50,000 homes.
According to local authorities, Tesla invested about 1.45 billion Yuan at the factory, located on a plot of 200,000 square meters.
Tesla already has one of these 'megafábricas' in Lathrop, California, southwest of the US, where he manufactures about 10,000 batteries a year, which add up to a storage of about 40 gigawatts-hours (GWh).
In 2019, Tesla opened its first 'gigable' outside the United States in Shanghai. The factory produced about 947,000 vehicles in 2023, which, according to Xinhua, represented just over half of the company's global sales.
Since 2019, Tesla has intensified its investment in the Lingang free trade zone, the Shanghai area where it has operations, expanding production in its 'gigable' and building additional facilities, such as a production factory for its 'superloaders' of electric vehicles.
Tesla's executive president, Elon Musk, who is the richest man in the world and an ally close to the new US President Donald Trump, maintains good relations with China's authorities, a country he has visited several times and where he has one of the its main markets. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:49:12+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New loans falling</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/novos-emprestimos-em-queda/</link><description>Both the new mortgage loans for housing and trade loans for approved real estate activities decreased in December last year compared to the previous month.
According to the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM), in December 2024, the new mortgage loans for housing approved by Macao banks decreased 17.9% over the month last, up to 1.01 billion. Of which, the new mortgage loans for housing approved to local residents representing 96.6% of the total decreased 17.7% to 975.39 million patacas; The non-resident component decreased 22.6% to 34.4 million patacas. From October to December 2024, the average monthly number of new mortgage loans for approved housing reached 1.18 billion patacas, corresponding to a 36.5% decrease compared to the period between September and November 2024.
The new commercial loans for approved real estate activities decreased 22.7% in relation to the previous month for 685.51 million patacas. Of these, 96% were granted to local residents and 18.7% to 658.01 million patacas were decreased; While the non-resident component decreased 64.4% to 27.5 million patacas. From October to December 2024, the average monthly number of new trade loans for approved real estate activities reached 738.25 million patacas, corresponding to a decrease of 13.6%compared to the period between September and November 2024.
AMCM also says that by the end of last year, the debt ratio not paid to new mortgage loans for housing reached 3.5%, corresponding to an increase of 0.1 percentage point (PP) over the previous month or 2.7 percentage points in relation to the same year period of the year. The non -paid debt ratio to commercial loans for real estate activities reached 5.3%, corresponding to an increase of 0.5 percentage points over the previous month or 2.3 percentage points compared to the end of 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:52:26+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China creates planetary defense team against possible asteroid clash</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/china-cria-equipa-de-defesa-planetaria-face-a-possivel-embate-de-asteroide/</link><description>China began gathering a planetary defense team following the discovery of a large asteroid that could reach Earth within seven years, local media advanced yesterday. According to the South China Morning Post newspaper, the state administration of science, technology and industry for China's national defense is looking for professionals with experience in monitoring asteroids and early alert systems. The initiative is in line with the widest planetary defense strategy in the Asian country, which includes an asteroid deviation mission planned for 2027.
China has been working on the development of technologies to follow, analyze and potentially change the trajectory of objects near Earth. NASA and the European Space Agency (ESA) had similar programs in the past. On Friday, ESA updated to 2.2% the likelihood of Asteroid 2024 YR4 reaching Earth by 2032, placing it at the top of the agency's risk list. The asteroid, with an estimated width between 40 and 90 meters, was discovered by the University of Hawaii Institute of Astronomy at the end of December. The discovery activated global asteroid response mechanisms, after the odds of impact on Earth had overcome an international monitoring threshold. The announcement of the state administration of science, technology and industry for China's national defense aims to recruit three professionals for a “planetary defense post”.
The Center, which is responsible for the investigation and implementation of aerospace engineering and the observation of the land, is recruiting graduates to study asteroid monitoring and create early warning methods, according to the announcement, published in the China Space magazine account wechat account Science and Technology. There are several methods that can be used to try to prevent an asteroid from reaching the earth. In the world's first successful planetary defense test in 2022, the US space agency NASA altered the trajectory of an asteroid by causing a clash against a ship. Scientists will be able to follow the 2024 YR4 until April 2025, with the next observation opportunity to arrive in 2028. In early February 2025, NASA placed the asteroid at level 3 of the Torino Impact Danger scale, a classification that Indicates a situation that deserves attention, but not immediate concern.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:49:12+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of workers involved in labor conflicts increased by 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/numero-de-trabalhadores-envolvidos-em-conflitos-laborais-aumentou-em-2024/</link><description>Although the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) has established fewer cases due to labor conflicts, the number of workers involved in disputes with employers increased last year. According to information from Dsal sent to the end, the main reasons for conflicts had to do with salaries and compensation.
 
Last year, there was a descent of the number of cases established by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) related to labor conflicts. However, the number of workers involved in these disputes has grown.
The data sent by DSAL to the end show that in 2024 they were involved in labor disputes 2,964 workers, and the number of cases established by the authorities was 1,582. The number of employers involved was 981.
In 2023, the number of workers involved in disputes with employer entities was lower: 2,430. However, the number of lawsuits filed by DSAL was higher than last year: 1,653. In 2023, 945 employer entities were involved in disputes.
In 2022, there were 3,735 workers involved in conflicts - the highest number of recent years. This year, they had been involved in disputes 963 entities. The number of cases instituted was 1,752. By 2021, the number of cases established was similar (1,720), with the number of workers affected from 3,266. The employers involved reached 1,087.
In the first year of pandemic restrictions, 2020, DSAL instituted 1,519 cases due to labor conflicts, involving 941 companies and 2,841 workers. In 2019, there were 1,729 cases established by DSAL, which involved a total of 3,659 workers and 1,006 employers.
According to DSSA data, the main reasons for labor conflicts over the years have been issues related to salaries, dismissal compensation or compensation due to extraordinary hours.
On its website, DSAL recommends that when workers feel their injured interests, such as debt salary, compensation for the provision of extraordinary work, compensation for work on weekly rest days and mandatory holidays, termination compensation, can denounce the situation with the body. Received the complaint filed by the worker, DSAL institutes the process for investigation.
Once the complaint has been received, the DSAL investigators will find out of the conflict stories and try to have a concertation between the labor and employer parties to resolve the dispute. If it is confirmed the existence of offenses committed by the employer, an auto is issued requesting the payment of the amount of debt to the worker.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:47:26+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>21 processes related to work of minors between 2022 and 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/instruidos-21-processos-relacionados-com-trabalho-de-menores-entre-2022-e-2024/</link><description>In two years, 1,333 minor workers were registered in legalized situation and 21 cases in which infringements were detected. Dsal is accompanying the occurrences and is said to be committed to fulfilling the rights, interests and special guarantees of the worker between 16 and 18 years.
 
In two years, between 2022 and 2024, 21 cases related to irregularities in hiring smaller workers were instructed, mostly related to violations of admission requirements or non -compliance with employers' duty of communication.
The data are advanced by the Directorate of the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs (DSAL), Wong Chi Hong, in a response to the written interplies presented by Chan U Law, Deputy to the Legislative Assembly (AL) of MSAR, where it expressed concern for the absence of Statistics regarding the employment situation of minors between 16 and 18 years. The only statistics available, lamented, encompass a broader age group between 16 and 24 years (14,200 workers in total).
In the response, the DSSA states that between 2022 and 2024 were recorded 667 cases of hiring minor workers, involving a total of 1,333 people, whose functions performed were mostly those of “table employee” in the hotel and restoration sector or “employee of retail sales ”.
Wong Chi Hong reinforces that the rights, labor interests and special guarantees of workers of this age group - such as admission requirements, prohibited and conditional work and health protection - are contemplated in the current law of labor relations, as well as the various duties tasked to the employer. It is this duty to establish contact with the DSal and share copies of the contract entered into, the written authorization of legal represented and a proof medical certificate that the minor has completed the minimum age of admission and has the physical and psychic capabilities appropriate to the functions to be performed.
As for the situations in which irregularities were detected, DSAL guarantees to have proceeded, “under the terms of the law”, to the “monitoring of the offenses committed”. It also ensures to continue closely the fulfillment of workers' rights and interests, namely through the argument of opinions and suggestions of “various quadrants of the company”, dissemination actions, clarification sessions and inspection and preventive inspection actions.
The new data arise in the path of a written interpellation presented in December by the deputy to Ali Lei Chan U. In this document, the deputy emphasized the “physical and psychological immaturity” of smaller workers as disadvantage factors that could lead to “risks and treatment unequal at work ”. Although recognizing the importance of the law of labor relations, law chan u warned of the need to “improve labor legislation, reinforce the execution of the law and the supervision of society” in order to protect the physical and mental health of this special group of workers.
In this sense, the deputy concluded the interpellation by appealing to which detailed statistics were disclosed about the dimension of employment between the ages of 16 and 18 and the existence of any cases in which the rights of minor workers were compromised. At the last point, law Chan U directly questions the government about the possible need to review the lists of conditional and prohibited work to minors, already in force 16 years ago.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:46:40+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS approved 80 requests for attribution of subsidy for caregivers in the last four years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/ias-aprovou-80-pedidos-de-atribuicao-de-subsidio-para-cuidadores-nos-ultimos-quatro-anos/</link><description>Since the implementation of caregivers' allowance in 2020, the Institute of Social Action has received a total of 111 requests, of which 80 were approved. The body has ensured, in response to an interpellation of Mrs Song Pek Kei, that the allowance is already covering, basically, the respective low -performance caregivers families. The executive said that there are 13 social equipment with host service for disabled people with more than a thousand vacancies, advancing that it will create even another home in zone A for the elderly and people with intellectual disabilities.
 
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) launched the caregiver subsidy project in 2020 and received, by the end of last year, 111 requests involving persons with an unconnected intellectual disabilities attributed, severe or deep. Among the requests submitted, 80 were approved. According to the body, the remaining 31 cases were rejected because they were not “belonging to the types of corresponding degrees” and “not being approved in the economic evaluation or the evaluation of self-care capacity”.
Authorities released the data following a written interpellation of Deputy Song Pek Kei about the relaxation of the request of the subsidy for caregivers. The IAS, in this case, dismissed the revision of the mechanism and said it will maintain the current regime of assignment of the subsidy for caregivers.
"Currently, the caregiver allowance can basically cover their respective low -performance caregivers families, thus allowing them to benefit from another economic support to live in the community," said Hon Wai, president of IAS, in the answer. The official added that caregiver families, who do not have enough economic resources to face the basic needs of life may still require a subsidy from the executive.
IAS stressed to have implemented the pilot project of the subsidy for caregivers in December 2020 and the range of the recipients “was gradually extended”, and the measure has been permanent since 2023.
It is recalled that the recipients of the subsidy cover four types of people who need continuing and intensive care of third parties in their self-care and in their daily lives, including permanent beds unable to perform actions such as sitting and lifting without help, people with people with Intellectual deficiency, people with autism and people with motor disabilities, all of them of severe or deep degree, including those without grade attributed. Currently, beneficiaries may receive a monthly subsidy of 2,175 patacas.
Authorities also left the guarantee that they will continue to pay attention to the implementation of the allowance, and support people with disabilities and caregivers families through "different types of services to meet their needs."
 
Homes
 
According to statistics on the disability assessment record, cited by Song Pek Kei, there are, until September last year, 1,311 patients with intellectual disabilities, of which 572 are serious and deep. The deputy questioned the government about the search for home vacancies for patients with intellectual disabilities, since “there are 275 patients with intellectual disabilities aged between 35 and 44, who in the next 10 years will come in successively in the senior age. ”.
IAS indicated that there is now in Macao a total of 13 social equipment with the reception service for disabled people, which can make available about 1,060 vacancies, which “can basically meet the needs of the services concerned”.
In this respect, until November last year, there was a total accumulated of 44 people with intellectual disabilities who requested the reception service in rehabilitation care molds, but most applicants do not have the immediate need to enter into in rehabilitation homes with the reception service. "These people and families, upon receiving this daytime rehabilitation service and the temporary reception service that is given in the community, can effectively maintain and balance the dependency relationship between family members," IAS said.
The body also revealed that it is planning the creation of a home in zone A of new landfills that can provide vacancies for the elderly and people with intellectual disabilities, but will only later disclose more details.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:48:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government acquires another 11,000 doses of flu vaccine</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/governo-adquire-mais-11-mil-doses-de-vacina-contra-a-gripe/</link><description>Health services admit to having made an emergency acquisition of 11,000 doses of flu vaccine in response to the “significant increase in the search for anti -flu vaccines” in Macao and neighboring regions. Thus, from today, more vacancies will be available for vaccination. Health services revealed that the number of flu vaccines accumulated 225,000 doses, plus 45,000 doses compared to last year.
 
Another 11,000 doses of flu vaccine have arrived in Macau to cope with increasing the demand for vaccination by residents during the influenza peak period this year. Health services claimed to have acquired, urgently, 11 thousand doses of anti-the-flu vaccines, since "there has been a substantial increase in the demand for anti-the flu vaccination in Macao and neighboring regions."
According to a statement issued by health services, thus the number of vacancies for marking anti -sprite vaccination will be extended from today, and residents need to mark prior through a vaccination marking system against vaccination system Flu and vaccinates according to the date and place scheduled. However, residents aged 65 or older and children aged six months and nine years are exempt from marking for vaccination.
Authorities stated that Macau entered the peak period last month and advanced an estimate that the flu virus remains active later this month, as Chinese New Year's holidays should have increased the risk of propagation due to the flow of people.
For this period of this year's influenza, which has the years 2024 and 2025, health services have successively acquired a total of 225,000 doses of anti -the -flu vaccines, according to the statement, more 45,000 doses than last year. In total 204 thousand doses have already been managed until the past Monday, representing an increase of 22.2% over the same period last year, when 167,000 doses of vaccines against influenza were inoculated.
"The general situation of vaccination of Macau's high -risk groups is satisfactory" this year, the body stressed, advancing that the vaccination rate of Macao homes exceeded 90%. In addition, the rate of vaccination in day care centers was higher than 65%, the rate in kindergarten and primary schools reached 80%and the rate in secondary education is close to 70%. Already the vaccination rate of the elderly of 65 years or over or over, was 60%.
“Compared to last year's same -year period, the vaccination rate of all groups of people at high risk increased,” they stressed. Health services began the vaccination service for high -risk individuals in September last year and the service began to all residents of Macao in November last year.
The organism says that anti -the -flu vaccines currently supplied in Macao are used in the northern hemisphere regions and usually expire between May and June of each year. Thus, the seasonal flu vaccination program will end when existing vaccines run or expire.
It is recalled that Macau registered the first two cases of death caused by this year's flu last week, having died two residents, 69 and 35, respectively, by flu complications. Health services made several appeals to influenza vaccination and more than 5,400 residents were vaccinated last weekend.
 
Collective flu infection involves five students
 
Another case of collective flu infection diagnosed on Monday was registered. According to health services, the case was detected in the P3A class of the School of Application attached to the University of Macau, located at Tai Lin Street, Taipa, and five students were infected. Patients began last Friday to express symptoms of upper respiratory tract infection such as fever, cough, among others. The clinical conditions of the patients are considered slight, no serious cases and hospitalization have been recorded. Authorities indicate that the school space has already reinforced the disinfection, cleaning and maintenance of air ventilation inside the facilities.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:49:38+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian police interrupted the street concert of British singer Ed Sheeran</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/policia-indiana-interrompeu-concerto-de-rua-do-cantor-britanico-ed-sheeran/</link><description>Indian police interrupted on Sunday a performance by British pop artist Ed Sheeran, who denied having illegally sung in Bangalore, southern India. The artist, who is touring the most populous country on the planet, decided on Sunday to act between two concerts before passers -by in the Indian capital of new technologies.
Videos shared on social networks show a police off the 33 -year -old singer's microphone in the middle of his hit "Shape of You" at Church Street, a bustling commercial neighborhood.
According to the authorities, the authorization issued for Ed Sheeran acts in concerts does not include improvised outdoor performances. “He is a very famous singer and this will naturally create chaos. To avoid this, the police did not give him permission, ”said the interior minister of Karnataka, G. Parameshwara on Monday. “Despite this, he came and tried to act, so police stopped him. Nothing beyond that, ”he added.
Ed Sheeran denied having violated the law, advanced on the Instagram social network on Sunday night that he received permission to play "exactly in this place, was planned in advance." "It was not as if we had arrived by chance," he said shortly after the incident. The attitude of the police that turned off the microphone was widely criticized on social networks.
The British star is currently touring six cities in India, including a depleted concert in Mumbai.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:52:41+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pyongyang denounces “hostile military act” from the US after submarine passed through South Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/pyongyang-denuncia-acto-militar-hostil-dos-eua-apos-submarino-passar-pela-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>North Korea yesterday accused the United States of committing a "hostile military act," after a US Navy submarine was docked in South Korea for refueling.
 
"We are very concerned about the Hostile Hostile Military Act of the United States, which can lead the acute military confrontation in the Korean Peninsula to a total armed conflict," said a spokesman for the Ministry of Defense, quoted in a statement released by the agency of State News KCNA.
Pyongyang has asked the United States to "stop the provocations that feed instability," accusing them of ignoring North Korean security concerns.
South Korea Yonhap news agency said USS Alexandria, an American nuclear submarine, reached the Busan naval base yesterday in South Korea on Monday. A similar visit had occurred in November. "Our Armed Forces are closely monitoring the frequent appearance of US strategic assets on the Korean Peninsula and are ready to use all means to defend state security and interests, as well as regional peace," said the port -Voice of the Ministry of Defense of North Korea.
North Korea emphasized the importance of developing its self -defense capabilities and referred to the promise of leader Kim Jong Un in January to continue his country's nuclear program "indefinitely."
United States President Donald Trump expressed on Friday the intention to build bridges with Kim Jong-un's North Korean regime. “I think it's a great advantage for everyone that I get along with him. I like him, I mean, I get along with him, he gets along with me. And that's a good thing, it's not a bad thing, ”said the Republican. But North Korea replied that the nuclear weapons it possesses are not a bargaining chip to negotiate, but a force to stop threats, and justified the reinforcement of weapons with the geopolitical aspirations of the West.
The statement suggests that Pyongyang has no interest in returning to the negotiating table with Washington. In the first term as president of the United States (2017-2021), Donald Trump proposed to North Korea to end nuclear weapons in exchange for support in economic development.
The North Korean message also mentioned the recent statements of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and the European Union, which reaffirmed that they will not recognize North Korea as nuclear power. Pyongyang accuses the West of being a destabilizing force of peace.
Pyongyang, in addition, denounced the growing participation of NATO and European countries in military maneuvers around the Korean Peninsula, accusing them of seeking the confrontation and disarmament of the Asian country, not for safety reasons, but to “reach the ones their political objectives and impure military ”.
 
USA and South Korea in joint military exercises near the North Korea border
 
The United States and South Korean Armed Forces announced yesterday that they are performing a series of real -set military exercises by the North Korea border. The exercises occur just 30 kilometers from the demilitarized zone that delimits the two countries, technically still at war.
Military maneuvers explained the South Korean Armed Forces started a week ago and will be extended for two more weeks, including royal fire in the Rodriguez shooting field, a complex located in pocheon that is used for this type of maneuvers. According to the South Korean news agency Yonhap, the maneuvers involve 2,000 soldiers and 150 combat teams, including “K1A2” South Korean tanks and “K21” infantry vehicles, as well as “Stryker” vehicles, obuses, “apache” helicopters and soil attack planes “A-10”.
In this sense, the armed forces of both countries plan to form small battalions to carry out air force support training, as well as artillery and air defense attacks. According to the South Korean military, these exercises are intended to “reinforce combined operation and defense capabilities” and help US troops on the ground “adapt their“ Stryker ’vehicles to pre-existing conditions on the Korean peninsula”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:52:42+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Four projects in the area of ​​health in the Palop will receive 100 thousand euros each</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/quatro-projectos-na-area-da-saude-nos-palop-vao-receber-100-mil-euros-cada/</link><description>Four projects in the area of ​​health sciences in the Palop will receive about 100 thousand euros in the next three years in the context of a partnership of the Gulbenkian Foundation and the “La Caixa” Foundation.
 
The Gulbenkian Foundation indicated yesterday in a statement that, “over the next three years, four projects in the area of ​​cancer, pediatrics and the relationship between tuberculosis and diabetes will be supported by the“ We Forward - Palop Health Sciences Training - [African countries of Portuguese official language] ”.
In the same note it is said that the projects were selected by an international jury of between 20 applications in areas of health sciences considered fundamental in Angola, Guinea-Bissau and Mozambique.
In Angola, the project of the Katyavala Bwila University - “Training for the Research, Prevention and Treatment of Oncological Diseases in Albinos” will be supported - which also has as partners the Lubango Central Hospital, the Portuguese Institute of Oncology of Porto and Goncoinitiva, read in the statement.
With the leadership of researcher Maria Madalena Paulo Chimpolo, "the project arises in response to the high number of albinism in the provinces of Huila and Benguela - regions marked by high sun exposure, vulnerabilities and a high incidence of cancer diseases."
Already in Guinea-Bissau, the project “Initiative in Oncology”, promoted by Jean Piaget University, “intends to create an research ecosystem, integrating teaching, research and care”.
Led by researcher Bubacar Embaló, “the project bets on reinforcing Guinea-Bissau's response capacity to the cancer challenges it goes through, improving infrastructures and training specialized professionals to increase the early diagnostic rate and treatment options”. Still in Guinea-Bissau, the Lusófona University will receive support for the project “which aims to perceive the relationship between tuberculosis and diabetes mellitus, one of the noncommunicable chronic diseases that are emerging as a growing problem in sub-Saharan Africa, coexisting with high rates of infectious diseases such as tuberculosis ”.
In Mozambique, the project of the Faculty of Medicine of Eduardo Mondlane University intends to reinforce the capacity of pediatric research nuclei that “aim to do cutting -edge research in the pediatric area, especially in the preparation of clinical trials for new medicines and vaccines, in collaboration with external institutions and financing from EDCTP ”. Led by José Sumbana, this project aims to “create infrastructure and technology conditions and strengthen human resources to the University's Microbiology Laboratory”.
The initiative “We Forward” was born in late 2024, the result of a collaboration protocol between the Gulbenkian Foundation and the “La Caixa” Foundation with the objective of developing a program that promotes training in the area of ​​health sciences in Palop, through reinforcement of nuclei or research centers of higher education institutions and their connection to health facilities in these countries. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:46:53+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title /><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/sonhos-sobre-a-identidade-de-macau-na-arte-de-huang-xuan/</link><description>The exhibition “I Had Too Much to Dream Last Night”, by artist Huang Xuan, will be inaugurated on February 15 at the Boi Warehouse. Through photography, video, installation and performance, Huang explores the brands left by workers and tourists in the city, offering a new perspective on urban life. The show, opened from February 16 to March 17, invites visitors to reflect on Macao's identity and memory. The inauguration is scheduled for 5:30 pm, with DJ Farinha music at 18:30.
 
The exhibition “I Had Too Much to Dream Last Night”, by artist Huang Xuan, will be inaugurated on February 15, at 5:30 pm, at the Gallery of the Boi Warehouse, located at the intersection of Colonel Mesquita Avenue and Avenida Almirante Lacerda. This event will take place after a three -week artistic residency at the Boi Warehouse itself, held between October and November 2024, where Huang had the opportunity to interact with the local community and explore the cultural context and structure of the city.
During this period, Huang Xuan observed the dynamics of urban life in Macau, capturing as different groups, such as workers, tourists and individuals with resources, leave their mark in the various recesses of the city. The artist highlights the way everyday life unfolds through small details, such as the windows of buildings that open to the daily rhythm, providing a dynamic view of the movements and conversations that occur in the interiors of common life.
"Objects abandoned on the streets, marks erased on the walls and the persistent aromas of food on the roads reflect ephemeral moments that, although they have passed, continue to infuse the city with their own identity," highlights the description of the ox warehouse.
According to Huang, “this exhibition combines many of my impressions while in residence in the city, such as the many rolling stages on the road, the long and narrow bridge that connects the peninsula to the mud, the theatrical and splendid scenery of casinos. The scenarios of the streets, where surrealism and vintage coexist, is like a magical theater or a beautiful dream that is constantly being staged in the exhibition. ”
In this new show, Huang uses a variety of means, including photography, video, installation and performance. Through these formats, it proposes a reinterpretation of the urban narrative, seen through its perspective of “foreign”. Visitors will be able to find objects, both real estate and moving, observe the transformation of urban scenes, and realize the reconfiguration of symbols that emerge in a game of dynamic forms. The narrative presents itself as a stage where the celebrations have already taken place, with actors, objects and even the stage itself to participate in automatic and meditative performance after its end.
This proposal of Huang Xuan is an exhaust exploitation of what it means to live and exist in Macau, inviting visitors to reflect on the interconnections between space, identity and memory in the city, through contemporary art, ”says the organization, adding that his work It is a “reflective dialogue between body, space and object”.
Huang Xuan's body of work, born in 1995 in Taipei, Taiwan, stands out in the areas of performance and video art, always with the body as a central object of expression. His works exploit the subtleties of daily limitations and dynamics, as well as investigate the relationship between human objects and gestures. By employing unexpected uses of objects, Huang challenges public perception, leading to reflection on human experience. His recent career includes nominations for exhibitions such as “No Language”, Moca Taipei (2025), “Mipaf 2024: Body Sphere of East Asia” at the Boi Warehouse in Macao and “Everyday Performing” at Chiayi Art Museum. In 2023, he participated in the "4th Kirishima Lobby Project" at the Kirishima Open-Air Museum and, in 2022, at the Biennale Polska Media in Venice and Gdańsk.
The exhibition “I Had Too Much to Dream Last Night” opens its doors this Saturday, with a party with music with DJ Farinha at 18:30. The show will be available to the public from February 16 to March 17, with opening hours from 10h00 to 19h00, and the entry will be free. The organization of the event is in charge of the Boi Warehouse, with the support of the Cultural Development Fund and the “Beyond The Bay” platform.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sands China donates 300 thousand patacas to the social store of Santa Casa da Misericórdia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/sands-china-doa-300-mil-patacas-a-loja-social-da-santa-casa-da-misericordia/</link><description>Sands China Ltd. has made a significant donation of 300,000 patacas to the Santa Casa de Misericódia social store of Macao, continuing its support for the cause for 13 consecutive years. The initiative aims to help with the operating expenses of the Charitable Organization, which works to support families in difficult financial situations.
“It is a privilege to work with the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao for 13 consecutive years to support this significant initiative of food baskets. As a member of the Macau community, it is an honor for Sands China to extend its charity and community support, especially vulnerable people, ”said Wilfred Wong, Executive Vice President of Sands China Ltd., who was present during the event.
About 40 Sands Cares ambassadors also attended volunteers to distribute more than 370 Chinese New Year food baskets to disadvantaged families served by the store. Since its founding in 2013, the social store has been an important source of essential food and products, reaching several hundred families every month in the most needy neighborhoods.
Food baskets include essential items such as food and hygiene products. In addition, each family received a package with Chinese New Year gifts acquired by the Fuhong Society of Macau, in tune with the festivities.
Sands Cares is part of Las Vegas Sands Corporation's philanthropic work around the world in four key areas, these financial donations, social problems solving and collaborations with the community, as well as volunteering of company members.
The main areas of the Sands Cares Program in Macau include the Sands Cares Ambassador Program for Volunteering in the Local Community, Charitable Contributions to NGOs and community organizations, and sponsorship of community events.
During the donation delivery ceremony, Wilfred Wong handed the check of 300,000 Patacas to António José de Freitas, chairman of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia Administrative Council of Macao, given the presence of several members of the beneficiary institution.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:46:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Local governments in China begin to use Deepseek to increase efficiency</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/12/governos-locais-da-china-comecam-a-utilizar-deepseek-para-aumentar-eficiencia/</link><description>Several local governments in China have begun to incorporate DeepSeek's artificial intelligence (AI) model to help with administrative tasks and improve assistance to public needs, local media told yesterday. Large cities like Shenzhen, Canton or Suzhou have already joined the new great model of Chinese language, according to the Official Global Times.
Longgang district in Shenzhen installed the Deepseek-R1 model on its external network with access to all departments, while Suzhou, in Jiangsu province, along with Shanghai, incorporated this model and also DeepSeek-V3 on its platform public service information technologies. "The goal is to make AI an efficient assistant to government tasks and transform the way its operations are conducted, making it smarter, collaborative and data-oriented," said the director of the data management office and Governmental Services of Shenzhen, XI Wei, quoted by the Shenzhen News portal.
In the case of Suzhou, the model will be applied for research and generation of images, among other purposes.
The incorporation of this tool by Chinese institutions contrasts with the response received by Deepseek in countries in Asia, Europe, America and Oceania, which decided to block the use of Chinese application, especially among civil servants.
The reason invoked is the suspicion that the data collection system - stored in China - can disclose sensitive information or "distribute malicious software" and infect devices, "as the United States defended.
DeepSeek caused a major excitement in the Global AI sector after the launch a few weeks ago from its V3 model, which will only have been developing and cost less than six million dollars.
Launched in 2023 by the Chinese investment fund High-Flyer Quant, DeepSeek is open source and offers cheaper services than OpenAi's O1 model.
However, the enormous attention he generated - was a leader in unloading for Apple devices in the US - also translated into criticism, as the application refuses to comment on censorship issues in China, such as the 1989 Tiananmen massacre or the Taiwan Statute.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12T05:49:11+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>